<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000083" source="NHLBI" url="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/kd">
<Focus>Kawasaki Disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0026691</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000083-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Kawasaki Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kawasaki (KAH-wah-SAH-ke) disease is a rare childhood disease. It&apos;s a form of a condition calledvasculitis(vas-kyu-LI-tis). This condition involves inflammation of the blood vessels.
                
In Kawasaki disease, the walls of the blood vessels throughout the body become inflamed. The disease can affect any type of blood vessel in the body, including the arteries, veins, and capillaries.
                
Sometimes Kawasaki disease affects the coronary arteries, which carry oxygen-rich blood to the heart. As a result, some children who have Kawasaki disease may develop serious heart problems.
                
Overview
                
The cause of Kawasaki disease isn&apos;t known. The body&apos;s response to a virus or infection combined with genetic factors may cause the disease. However, no specific virus or infection has been found, and the role of genetics isn&apos;t known.
                
The disease can&apos;t be passed from one child to another. Your child won&apos;t get it from close contact with a child who has the disease. Also, if your child has the disease, he or she can&apos;t pass it to another child.
                
Kawasaki disease affects children of all races and ages and both genders. It occurs most often in children of Asian and Pacific Island descent. The disease is more likely to affect boys than girls. Most cases occur in children younger than 5years old.
                
One of the main symptoms of Kawasaki disease is a fever that lasts longer than5days. The fever remains high even after treatment with standard childhood fever medicines.
                
Children who have the disease also may have red eyes, red lips, and redness on the palms of their hands and soles of their feet. These are all signs of inflamed blood vessels.
                
Early treatment helps reduce the risk of Kawasaki disease affecting the coronary arteries and causing serious problems.
                
Outlook
                
Kawasaki disease can&apos;t be prevented. However, most children who have the disease usually recover within weeks of getting symptoms. Further problems are rare.
                
The disease affects some children&apos;s coronary arteries, which can cause serious problems. These children need long-term care and treatment.
                
Researchers continue to look for the cause of Kawasaki disease and better ways to diagnose and treat it. They also hope to learn more about long-term health risks, if any, for people who have had the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000083-3" qtype="causes">What causes Kawasaki Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The cause of Kawasaki disease isn&apos;t known. The body&apos;s response to a virus or infection combined with genetic factors may cause the disease. However, no specific virus or infection has been found, and the role of genetics isn&apos;t known.
                
Kawasaki disease can&apos;t be passed from one child to another. Your child won&apos;t get it from close contact with a child who has the disease. Also, if your child has the disease, he or she can&apos;t pass it to another child.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000083-4" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Kawasaki Disease? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kawasaki disease affects children of all races and ages and both genders. It occurs most often in children of Asian and Pacific Island descent.
                
The disease is more likely to affect boys than girls. Most cases occur in children younger than 5 years old. Kawasaki disease is rare in children older than 8.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000083-5" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Kawasaki Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Major Signs and Symptoms
                
One of the main symptoms during the early part of Kawasaki disease, called the acute phase, is fever. The fever lasts longer than 5 days. It remains high even after treatment with standard childhood fever medicines.
                
Other classic signs of the disease are:
                
Swollen lymph nodes in the neck
                
A rash on the mid-section of the body and in the genital area
                
Red, dry, cracked lips and a red, swollen tongue
                
Red, swollen palms of the hands and soles of the feet
                
Redness of the eyes
                
Other Signs and Symptoms
                
During the acute phase, your child also may be irritable and have a sore throat, joint pain, diarrhea, vomiting, and stomach pain.
                
Within 2 to 3 weeks of the start of symptoms, the skin on your child&apos;s fingers and toes may peel, sometimes in large sheets.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000083-6" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Kawasaki Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kawasaki disease is diagnosed based on your child&apos;s signs and symptoms and the results from tests and procedures.
                
Specialists Involved
                
Pediatricians often are the first to suspect a child has Kawasaki disease. Pediatricians are doctors who specialize in treating children.
                
If the disease has affected your child&apos;s coronary (heart) arteries, a pediatric cardiologist will confirm the diagnosis and give ongoing treatment. Pediatric cardiologists treat children who have heart problems.
                
Other specialists also may be involved in treating children who have Kawasaki disease.
                
Signs and Symptoms
                
The doctor will check your child for the classic signs and symptoms of Kawasaki disease.
                
The doctor will rule out other diseases that cause similar symptoms. These diseases include Rocky Mountain spotted fever, scarlet fever, and juvenile rheumatoid arthritis.
                
Generally, your child will be diagnosed with Kawasaki disease if he or she has a fever that lasts longer than 5 days plus four other classic signs or symptoms of the disease.
                
However, not all children have classic signs and symptoms of Kawasaki disease. Tests and procedures can help confirm whether a child has the disease.
                
Tests and Procedures
                
Echocardiography
                
If the doctor thinks that your child has Kawasaki disease, he or she will likely recommendechocardiography(EK-o-kar-de-OG-ra-fee), or echo. This painless test uses sound waves to create pictures of the heart and coronary arteries.
                
Echo also can help show the disease&apos;s effects over time, if any, on your child&apos;s coronary arteries. Often, the disease&apos;s effects on the coronary arteries don&apos;t show up until the second or third week after the first symptoms appear. Thus, this test is done regularly after the diagnosis.
                
Some children who have Kawasaki disease don&apos;t have the classic signs and symptoms of the acute phase. Doctors may not diagnose these children until 2 to 3 weeks after the onset of the disease. This is when another common sign of Kawasaki disease occurspeeling of the skin on the fingers and toes.
                
If your child is diagnosed at this point, he or she will likely need echo right away to see whether the disease has affected the coronary arteries.
                
Other Diagnostic Tests
                
Doctors also use other tests to help diagnose Kawasaki disease, such as:
                
Blood tests. The results from blood tests can show whether the body&apos;s blood vessels are inflamed.
                
Chest x ray. This painless test creates pictures of structures inside the chest, such as the heart and lungs. A chest x ray can show whether Kawasaki disease has affected the heart.
                
EKG (electrocardiogram). This simple test detects and records the heart&apos;s electrical activity. An EKG can show whether Kawasaki disease has affected the heart.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000083-7" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Kawasaki Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Medicines are the main treatment for Kawasaki disease. Rarely, children whose coronary (heart) arteries are affected may need medical procedures or surgery.
                
The goals of treatment include:
                
Reducing fever and inflammation to improve symptoms
                
Preventing the disease from affecting the coronary arteries
                
Initial Treatment
                
Kawasaki disease can cause serious health problems. Thus, your child will likely be treated in a hospital, at least for the early part of treatment.
                
The standard treatment during the disease&apos;s acute phase is high-dose aspirin and immune globulin. Immune globulin is a medicine that&apos;s injected into a vein.
                
Most children who receive these treatments improve greatly within 24 hours. For a small number of children, fever remains. These children may need a second round of immune globulin.
                
At the start of treatment, your child will receive high doses of aspirin. As soon as his or her fever goes away, a low dose of aspirin is given. The low dose helps prevent blood clots, which can form in the inflamed small arteries.
                
Most children treated for Kawasaki disease fully recover from the acute phase and don&apos;t need any further treatment. They should, however, follow a healthy diet and adopt healthy lifestyle habits. Taking these steps can help lower the risk of future heart disease. (Following a healthy lifestyle is advised for all children, not just those who have Kawasaki disease.)
                
Children who have had immune globulin should wait 11 months before having the measles and chicken pox vaccines. Immune globulin can prevent those vaccines from working well.
                
Long-Term Care and Treatment
                
If Kawasaki disease has affected your child&apos;s coronary arteries, he or she will need ongoing care and treatment.
                
It&apos;s best if a pediatric cardiologist provides this care to reduce the risk of severe heart problems. A pediatric cardiologist is a doctor who specializes in treating children who have heart problems.
                
Medicines and Tests
                
When Kawasaki disease affects the coronary arteries, they may expand and twist. If this happens, your child&apos;s doctor may prescribe blood-thinning medicines (for example, warfarin). These medicines help prevent blood clots from forming in the affected coronary arteries.
                
Blood-thinning medicines usually are stopped after the coronary arteries heal. Healing may occur about 18 months after the acute phase of the disease.
                
In a small number of children, the coronary arteries don&apos;t heal. These children likely will need routine tests, such as:
                
Echocardiography. This test uses sound waves to create images of the heart.
                
EKG (electrocardiogram). This test detects and records the heart&apos;s electrical activity.
                
Stress test. This test provides information about how the heart works during physical activity or stress.
                
Medical Procedures and Surgery
                
Rarely, a child who has Kawasaki disease may needcardiac catheterization(KATH-eh-ter-ih-ZA-shun). Doctors use this procedure to diagnose and treat some heart conditions.
                
A flexible tube called a catheter is put into a blood vessel in the arm, groin (upper thigh), or neck and threaded to the heart. Through the catheter, doctors can perform tests and treatments on the heart.
                
Very rarely, a child may need to have other procedures or surgery if inflammation narrows his or her coronary arteries and blocks blood flow to the heart.
                
Percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI), stent placement, or coronary artery bypass grafting(CABG) may be used.
                
Coronary angioplasty restores blood flow through narrowed or blocked coronary arteries. A thin tube with a balloon on the end is inserted into a blood vessel in the arm or groin. The tube is threaded to the narrowed or blocked coronary artery. Then, the balloon is inflated to widen the artery and restore blood flow.
                
A stent (small mesh tube) may be placed in the coronary artery during angioplasty. This device helps support the narrowed or weakened artery. A stent can improve blood flow and prevent the artery from bursting.
                
Rarely, a child may need to have CABG. This surgery is used to treat blocked coronary arteries. During CABG, a healthy artery or vein from another part of the body is connected, or grafted, to the blocked coronary artery.
                
The grafted artery or vein bypasses (that is, goes around) the blocked part of the coronary artery. This improves blood flow to the heart.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000083-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Kawasaki Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kawasaki disease can&apos;t be prevented. However, most children who have the disease recoverusually within weeks of getting signs and symptoms. Further problems are rare.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
