<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000119" source="NHLBI" url="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/sdd">
<Focus>Sleep Deprivation and Deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0037316</CUI>
			<CUI>C0162429</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000119-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sleep Deprivation and Deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sleep deprivation (DEP-rih-VA-shun) is a condition that occurs if you don&apos;t get enough sleep. Sleep deficiency is a broader concept. It occurs if you have one or more of the following:
                
You don&apos;t get enough sleep (sleep deprivation)
                
You sleep at the wrong time of day (that is, you&apos;re out of sync with your body&apos;s natural clock)
                
You don&apos;t sleep well or get all of the different types of sleep that your body needs
                
You have a sleep disorder that prevents you from getting enough sleep or causes poor quality sleep
                
This article focuses on sleep deficiency, unless otherwise noted.
                
Sleeping is a basic human need, like eating, drinking, and breathing. Like these other needs, sleeping is a vital part of the foundation for good health and well-being throughout your lifetime.
                
Sleep deficiency can lead to physical and mental health problems, injuries, loss of productivity, and even a greater risk of death.
                
Overview
                
To understand sleep deficiency, it helps to understand how sleep works and why it&apos;s important. The two basic types of sleep are rapid eye movement (REM) and non-REM.
                
Non-REM sleep includes what is commonly known as deep sleep or slow wave sleep. Dreaming typically occurs during REM sleep. Generally, non-REM and REM sleep occur in a regular pattern of 35 cycles each night.
                
Your ability to function and feel well while you&apos;re awake depends on whether you&apos;re getting enough total sleep and enough of each type of sleep. It also depends on whether you&apos;re sleeping at a time when your body is prepared and ready to sleep.
                
You have an internal &quot;body clock&quot; that controls when you&apos;re awake and when your body is ready for sleep. This clock typically follows a 24-hour repeating rhythm (called the circadian rhythm). The rhythm affects every cell, tissue, and organ in your body and how they work. (For more information, go to &quot;What Makes You Sleep?&quot;)
                
If you aren&apos;t getting enough sleep, are sleeping at the wrong times, or have poor quality sleep, you&apos;ll likely feel very tired during the day. You may not feel refreshed and alert when you wake up.
                
Sleep deficiency can interfere with work, school, driving, and social functioning. You might have trouble learning, focusing, and reacting. Also, you might find it hard to judge other people&apos;s emotions and reactions. Sleep deficiency also can make you feel frustrated, cranky, or worried in social situations.
                
The signs and symptoms of sleep deficiency may differ between children and adults. Children who are sleep deficient might be overly active and have problems paying attention. They also might misbehave, and their school performance can suffer.
                
Outlook
                
Sleep deficiency is a common public health problem in the United States. People in all age groups report not getting enough sleep.
                
As part of a health survey for the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, about 719 percent of adults in the United States reported not getting enough rest or sleep every day. 
                
Nearly 40 percent of adults report falling asleep during the day without meaning to at least once a month. Also, an estimated 50 to 70 million Americans have chronic (ongoing) sleep disorders.
                
Sleep deficiency is linked to many chronic health problems, including heart disease, kidney disease, high blood pressure, diabetes, stroke, obesity, and depression.
                
Sleep deficiency also is associated with an increased risk of injury in adults, teens, and children. For example, driver sleepiness (not related to alcohol) is responsible for serious car crash injuries and death. In the elderly, sleep deficiency might be linked to an increased risk of falls and broken bones.
                
In addition, sleep deficiency has played a role in human errors linked to tragic accidents, such as nuclear reactor meltdowns, grounding of large ships, and aviation accidents.
                
A common myth is that people can learn to get by on little sleep with no negative effects. However, research shows that getting enough quality sleep at the right times is vital for mental health, physical health, quality of life, and safety.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000119-5" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Sleep Deprivation and Deficiency? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sleep deficiency, which includes sleep deprivation, affects people of all ages, races, and ethnicities. Certain groups of people may be more likely to be sleep deficient. Examples include people who:
                
Have limited time available for sleep, such as caregivers or people working long hours or more than one job
                
Have schedules that conflict with their internal body clocks, such as shift workers, first responders, teens who have early school schedules, or people who must travel for work
                
Make lifestyle choices that prevent them from getting enough sleep, such as taking medicine to stay awake, abusing alcohol or drugs, or not leaving enough time for sleep
                
Have undiagnosed or untreated medical problems, such as stress, anxiety, or sleep disorders
                
Have medical conditions or take medicines that interfere with sleep
                
Certain medical conditions have been linked to sleep disorders. These conditions include heart failure, heart disease, obesity, diabetes, high blood pressure, stroke or transient ischemic attack (mini-stroke), depression, and attention-deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD).
                
If you have or have had one of these conditions, ask your doctor whether you might benefit from a sleep study.
                
A sleep study allows your doctor to measure how much and how well you sleep. It also helps show whether you have sleep problems and how severe they are. For more information, go to the Health Topics Sleep Studies article.
                
If you have a child who is overweight, talk with the doctor about your child&apos;s sleep habits.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000119-6" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sleep Deprivation and Deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sleep deficiency can cause you to feel very tired during the day. You may not feel refreshed and alert when you wake up. Sleep deficiency also can interfere with work, school, driving, and social functioning.
                
How sleepy you feel during the day can help you figure out whether you&apos;re having symptoms of problem sleepiness. You might be sleep deficient if you often feel like you could doze off while:
                
Sitting and reading or watching TV
                
Sitting still in a public place, such as a movie theater, meeting, or classroom
                
Riding in a car for an hour without stopping
                
Sitting and talking to someone
                
Sitting quietly after lunch
                
Sitting in traffic for a few minutes
                
Sleep deficiency can cause problems with learning, focusing, and reacting. You may have trouble making decisions, solving problems, remembering things, controlling your emotions and behavior, and coping with change. You may take longer to finish tasks, have a slower reaction time, and make more mistakes.
                
The signs and symptoms of sleep deficiency may differ between children and adults. Children who are sleep deficient might be overly active and have problems paying attention. They also might misbehave, and their school performance can suffer.
                
Sleep-deficient children may feel angry and impulsive, have mood swings, feel sad or depressed, or lack motivation.
                
You may not notice how sleep deficiency affects your daily routine. A common myth is that people can learn to get by on little sleep with no negative effects. However, research shows that getting enough quality sleep at the right times is vital for mental health, physical health, quality of life, and safety.
                
To find out whether you&apos;re sleep deficient, try keeping a sleep diary for a couple of weeks. Write down how much you sleep each night, how alert and rested you feel in the morning, and how sleepy you feel during the day.
                
Compare the amount of time you sleep each day with the average amount of sleep recommended for your age group, as shown in the chart in &quot;How Much Sleep Is Enough?&quot; If you often feel very sleepy, and efforts to increase your sleep don&apos;t help, talk with your doctor.
                
You can find a sample sleep diary in the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute&apos;s &quot;Your Guide to Healthy Sleep.&quot;</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
