<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000139" source="NHLBI" url="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/vwd">
<Focus>Von Willebrand Disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0042974</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000139-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Von Willebrand Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Von Willebrand disease (VWD) is a bleeding disorder. It affects your blood&apos;s ability to clot. If your blood doesn&apos;t clot, you can have heavy, hard-to-stop bleeding after an injury. The bleeding can damage your internal organs. Rarely, the bleeding may even cause death.
                
In VWD, you either have low levels of a certain protein in your blood or the protein doesn&apos;t work well. The protein is called von Willebrand factor, and it helps your blood clot.
                
Normally, when one of your blood vessels is injured, you start to bleed. Small blood cell fragments called platelets (PLATE-lets) clump together to plug the hole in the blood vessel and stop the bleeding. Von Willebrand factor acts like glue to help the platelets stick together and form a blood clot.
                
Von Willebrand factor also carries clotting factor VIII (8), another important protein that helps your blood clot. Factor VIII is the protein that&apos;s missing or doesn&apos;t work well in people who have hemophilia, another bleeding disorder.
                
VWD is more common and usually milder than hemophilia. In fact, VWD is the most common inherited bleeding disorder. It occurs in about 1 out of every 100 to 1,000 people. VWD affects both males and females, while hemophilia mainly affects males.
                
Types of von Willebrand Disease
                
The three major types of VWD are called type 1, type 2, and type 3.
                
Type 1
                
People who have type 1 VWD have low levels of von Willebrand factor and may have low levels of factor VIII. Type 1 is the mildest and most common form of VWD. About 3 out of 4 people who have VWD have type 1.
                
Type 2
                
In type 2 VWD, the von Willebrand factor doesn&apos;t work well. Type 2 is divided into subtypes: 2A, 2B, 2M, and 2N. Different gene mutations (changes) cause each type, and each is treated differently. Thus, it&apos;s important to know the exact type of VWD that you have.
                
Type 3
                
People who have type 3 VWD usually have no von Willebrand factor and low levels of factor VIII. Type 3 is the most serious form of VWD, but it&apos;s very rare.
                
Overview
                
Most people who have VWD have type 1, a mild form. This type usually doesn&apos;t cause life-threatening bleeding. You may need treatment only if you have surgery, tooth extraction, or trauma. Treatment includes medicines and medical therapies.
                
Some people who have severe forms of VWD need emergency treatment to stop bleeding before it becomes life threatening.
                
Early diagnosis is important. With the proper treatment plan, even people who have type 3 VWD can live normal, active lives.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000139-2" qtype="causes">What causes Von Willebrand Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Von Willebrand disease (VWD) is almost always inherited. &quot;Inherited&quot; means that the disorder is passed from parents to children though genes. 
                
You can inherit type 1 or type 2 VWD if only one of your parents passes the gene on to you. You usually inherit type 3 VWD only if both of your parents pass the gene on to you. Your symptoms may be different from your parents&apos; symptoms.
                
Some people have the genes for the disorder but don&apos;t have symptoms. However, they still can pass the genes on to their children.
                
Some people get VWD later in life as a result of other medical conditions. This type of VWD is called acquired von Willebrand syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000139-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Von Willebrand Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The signs and symptoms of von Willebrand disease (VWD) depend on which type of the disorder you have. They also depend on how serious the disorder is. Many people have such mild symptoms that they don&apos;t know they have VWD.
                
If you have type 1 or type 2 VWD, you may have the following mild-to-moderate bleeding symptoms:
                
Frequent, large bruises from minor bumps or injuries
                
Frequent or hard-to-stop nosebleeds
                
Prolonged bleeding from the gums after a dental procedure
                
Heavy or prolonged menstrual bleeding in women
                
Blood in your stools from bleeding in your intestines or stomach
                
Blood in your urine from bleeding in your kidneys or bladder
                
Heavy bleeding after a cut or other accident
                
Heavy bleeding after surgery
                
People who have type 3 VWD may have all of the symptoms listed above and severe bleeding episodes for no reason. These bleeding episodes can be fatal if not treated right away. People who have type 3 VWD also may have bleeding into soft tissues or joints, causing severe pain and swelling.
                
Heavy menstrual bleeding often is the main symptom of VWD in women. Doctors call this menorrhagia (men-o-RA-je-ah). They define it as:
                
Bleeding with clots larger than about 1-inch in diameter
                
Anemia (low red blood cell count) or low blood iron
                
The need to change pads or tampons more than every hour
                
However, just because a woman has heavy menstrual bleeding doesn&apos;t mean she has VWD.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000139-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Von Willebrand Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Early diagnosis of von Willebrand disease (VWD) is important to make sure that you&apos;re treated and can live a normal, active life.
                
Sometimes VWD is hard to diagnose. People who have type 1 or type 2 VWD may not have major bleeding problems. Thus, they may not be diagnosed unless they have heavy bleeding after surgery or some other trauma.
                
On the other hand, type 3 VWD can cause major bleeding problems during infancy and childhood. So, children who have type 3 VWD usually are diagnosed during their first year of life.
                
To find out whether you have VWD, your doctor will review your medical history and the results from a physical exam and tests.
                
Medical History
                
Your doctor will likely ask questions about your medical history and your family&apos;s medical history. He or she may ask about:
                
Any bleeding from a small wound that lasted more than 15 minutes or started up again within the first 7 days following the injury.
                
Any prolonged, heavy, or repeated bleeding that required medical care after surgery or dental extractions.
                
Any bruising with little or no apparent trauma, especially if you could feel a lump under the bruise.
                
Any nosebleeds that occurred for no known reason and lasted more than 10 minutes despite pressure on the nose, or any nosebleeds that needed medical attention.
                
Any blood in your stools for no known reason.
                
Any heavy menstrual bleeding (for women). This bleeding usually involves clots or lasts longer than 7 to 10 days.
                
Any history of muscle or joint bleeding.
                
Any medicines you&apos;ve taken that might cause bleeding or increase the risk of bleeding. Examples include aspirin and other nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), clopidogrel, warfarin, or heparin.
                
Any history of liver or kidney disease, blood or bone marrow disease, or high or low blood platelet counts.
                
Physical Exam
                
Your doctor will do a physical exam to look for unusual bruising or other signs of recent bleeding. He or she also will look for signs of liver disease or anemia (a low red blood cell count).
                
Diagnostic Tests
                
No single test can diagnose VWD. Your doctor may recommend one or more blood tests to diagnose the disorder. These tests may include:
                
Von Willebrand factor antigen. This test measures the amount of von Willebrand factor in your blood.
                
Von Willebrand factor ristocetin (ris-to-SEE-tin) cofactor activity. This test shows how well your von Willebrand factor works.
                
Factor VIII clotting activity. This test checks the clotting activity of factor VIII. Some people who have VWD have low levels of factor VIII activity, while others have normal levels.
                
Von Willebrand factor multimers. This test is done if one or more of the first three tests are abnormal. It shows the structure of your von Willebrand factor. The test helps your doctor diagnose what type of VWD you have.
                
Platelet function test. This test measures how well your platelets are working.
                
You may have these tests more than once to confirm a diagnosis. Your doctor also may refer you to a hematologist to confirm the diagnosis and for followup care. A hematologist is a doctor who specializes in diagnosing and treating blood disorders.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000139-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Von Willebrand Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment for von Willebrand disease (VWD) is based on the type of VWD you have and how severe it is. Most cases of VWD are mild, and you may need treatment only if you have surgery, tooth extraction, or an accident.
                
Medicines are used to:
                
Increase the amount of von Willebrand factor and factor VIII released into the bloodstream
                
Replace von Willebrand factor
                
Prevent the breakdown of blood clots
                
Control heavy menstrual bleeding in women
                
Specific Treatments
                
One treatment for VWD is a man-made hormone called desmopressin. You usually take this hormone by injection or nasal spray. It makes your body release more von Willebrand factor and factor VIII into your bloodstream. Desmopressin works for most people who have type 1 VWD and for some people who have type 2 VWD.
                
Another type of treatment is von Willebrand factor replacement therapy. This involves an infusion of concentrated von Willebrand factor and factor VIII into a vein in your arm. This treatment may be used if you:
                
Can&apos;t take desmopressin or need extended treatment
                
Have type 1 VWD that doesn&apos;t respond to desmopressin
                
Have type 2 or type 3 VWD
                
Antifibrinolytic (AN-te-fi-BRIN-o-LIT-ik) medicines also are used to treat VWD. These medicines help prevent the breakdown of blood clots. They&apos;re mostly used to stop bleeding after minor surgery, tooth extraction, or an injury. These medicines may be used alone or with desmopressin and replacement therapy.
                
Fibrin glue is medicine that&apos;s placed directly on a wound to stop bleeding.
                
Treatments for Women
                
Treatments for women who have VWD with heavy menstrual bleeding include:
                
Birth control pills. The hormones in these pills can increase the amount of von Willebrand factor and factor VIII in your blood. The hormones also can reduce menstrual blood loss. Birth control pills are the most recommended birth control method for women who have VWD.
                
A levonorgestrel intrauterine device. This is a birth control device that contains the hormone progestin. The device is placed in the uterus (womb).
                
Aminocaproic acid or tranexamic acid. These antifibrinolytic medicines can reduce bleeding by slowing the breakdown of blood clots.
                
Desmopressin.
                
For some women who are done having children or don&apos;t want children, endometrial ablation (EN-do-ME-tre-al ab-LA-shun) is done. This procedure destroys the lining of the uterus. It has been shown to reduce menstrual blood loss in women who have VWD.
                
If you need a hysterectomy (HIS-ter-EK-to-me; surgical removal of the uterus) for another reason, this procedure will stop menstrual bleeding and possibly improve your quality of life. However, hysterectomy has its own risk of bleeding complications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
