<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000063" source="NHLBI" url="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/hpl">
<Focus>Heart Palpitations</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1822022</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000063-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Heart Palpitations ?</Question>
			<Answer>Palpitations (pal-pi-TA-shuns) are feelings that your heart is skipping a beat, fluttering, or beating too hard or too fast. You may have these feelings in your chest, throat, or neck. They can occur during activity or even when you&apos;re sitting still or lying down.
                
Overview
                
Many things can trigger palpitations, including:
                
Strong emotions
                
Vigorous physical activity
                
Medicines such as diet pills and decongestants
                
Caffeine, alcohol, nicotine, and illegal drugs
                
Certain medical conditions, such as thyroid disease or anemia (uh-NEE-me-uh)
                
These factors can make the heart beat faster or stronger than usual, or they can cause premature (extra) heartbeats. In these situations, the heart is still working normally. Thus, these palpitations usually are harmless.
                
Some palpitations are symptoms of arrhythmias (ah-RITH-me-ahs). Arrhythmias are problems with the rate or rhythm of the heartbeat.
                
Some arrhythmias are signs of heart conditions, such as heart attack, heart failure, heart valve disease, or heart muscle disease. However, less than half of the people who have palpitations have arrhythmias.
                
You can take steps to reduce or prevent palpitations. Try to avoid things that trigger them (such as stress and stimulants) and treat related medical conditions.
                
Outlook
                
Palpitations are very common. They usually aren&apos;t serious or harmful, but they can be bothersome. If you have them, your doctor can decide whether you need treatment or ongoing care.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000063-2" qtype="causes">What causes Heart Palpitations ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many things can cause palpitations. You may have these feelings even when your heart is beating normally or somewhat faster than normal.
                
Most palpitations are harmless and often go away on their own. However, some palpitations are signs of a heart problem. Sometimes the cause of palpitations can&apos;t be found.
                
If you start having palpitations, see your doctor to have them checked.
                
Causes Not Related to Heart Problems
                
Strong Emotions
                
You may feel your heart pounding or racing during anxiety, fear, or stress. You also may have these feelings if you&apos;re having a panic attack.
                
Vigorous Physical Activity
                
Intense activity can make your heart feel like its beating too hard or too fast, even though it&apos;s working normally. Intense activity also can cause occasional premature (extra) heartbeats.
                
Medical Conditions
                
Some medical conditions can cause palpitations. These conditions can make the heart beat faster or stronger than usual. They also can cause premature (extra) heartbeats.
                
Examples of these medical conditions include:
                
An overactive thyroid
                
A low blood sugar level
                
Anemia
                
Some types of low blood pressure
                
Fever
                
Dehydration (not enough fluid in the body)
                
Hormonal Changes
                
The hormonal changes that happen during pregnancy, menstruation, and the perimenopausal period may cause palpitations. The palpitations will likely improve or go away as these conditions go away or change.
                
Some palpitations that occur during pregnancy may be due to anemia.
                
Medicines and Stimulants
                
Many medicines can trigger palpitations because they can make the heart beat faster or stronger than usual. Medicines also can cause premature (extra) heartbeats.
                
Examples of these medicines include:
                
Inhaled asthma medicines.
                
Medicines to treat an underactive thyroid. Taking too much of these medicines can cause an overactive thyroid and lead to palpitations.
                
Medicines to prevent arrhythmias. Medicines used to treat irregular heart rhythms can sometimes cause other irregular heart rhythms.
                
Over-the-counter medicines that act as stimulants also may cause palpitations. These include decongestants (found in cough and cold medicines) and some herbal and nutritional supplements.
                
Caffeine, nicotine (found in tobacco), alcohol, and illegal drugs (such as cocaine and amphetamines) also can cause palpitations.
                
Causes Related to Heart Problems
                
Some palpitations are symptoms of arrhythmias. Arrhythmias are problems with the rate or rhythm of the heartbeat. However, less than half of the people who have palpitations have arrhythmias.
                
During an arrhythmia, the heart can beat too fast, too slow, or with an irregular rhythm. An arrhythmia happens if some part of the heart&apos;s electrical system doesn&apos;t work as it should.
                
Palpitations are more likely to be related to an arrhythmia if you:
                
Have had a heart attack or are at risk for one.
                
Have coronary heart disease (CHD) or risk factors for CHD.
                
Have other heart problems, such as heart failure, heart valve disease, or heart muscle disease.
                
Have abnormal electrolyte levels. Electrolytes are minerals, such as potassium and sodium, found in blood and body fluids. They&apos;re vital for normal health and functioning of the body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000063-3" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Heart Palpitations? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Some people may be more likely than others to have palpitations. People at increased risk include those who:
                
Have anxiety or panic attacks, or people who are highly stressed
                
Take certain medicines or stimulants
                
Have certain medical conditions that aren&apos;t related to heart problems, such as an overactive thyroid
                
Have certain heart problems, such as arrhythmias (irregular heartbeats), a previous heart attack, heart failure, heart valve disease, or heart muscle disease
                
Women who are pregnant, menstruating, or perimenopausal also may be at higher risk for palpitations because of hormonal changes. Some palpitations that occur during pregnancy may be due to anemia.
                
For more information about these risk factors, go to &quot;What Causes Palpitations?&quot;</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000063-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Heart Palpitations ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of palpitations include feelings that your heart is:
                
Skipping a beat
                
Fluttering
                
Beating too hard or too fast
                
You may have these feelings in your chest, throat, or neck. They can occur during activity or even when you&apos;re sitting still or lying down.
                
Palpitations often are harmless, and your heart is working normally. However, these feelings can be a sign of a more serious problem if you also:
                
Feel dizzy or confused
                
Are light-headed, think you may faint, or do faint
                
Have trouble breathing
                
Have pain, pressure, or tightness in your chest, jaw, or arms
                
Feel short of breath
                
Have unusual sweating
                
Your doctor may have already told you that your palpitations are harmless. Even so, see your doctor again if your palpitations:
                
Start to occur more often or are more noticeable or bothersome
                
Occur with other symptoms, such as those listed above
                
Your doctor will want to check whether your palpitations are the symptom of a heart problem, such as an arrhythmia (irregular heartbeat).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000063-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Heart Palpitations ?</Question>
			<Answer>First, your doctor will want to find out whether your palpitations are harmless or related to a heart problem. He or she will ask about your symptoms and medical history, do a physical exam, and recommend several basic tests.
                
This information may point to a heart problem as the cause of your palpitations. If so, your doctor may recommend more tests. These tests will help show what the problem is, so your doctor can decide how to treat it.
                
The cause of palpitations may be hard to diagnose, especially if symptoms don&apos;t occur regularly.
                
Specialists Involved
                
Several types of doctors may work with you to diagnose and treat your palpitations. These include a:
                
Primary care doctor
                
Cardiologist (a doctor who specializes in diagnosing and treating heart diseases and conditions)
                
Electrophysiologist (a cardiologist who specializes in the heart&apos;s electrical system)
                
Medical History
                
Your doctor will ask questions about your palpitations, such as:
                
When did they begin?
                
How long do they last?
                
How often do they occur?
                
Do they start and stop suddenly?
                
Does your heartbeat feel steady or irregular during the palpitations?
                
Do other symptoms occur with the palpitations?
                
Do your palpitations have a pattern? For example, do they occur when you exercise or drink coffee? Do they happen at a certain time of day?
                
Your doctor also may ask about your use of caffeine, alcohol, supplements, and illegal drugs.
                
Physical Exam
                
Your doctor will take your pulse to find out how fast your heart is beating and whether its rhythm is normal. He or she also will use a stethoscope to listen to your heartbeat.
                
Your doctor may look for signs of conditions that can cause palpitations, such as an overactive thyroid.
                
Diagnostic Tests
                
Often, the first test that&apos;s done is an EKG (electrocardiogram). This simple test records your heart&apos;s electrical activity.
                
An EKG shows how fast your heart is beating and its rhythm (steady or irregular). It also records the strength and timing of electrical signals as they pass through your heart.
                
Even if your EKG results are normal, you may still have a medical condition that&apos;s causing palpitations. If your doctor suspects this is the case, you may have blood tests to gather more information about your heart&apos;s structure, function, and electrical system.
                
Holter or Event Monitor
                
A standard EKG only records the heartbeat for a few seconds. It won&apos;t detect heart rhythm problems that don&apos;t happen during the test. To diagnose problems that come and go, your doctor may have you wear a Holter or event monitor.
                
A Holter monitor records the hearts electrical activity for a full 24- or 48-hour period. You wear patches called electrodes on your chest. Wires connect the patches to a small, portable recorder. The recorder can be clipped to a belt, kept in a pocket, or hung around your neck.
                
During the 24- or 48-hour period, you do your usual daily activities. You use a notebook to record any symptoms you have and the time they occur. You then return both the recorder and the notebook to your doctor to read the results. Your doctor can see how your heart was beating at the time you had symptoms.
                
An event monitor is similar to a Holter monitor. You wear an event monitor while doing your normal activities. However, an event monitor only records your heart&apos;s electrical activity at certain times while you&apos;re wearing it.
                
For many event monitors, you push a button to start the monitor when you feel symptoms. Other event monitors start automatically when they sense abnormal heart rhythms.
                
You can wear an event monitor for weeks or until symptoms occur.
                
Holter or Event Monitor
                

                
Echocardiography
                
Echocardiography uses sound waves to create a moving picture of your heart. The picture shows the size and shape of your heart and how well your heart chambers and valves are working.
                
The test also can identify areas of poor blood flow to the heart, areas of heart muscle that aren&apos;t contracting normally, and previous injury to the heart muscle caused by poor blood flow.
                
Stress Test
                
Some heart problems are easier to diagnose when your heart is working hard and beating fast. During stress testing, you exercise to make your heart work hard and beat fast while heart tests are done. If you cant exercise, you may be given medicine to make your heart work hard and beat fast.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000063-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Heart Palpitations ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment for palpitations depends on their cause. Most palpitations are harmless and often go away on their own. In these cases, no treatment is needed.
                
Avoiding Triggers
                
Your palpitations may be harmless but bothersome. If so, your doctor may suggest avoiding things that trigger them. For examples, your doctor may advise you to:
                
Reduce anxiety and stress. Anxiety and stress (including panic attacks) are a common cause of harmless palpitations. Relaxation exercises, yoga or tai chi, biofeedback or guided imagery, or aromatherapy may help you relax.
                
Avoid or limit stimulants, such as caffeine, nicotine, or alcohol.
                
Avoid illegal drugs, such as cocaine and amphetamines.
                
Avoid medicines that act as stimulants, such as cough and cold medicines and some herbal and nutritional supplements.
                
Treating Medical Conditions That May Cause Palpitations
                
Work with your doctor to control medical conditions that can cause palpitations, such as an overactive thyroid. If you&apos;re taking medicine that&apos;s causing palpitations, your doctor will try to find a different medicine for you.
                
If your palpitations are caused by an arrhythmia (irregular heartbeat), your doctor may recommend medicines or procedures to treat the problem. For more information, go to the Health Topics Arrhythmia article.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000063-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Heart Palpitations ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can take steps to prevent palpitations. Try to avoid things that trigger them. For example:
                
Reduce anxiety and stress. Anxiety and stress (including panic attacks) are a common cause of harmless palpitations. Relaxation exercises, yoga or tai chi, biofeedback or guided imagery, or aromatherapy may help you relax.
                
Avoid or limit stimulants, such as caffeine, nicotine, or alcohol.
                
Avoid illegal drugs, such as cocaine and amphetamines.
                
Avoid medicines that act as stimulants, such as cough and cold medicines and some herbal and nutritional supplements.
                
Also, work with your doctor to treat medical conditions that can cause palpitations.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
