<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000002" source="NHLBI" url="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/anemia">
<Focus>Anemia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0002871</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000002-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Espaol
                
Anemia (uh-NEE-me-uh) is a condition in which your blood has a lower than normal number of red blood cells.
                
Anemia also can occur if your red blood cells don&apos;t contain enough hemoglobin (HEE-muh-glow-bin). Hemoglobin is an iron-rich protein that gives blood its red color. This protein helps red blood cells carry oxygen from the lungs to the rest of the body.
                
If you have anemia, your body doesn&apos;t get enough oxygen-rich blood. As a result, you may feel tired or weak. You also may have other symptoms, such as shortness of breath, dizziness, or headaches.
                
Severe or long-lasting anemia can damage your heart, brain, and other organs in your body. Very severe anemia may even cause death.
                
Overview
                
Blood is made up of many parts, including red blood cells, white blood cells, platelets (PLATE-lets), and plasma (the fluid portion of blood).
                
Red blood cells are disc-shaped and look like doughnuts without holes in the center. They carry oxygen and remove carbon dioxide (a waste product) from your body. These cells are made in the bone marrowa sponge-like tissue inside the bones.
                
White blood cells and platelets (PLATE-lets) also are made in the bone marrow. White blood cells help fight infection. Platelets stick together to seal small cuts or breaks on the blood vessel walls and stop bleeding. With some types of anemia, you may have low numbers of all three types of blood cells.
                
Anemia has three main causes: blood loss, lack of red blood cell production, or high rates of red blood cell destruction. These causes might be the result of diseases, conditions, or other factors.
                
Outlook
                
Many types of anemia can be mild, short term, and easily treated. You can even prevent some types with a healthy diet. Other types can be treated with dietary supplements.
                
However, certain types of anemia can be severe, long lasting, and even life threatening if not diagnosed and treated.
                
If you have signs or symptoms of anemia, see your doctor to find out whether you have the condition. Treatment will depend on the cause of the anemia and how severe it is.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000002-3" qtype="causes">What causes Anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The three main causes of anemia are:
                
Blood loss
                
Lack of red blood cell production
                
High rates of red blood cell destruction
                
For some people, the condition is caused by more than one of these factors.
                
Blood Loss
                
Blood loss is the most common cause of anemia, especially iron-deficiency anemia. Blood loss can be short term or persist over time.
                
Heavy menstrual periods or bleeding in the digestive or urinary tract can cause blood loss. Surgery, trauma, or cancer also can cause blood loss.
                
If a lot of blood is lost, the body may lose enough red blood cells to cause anemia.
                
Lack of Red Blood Cell Production
                
Both acquired and inherited conditions and factors can prevent your body from making enough red blood cells. &quot;Acquired&quot; means you aren&apos;t born with the condition, but you develop it. &quot;Inherited&quot; means your parents passed the gene for the condition on to you.
                
Acquired conditions and factors that can lead to anemia include poor diet, abnormal hormone levels, some chronic (ongoing) diseases, and pregnancy.
                
Aplastic anemia also can prevent your body from making enough red blood cells. This condition can be acquired or inherited.
                
Diet
                
A diet that lacks iron, folic acid (folate), or vitamin B12 can prevent your body from making enough red blood cells. Your body also needs small amounts of vitamin C, riboflavin, and copper to make red blood cells.
                
Conditions that make it hard for your body to absorb nutrients also can prevent your body from making enough red blood cells.
                
Hormones
                
Your body needs the hormone erythropoietin (eh-rith-ro-POY-eh-tin) to make red blood cells. This hormone stimulates the bone marrow to make these cells. A low level of this hormone can lead to anemia.
                
Diseases and Disease Treatments
                
Chronic diseases, like kidney disease and cancer, can make it hard for your body to make enough red blood cells.
                
Some cancer treatments may damage the bone marrow or damage the red blood cells&apos; ability to carry oxygen. If the bone marrow is damaged, it can&apos;t make red blood cells fast enough to replace the ones that die or are destroyed.
                
People who have HIV/AIDS may develop anemia due to infections or medicines used to treat their diseases.
                
Pregnancy
                
Anemia can occur during pregnancy due to low levels of iron and folic acid and changes in the blood.
                
During the first 6 months of pregnancy, the fluid portion of a woman&apos;s blood (the plasma) increases faster than the number of red blood cells. This dilutes the blood and can lead to anemia.
                
Aplastic Anemia
                
Some infants are born without the ability to make enough red blood cells. This condition is called aplastic anemia. Infants and children who have aplastic anemia often need blood transfusions to increase the number of red blood cells in their blood.
                
Acquired conditions or factors, such as certain medicines, toxins, and infectious diseases, also can cause aplastic anemia.
                
High Rates of Red Blood Cell Destruction
                
Both acquired and inherited conditions and factors can cause your body to destroy too many red blood cells. One example of an acquired condition is an enlarged or diseased spleen.
                
The spleen is an organ that removes wornout red blood cells from the body. If the spleen is enlarged or diseased, it may remove more red blood cells than normal, causing anemia.
                
Examples of inherited conditions that can cause your body to destroy too many red blood cells include sickle cell anemia, thalassemias, and lack of certain enzymes. These conditions create defects in the red blood cells that cause them to die faster than healthy red blood cells.
                
Hemolytic anemia is another example of a condition in which your body destroys too many red blood cells. Inherited or acquired conditions or factors can cause hemolytic anemia. Examples include immune disorders, infections, certain medicines, or reactions to blood transfusions.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000002-4" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Anemia? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anemia is a common condition. It occurs in all age, racial, and ethnic groups. Both men and women can have anemia. However, women of childbearing age are at higher risk for the condition because of blood loss from menstruation.
                
Anemia can develop during pregnancy due to low levels of iron and folic acid (folate) and changes in the blood. During the first 6 months of pregnancy, the fluid portion of a woman&apos;s blood (the plasma) increases faster than the number of red blood cells. This dilutes the blood and can lead to anemia.
                
During the first year of life, some babies are at risk for anemia because of iron deficiency. At-risk infants include those who are born too early and infants who are fed breast milk only or formula that isn&apos;t fortified with iron. These infants can develop iron deficiency by 6 months of age.
                
Infants between 1 and 2 years of age also are at risk for anemia. They may not get enough iron in their diets, especially if they drink a lot of cow&apos;s milk. Cow&apos;s milk is low in the iron needed for growth.
                
Drinking too much cow&apos;s milk may keep an infant or toddler from eating enough iron-rich foods or absorbing enough iron from foods.
                
Older adults also are at increased risk for anemia. Researchers continue to study how the condition affects older adults. Many of these people have other medical conditions as well.
                
Major Risk Factors
                
Factors that raise your risk for anemia include:
                
A diet that is low in iron, vitamins, or minerals
                
Blood loss from surgery or an injury
                
Long-term or serious illnesses, such as kidney disease, cancer, diabetes, rheumatoid arthritis, HIV/AIDS, inflammatory bowel disease (including Crohn&apos;s disease), liver disease, heart failure, and thyroid disease
                
Long-term infections
                
A family history of inherited anemia, such as sickle cell anemia or thalassemia</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000002-5" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The most common symptom of anemia is fatigue (feeling tired or weak). If you have anemia, you may find it hard to find the energy to do normal activities.
                
Other signs and symptoms of anemia include:
                
Shortness of breath
                
Dizziness
                
Headache
                
Coldness in the hands and feet
                
Pale skin
                
Chest pain
                
These signs and symptoms can occur because your heart has to work harder to pump oxygen-rich blood through your body.
                
Mild to moderate anemia may cause very mild symptoms or none at all.
                
Complications of Anemia
                
Some people who have anemia may have arrhythmias (ah-RITH-me-ahs). Arrhythmias are problems with the rate or rhythm of the heartbeat. Over time, arrhythmias can damage your heart and possibly lead to heart failure.
                
Anemia also can damage other organs in your body because your blood can&apos;t get enough oxygen to them.
                
Anemia can weaken people who have cancer or HIV/AIDS. This can make their treatments not work as well.
                
Anemia also can cause many other health problems. People who have kidney disease and anemia are more likely to have heart problems. With some types of anemia, too little fluid intake or too much loss of fluid in the blood and body can occur. Severe loss of fluid can be life threatening.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000002-6" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your doctor will diagnose anemia based on your medical and family histories, a physical exam, and results from tests and procedures.
                
Because anemia doesn&apos;t always cause symptoms, your doctor may find out you have it while checking for another condition.
                
Medical and Family Histories
                
Your doctor may ask whether you have any of the common signs or symptoms of anemia. He or she also may ask whether you&apos;ve had an illness or condition that could cause anemia.
                
Let your doctor know about any medicines you take, what you typically eat (your diet), and whether you have family members who have anemia or a history of it.
                
Physical Exam
                
Your doctor will do a physical exam to find out how severe your anemia is and to check for possible causes. He or she may:
                
Listen to your heart for a rapid or irregular heartbeat
                
Listen to your lungs for rapid or uneven breathing
                
Feel your abdomen to check the size of your liver and spleen
                
Your doctor also may do a pelvic or rectal exam to check for common sources of blood loss.
                
Diagnostic Tests and Procedures
                
You may have various blood tests and other tests or procedures to find out what type of anemia you have and how severe it is.
                
Complete Blood Count
                
Often, the first test used to diagnose anemia is a complete blood count (CBC). The CBC measures many parts of your blood.
                
The test checks your hemoglobin and hematocrit (hee-MAT-oh-crit) levels. Hemoglobin is the iron-rich protein in red blood cells that carries oxygen to the body. Hematocrit is a measure of how much space red blood cells take up in your blood. A low level of hemoglobin or hematocrit is a sign of anemia.
                
The normal range of these levels might be lower in certain racial and ethnic populations. Your doctor can explain your test results to you.
                
The CBC also checks the number of red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets in your blood. Abnormal results might be a sign of anemia, another blood disorder, an infection, or another condition.
                
Finally, the CBC looks at mean corpuscular (kor-PUS-kyu-lar) volume (MCV). MCV is a measure of the average size of your red blood cells and a clue as to the cause of your anemia. In iron-deficiency anemia, for example, red blood cells usually are smaller than normal.
                
Other Tests and Procedures
                
If the CBC results show that you have anemia, you may need other tests, such as:
                
Hemoglobin electrophoresis (e-lek-tro-FOR-e-sis). This test looks at the different types of hemoglobin in your blood. The test can help diagnose the type of anemia you have.
                
A reticulocyte (re-TIK-u-lo-site) count. This test measures the number of young red blood cells in your blood. The test shows whether your bone marrow is making red blood cells at the correct rate.
                
Tests for the level of iron in your blood and body. These tests include serum iron and serum ferritin tests. Transferrin level and total iron-binding capacity tests also measure iron levels.
                
Because anemia has many causes, you also might be tested for conditions such as kidney failure, lead poisoning (in children), and vitamin deficiencies (lack of vitamins, such as B12 and folic acid).
                
If your doctor thinks that you have anemia due to internal bleeding, he or she may suggest several tests to look for the source of the bleeding. A test to check the stool for blood might be done in your doctor&apos;s office or at home. Your doctor can give you a kit to help you get a sample at home. He or she will tell you to bring the sample back to the office or send it to a laboratory.
                
If blood is found in the stool, you may have other tests to find the source of the bleeding. One such test is endoscopy (en-DOS-ko-pe). For this test, a tube with a tiny camera is used to view the lining of the digestive tract.
                
Your doctor also may want to do bone marrow tests. These tests show whether your bone marrow is healthy and making enough blood cells.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000002-7" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment for anemia depends on the type, cause, and severity of the condition. Treatments may include dietary changes or supplements, medicines, procedures, or surgery to treat blood loss.
                
Goals of Treatment
                
The goal of treatment is to increase the amount of oxygen that your blood can carry. This is done by raising the red blood cell count and/or hemoglobin level. (Hemoglobin is the iron-rich protein in red blood cells that carries oxygen to the body.)
                
Another goal is to treat the underlying cause of the anemia.
                
Dietary Changes and Supplements
                
Low levels of vitamins or iron in the body can cause some types of anemia. These low levels might be the result of a poor diet or certain diseases or conditions.
                
To raise your vitamin or iron level, your doctor may ask you to change your diet or take vitamin or iron supplements. Common vitamin supplements are vitamin B12 and folic acid (folate). Vitamin C sometimes is given to help the body absorb iron.
                
Iron
                
Your body needs iron to make hemoglobin. Your body can more easily absorb iron from meats than from vegetables or other foods. To treat your anemia, your doctor may suggest eating more meatespecially red meat (such as beef or liver), as well as chicken, turkey, pork, fish, and shellfish.
                
Nonmeat foods that are good sources of iron include:
                
Spinach and other dark green leafy vegetables
                
Tofu
                
Peas; lentils; white, red, and baked beans; soybeans; and chickpeas
                
Dried fruits, such as prunes, raisins, and apricots
                
Prune juice
                
Iron-fortified cereals and breads
                
You can look at the Nutrition Facts label on packaged foods to find out how much iron the items contain. The amount is given as a percentage of the total amount of iron you need every day.
                
Iron also is available as a supplement. It&apos;s usually combined with multivitamins and other minerals that help your body absorb iron.
                
Doctors may recommend iron supplements for premature infants, infants and young children who drink a lot of cow&apos;s milk, and infants who are fed breast milk only or formula that isn&apos;t fortified with iron.
                
Large amounts of iron can be harmful, so take iron supplements only as your doctor prescribes.
                
Vitamin B12
                
Low levels of vitamin B12 can lead to pernicious anemia. This type of anemia often is treated with vitamin B12 supplements.
                
Good food sources of vitamin B12 include:
                
Breakfast cereals with added vitamin B12
                
Meats such as beef, liver, poultry, and fish
                
Eggs and dairy products (such as milk, yogurt, and cheese)
                
Foods fortified with vitamin B12, such as soy-based beverages and vegetarian burgers
                
Folic Acid
                
Folic acid (folate) is a form of vitamin B that&apos;s found in foods. Your body needs folic acid to make and maintain new cells. Folic acid also is very important for pregnant women. It helps them avoid anemia and promotes healthy growth of the fetus.
                
Good sources of folic acid include:
                
Bread, pasta, and rice with added folic acid
                
Spinach and other dark green leafy vegetables
                
Black-eyed peas and dried beans
                
Beef liver
                
Eggs
                
Bananas, oranges, orange juice, and some other fruits and juices
                
Vitamin C
                
Vitamin C helps the body absorb iron. Good sources of vitamin C are vegetables and fruits, especially citrus fruits. Citrus fruits include oranges, grapefruits, tangerines, and similar fruits. Fresh and frozen fruits, vegetables, and juices usually have more vitaminC than canned ones.
                
If you&apos;re taking medicines, ask your doctor or pharmacist whether you can eat grapefruit or drink grapefruit juice. This fruit can affect the strength of a few medicines and how well they work.
                
Other fruits rich in vitamin C include kiwi fruit, strawberries, and cantaloupes.
                
Vegetables rich in vitamin C include broccoli, peppers, Brussels sprouts, tomatoes, cabbage, potatoes, and leafy green vegetables like turnip greens and spinach.
                
Medicines
                
Your doctor may prescribe medicines to help your body make more red blood cells or to treat an underlying cause of anemia. Some of these medicines include:
                
Antibiotics to treat infections.
                
Hormones to treat heavy menstrual bleeding in teenaged and adult women.
                
A man-made version of erythropoietin to stimulate your body to make more red blood cells. This hormone has some risks. You and your doctor will decide whether the benefits of this treatment outweigh the risks.
                
Medicines to prevent the body&apos;s immune system from destroying its own red blood cells.
                
Chelation (ke-LAY-shun) therapy for lead poisoning. Chelation therapy is used mainly in children. This is because children who have iron-deficiency anemia are at increased risk of lead poisoning.
                
Procedures
                
If your anemia is severe, your doctor may recommend a medical procedure. Procedures include blood transfusions and blood and marrow stem cell transplants.
                
Blood Transfusion
                
A blood transfusion is a safe, common procedure in which blood is given to you through an intravenous (IV) line in one of your blood vessels. Transfusions require careful matching of donated blood with the recipient&apos;s blood.
                
For more information, go to the Health Topics Blood Transfusion article.
                
Blood and Marrow Stem Cell Transplant
                
A blood and marrow stem cell transplant replaces your faulty stem cells with healthy ones from another person (a donor). Stem cells are made in the bone marrow. They develop into red and white blood cells and platelets.
                
During the transplant, which is like a blood transfusion, you get donated stem cells through a tube placed in a vein in your chest. Once the stem cells are in your body, they travel to your bone marrow and begin making new blood cells.
                
For more information, go to the Health Topics Blood and Marrow Stem Cell Transplant article.
                
Surgery
                
If you have serious or life-threatening bleeding that&apos;s causing anemia, you may need surgery. For example, you may need surgery to control ongoing bleeding due to a stomach ulcer or colon cancer.
                
If your body is destroying red blood cells at a high rate, you may need to have your spleen removed. The spleen is an organ that removes wornout red blood cells from the body. An enlarged or diseased spleen may remove more red blood cells than normal, causing anemia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000002-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>You might be able to prevent repeat episodes of some types of anemia, especially those caused by lack of iron or vitamins. Dietary changes or supplements can prevent these types of anemia from occurring again.
                
Treating anemia&apos;s underlying cause may prevent the condition (or prevent repeat episodes). For example, if medicine is causing your anemia, your doctor may prescribe another type of medicine.
                
To prevent anemia from getting worse, tell your doctor about all of your signs and symptoms. Talk with your doctor about the tests you may need and follow your treatment plan.
                
You can&apos;t prevent some types of inherited anemia, such as sickle cell anemia. If you have an inherited anemia, talk with your doctor about treatment and ongoing care.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
