<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000125" source="NHLBI" url="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/scda">
<Focus>Sudden Cardiac Arrest</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1720824</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000125-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sudden Cardiac Arrest ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sudden cardiac arrest (SCA) is a condition in which the heart suddenly and unexpectedly stops beating. If this happens, blood stops flowing to the brain and other vital organs.
                
SCA usually causes death if it&apos;s not treated within minutes.
                
Overview
                
To understand SCA, it helps to understand how the heart works. The heart has an electrical system that controls the rate and rhythm of the heartbeat. Problems with the heart&apos;s electrical system can cause irregular heartbeats called arrhythmias.
                
There are many types of arrhythmias. During an arrhythmia, the heart can beat too fast, too slow, or with an irregular rhythm. Some arrhythmias can cause the heart to stop pumping blood to the bodythese arrhythmias cause SCA.
                
SCA is not the same as a heart attack. A heart attack occurs if blood flow to part of the heart muscle is blocked. During a heart attack, the heart usually doesn&apos;t suddenly stop beating. SCA, however, may happen after or during recovery from a heart attack.
                
People who have heart disease are at higher risk for SCA. However, SCA can happen in people who appear healthy and have no known heart disease or other risk factors for SCA.
                
Outlook
                
Most people who have SCA die from itoften within minutes. Rapid treatment of SCA with a defibrillator can be lifesaving. A defibrillator is a device that sends an electric shock to the heart to try to restore its normal rhythm.
                
Automated external defibrillators (AEDs) can be used by bystanders to save the lives of people who are having SCA. These portable devices often are found in public places, such as shopping malls, golf courses, businesses, airports, airplanes, casinos, convention centers, hotels, sports venues, and schools.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000125-2" qtype="causes">What causes Sudden Cardiac Arrest ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ventricular fibrillation (v-fib) causes most sudden cardiac arrests (SCAs). V-fib is a type of arrhythmia.
                
During v-fib, the ventricles (the heart&apos;s lower chambers) don&apos;t beat normally. Instead, they quiver very rapidly and irregularly. When this happens, the heart pumps little or no blood to the body. V-fib is fatal if not treated within a few minutes.
                
Other problems with the heart&apos;s electrical system also can cause SCA. For example, SCA can occur if the rate of the heart&apos;s electrical signals becomes very slow and stops. SCA also can occur if the heart muscle doesn&apos;t respond to the heart&apos;s electrical signals.
                
Certain diseases and conditions can cause the electrical problems that lead to SCA. Examples include coronary heart disease (CHD), also called coronary artery disease; severe physical stress; certain inherited disorders; and structural changes in the heart.
                
Several research studies are under way to try to find the exact causes of SCA and how to prevent them.
                
Coronary Heart Disease
                
CHD is a disease in which a waxy substance called plaque (plak) builds up in the coronary arteries. These arteries supply oxygen-rich blood to your heart muscle.
                
Plaque narrows the arteries and reduces blood flow to your heart muscle. Eventually, an area of plaque can rupture (break open). This may cause a blood clot to form on the plaque&apos;s surface.
                
A blood clot can partly or fully block the flow of oxygen-rich blood to the portion of heart muscle fed by the artery. This causes a heart attack.
                
During a heart attack, some heart muscle cells die and are replaced with scar tissue. The scar tissue damages the heart&apos;s electrical system. As a result, electrical signals may spread abnormally throughout the heart. These changes to the heart increase the risk of dangerous arrhythmias and SCA.
                
CHD seems to cause most cases of SCA in adults. Many of these adults, however, have no signs or symptoms of CHD before having SCA.
                
Physical Stress
                
Certain types of physical stress can cause your heart&apos;s electrical system to fail. Examples include:
                
Intense physical activity. The hormone adrenaline is released during intense physical activity. This hormone can trigger SCA in people who have heart problems.
                
Very low blood levels of potassium or magnesium. These minerals play an important role in your heart&apos;s electrical signaling.
                
Major blood loss.
                
Severe lack of oxygen.
                
Inherited Disorders
                
A tendency to have arrhythmias runs in some families. This tendency is inherited, which means it&apos;s passed from parents to children through the genes. Members of these families may be at higher risk for SCA.
                
An example of an inherited disorder that makes you more likely to have arrhythmias is long QT syndrome (LQTS). LQTS is a disorder of the heart&apos;s electrical activity. Problems with tiny pores on the surface of heart muscle cells cause the disorder. LQTS can cause sudden, uncontrollable, dangerous heart rhythms.
                
People who inherit structural heart problems also may be at higher risk for SCA. These types of problems often are the cause of SCA in children.
                
Structural Changes in the Heart
                
Changes in the heart&apos;s normal size or structure may affect its electrical system. Examples of such changes include an enlarged heart due to high blood pressure or advanced heart disease. Heart infections also may cause structural changes in the heart.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000125-3" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Sudden Cardiac Arrest? ?</Question>
			<Answer>The risk of sudden cardiac arrest (SCA) increases:
                
With age
                
If you are a man. Men are more likely than women to have SCA.
                
Some studies show that blacksparticularly those with underlying conditions such as diabetes, high blood pressure, heart failure, and chronic kidney disease or certain cardiac findings on tests such as an electrocardiogramhave a higher risk forSCA.
                
Major Risk Factor
                
The major risk factor for SCA is coronary heart disease. Most people who have SCA have some degree of coronary heart disease; however, many people may not know that they have coronary heart disease until SCA occurs. Usually their coronary heart disease is silentthat is, it has no signs or symptoms. Because of this, doctors and nurses have not detected it.
                
Many people who have SCA also have silent, or undiagnosed, heart attacks before sudden cardiac arrest happens. These people have no clear signs of heart attack, and they dont even realize that theyve had one. Read more about coronary heart disease risk factors.
                
Other Risk Factors
                
Other risk factors for SCA include:
                
A personal history of arrhythmias
                
A personal or family history of SCA or inherited disorders that make you prone toarrhythmias
                
Drug or alcohol abuse
                
Heart attack
                
Heart failure</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000125-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sudden Cardiac Arrest ?</Question>
			<Answer>Usually, the first sign of sudden cardiac arrest (SCA) is loss of consciousness (fainting). At the same time, no heartbeat (or pulse) can be felt.
                
Some people may have a racing heartbeat or feel dizzy or light-headed just before they faint. Within an hour before SCA, some people have chest pain, shortness of breath, nausea (feeling sick to the stomach), or vomiting.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000125-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Sudden Cardiac Arrest ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sudden cardiac arrest (SCA) happens without warning and requires emergency treatment. Doctors rarely diagnose SCA with medical tests as it&apos;s happening. Instead, SCA often is diagnosed after it happens. Doctors do this by ruling out other causes of a person&apos;s sudden collapse.
                
Specialists Involved
                
If you&apos;re at high risk for SCA, your doctor may refer you to a cardiologist. This is a doctor who specializes in diagnosing and treating heart diseases and conditions. Your cardiologist will work with you to decide whether you need treatment to prevent SCA.
                
Some cardiologists specialize in problems with the heart&apos;s electrical system. These specialists are called cardiac electrophysiologists.
                
Diagnostic Tests and Procedures
                
Doctors use several tests to help detect the factors that put people at risk for SCA.
                
EKG (Electrocardiogram)
                
An EKG is a simple, painless test that detects and records the heart&apos;s electrical activity. The test shows how fast the heart is beating and its rhythm (steady or irregular). An EKG also records the strength and timing of electrical signals as they pass through each part of the heart.
                
An EKG can show evidence of heart damage due to coronary heart disease (CHD). The test also can show signs of a previous or current heart attack.
                
Echocardiography
                
Echocardiography, or echo, is a painless test that uses sound waves to create pictures of your heart. The test shows the size and shape of your heart and how well your heart chambers and valves are working.
                
Echo also can identify areas of poor blood flow to the heart, areas of heart muscle that aren&apos;t contracting normally, and previous injury to the heart muscle caused by poor blood flow.
                
There are several types of echo, including stress echo. This test is done both before and after a cardiac stress test. During this test, you exercise (or are given medicine if you&apos;re unable to exercise) to make your heart work hard and beat fast.
                
Stress echo shows whether you have decreased blood flow to your heart (a sign of CHD).
                
MUGA Test or Cardiac MRI
                
A MUGA (multiple gated acquisition) test shows how well your heart is pumping blood. For this test, a small amount of radioactive substance is injected into a vein and travels to your heart.
                
The substance releases energy, which special cameras outside of your body can detect. The cameras use the energy to create pictures of many parts of your heart.
                
Cardiac MRI (magnetic resonance imaging) is a safe procedure that uses radio waves and magnets to create detailed pictures of your heart. The test creates still and moving pictures of your heart and major blood vessels.
                
Doctors use cardiac MRI to get pictures of the beating heart and to look at the structure and function of the heart.
                
Cardiac Catheterization
                
Cardiac catheterization is a procedure used to diagnose and treat certain heart conditions. A long, thin, flexible tube called a catheter is put into a blood vessel in your arm, groin (upper thigh), or neck and threaded to your heart. Through the catheter, your doctor can do diagnostic tests and treatments on your heart.
                
Sometimes dye is put into the catheter. The dye will flow through your bloodstream to your heart. The dye makes your coronary (heart) arteries visible on x-ray pictures. The dye can show whether plaque has narrowed or blocked any of your coronary arteries.
                
Electrophysiology Study
                
For an electrophysiology study, doctors use cardiac catheterization to record how your heart&apos;s electrical system responds to certain medicines and electrical stimulation. This helps your doctor find where the heart&apos;s electrical system is damaged.
                
Blood Tests
                
Your doctor may recommend blood tests to check the levels of potassium, magnesium, and other chemicals in your blood. These chemicals play an important role in your heart&apos;s electrical signaling.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000125-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Sudden Cardiac Arrest ?</Question>
			<Answer>Emergency Treatment
                
Sudden cardiac arrest (SCA) is an emergency. A person having SCA needs to be treated with a defibrillator right away. This device sends an electric shock to the heart. The electric shock can restore a normal rhythm to a heart that&apos;s stopped beating.
                
To work well, defibrillation must be done within minutes of SCA. With every minute that passes, the chances of surviving SCA drop rapidly.
                
Police, emergency medical technicians, and other first responders usually are trained and equipped to use a defibrillator. Call 911 right away if someone has signs or symptoms of SCA. The sooner you call for help, the sooner lifesaving treatment can begin.
                
Automated External Defibrillators
                
Automated external defibrillators (AEDs) are special defibrillators that untrained bystanders can use. These portable devices often are found in public places, such as shopping malls, golf courses, businesses, airports, airplanes, casinos, convention centers, hotels, sports venues, and schools.
                
AEDs are programmed to give an electric shock if they detect a dangerous arrhythmia, such as ventricular fibrillation. This prevents giving a shock to someone who may have fainted but isn&apos;t having SCA.
                
You should give cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) to a person having SCA until defibrillation can be done.
                
People who are at risk for SCA may want to consider having an AED at home. A 2008 study by the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute and the National Institutes of Health found that AEDs in the home are safe and effective.
                
Some people feel that placing these devices in homes will save many lives because many SCAs occur at home.Others note that no evidence supports the idea that home-use AEDs save more lives. These people fear that people who have AEDs in their homes will delay calling for help during an emergency. They&apos;re also concerned that people who have home-use AEDs will not properly maintain the devices or forget where they are.
                
When considering a home-use AED, talk with your doctor. He or she can help you decide whether having an AED in your home will benefit you.
                
Treatment in a Hospital
                
If you survive SCA, you&apos;ll likely be admitted to a hospital for ongoing care and treatment. In the hospital, your medical team will closely watch your heart. They may give you medicines to try to reduce the risk of another SCA.
                
While in the hospital, your medical team will try to find out what caused your SCA. If you&apos;re diagnosed with coronary heart disease, you may havepercutaneous coronary intervention, also known as coronary angioplasty,or coronary artery bypass grafting. These procedures help restore blood flow through narrowed or blocked coronary arteries.
                
Often, people who have SCA get a device called an implantable cardioverter defibrillator (ICD). This small device is surgically placed under the skin in your chest or abdomen. An ICD uses electric pulses or shocks to help control dangerous arrhythmias. (For more information, go to &quot;How Can Death Due to Sudden Cardiac Arrest Be Prevented?&quot;)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000125-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Sudden Cardiac Arrest ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ways to prevent death due to sudden cardiac arrest (SCA) differ depending on whether:
                
You&apos;ve already had SCA
                
You&apos;ve never had SCA but are at high risk for the condition
                
You&apos;ve never had SCA and have no known risk factors for the condition
                
For People Who Have Survived Sudden Cardiac Arrest
                
If you&apos;ve already had SCA, you&apos;re at high risk of having it again. Research shows that an implantable cardioverter defibrillator (ICD) reduces the chances of dying from a second SCA.An ICD is surgically placed under the skin in your chest or abdomen. The device has wires with electrodes on the ends that connect to your heart&apos;s chambers. The ICD monitors your heartbeat.
                
If the ICD detects a dangerous heart rhythm, it gives an electric shock to restore the heart&apos;s normal rhythm. Your doctor may give you medicine to limit irregular heartbeats that can trigger the ICD.
                
Implantable Cardioverter Defibrillator
                

                
An ICD isn&apos;t the same as a pacemaker. The devices are similar, but they have some differences. Pacemakers give off low-energy electrical pulses. They&apos;re often used to treat less dangerous heart rhythms, such as those that occur in the upper chambers of the heart. Most new ICDs work as both pacemakers and ICDs.
                
For People at High Risk for a First Sudden Cardiac Arrest
                
If you have severe coronary heart disease (CHD), you&apos;re at increased risk for SCA. This is especially true if you&apos;ve recently had a heart attack.
                
Your doctor may prescribe a type of medicine called a beta blocker to help lower your risk for SCA. Your doctor also may discuss beginning statin treatment if you have an elevated risk for developing heart disease or having a stroke. Doctors usually prescribe statins for people who have:
                
Diabetes
                
Heart disease or had a prior stroke
                
High LDL cholesterol levels
                
Your doctor also may prescribe other medications to:
                
Decrease your chance of having a heart attack or dying suddenly.
                
Lower blood pressure.
                
Prevent blood clots, which can lead to heart attack or stroke.
                
Prevent or delay the need for a procedure or surgery, such as angioplasty or coronary artery bypass grafting.
                
Reduce your hearts workload and relieve coronary heart disease symptoms.
                
Take all medicines regularly, as your doctor prescribes. Dont change the amount of your medicine or skip a dose unless your doctor tells you to. You should still follow a heart-healthy lifestyle, even if you take medicines to treat your coronary heart disease.
                
Other treatments for coronary heart diseasesuch as percutaneous coronary intervention, also known as coronary angioplasty, or coronary artery bypass graftingalso may lower your risk for SCA. Your doctor also may recommend an ICD if youre at high risk for SCA.
                
For People Who Have No Known Risk Factors for Sudden Cardiac Arrest
                
CHD seems to be the cause of most SCAs in adults. CHD also is a major risk factor for angina (chest pain or discomfort) and heart attack, and it contributes to other heart problems.
                
Following a healthy lifestyle can help you lower your risk for CHD, SCA, and other heart problems. A heart-healthy lifestyle includes:
                
Heart-healthy eating
                
Maintaining a healthy weight
                
Managing stress
                
Physical activity
                
Quitting smoking
                
Heart-Healthy Eating
                
Heart-healthy eating is an important part of a heart-healthy lifestyle. Your doctor may recommend heart-healthy eating, which should include:
                
Fat-free or low-fat dairy products, such as skim milk
                
Fish high in omega-3 fatty acids, such as salmon, tuna, and trout, about twice a week
                
Fruits, such as apples, bananas, oranges, pears, and prunes
                
Legumes, such as kidney beans, lentils, chickpeas, black-eyed peas, and lima beans
                
Vegetables, such as broccoli, cabbage, and carrots
                
Whole grains, such as oatmeal, brown rice, and corn tortillas
                
When following a heart-healthy diet, you should avoid eating:
                
A lot of red meat
                
Palm and coconut oils
                
Sugary foods and beverages
                
Two nutrients in your diet make blood cholesterol levels rise:
                
Saturated fatfound mostly in foods that come from animals
                
Trans fat (trans fatty acids)found in foods made with hydrogenated oils and fats, such as stick margarine; baked goods, such as cookies, cakes, and pies; crackers; frostings; and coffee creamers. Some trans fats also occur naturally in animal fats and meats.
                
Saturated fat raises your blood cholesterol more than anything else in your diet. When you follow a heart-healthy eating plan, only 5percent to 6percent of your daily calories should come from saturated fat. Food labels list the amounts of saturated fat. To help you stay on track, here are some examples:
                
If you eat:
                
Try to eat no more than:
                
1,200 calories a day              
                
8 grams of saturated fat a day    
                
1,500 calories a day           
                
10 grams of saturated fat a day
                
1,800 calories a day           
                
12 grams of saturated fat a day
                
2,000 calories a day           
                
13 grams of saturated fat a day
                
2,500 calories a day           
                
17 grams of saturated fat a day
                
Not all fats are bad. Monounsaturated and polyunsaturated fats actually help lower blood cholesterol levels. Some sources of monounsaturated and polyunsaturated fats are:
                
Avocados
                
Corn, sunflower, and soybean oils
                
Nuts and seeds, such as walnuts
                
Olive, canola, peanut, safflower, and sesame oils
                
Peanut butter
                
Salmon and trout
                
Tofu
                
Sodium
                
You should try to limit the amount of sodium that you eat. This means choosing and preparing foods that are lower in salt and sodium. Try to use low-sodium and no added salt foods and seasonings at the table or while cooking. Food labels tell you what you need to know about choosing foods that are lower in sodium. Try to eat no more than 2,300milligrams of sodium a day. If you have high blood pressure, you may need to restrict your sodium intake even more.
                
Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension
                
Your doctor may recommend the Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension (DASH) eating plan if you have high blood pressure. The DASH eating plan focuses on fruits, vegetables, whole grains, and other foods that are heart healthy and low in fat, cholesterol, and sodium and salt.
                
The DASH eating plan is a good heart-healthy eating plan, even for those who dont have high blood pressure. Read more about DASH.
                
Limiting Alcohol
                
Try to limit alcohol intake. Too much alcohol can raise your blood pressure and triglyceride levels, a type of fat found in the blood. Alcohol also adds extra calories, which may cause weight gain.
                
Men should have no more than two drinks containing alcohol a day. Women should have no more than one drink containing alcohol a day. One drink is:
                
12 ounces of beer
                
5 ounces of wine
                
1 ounces of liquor
                
Maintaining a Healthy Weight
                
Maintaining a healthy weight is important for overall health and can lower your risk for sudden cardiac arrest. Aim for a Healthy Weight by following a heart-healthy eating plan and keeping physically active.
                
Knowing your body mass index (BMI) helps you find out if youre a healthy weight in relation to your height and gives an estimate of your total body fat. To figure out your BMI, check out the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institutes online BMI calculator or talk to your doctor. A BMI:
                
Below 18.5 is a sign that you are underweight.
                
Between 18.5 and 24.9 is in the normal range
                
Between 25.0 and 29.9 is considered overweight
                
Of 30.0 or higher is considered obese
                
A general goal to aim for is a BMI of less than 25. Your doctor or health care provider can help you set an appropriate BMI goal.
                
Measuring waist circumference helps screen for possible health risks. If most of your fat is around your waist rather than at your hips, youre at a higher risk for heart disease and type2 diabetes. This risk may be higher with a waist size that is greater than 35 inches for women or greater than 40 inches for men. To learn how to measure your waist, visit Assessing Your Weight and Health Risk.
                
If youre overweight or obese, try to lose weight. A loss of just 3percent to 5percent of your current weight can lower your triglycerides, blood glucose, and the risk of developing type2 diabetes. Greater amounts of weight loss can improve blood pressure readings, lower LDL cholesterol, and increase HDL cholesterol.
                
Managing Stress
                
Managing and coping with stress. Learning how to manage stress, relax, and cope with problems can improve your emotional and physical health. Consider healthy stress-reducing activities, such as:
                
A stress management program
                
Meditation
                
Physical activity
                
Relaxation therapy
                
Talking things out with friends or family
                
Physical Activity
                
Regular physical activity can lower your risk for coronary heart disease, sudden cardiac arrest, and other health problems. Everyone should try to participate in moderate-intensity aerobic exercise at least 2hours and 30minutes per week or vigorous aerobic exercise for 1hour and 15minutes per week. Aerobic exercise, such as brisk walking, is any exercise in which your heart beats faster and you use more oxygen than usual. The more active you are, the more you will benefit. Participate in aerobic exercise for at least 10minutes at a time spread throughout the week.
                
Talk with your doctor before you start a new exercise plan. Ask your doctor how much and what kinds of physical activity are safe for you.
                
Read more about physical activity at:
                
Physical Activity and Your Heart
                
U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, 2008 Physical Activity Guidelines for Americans
                
Quitting Smoking
                
People who smoke are more likely to have a heart attack than are people who dont smoke. The risk of having a heart attack increases with the number of cigarettes smoked each day. Smoking also raises your risk for stroke and lung diseases, such as chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and lung cancer.
                
Quitting smoking can greatly reduce your risk for heart and lung diseases. Ask your doctor about programs and products that can help you quit. Also, try to avoid secondhand smoke. If you have trouble quitting smoking on your own, consider joining a support group. Many hospitals, workplaces, and community groups offer classes to help people quit smoking. Read more about how to quit smoking.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
