<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000096" source="NHLBI" url="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/oxt">
<Focus>Oxygen Therapy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1546419</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000096-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Oxygen Therapy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Oxygen therapy is a treatment that provides you with extra oxygen, a gas that your body needs to work well. Normally, your lungs absorb oxygen from the air. However, some diseases and conditions can prevent you from getting enough oxygen.
                
Oxygen therapy may help you function better and be more active. Oxygen is supplied in a metal cylinder or other container. It flows through a tube and is delivered to your lungs in one of the following ways:
                
Through a nasal cannula, which consists of two small plastic tubes, or prongs, that are placed in both nostrils.
                
Through a face mask, which fits over your nose and mouth.
                
Through a small tube inserted into your windpipe through the front of your neck. Your doctor will use a needle or small incision (cut) to place the tube. Oxygen delivered this way is called transtracheal oxygen therapy.
                
Oxygen therapy can be done in a hospital, another medical setting, or at home. If you need oxygen therapy for a chronic (ongoing) disease or condition, you might receive home oxygen therapy.
                
Overview
                
To learn how oxygen therapy works, it helps to understand how your respiratory system works. This system is a group of organs and tissues that help you breathe. The respiratory system includes the airways and lungs.
                
The airways carry oxygen-rich air to your lungs. They also carry carbon dioxide (a waste gas) out of your lungs.
                
Air enters your body through your nose or mouth, which moistens and warms the air. The air then travels through your voice box and down your windpipe. The windpipe divides into two tubes called bronchi that enter your lungs.
                
Within your lungs, your bronchi branch into thousands of smaller, thinner tubes called bronchioles (BRONG-ke-ols). These tubes end in bunches of tiny round air sacs called alveoli (al-VEE-uhl-eye).
                
Each of the air sacs is covered in a mesh of tiny blood vessels called capillaries (KAP-ih-lare-ees). The capillaries connect to a network of arteries and veins that move blood throughout your body.
                
When air reaches the air sacs, the oxygen in the air passes through the air sac walls into the blood in the capillaries.
                
The oxygen-rich blood then travels to the heart through the pulmonary vein and its branches. The heart pumps the oxygen-rich blood to your organs. (For more information, go to the Health Topics How the Lungs Work article.)
                
Certain acute (short-term) and chronic (ongoing) diseases and conditions can affect the transfer of oxygen from the alveoli into the blood. Examples include pneumonia (nu-MO-ne-ah) and COPD (chronic obstructive pulmonary disease).
                
Your doctor will decide whether you need oxygen therapy based on the results of tests, such as an arterial blood gas test and a pulse oximetry test. These tests measure how much oxygen is in your blood. A low oxygen level is a sign that you need oxygen therapy.
                
Oxygen is considered a medicine, so your doctor must prescribe it.
                
Outlook
                
Oxygen therapy helps many people function better and be more active. It also may help:
                
Decrease shortness of breath and fatigue (tiredness)
                
Improve sleep in some people who have sleep-related breathing disorders
                
Increase the lifespan of some people who have COPD
                
Although you may need oxygen therapy long term, it doesn&apos;t have to limit your daily routine. Portable oxygen units can make it easier for you to move around and do many daily activities. Talk with your doctor if you have questions about whether certain activities are safe for you.
                
A home equipment provider will work with you to make sure you have the supplies and equipment you need. Trained staff also will show you how to use the equipment correctly and safely.
                
Oxygen therapy generally is safe, but it can pose a fire hazard. To use your oxygen safely, follow the instructions you receive from your home equipment provider.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000096-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Oxygen Therapy ?</Question>
			<Answer>During an emergencysuch as a serious accident, possible heart attack, or other life-threatening eventyou might be started on oxygen therapy right away.
                
Otherwise, your doctor will decide whether you need oxygen therapy based on test results. An arterial blood gas test and a pulse oximetry test can measure the amount of oxygen in your blood.
                
For an arterial blood gas test, a small needle is inserted into an artery, usually in your wrist. A sample of blood is taken from the artery. The sample is then sent to a laboratory, where its oxygen level is measured.
                
For a pulse oximetry test, a small sensor is attached to your fingertip or toe. The sensor uses light to estimate how much oxygen is in your blood.
                
If the tests show that your blood oxygen level is low, your doctor may prescribe oxygen therapy. In the prescription, your doctor will include the number of liters of oxygen per minute that you need (oxygen flow rate). He or she also will include how often you need to use the oxygen (frequency of use).
                
Frequency of use includes when and for how long you should use the oxygen. Depending on your condition and blood oxygen level, you may need oxygen only at certain times, such as during sleep or while exercising.
                
If your doctor prescribes home oxygen therapy, he or she can help you find a home equipment provider. The provider will give you the equipment and other supplies you need.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000096-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Oxygen Therapy ?</Question>
			<Answer>During an emergencysuch as a serious accident, possible heart attack, or other life-threatening eventyou might be started on oxygen therapy right away.
                
While you&apos;re in the hospital, your doctor will check on you to make sure you&apos;re getting the right amount of oxygen. Nurses or respiratory therapists also may assist with the oxygen therapy.
                
If you&apos;re having oxygen therapy at home, a home equipment provider will help you set up the oxygen therapy equipment at your house.
                
Trained staff will show you how to use and take care of the equipment. They&apos;ll supply the oxygen and teach you how to safely handle it.
                
Because oxygen poses a fire risk, you&apos;ll need to take certain safety steps. Oxygen isn&apos;t explosive, but it can worsen a fire. In the presence of oxygen, a small fire can quickly get out of control. Also, the cylinder that compressed oxygen gas comes in can explode if it&apos;s exposed to heat.
                
Your home equipment provider will give you a complete list of safety steps that you&apos;ll need to follow at home and in public. For example, while on oxygen, you should:
                
Never smoke or be around people who are smoking
                
Never use paint thinners, cleaning fluids, gasoline, aerosol sprays, and other flammable materials
                
Stay at least 5 feet away from gas stoves, candles, and other heat sources
                
When you&apos;re not using the oxygen, keep it in a large, airy room. Never store compressed oxygen gas cylinders and liquid oxygen containers in small, enclosed places, such as in closets, behind curtains, or under clothes.
                
Oxygen containers let off small amounts of oxygen. These small amounts can build up to harmful levels if they&apos;re allowed to escape into small spaces.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000096-7" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Oxygen Therapy? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Oxygen therapy can cause complications and side effects. These problems might include a dry or bloody nose, skin irritation from the nasal cannula or face mask, fatigue (tiredness), and morning headaches.
                
If these problems persist, tell your doctor and home equipment provider. Depending on the problem, your doctor may need to change your oxygen flow rate or the length of time you&apos;re using the oxygen.
                
If nose dryness is a problem, your doctor may recommend a nasal spray or have a humidifier added to your oxygen equipment.
                
If you have an uncomfortable nasal cannula or face mask, your home equipment provider can help you find a device that fits better. Your provider also can recommend over-the-counter gels and devices that are designed to lessen skin irritation.
                
Complications from transtracheal oxygen therapy can be more serious. With this type of oxygen therapy, oxygen is delivered through a tube inserted into your windpipe through the front of your neck.
                
With transtracheal oxygen therapy:
                
Mucus balls might develop on the tube inside the windpipe. Mucus balls tend to form as a result of the oxygen drying out the airways. Mucus balls can cause coughing and clog the windpipe or tube.
                
Problems with the tube slipping or breaking.
                
Infection.
                
Injury to the lining of the windpipe.
                
Proper medical care and correct handling of the tube and other supplies may reduce the risk of complications.
                
Other Risks
                
In certain people, oxygen therapy may suppress the drive to breathe, affecting how well the respiratory system works. This is managed by adjusting the oxygen flow rate.
                
Oxygen poses a fire risk, so you&apos;ll need to take certain safety steps. Oxygen itself isn&apos;t explosive, but it can worsen a fire. In the presence of oxygen, a small fire can quickly get out of control. Also, the cylinder that compressed oxygen gas comes in might explode if exposed to heat.
                
Your home equipment provider will give you a complete list of safety steps you&apos;ll need to take at home and when out in public.
                
For example, when you&apos;re not using the oxygen, keep it in an airy room. Never store compressed oxygen gas cylinders and liquid oxygen containers in small, enclosed places, such as in closets, behind curtains, or under clothes.
                
Oxygen containers let off small amounts of oxygen. These small amounts can build up to harmful levels if they&apos;re allowed to escape into small spaces.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
