<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000136" source="NHLBI" url="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/vas">
<Focus>Vasculitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1963274</CUI>
			<CUI>C0042384</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000136-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Vasculitis (vas-kyu-LI-tis) is a condition that involves inflammation in the blood vessels. The condition occurs if your immune system attacks your blood vessels by mistake. This may happen as the result of an infection, a medicine, or another disease or condition.
                
Inflammation refers to the bodys response to injury, including injury to the blood vessels. Inflammation may involve pain, redness, warmth, swelling, and loss of function in the affected tissues.
                
In vasculitis, inflammation can lead to serious problems. Complications depend on which blood vessels, organs, or other body systems are affected.
                
Overview
                
Vasculitis can affect any of the body&apos;s blood vessels. These include arteries, veins, and capillaries. Arteries carry blood from your heart to your body&apos;s organs. Veins carry blood from your organs and limbs back to your heart. Capillaries connect the small arteries and veins.
                
If a blood vessel is inflamed, it can narrow or close off. This limits or prevents blood flow through the vessel. Rarely, the blood vessel will stretch and weaken, causing it to bulge. This bulge is known as an aneurysm (AN-u-rism).
                
Vasculitis
                

                
The disruption in blood flow caused by inflammation can damage the body&apos;s organs. Signs and symptoms depend on which organs have been damaged and the extent of the damage.
                
Typical symptoms of inflammation, such as fever and general aches and pains, are common among people who have vasculitis.
                
Outlook
                
There are many types of vasculitis, but overall the condition is rare. If you have vasculitis, the outlook depends on:
                
The type of vasculitis you have
                
Which organs are affected
                
How quickly the condition worsens
                
The severity of the condition
                
Treatment often works well if its started early. In some cases, vasculitis may go into remission. &quot;Remission&quot; means the condition isn&apos;t active, but it can come back, or &quot;flare,&quot; at any time.
                
Sometimes vasculitis is chronic (ongoing) and never goes into remission. Long-term treatment with medicines often can control the signs and symptoms of chronic vasculitis.
                
Rarely, vasculitis doesn&apos;t respond well to treatment. This can lead to disability and even death.
                
Much is still unknown about vasculitis. However, researchers continue to learn more about the condition and its various types, causes, and treatments.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000136-4" qtype="causes">What causes Vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Vasculitis occurs if your immune system attacks your blood vessels by mistake. What causes this to happen isn&apos;t fully known.
                
A recent or chronic (ongoing) infection may prompt the attack. Your body also may attack its own blood vessels in reaction to a medicine.
                
Sometimes an autoimmune disorder triggers vasculitis. Autoimmune disorders occur if the immune system makes antibodies (proteins) that attack and damage the body&apos;s own tissues or cells. Examples of these disorders include lupus, rheumatoid arthritis, and scleroderma. You can have these disorders for years before developing vasculitis.
                
Vasculitis also may be linked to certain blood cancers, such as leukemia and lymphoma.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000136-5" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Vasculitis? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Vasculitis can affect people of all ages and races and both sexes. Some types of vasculitis seem to occur more often in people who:
                
Have certain medical conditions, such as chronic hepatitis B or C infection
                
Have certain autoimmune diseases, such a lupus, rheumatoid arthritis, and scleroderma
                
Smoke
                
For more information, go to &quot;Types of Vasculitis.&quot;</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000136-6" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The signs and symptoms of vasculitis vary. They depend on the type of vasculitis you have, the organs involved, and the severity of the condition. Some people may have few signs and symptoms. Other people may become very sick.
                
Sometimes the signs and symptoms develop slowly, over months. Other times, the signs and symptoms develop quickly, over days or weeks.
                
Systemic Signs and Symptoms
                
Systemic signs and symptoms are those that affect you in a general or overall way. Common systemic signs and symptoms of vasculitis are:
                
Fever
                
Loss of appetite
                
Weight loss
                
Fatigue (tiredness)
                
General aches and pains
                
Organ- or Body System-Specific Signs and Symptoms
                
Vasculitis can affect specific organs and body systems, causing a range of signs and symptoms.
                
Skin
                
If vasculitis affects your skin, you may notice skin changes. For example, you may have purple or red spots or bumps, clusters of small dots, splotches, bruises, or hives. Your skin also may itch.
                
Joints
                
If vasculitis affects your joints, you may ache or develop arthritis in one or more joints.
                
Lungs
                
If vasculitis affects your lungs, you may feel short of breath. You may even cough up blood. The results from a chest x ray may show signs that suggest pneumonia, even though that may not be what you have.
                
Gastrointestinal Tract
                
If vasculitis affects your gastrointestinal tract, you may get ulcers (sores) in your mouth or have stomach pain.
                
In severe cases, blood flow to the intestines can be blocked. This can cause the wall of the intestines to weaken and possibly rupture (burst). A rupture can lead to serious problems or even death.
                
Sinuses, Nose, Throat, and Ears
                
If vasculitis affects your sinuses, nose, throat, and ears, you may have sinus or chronic (ongoing) middle ear infections. Other symptoms include ulcers in the nose and, in some cases, hearing loss.
                
Eyes
                
If vasculitis affects your eyes, you may develop red, itchy, burning eyes. Your eyes also may become sensitive to light, and your vision may blur. Rarely, certain types of vasculitis may cause blindness.
                
Brain
                
If vasculitis affects your brain, symptoms may include headaches, problems thinking clearly, changes in mental function, or stroke-like symptoms, such as muscle weakness and paralysis (an inability to move).
                
Nerves
                
If vasculitis affects your nerves, you may have numbness, tingling, and weakness in various parts of your body. You also may have a loss of feeling or strength in your hands and feet and shooting pains in your arms and legs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000136-7" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your doctor will diagnose vasculitis based on your signs and symptoms, your medical history, a physical exam, and test results.
                
Specialists Involved
                
Depending on the type of vasculitis you have and the organs affected, your doctor may refer you to various specialists, including:
                
A rheumatologist (joint and muscle specialist)
                
An infectious disease specialist
                
A dermatologist (skin specialist)
                
A pulmonologist (lung specialist)
                
A nephrologist (kidney specialist)
                
A neurologist (nervous system specialist)
                
A cardiologist (heart specialist)
                
An ophthalmologist (eye specialist)
                
A urologist (urinary tract and urogenital system specialist)
                
Diagnostic Tests and Procedures
                
Many tests are used to diagnose vasculitis.
                
Blood Tests
                
Blood tests can show whether you have abnormal levels of certain blood cells and antibodies (proteins) in your blood. These tests may look at:
                
Hemoglobin and hematocrit. A low hemoglobin or hematocrit level suggests anemia, a complication of vasculitis. Vasculitis can interfere with the body&apos;s ability to make enough red blood cells. Vasculitis also can be linked to increased destruction of red blood cells.
                
Antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibodies (ANCA). These antibodies are present in people who have certain types of vasculitis.
                
Erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR). A high ESR may be a sign of inflammation in the body.
                
The amount of C-reactive protein (CRP) in your blood. A high CRP level suggests inflammation.
                
Biopsy
                
A biopsy often is the best way for your doctor to make a firm diagnosis of vasculitis. During a biopsy, your doctor will take a small sample of your body tissue to study under a microscope. He or she will take the tissue sample from a blood vessel or an organ.
                
A pathologist will study the sample for signs of inflammation or tissue damage. A pathologist is a doctor who specializes in identifying diseases by studying cells and tissues under a microscope.
                
Blood Pressure
                
People who have vasculitis should have their blood pressure checked routinely. Vasculitis that damages the kidneys can cause high blood pressure.
                
Urinalysis
                
For this test, you&apos;ll provide a urine sample for analysis. This test detects abnormal levels of protein or blood cells in the urine. Abnormal levels of these substances can be a sign of vasculitis affecting the kidneys.
                
EKG (Electrocardiogram)
                
An EKG is a simple, painless test that records the heart&apos;s electrical activity. You might have this test to show whether vasculitis is affecting your heart.
                
Echocardiography
                
Echocardiography is a painless test that uses sound waves to create a moving picture of your heart. The test gives information about the size and shape of your heart and how well your heart chambers and valves are working.
                
Chest X Ray
                
A chest x ray is a painless test that creates pictures of the structures inside your chest, such as your heart, lungs, and blood vessels. Abnormal chest x-ray results may show whether vasculitis is affecting your lungs or your large arteries (such as the aorta or the pulmonary arteries).
                
Lung Function Tests
                
Lung function tests measure how much air you can breathe in and out, how fast you can breathe air out, and how well your lungs deliver oxygen to your blood.
                
Lung function tests can help your doctor find out whether airflow into and out of your lungs is restricted or blocked.
                
Abdominal Ultrasound
                
An abdominal ultrasound uses sound waves to create a picture of the organs and structures in your abdomen. The picture may show whether vasculitis is affecting your abdominal organs.
                
Computed Tomography Scan
                
A computed tomography (to-MOG-rah-fee) scan, or CT scan, is a type of x ray that creates more detailed pictures of your internal organs than a standard x ray. The results from this test can show whether you have a type of vasculitis that affects your abdominal organs or blood vessels.
                
Magnetic Resonance Imaging
                
A magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) test uses radio waves, magnets, and a computer to create detailed pictures of your internal organs.
                
Other Advanced Imaging Techniques
                
Several new imaging techniques are now being used to help diagnose vasculitis. Duplex ultrasonography combines an image of the structure of the blood vessel with a color image of the blood flow through that vein or artery. 18F-fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) identifies areas that show higher glucose metabolism leading to problems in the blood vessels.
                
Angiography
                
Angiography (an-jee-OG-ra-fee) is a test that uses dye and special x rays to show blood flowing through your blood vessels.
                
The dye is injected into your bloodstream. Special x-ray pictures are taken while the dye flows through your blood vessels. The dye helps highlight the vessels on the x-ray pictures.
                
Doctors use angiography to help find out whether blood vessels are narrowed, swollen, deformed, or blocked.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000136-8" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment for vasculitis will depend on the type of vasculitis you have, which organs are affected, and the severity of the condition.
                
People who have severe vasculitis are treated with prescription medicines. Rarely, surgery may be done. People who have mild vasculitis may find relief with over-the-counter pain medicines, such as acetaminophen, aspirin, ibuprofen, or naproxen.
                
The main goal of treating vasculitis is to reduce inflammation in the affected blood vessels. This usually is done by reducing or stopping the immune response that caused the inflammation.
                
Types of Treatment
                
Common prescription medicines used to treat vasculitis include corticosteroids and cytotoxic medicines.
                
Corticosteroids help reduce inflammation in your blood vessels. Examples of corticosteroids are prednisone, prednisolone, and methylprednisolone.
                
Doctors may prescribe cytotoxic medicines if vasculitis is severe or if corticosteroids don&apos;t work well. Cytotoxic medicines kill the cells that are causing the inflammation. Examples of these medicines are azathioprine, methotrexate, and cyclophosphamide.
                
Your doctor may prescribe both corticosteroids and cytotoxic medicines.
                
Other treatments may be used for certain types of vasculitis. For example, the standard treatment for Kawasaki disease is high-dose aspirin and immune globulin. Immune globulin is a medicine thats injected into a vein.
                
Certain types of vasculitis may require surgery to remove aneurysms that have formed as a result of the condition. (An aneurysm is an abnormal bulge in the wall of a blood vessel.)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000136-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can&apos;t prevent vasculitis. However, treatment can help prevent or delay the complications of vasculitis.
                
People who have severe vasculitis are treated with prescription medicines. Rarely, surgery may be done. People who have mild vasculitis may find relief with over-the-counter pain medicines, such as acetaminophen, aspirin, ibuprofen, or naproxen.
                
For more information about vasculitis treatments, go to &quot;How Is Vasculitis Treated?&quot;</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
