<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000077" source="NHLBI" url="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/hyp">
<Focus>Hypotension</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0020649</CUI>
			<CUI>C3163620</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000077-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hypotension ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypotension (HI-po-TEN-shun) is abnormally low blood pressure. Blood pressure is the force of blood pushing against the walls of the arteries as the heart pumps out blood.
                
Blood pressure is measured as systolic (sis-TOL-ik) and diastolic (di-a-STOL-ik) pressures. &quot;Systolic&quot; refers to blood pressure when the heart beats while pumping blood. &quot;Diastolic&quot; refers to blood pressure when the heart is at rest between beats.
                
You most often will see blood pressure numbers written with the systolic number above or before the diastolic number, such as 120/80 mmHg. (The mmHg is millimeters of mercurythe units used to measure blood pressure.)
                
Normal blood pressure in adults is lower than 120/80 mmHg. Hypotension is blood pressure that&apos;s lower than 90/60 mmHg.
                
Overview
                
Blood pressure doesn&apos;t stay the same all the time. It lowers as you sleep and rises when you wake up. Blood pressure also rises when you&apos;re excited, nervous, or active.
                
Your body is very sensitive to changes in blood pressure. For example, if you stand up quickly, your blood pressure may drop for a short time. Your body adjusts your blood pressure to make sure enough blood and oxygen are flowing to your brain, kidneys, and other vital organs.
                
Most forms of hypotension happen because your body can&apos;t bring blood pressure back to normal or can&apos;t do it fast enough.
                
Some people have low blood pressure all the time. They have no signs or symptoms, and their low blood pressure is normal for them.
                
In other people, certain conditions or factors cause abnormally low blood pressure. As a result, less blood and oxygen flow to the body&apos;s organs.
                
For the most part, hypotension is a medical concern only if it causes signs or symptoms or is linked to a serious condition, such as heart disease. Signs and symptoms of hypotension may include dizziness, fainting, cold and sweaty skin, fatigue (tiredness), blurred vision, or nausea (feeling sick to your stomach).
                
In extreme cases, hypotension can lead to shock.
                
Outlook
                
In a healthy person, low blood pressure without signs or symptoms usually isn&apos;t a problem and needs no treatment. If it causes signs or symptoms, your doctor will try to find and treat the condition that&apos;s causing it.
                
Hypotension can be dangerous. It can make you fall because of dizziness or fainting. Shock, a severe form of hypotension, is a condition that&apos;s often fatal if not treated right away. With prompt and proper treatment, shock can be successfully treated.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000077-4" qtype="causes">What causes Hypotension ?</Question>
			<Answer>Conditions or factors that disrupt the body&apos;s ability to control blood pressure cause hypotension. The different types of hypotension have different causes.
                
Orthostatic Hypotension
                
Orthostatic hypotension has many causes. Sometimes two or more factors combine to cause this type of low blood pressure.
                
Dehydration (de-hi-DRA-shun) is the most common cause of orthostatic hypotension. Dehydration occurs if the body loses more water than it takes in.
                
You may become dehydrated if you don&apos;t drink enough fluids or if you sweat a lot during physical activity. Fever, vomiting, and severe diarrhea also can cause dehydration.
                
Orthostatic hypotension also may occur during pregnancy, but it usually goes away after birth.
                
Because an older body doesn&apos;t manage changes in blood pressure as well as a younger body, getting older also can lead to this type of hypotension.
                
Postprandial hypotension (a type of orthostatic hypotension) mostly affects older adults. Postprandial hypotension is a sudden drop in blood pressure after a meal.
                
Certain medical conditions can raise your risk of orthostatic hypotension, including:
                
Heart conditions, such as heart attack, heart valve disease, bradycardia (a very low heart rate), and heart failure. These conditions prevent the heart from pumping enough blood to the body.
                
Anemia.
                
Severe infections.
                
Endocrine conditions, such as thyroid disorders, Addison&apos;s disease, low blood sugar, and diabetes.
                
Central nervous system disorders, such as Parkinson&apos;s disease.
                
Pulmonary embolism.
                
Some medicines for high blood pressure and heart disease can raise your risk of orthostatic hypotension. These medicines include:
                
Diuretics, also called &quot;water pills&quot;
                
Calcium channel blockers
                
Angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors
                
Angiotensin II receptor blockers
                
Nitrates
                
Beta blockers
                
Medicines for conditions such as anxiety, depression, erectile dysfunction, and central nervous system disorders also can increase your risk of orthostatic hypotension.
                
Other substances, when taken with high blood pressure medicines, also can lead to orthostatic hypotension. These substances include alcohol, barbiturates, and some prescription and over-the-counter medicines.
                
Finally, other factors or conditions that can trigger orthostatic hypotension include being out in the heat or being immobile for a long time. &quot;Immobile&quot; means you can&apos;t move around very much.
                
Neurally Mediated Hypotension
                
Neurally mediated hypotension (NMH) occurs when the brain and heart don&apos;t communicate with each other properly.
                
For example, when you stand for a long time, blood begins to pool in your legs. This causes your blood pressure to drop. In NMH, the body mistakenly tells the brain that blood pressure is high. In response, the brain slows the heart rate. This makes blood pressure drop even more, causing dizziness and other symptoms.
                
Severe Hypotension Linked to Shock
                
Many factors and conditions can cause severe hypotension linked to shock. Some of these factors also can cause orthostatic hypotension. In shock, though, blood pressure drops very low and doesn&apos;t return to normal on its own.
                
Shock is an emergency and must be treated right away. If a person has signs or symptoms of shock, call 911.
                
Some severe infections can cause shock. This is known as septic shock. It can occur if bacteria enter the bloodstream. The bacteria release a toxin (poison) that leads to a dangerous drop in blood pressure.
                
A severe loss of blood or fluids from the body also can cause shock. This is known as hypovolemic (HI-po-vo-LE-mik) shock. Hypovolemic shock can happen as a result of:
                
Major external bleeding (for example, from a severe cut or injury)
                
Major internal bleeding (for example, from a ruptured blood vessel or injury that causes bleeding inside the body)
                
Major loss of body fluids from severe burns
                
Severe swelling of the pancreas (an organ that produces enzymes and hormones, such as insulin)
                
Severe diarrhea
                
Severe kidney disease
                
Overuse of diuretics
                
A major decrease in the heart&apos;s ability to pump blood also can cause shock. This is known as cardiogenic (KAR-de-o-JEN-ik) shock.
                
A heart attack, pulmonary embolism, or an ongoing arrhythmia (ah-RITH-me-ah) that disrupts heart function can cause this type of shock.
                
A sudden and extreme relaxation of the arteries linked to a drop in blood pressure also can cause shock. This is known as vasodilatory (VA-so-DI-la-tory) shock. It can occur due to:
                
A severe head injury
                
A reaction to certain medicines
                
Liver failure
                
Poisoning
                
A severe allergic reaction (called anaphylactic (AN-a-fi-LAK-tik) shock)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000077-5" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Hypotension? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypotension can affect people of all ages. However, people in certain age groups are more likely to have certain types of hypotension.
                
Older adults are more likely to have orthostatic and postprandial hypotension. Children and young adults are more likely to have neurally mediated hypotension.
                
People who take certain medicinessuch as diuretics (&quot;water pills&quot;) or other high blood pressure medicinesare at increased risk for hypotension. Certain conditions also increase the risk for hypotension. Examples include central nervous system disorders (such as Parkinson&apos;s disease) and some heart conditions.
                
Other risk factors for hypotension include being immobile (not being able to move around very much) for long periods, being out in the heat for a long time, and pregnancy. Hypotension during pregnancy is normal and usually goes away after birth.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000077-6" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hypotension ?</Question>
			<Answer>Orthostatic Hypotension and Neurally Mediated Hypotension
                
The signs and symptoms of orthostatic hypotension and neurally mediated hypotension (NMH) are similar. They include:
                
Dizziness or light-headedness
                
Blurry vision
                
Confusion
                
Weakness
                
Fatigue (feeling tired)
                
Nausea (feeling sick to your stomach)
                
Orthostatic hypotension may happen within a few seconds or minutes of standing up after you&apos;ve been sitting or lying down.
                
You may feel that you&apos;re going to faint, or you may actually faint. These signs and symptoms go away if you sit or lie down for a few minutes until your blood pressure adjusts to normal.
                
The signs and symptoms of NMH occur after standing for a long time or in response to an unpleasant, upsetting, or scary situation. The drop in blood pressure with NMH doesn&apos;t last long and often goes away after sitting down.
                
Severe Hypotension Linked to Shock
                
In shock, not enough blood and oxygen flow to the body&apos;s major organs, including the brain. The early signs and symptoms of reduced blood flow to the brain include light-headedness, sleepiness, and confusion.
                
In the earliest stages of shock, it may be hard to detect any signs or symptoms. In older people, the first symptom may only be confusion.
                
Over time, as shock worsens, a person won&apos;t be able to sit up without passing out. If the shock continues, the person will lose consciousness. Shock often is fatal if not treated right away.
                
Other signs and symptoms of shock vary, depending on what&apos;s causing the shock. When low blood volume (from major blood loss, for example) or poor pumping action in the heart (from heart failure, for example) causes shock:
                
The skin becomes cold and sweaty. It often looks blue or pale. If pressed, the color returns to normal more slowly than usual. A bluish network of lines appears under the skin.
                
The pulse becomes weak and rapid.
                
The person begins to breathe very quickly.
                
When extreme relaxation of blood vessels causes shock (such as in vasodilatory shock), a person feels warm and flushed at first. Later, the skin becomes cold and sweaty, and the person feels very sleepy.
                
Shock is an emergency and must be treated right away. If a person has signs or symptoms of shock, call 911.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000077-7" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hypotension ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypotension is diagnosed based on your medical history, a physical exam, and test results. Your doctor will want to know:
                
The type of hypotension you have and how severe it is
                
Whether an underlying condition is causing the hypotension
                
Specialists Involved
                
A primary care doctor or specialist may diagnose and treat hypotension. The type of specialist most commonly involved is a cardiologist (heart specialist).
                
Other specialists also may be involved, such as surgeons, nephrologists (kidney specialists), or neurologists (brain and nerve specialists).
                
Diagnostic Tests
                
Shock is a life-threatening condition that requires emergency treatment. For other types of hypotension, your doctor may recommend tests to find out how your blood pressure responds in certain situations.
                
The test results will help your doctor understand why you&apos;re fainting or having other symptoms.
                
Blood Tests
                
During a blood test, a small amount of blood is taken from your body. It&apos;s usually drawn from a vein in your arm using a needle. The procedure is quick and easy, although it may cause some short-term discomfort.
                
Blood tests can show whether anemia or low blood sugar is causing your hypotension.
                
EKG (Electrocardiogram)
                
An EKG is a simple test that detects and records your heart&apos;s electrical activity. It shows how fast your heart is beating and whether its rhythm is steady or irregular. An EKG also shows the strength and timing of electrical signals as they pass through each part of your heart.
                
Holter and Event Monitors
                
Holter and event monitors are medical devices that record your heart&apos;s electrical activity. These monitors are similar to an EKG. However, a standard EKG only records your heartbeat for a few seconds. It won&apos;t detect heart rhythm problems that don&apos;t occur during the test.
                
Holter and event monitors are small, portable devices. You can wear one while you do your normal daily activities. This allows the monitor to record your heart for longer periods than a standard EKG.
                
Echocardiography
                
Echocardiography (echo) is a test that uses sound waves to create a moving picture of your heart. The picture shows how well your heart is working and its size and shape.
                
There are several types of echo, including stress echo. This test is done as part of a stress test (see below). Stress echo usually is done to find out whether you have decreased blood flow to your heart, a sign of coronary heart disease (also called coronary artery disease).
                
Stress Test
                
Some heart problems are easier to diagnose when your heart is working hard and beating fast. During stress testing, you exercise (or are given medicine if you&apos;re unable to exercise) to make your heart work hard and beat fast while heart tests are done.
                
These tests may include nuclear heart scanning, echo, and positron emission tomography (PET) scanning of the heart.
                
Valsalva Maneuver
                
This is a simple test for the part of your nervous system that controls functions such as your heartbeat and the narrowing and widening of your blood vessels. If something goes wrong with this part of the nervous system, blood pressure problems may occur.
                
During this test, you take a deep breath and then force the air out through your lips. You will do this several times. Your heart rate and blood pressure will be checked during the test.
                
Tilt Table Test
                
This test is used if you have fainting spells for no known reason. For the test, you lie on a table that moves from a lying down to an upright position. Your doctor checks your reaction to the change in position.
                
Doctors use a tilt table test to diagnose orthostatic hypotension and neurally mediated hypotension (NMH). People who have NMH usually faint during this test. The test can help your doctor find any underlying brain or nerve condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000077-8" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hypotension ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment depends on the type of hypotension you have and the severity of your signs and symptoms. The goal of treatment is to bring blood pressure back to normal to relieve signs and symptoms. Another goal is to manage any underlying condition causing the hypotension.
                
Your response to treatment depends on your age, overall health, and strength. It also depends on how easily you can stop, start, or change medicines.
                
In a healthy person, low blood pressure without signs or symptoms usually isn&apos;t a problem and needs no treatment.
                
If you have signs or symptoms of hypotension, you should sit or lie down right away. Put your feet above the level of your heart. If your signs or symptoms don&apos;t go away quickly, you should seek medical care.
                
Orthostatic Hypotension
                
Many treatments are available for orthostatic hypotension. If you have this condition, your doctor may advise making lifestyle changes, such as:
                
Drinking plenty of fluids, such as water or sports drinks that contain nutrients like sodium and potassium.
                
Drinking little or no alcohol.
                
Standing up slowly.
                
Not crossing your legs while sitting.
                
Slowly increasing the amount of time you sit up if you&apos;ve been immobile for a long time because of a medical condition. The term &quot;immobile&quot; refers to not being able to move around very much.
                
Eating small, low-carbohydrate meals if you have postprandial hypotension (a form of orthostatic hypotension).
                
Talk with your doctor about using compression stockings. These stockings apply pressure to your lower legs. The pressure helps move blood throughout your body.
                
If medicine is causing your low blood pressure, your doctor may change the medicine or adjust the dose you take.
                
Several medicines are used to treat orthostatic hypotension. These medicines, which raise blood pressure, include fludrocortisone and midodrine.
                
Neurally Mediated Hypotension
                
If you have neurally mediated hypotension (NMH), you may need to make lifestyle changes. These may include:
                
Avoiding situations that trigger symptoms, such as standing for long periods. Unpleasant, upsetting, or scary situations also can trigger symptoms.
                
Drinking plenty of fluids, such as water or sports drinks that contain nutrients like sodium and potassium.
                
Increasing your salt intake (as your doctor advises).
                
Learning to recognize symptoms that occur before fainting and taking action to raise your blood pressure. For example, sitting down and putting your head between your knees or lying down can help raise blood pressure.
                
If medicine is causing your hypotension, your doctor may change the medicine or adjust the dose you take. He or she also may prescribe medicine to treat NMH.
                
Children who have NHM often outgrow it.
                
Severe Hypotension Linked to Shock
                
Shock is a life-threatening emergency. People who have shock need prompt treatment from medical personnel. If a person has signs or symptoms of shock, call 911 right away.
                
The goals of treating shock are to:
                
Restore blood flow to the organs as quickly as possible to prevent organ damage
                
Find and reverse the cause of shock
                
Blood or special fluids are put into the bloodstream to restore blood flow to the organs. Medicines can help raise blood pressure or make the heartbeat stronger. Depending on the cause of the shock, other treatmentssuch as antibiotics or surgerymay be needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
