<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000045" source="NHLBI" url="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/hd">
<Focus>Coronary Heart Disease Risk Factors</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0742831</CUI>
			<CUI>C1113667</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000045-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Coronary Heart Disease Risk Factors ?</Question>
			<Answer>Coronary heart disease risk factors are conditions or habits that raise your risk of coronary heart disease (CHD) and heart attack. These risk factors also increase the chance that existing CHD will worsen.
                
CHD, also called coronary artery disease, is a condition in which a waxy substance called plaque (plak) builds up on the inner walls of the coronary arteries. These arteries supply oxygen-rich blood to your heart muscle.
                
Plaque narrows the arteries and reduces blood flow to your heart muscle. Reduced blood flow can cause chest pain, especially when you&apos;re active. Eventually, an area of plaque can rupture (break open). This causes a blood clot to form on the surface of the plaque.
                
If the clot becomes large enough, it can block the flow of oxygen-rich blood to the portion of heart muscle fed by the artery. Blocked blood flow to the heart muscle causes a heart attack.
                
Overview
                
There are many known CHD risk factors. You can control some risk factors, but not others. Risk factors you can control include:
                
High blood cholesterol and triglyceride levels (a type of fat found in the blood)
                
High blood pressure
                
Diabetes and prediabetes
                
Overweight and obesity
                
Smoking
                
Lack of physical activity
                
Unhealthy diet
                
Stress
                
The risk factors you can&apos;t control are age, gender, and family history of CHD.
                
Many people have at least one CHD risk factor. Your risk of CHD and heart attack increases with the number of risk factors you have and their severity. Also, some risk factors put you at greater risk of CHD and heart attack than others. Examples of these risk factors include smoking and diabetes.
                
Many risk factors for coronary heart disease start during childhood. This is even more common now because many children are overweight and dont get enough physical activity.
                
Researchers continue to study and learn more about CHD risk factors.
                
Outlook
                
Following a healthy lifestyle can help you and your children prevent or control many CHD risk factors.
                
Because many lifestyle habits begin during childhood, parents and families should encourage their children to make heart healthy choices. For example, you and your children can lower your risk of CHD if you maintain a healthy weight, follow a healthy diet, do physical activity regularly, and don&apos;t smoke.
                
If you already have CHD, lifestyle changes can help you control your risk factors. This may prevent CHD from worsening. Even if you&apos;re in your seventies or eighties, a healthy lifestyle can lower your risk of dying from CHD.
                
If lifestyle changes aren&apos;t enough, your doctor may recommend other treatments to help control your risk factors.
                
Your doctor can help you find out whether you have CHD risk factors. He or she also can help you create a plan for lowering your risk of CHD, heart attack, and other heart problems.
                
If you have children, talk with their doctors about their heart health and whether they have CHD risk factors. If they do, ask your doctor to help create a treatment plan to reduce or control these risk factors.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000045-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Coronary Heart Disease Risk Factors? ?</Question>
			<Answer>High Blood Cholesterol and Triglyceride Levels
                
Cholesterol
                
High blood cholesterol is a condition in which your blood has too much cholesterola waxy, fat-like substance. The higher your blood cholesterol level, the greater your risk of coronary heart disease (CHD) and heart attack.
                
Cholesterol travels through the bloodstream in small packages called lipoproteins. Two major kinds of lipoproteins carry cholesterol throughout your body:
                
Low-density lipoproteins (LDL). LDL cholesterol sometimes is called &quot;bad&quot; cholesterol. This is because it carries cholesterol to tissues, including your heart arteries. A high LDL cholesterol level raises your risk of CHD.
                
High-density lipoproteins (HDL). HDL cholesterol sometimes is called &quot;good&quot; cholesterol. This is because it helps remove cholesterol from your arteries. A low HDL cholesterol level raises your risk of CHD.
                
Many factors affect your cholesterol levels. For example, after menopause, women&apos;s LDL cholesterol levels tend to rise, and their HDL cholesterol levels tend to fall. Other factorssuch as age, gender, diet, and physical activityalso affect your cholesterol levels.
                
Healthy levels of both LDL and HDL cholesterol will prevent plaque from building up in your arteries. Routine blood tests can show whether your blood cholesterol levels are healthy. Talk with your doctor about having your cholesterol tested and what the results mean.
                
Children also can have unhealthy cholesterol levels, especially if they&apos;re overweight or their parents have high blood cholesterol. Talk with your child&apos;s doctor about testing your child&apos; cholesterol levels.
                
To learn more about high blood cholesterol and how to manage the condition, go to the Health Topics High Blood Cholesterol article.
                
Triglycerides
                
Triglycerides are a type of fat found in the blood. Some studies suggest that a high level of triglycerides in the blood may raise the risk of CHD, especially in women.
                
High Blood Pressure
                
&quot;Blood pressure&quot; is the force of blood pushing against the walls of your arteries as your heart pumps blood. If this pressure rises and stays high over time, it can damage your heart and lead to plaque buildup.All levels above 120/80 mmHg raise your risk of CHD. This risk grows as blood pressure levels rise. Only one of the two blood pressure numbers has to be above normal to put you at greater risk of CHD and heart attack.
                

                
Most adults should have their blood pressure checked at least once a year. If you have high blood pressure, you&apos;ll likely need to be checked more often. Talk with your doctor about how often you should have your blood pressure checked.
                
Children also can develop high blood pressure, especially if they&apos;re overweight. Your child&apos;s doctor should check your child&apos;s blood pressure at each routine checkup.
                
Both children and adults are more likely to develop high blood pressure if they&apos;re overweight or have diabetes.
                
For more information about high blood pressure and how to manage the condition, go to the Health Topics High Blood Pressure article.
                
Diabetes and Prediabetes
                
Diabetes is a disease in which the body&apos;s blood sugar level is too high. The two types of diabetes are type 1 and type 2.
                
In type 1 diabetes, the body&apos;s blood sugar level is high because the body doesn&apos;t make enough insulin. Insulin is a hormone that helps move blood sugar into cells, where it&apos;s used for energy. In type 2 diabetes, the body&apos;s blood sugar level is high mainly because the body doesn&apos;t use its insulin properly.
                
Over time, a high blood sugar level can lead to increased plaque buildup in your arteries. Having diabetes doubles your risk of CHD.
                
Prediabetes is a condition in which your blood sugar level is higher than normal, but not as high as it is in diabetes. If you have prediabetes and don&apos;t take steps to manage it, you&apos;ll likely develop type 2 diabetes within 10 years. You&apos;re also at higher risk of CHD.
                
Being overweight or obese raises your risk of type 2 diabetes. With modest weight loss and moderate physical activity, people who have prediabetes may be able to delay or prevent type 2 diabetes. They also may be able to lower their risk of CHD and heart attack. Weight loss and physical activity also can help control diabetes.
                
Even children can develop type 2 diabetes. Most children who have type 2 diabetes are overweight.
                
Type 2 diabetes develops over time and sometimes has no symptoms. Go to your doctor or local clinic to have your blood sugar levels tested regularly to check for diabetes and prediabetes.
                
For more information about diabetes and heart disease, go to the Health Topics Diabetic Heart Disease article. For more information about diabetes and prediabetes, go to the National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases&apos; (NIDDK&apos;s) Introduction to Diabetes.
                
Overweight and Obesity
                
The terms &quot;overweight&quot; and &quot;obesity&quot; refer to body weight that&apos;s greater than what is considered healthy for a certain height. More than two-thirds of American adults are overweight, and almost one-third of these adults are obese.
                
The most useful measure of overweight and obesity is body mass index (BMI).You can use the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute&apos;s (NHLBI&apos;s) online BMI calculator to figure out your BMI, or your doctor can help you.
                
Overweight is defined differently for children and teens than it is for adults. Children are still growing, and boys and girls mature at different rates. Thus, BMIs for children and teens compare their heights and weights against growth charts that take age and gender into account. This is called BMI-for-age percentile.
                
Being overweight or obese can raise your risk of CHD and heart attack. This is mainly because overweight and obesity are linked to other CHD risk factors, such as high blood cholesterol and triglyceride levels, high blood pressure, and diabetes.
                
For more information, go to the Health Topics Overweight and Obesity article.
                
Smoking
                
Smoking tobacco or long-term exposure to secondhand smoke raises your risk of CHD and heart attack.
                
Smoking triggers a buildup of plaque in your arteries. Smoking also increases the risk of blood clots forming in your arteries. Blood clots can block plaque-narrowed arteries and cause a heart attack.Some research shows that smoking raises your risk of CHD in part by lowering HDL cholesterol levels.
                
The more you smoke, the greater your risk of heart attack. The benefits of quitting smoking occur no matter how long or how much you&apos;ve smoked. Heart disease risk associated with smoking begins to decrease soon after you quit, and for many people it continues to decrease over time.
                
Most people who smoke start when they&apos;re teens. Parents can help prevent their children from smoking by not smoking themselves. Talk with your child about the health dangers of smoking and ways to overcome peer pressure to smoke.
                
For more information, including tips on how to quit smoking, go to the Health Topics Smoking and Your Heart article and the NHLBI&apos;s &quot;Your Guide to a Healthy Heart.&quot;
                
For more information about children and smoking, go to the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services&apos; (HHS&apos;) Kids and Smoking Web page and the CDC&apos;s Smoking and Tobacco Use Web page.
                
Lack of Physical Activity
                
Inactive people are nearly twice as likely to develop CHD as those who are active. A lack of physical activity can worsen other CHD risk factors, such as high blood cholesterol and triglyceride levels, high blood pressure, diabetes and prediabetes, and overweight and obesity.
                
It&apos;s important for children and adults to make physical activity part of their daily routines. One reason many Americans aren&apos;t active enough is because of hours spent in front of TVs and computers doing work, schoolwork, and leisure activities.
                
Some experts advise that children and teens should reduce screen time because it limits time for physical activity. They recommend that children aged 2 and older should spend no more than 2 hours a day watching TV or using a computer (except for school work).
                
Being physically active is one of the most important things you can do to keep your heart healthy. The good news is that even modest amounts of physical activity are good for your health. The more active you are, the more you will benefit.
                
For more information, go to HHS&apos; &quot;2008 Physical Activity Guidelines for Americans,&quot; the Health Topics Physical Activity and Your Heart article, and the NHLBI&apos;s &quot;Your Guide to Physical Activity and Your Heart.&quot;
                
Unhealthy Diet
                
An unhealthy diet can raise your risk of CHD. For example, foods that are high in saturated and trans fats and cholesterol raise LDL cholesterol. Thus, you should try to limit these foods.
                
It&apos;s also important to limit foods that are high in sodium (salt) and added sugars. A high-salt diet can raise your risk of high blood pressure.
                
Added sugars will give you extra calories without nutrients like vitamins and minerals. This can cause you to gain weight, which raises your risk of CHD. Added sugars are found in many desserts, canned fruits packed in syrup, fruit drinks, and nondiet sodas.
                
Stress
                
Stress and anxiety may play a role in causing CHD. Stress and anxiety also can trigger your arteries to tighten. This can raise your blood pressure and your risk of heart attack.
                
The most commonly reported trigger for a heart attack is an emotionally upsetting event, especially one involving anger. Stress also may indirectly raise your risk of CHD if it makes you more likely to smoke or overeat foods high in fat and sugar.
                
Age
                
In men, the risk for coronary heart disease (CHD) increases starting around age 45. In women, the risk for CHD increases starting around age 55. Most people have some plaque buildup in their heart arteries by the time theyre in their 70s. However, only about 25 percent of those people have chest pain, heart attacks, or other signs of CHD.
                
Gender
                
Some risk factors may affect CHD risk differently in women than in men. For example, estrogen provides women some protection against CHD, whereas diabetes raises the risk of CHD more in women than in men.
                
Also, some risk factors for heart disease only affect women, such as preeclampsia, a condition that can develop during pregnancy. Preeclampsia is linked to an increased lifetime risk of heart disease, including CHD, heart attack, heart failure, and high blood pressure. (Likewise, having heart disease risk factors, such as diabetes or obesity, increases a womans risk of preeclampsia.)
                
Family History
                
A family history of early CHD is a risk factor for developing CHD, specifically if a father or brother is diagnosed before age 55, or a mother or sister is diagnosed before age 65.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000045-3" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Coronary Heart Disease Risk Factors ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can prevent and control many coronary heart disease (CHD) risk factors with heart-healthy lifestyle changes and medicines. Examples of risk factors you can control include high blood cholesterol, high blood pressure, and overweight and obesity. Only a few risk factorssuch as age, gender, and family historycant be controlled.
                
To reduce your risk of CHD and heart attack, try to control each risk factor you can. The good news is that many lifestyle changes help control several CHD risk factors at the same time. For example, physical activity may lower your blood pressure, help control diabetes and prediabetes, reduce stress, and help control your weight.
                
Heart-Healthy Lifestyle Changes
                
A heart-healthy lifestyle can lower the risk of CHD. If you already have CHD, a heart-healthy lifestyle may prevent it from getting worse. Heart-healthy lifestyle changes include:
                
Heart-healthy eating
                
Maintaining a healthy weight
                
Managing stress
                
Physical activity
                
Quitting smoking
                
Many lifestyle habits begin during childhood. Thus, parents and families should encourage their children to make heart-healthy choices, such as following a healthy diet and being physically active. Make following a healthy lifestyle a family goal. Making lifestyle changes can be hard. But if you make these changes as a family, it may be easier for everyone to prevent or control their CHD risk factors.
                
For tips on how to help your children adopt healthy habits, visit We Can! Ways to Enhance Childrens Activity &amp; Nutrition.
                
Heart-Healthy Eating
                
Your doctor may recommend heart-healthy eating, which should include:
                
Fat-free or low-fat dairy products, such as skim milk
                
Fish high in omega-3 fatty acids, such as salmon, tuna, and trout, about twice a week
                
Fruits, such as apples, bananas, oranges, pears, and prunes
                
Legumes, such as kidney beans, lentils, chickpeas, black-eyed peas, and lima beans
                
Vegetables, such as broccoli, cabbage, and carrots
                
Whole grains, such as oatmeal, brown rice, and corn tortillas
                
When following a heart-healthy diet, you should avoid eating:
                
A lot of red meat
                
Palm and coconut oils
                
Sugary foods and beverages
                
Two nutrients in your diet make blood cholesterol levels rise:
                
Saturated fatfound mostly in foods that come from animals
                
Trans fat (trans fatty acids)found in foods made with hydrogenated oils and fats, such as stick margarine; baked goods, such as cookies, cakes, and pies; crackers; frostings; and coffee creamers. Some trans fats also occur naturally in animal fats andmeats.
                
Saturated fat raises your blood cholesterol more than anything else in your diet. When you follow a heart-healthy eating plan, only 5 percent to 6 percent of your daily calories should come from saturated fat. Food labels list the amounts of saturated fat. To help you stay on track, here are some examples:
                
1,200 calories a day
                
8 grams of saturated fat a day
                
1,500 calories a day
                
10 grams of saturated fat a day
                
1,800 calories a day
                
12 grams of saturated fat a day
                
2,000 calories a day
                
13 grams of saturated fat a day
                
2,500 calories a day
                
17 grams of saturated fat a day
                
Not all fats are bad. Monounsaturated and polyunsaturated fats actually help lower blood cholesterol levels.
                
Some sources of monounsaturated and polyunsaturated fats are:
                
Avocados
                
Corn, sunflower, and soybean oils
                
Nuts and seeds, such as walnuts
                
Olive, canola, peanut, safflower, and sesame oils
                
Peanut butter
                
Salmon and trout
                
Tofu
                
Sodium
                
You should try to limit the amount of sodium that you eat. This means choosing and preparing foods that are lower in salt and sodium. Try to use low-sodium and no added salt foods and seasonings at the table or while cooking. Food labels tell you what you need to know about choosing foods that are lower in sodium. Try to eat no more than 2,300 milligrams of sodium a day. If you have high blood pressure, you may need to restrict your sodium intake even more.
                
Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension
                
Your doctor may recommend the Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension (DASH) eating plan if you have high blood pressure. The DASH eating plan focuses on fruits, vegetables, whole grains, and other foods that are heart healthy and low in fat, cholesterol, and sodium and salt.
                
The DASH eating plan is a good heart-healthy eating plan, even for those who dont have high blood pressure. Read more about DASH.
                
Alcohol
                
Try to limit alcohol intake. Too much alcohol canraise your blood pressure and triglyceride levels, a type of fat found in the blood. Alcohol also adds extra calories, which may cause weight gain.
                
Men should have no more than two drinks containing alcohol a day. Women should have no more than one drink containing alcohol a day. One drink is:
                
12 ounces of beer
                
5 ounces of wine
                
1 ounces of liquor
                
Maintaining a Healthy Weight
                
Maintaining a healthy weight is important for overall health and can lower your risk for coronary heart disease. Aim for a Healthy Weight by following a heart-healthy eating plan and keeping physically active.
                
Knowing your body mass index (BMI) helps you find out if youre a healthy weight in relation to your height and gives an estimate of your total body fat. To figure out your BMI, check out NHLBIs online BMI calculator or talk to your doctor. A BMI:
                
Below 18.5 is a sign that you are underweight.
                
Between 18.5 and 24.9 is in the normal range.
                
Between 25 and 29.9 is considered overweight.
                
Of 30 or more is considered obese.
                
A general goal to aim for is a BMI of less than 25. Your doctor or health care provider can help you set an appropriate BMI goal.
                
Measuring waist circumference helps screen for possible health risks. If most of your fat is around your waist rather than at your hips, youre at a higher risk for heart disease and type 2 diabetes. This risk may be high with a waist size that is greater than 35 inches for women or greater than 40 inches for men. To learn how to measure your waist, visit Assessing Your Weight and Health Risk.
                
If youre overweight or obese, try to lose weight. A loss of just 3 percent to 5 percent of your current weight can lower your triglycerides, blood glucose, and the risk of developing type 2 diabetes. Greater amounts of weight loss can improve blood pressure readings, lower LDL cholesterol, and increase HDL cholesterol.
                
Managing Stress
                
Research shows that the most commonly reported trigger for a heart attack is an emotionally upsetting eventparticularly one involving anger. Also, some of the ways people cope with stresssuch as drinking, smoking, or overeatingarent healthy.
                
Learning how to manage stress, relax, and cope with problems can improve your emotional and physical health. Consider healthy stress-reducing activities, such as:
                
A stress management program.
                
Meditation
                
Physical activity
                
Relaxation therapy
                
Talking things out with friends or family
                
Physical Activity
                
Routine physical activity can lower many CHD risk factors, including LDL (bad) cholesterol, high blood pressure, and excess weight. Physical activity also can lower your risk for diabetes and raise your HDL cholesterol level. HDL is the good cholesterol that helps prevent CHD.
                
Everyone should try to participate in moderate-intensity aerobic exercise at least 2hours and 30minutes per week, or vigorous aerobic exercise for 1 hour and 15 minutes per week. Aerobic exercise, such as brisk walking, is any exercise in which your heart beats faster and you use more oxygen than usual. The more active you are, the more you will benefit. Participate in aerobic exercise for at least 10 minutes at a time spread throughout the week.
                
Read more about physical activity at:
                
Physical Activity and Your Heart
                
U.S. Department of Health and Human Services 2008 Physical Activity Guidelines for Americans
                
Talk with your doctor before you start a new exercise plan. Ask your doctor how much and what kinds of physical activity are safe for you.
                
Quitting Smoking
                
If you smoke, quit. Smoking can raise your risk for coronary heart disease and heart attack and worsen other coronary heart disease risk factors. Talk with your doctor about programs and products that can help you quit smoking. Also, try to avoid secondhand smoke. If you have trouble quitting smoking on your own, consider joining a support group. Many hospitals, workplaces, and community groups offer classes to help people quit smoking.
                
Read more about quitting smoking at Smoking and Your Heart.
                
Medicines
                
Sometimes lifestyle changes arent enough to control your blood cholesterol levels. For example, you may need statin medications to control or lower your cholesterol. By lowering your cholesterol level, you can decrease your chance of having a heart attack or stroke. Doctors usually prescribe statins for people who have:
                
Coronary heart disease, peripheral artery disease, or had a prior stroke
                
Diabetes
                
High LDL cholesterol levels
                
Doctors may discuss beginning statin treatment with those who have an elevated risk for developing heart disease or having a stroke.
                
Your doctor also may prescribe other medications to:
                
Decrease your chance of having a heart attack or dying suddenly.
                
Lower your blood pressure.
                
Prevent blood clots, which can lead to heart attack or stroke.
                
Prevent or delay the need for a procedure or surgery, such as percutaneous coronary intervention or coronary artery bypass grafting. 
                
Reduce your hearts workload and relieve CHD.
                
Take all medicines regularly, as your doctor prescribes. Dont change the amount of your medicine or skip a dose unless your doctor tells you to.You should still follow a heart-healthy lifestyle, even if you take medicines to treat your CHD.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
