<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000068" source="NHLBI" url="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/ha">
<Focus>Hemolytic Anemia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0002878</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000068-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hemolytic Anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hemolytic anemia (HEE-moh-lit-ick uh-NEE-me-uh) is a condition in which red blood cells are destroyed and removed from the bloodstream before their normal lifespan is over.
                
Red blood cells are disc-shaped and look like doughnuts without holes in the center. These cells carry oxygen to your body. They also remove carbon dioxide (a waste product) from your body.
                
Red blood cells are made in the bone marrowa sponge-like tissue inside the bones. They live for about 120 days in the bloodstream and then die.
                
White blood cells and platelets (PLATE-lets) also are made in the bone marrow. White blood cells help fight infections. Platelets stick together to seal small cuts or breaks on blood vessel walls and stop bleeding.
                
When blood cells die, the body&apos;s bone marrow makes more blood cells to replace them. However, in hemolytic anemia, the bone marrow can&apos;t make red blood cells fast enough to meet the body&apos;s needs.
                
Hemolytic anemia can lead to many health problems, such as fatigue (tiredness), pain, irregular heartbeats called arrhythmias (ah-RITH-me-ahs), an enlarged heart, and heart failure.
                
Overview
                
Hemolytic anemia is a type of anemia. The term &quot;anemia&quot; usually refers to a condition in which the blood has a lower than normal number of red blood cells.
                
Anemia also can occur if your red blood cells don&apos;t contain enough hemoglobin (HEE-muh-glow-bin). Hemoglobin is an iron-rich protein that carries oxygen from the lungs to the rest of the body.
                
Anemia has three main causes: blood loss, lack of red blood cell production, or high rates of red blood cell destruction.
                
Hemolytic anemia is caused by high rates of red blood cell destruction. Many diseases, conditions, and factors can cause the body to destroy its red blood cells.
                
These causes can be inherited or acquired. &quot;Inherited&quot; means your parents passed the gene(s) for the condition on to you. &quot;Acquired&quot; means you aren&apos;t born with the condition, but you develop it. Sometimes the cause of hemolytic anemia isn&apos;t known.
                
Outlook
                
There are many types of hemolytic anemia. Treatment and outlook depend on what type you have and how severe it is. The condition can develop suddenly or slowly. Symptoms can range from mild to severe.
                
Hemolytic anemia often can be successfully treated or controlled. Mild hemolytic anemia may need no treatment at all. Severe hemolytic anemia requires prompt and proper treatment, or it may be fatal.
                
Inherited forms of hemolytic anemia are lifelong conditions that may require ongoing treatment. Acquired forms of hemolytic anemia may go away if the cause of the condition is found and corrected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000068-4" qtype="causes">What causes Hemolytic Anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The immediate cause of hemolytic anemia is the early destruction of red blood cells. This means that red blood cells are destroyed and removed from the bloodstream before their normal lifespan is over.
                
Many diseases, conditions, and factors can cause the body to destroy its red blood cells. These causes can be inherited or acquired. &quot;Inherited&quot; means your parents passed the gene for the condition on to you. &quot;Acquired&quot; means you aren&apos;t born with the condition, but you develop it.
                
Sometimes, the cause of hemolytic anemia isn&apos;t known.
                
For more information about the specific causes of hemolytic anemia, go to &quot;Types of Hemolytic Anemia.&quot;
                
Inherited Hemolytic Anemias
                
In inherited hemolytic anemias, the genes that control how red blood cells are made are faulty. You can get a faulty red blood cell gene from one or both of your parents.
                
Different types of faulty genes cause different types of inherited hemolytic anemia. However, in each type, the body makes abnormal red blood cells. The problem with the red blood cells may involve the hemoglobin, cell membrane, or enzymes that maintain healthy red blood cells.
                
The abnormal cells may be fragile and break down while moving through the bloodstream. If this happens, an organ called the spleen may remove the cell debris from the bloodstream.
                
Acquired Hemolytic Anemias
                
In acquired hemolytic anemias, the body makes normal red blood cells. However, a disease, condition, or other factor destroys the cells. Examples of conditions that can destroy the red blood cells include:
                
Immune disorders
                
Infections
                
Reactions to medicines or blood transfusions
                
Hypersplenism (HI-per-SPLEEN-izm; an enlarged spleen)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000068-5" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Hemolytic Anemia? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hemolytic anemia can affect people of all ages and races and both sexes. Some types of hemolytic anemia are more likely to occur in certain populations than others.
                
For example, glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency mostly affects males of African or Mediterranean descent. In the United States, the condition is more common among African Americans than Caucasians.
                
In the United States, sickle cell anemia mainly affects African Americans.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000068-6" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hemolytic Anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The signs and symptoms of hemolytic anemia will depend on the type and severity of the disease.
                
People who have mild hemolytic anemia often have no signs or symptoms. More severe hemolytic anemia may cause many signs and symptoms, and they may be serious.
                
Many of the signs and symptoms of hemolytic anemia apply to all types of anemia.
                
Signs and Symptoms of Anemia
                
The most common symptom of all types of anemia is fatigue (tiredness). Fatigue occurs because your body doesn&apos;t have enough red blood cells to carry oxygen to its various parts.
                
A low red blood cell count also can cause shortness of breath, dizziness, headache, coldness in your hands and feet, pale skin, and chest pain.
                
A lack of red blood cells also means that your heart has to work harder to move oxygen-rich blood through your body. This can lead to arrhythmias (irregular heartbeats), a heart murmur, an enlarged heart, or even heart failure.
                
Signs and Symptoms of Hemolytic Anemia
                
Jaundice
                
Jaundice refers to a yellowish color of the skin or whites of the eyes. When red blood cells die, they release hemoglobin into the bloodstream.
                
The hemoglobin is broken down into a compound called bilirubin, which gives the skin and eyes a yellowish color. Bilirubin also causes urine to be dark yellow or brown.
                
Pain in the Upper Abdomen
                
Gallstones or an enlarged spleen may cause pain in the upper abdomen. High levels of bilirubin and cholesterol (from the breakdown of red blood cells) can form into stones in the gallbladder. These stones can be painful.
                
The spleen is an organ in the abdomen that helps fight infection and filters out old or damaged blood cells. In hemolytic anemia, the spleen may be enlarged, which can be painful.
                
Leg Ulcers and Pain
                
In people who have sickle cell anemia, the sickle-shaped cells can clog small blood vessels and block blood flow. This can cause leg sores and pain throughout the body.
                
A Severe Reaction to a Blood Transfusion
                
You may develop hemolytic anemia due to a blood transfusion. This can happen if the transfused blood is a different blood type than your blood.
                
Signs and symptoms of a severe reaction to a transfusion include fever, chills, low blood pressure, and shock. (Shock is a life-threatening condition that occurs if the body isn&apos;t getting enough blood flow.)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000068-7" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hemolytic Anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your doctor will diagnose hemolytic anemia based on your medical and family histories, a physical exam, and test results.
                
Specialists Involved
                
Primary care doctors, such as a family doctor or pediatrician, may help diagnose and treat hemolytic anemia. Your primary care doctor also may refer you to a hematologist. This is a doctor who specializes in diagnosing and treating blood diseases and disorders.
                
Doctors and clinics that specialize in treating inherited blood disorders, such as sickle cell anemia and thalassemias, also may be involved.
                
If your hemolytic anemia is inherited, you may want to consult a genetic counselor. A counselor can help you understand your risk of having a child who has the condition. He or she also can explain the choices that are available to you.
                
Medical and Family Histories
                
To find the cause and severity of hemolytic anemia, your doctor may ask detailed questions about your symptoms, personal medical history, and your family medical history.
                
He or she may ask whether:
                
You or anyone in your family has had problems with anemia
                
You&apos;ve recently had any illnesses or medical conditions
                
You take any medicines, and which ones
                
You&apos;ve been exposed to certain chemicals or substances
                
You have an artificial heart valve or other medical device that could damage your red blood cells
                
Physical Exam
                
Your doctor will do a physical exam to check for signs of hemolytic anemia. He or she will try to find out how severe the condition is and what&apos;s causing it.
                
The exam may include:
                
Checking for jaundice (a yellowish color of the skin or whites of the eyes)
                
Listening to your heart for rapid or irregular heartbeats
                
Listening for rapid or uneven breathing
                
Feeling your abdomen to check the size of your spleen
                
Doing a pelvic and rectal exam to check for internal bleeding
                
Diagnostic Tests and Procedures
                
Many tests are used to diagnose hemolytic anemia. These tests can help confirm a diagnosis, look for a cause, and find out how severe the condition is.
                
Complete Blood Count
                
Often, the first test used to diagnose anemia is a complete blood count (CBC). The CBC measures many parts of your blood.
                
This test checks your hemoglobin and hematocrit (hee-MAT-oh-crit) levels. Hemoglobin is an iron-rich protein in red blood cells that carries oxygen to the body. Hematocrit is a measure of how much space red blood cells take up in your blood. A low level of hemoglobin or hematocrit is a sign of anemia.
                
The normal range of these levels may vary in certain racial and ethnic populations. Your doctor can explain your test results to you.
                
The CBC also checks the number of red blood cells, white blood cells, and platelets in your blood. Abnormal results may be a sign of hemolytic anemia, a different blood disorder, an infection, or another condition.
                
Finally, the CBC looks at mean corpuscular (kor-PUS-kyu-lar) volume (MCV). MCV is a measure of the average size of your red blood cells. The results may be a clue as to the cause of your anemia.
                
Other Blood Tests
                
If the CBC results confirm that you have anemia, you may need other blood tests to find out what type of anemia you have and how severe it is.
                
Reticulocyte count. A reticulocyte (re-TIK-u-lo-site) count measures the number of young red blood cells in your blood. The test shows whether your bone marrow is making red blood cells at the correct rate.
                
People who have hemolytic anemia usually have high reticulocyte counts because their bone marrow is working hard to replace the destroyed red blood cells.
                
Peripheral smear. For this test, your doctor will look at your red blood cells through a microscope. Some types of hemolytic anemia change the normal shape of red blood cells.
                
Coombs&apos; test. This test can show whether your body is making antibodies (proteins) to destroy red blood cells.
                
Haptoglobin, bilirubin, and liver function tests. When red blood cells break down, they release hemoglobin into the bloodstream. The hemoglobin combines with a chemical called haptoglobin. A low level of haptoglobin in the bloodstream is a sign of hemolytic anemia.
                
Hemoglobin is broken down into a compound called bilirubin. High levels of bilirubin in the bloodstream may be a sign of hemolytic anemia. High levels of this compound also occur with some liver and gallbladder diseases. Thus, you may need liver function tests to find out what&apos;s causing the high bilirubin levels.
                
Hemoglobin electrophoresis. This test looks at the different types of hemoglobin in your blood. It can help diagnose the type of anemia you have.
                
Testing for paroxysmal nocturnal hemoglobinuria (PNH). In PNH, the red blood cells are missing certain proteins. The test for PNH can detect red blood cells that are missing these proteins.
                
Osmotic fragility test. This test looks for red blood cells that are more fragile than normal. These cells may be a sign of hereditary spherocytosis (an inherited type of hemolytic anemia).
                
Testing for glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency. In G6PD deficiency, the red blood cells are missing an important enzyme called G6PD. The test for G6PD deficiency looks for this enzyme in a sample of blood.
                
Urine Test
                
A urine test will look for the presence of free hemoglobin (a protein that carries oxygen in the blood) and iron.
                
Bone Marrow Tests
                
Bone marrow tests show whether your bone marrow is healthy and making enough blood cells. The two bone marrow tests are aspiration (as-pi-RA-shun) and biopsy.
                
For a bone marrow aspiration, your doctor removes a small amount of fluid bone marrow through a needle. The sample is examined under a microscope to check for faulty cells.
                
A bone marrow biopsy may be done at the same time as an aspiration or afterward. For this test, your doctor removes a small amount of bone marrow tissue through a needle. The tissue is examined to check the number and type of cells in the bone marrow.
                
You may not need bone marrow tests if blood tests show what&apos;s causing your hemolytic anemia.
                
Tests for Other Causes of Anemia
                
Because anemia has many causes, you may have tests for conditions such as:
                
Kidney failure
                
Lead poisoning
                
Vitamin or iron deficiency
                
Newborn Testing for Sickle Cell Anemia and G6PD Deficiency
                
All States mandate screening for sickle cell anemia as part of their newborn screening programs. Some States also mandate screening for G6PD deficiency. These inherited types of hemolytic anemia can be detected with routine blood tests.
                
Diagnosing these conditions as early as possible is important so that children can get proper treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000068-8" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hemolytic Anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatments for hemolytic anemia include blood transfusions, medicines, plasmapheresis (PLAZ-meh-feh-RE-sis), surgery, blood and marrow stem cell transplants, and lifestyle changes.
                
People who have mild hemolytic anemia may not need treatment, as long as the condition doesn&apos;t worsen. People who have severe hemolytic anemia usually need ongoing treatment. Severe hemolytic anemia can be fatal if it&apos;s not properly treated.
                
Goals of Treatment
                
The goals of treating hemolytic anemia include:
                
Reducing or stopping the destruction of red blood cells
                
Increasing the red blood cell count to an acceptable level
                
Treating the underlying cause of the condition
                
Treatment will depend on the type, cause, and severity of the hemolytic anemia you have. Your doctor also will consider your age, overall health, and medical history.
                
If you have an inherited form of hemolytic anemia, it&apos;s a lifelong condition that may require ongoing treatment. If you have an acquired form of hemolytic anemia, it may go away if its cause can be found and corrected.
                
Blood Transfusions
                
Blood transfusions are used to treat severe or life-threatening hemolytic anemia.
                
A blood transfusion is a common procedure in which blood is given to you through an intravenous (IV) line in one of your blood vessels. Transfusions require careful matching of donated blood with the recipient&apos;s blood.
                
For more information, go to the Health Topics Blood Transfusion article.
                
Medicines
                
Medicines can improve some types of hemolytic anemia, especially autoimmune hemolytic anemia (AIHA). Corticosteroid medicines, such as prednisone, can stop your immune system from, or limit its ability to, make antibodies (proteins) against red blood cells.
                
If you don&apos;t respond to corticosteroids, your doctor may prescribe other medicines to suppress your immune system. Examples include the medicines rituximab and cyclosporine.
                
If you have severe sickle cell anemia, your doctor may recommend a medicine called hydroxyurea. This medicine prompts your body to make fetal hemoglobin. Fetal hemoglobin is the type of hemoglobin that newborns have.
                
In people who have sickle cell anemia, fetal hemoglobin helps prevent red blood cells from sickling and improves anemia.
                
Plasmapheresis
                
Plasmapheresis is a procedure that removes antibodies from the blood. For this procedure, blood is taken from your body using a needle inserted into a vein.
                
The plasma, which contains the antibodies, is separated from the rest of the blood. Then, plasma from a donor and the rest of the blood is put back in your body.
                
This treatment may help if other treatments for immune hemolytic anemia don&apos;t work.
                
Surgery
                
Some people who have hemolytic anemia may need surgery to remove their spleens. The spleen is an organ in the abdomen. A healthy spleen helps fight infection and filters out old or damaged blood cells.
                
An enlarged or diseased spleen may remove more red blood cells than normal, causing anemia. Removing the spleen can stop or reduce high rates of red blood cell destruction.
                
Blood and Marrow Stem Cell Transplant
                
In some types of hemolytic anemia, such as thalassemias, the bone marrow doesn&apos;t make enough healthy red blood cells. The red blood cells it does make may be destroyed before their normal lifespan is over. Blood and marrow stem cell transplants may be used to treat these types of hemolytic anemia.
                
A blood and marrow stem cell transplant replaces damaged stem cells with healthy ones from another person (a donor).
                
During the transplant, which is like a blood transfusion, you get donated stem cells through a tube placed in a vein. Once the stem cells are in your body, they travel to your bone marrow and begin making new blood cells.
                
For more information, go to the Health Topics Blood and Marrow Stem Cell Transplant article.
                
Lifestyle Changes
                
If you have AIHA with cold-reactive antibodies, try to avoid cold temperatures. This can help prevent the breakdown of red blood cells. It&apos;s very important to protect your fingers, toes, and ears from the cold.
                
To protect yourself, you can:
                
Wear gloves or mittens when taking food out of the refrigerator or freezer.
                
Wear a hat, scarf, and a coat with snug cuffs during cold weather.
                
Turn down air conditioning or dress warmly while in air-conditioned spaces.
                
Warm up the car before driving in cold weather.
                
People born with glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency can avoid substances that may trigger anemia. For example, avoid fava beans, naphthalene (a substance found in some moth balls), and certain medicines (as your doctor advises).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000068-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Hemolytic Anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can&apos;t prevent inherited types of hemolytic anemia. One exception is glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency.
                
If you&apos;re born with G6PD deficiency, you can avoid substances that may trigger the condition. For example, avoid fava beans, naphthalene (a substance found in some moth balls), and certain medicines (as your doctor advises).
                
Some types of acquired hemolytic anemia can be prevented. For example, reactions to blood transfusions, which can cause hemolytic anemia, can be prevented. This requires careful matching of blood types between the blood donor and the recipient.
                
Prompt and proper prenatal care can help you avoid the problems of Rh incompatibility. This condition can occur during pregnancy if a woman has Rh-negative blood and her baby has Rh-positive blood. &quot;Rh-negative&quot; and &quot;Rh-positive&quot; refer to whether your blood has Rh factor. Rh factor is a protein on red blood cells.
                
Rh incompatibility can lead to hemolytic anemia in a fetus or newborn.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
