<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000090" source="NHLBI" url="http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/ms">
<Focus>Metabolic Syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0524620</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000090-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Metabolic Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Metabolicsyndrome is the name for a group of risk factors that raises your risk for heart disease and other health problems, such as diabetes and stroke.
                
The term &quot;metabolic&quot; refers to the biochemical processes involved in the body&apos;s normal functioning. Risk factors are traits, conditions, or habits that increase your chance of developing a disease.
                
In this article, &quot;heart disease&quot; refers to coronary heart disease (CHD). CHD is a condition in which a waxy substance called plaque builds up inside the coronary (heart) arteries.
                
Plaque hardens and narrows the arteries, reducing blood flow to your heart muscle. This can lead to chest pain, a heart attack, heart damage, or even death.
                
Metabolic Risk Factors
                
The five conditions described below are metabolic risk factors. You can have any one of these risk factors by itself, but they tend to occur together. You must have at least three metabolic risk factors to be diagnosed with metabolic syndrome.
                
A large waistline. This also is called abdominal obesity or &quot;having an apple shape.&quot; Excess fat in the stomach area is a greater risk factor for heart disease than excess fat in other parts of the body, such as on the hips.
                
A high triglyceride level (or you&apos;re on medicine to treat high triglycerides). Triglycerides are a type of fat found in the blood.
                
A low HDL cholesterol level (or you&apos;re on medicine to treat low HDL cholesterol). HDL sometimes is called &quot;good&quot; cholesterol. This is because it helps remove cholesterol from your arteries. A low HDL cholesterol level raises your risk for heart disease.
                
High blood pressure (or you&apos;re on medicine to treat high blood pressure). Blood pressure is the force of blood pushing against the walls of your arteries as your heart pumps blood. If this pressure rises and stays high over time, it can damage your heart and lead to plaque buildup.
                
High fasting blood sugar (or you&apos;re on medicine to treat high blood sugar). Mildly high blood sugar may be an early sign of diabetes.
                
Overview
                
Your risk for heart disease, diabetes, and stroke increases with the number of metabolic risk factors you have. The risk of having metabolic syndrome is closely linked to overweight and obesity and a lack of physical activity.
                
Insulin resistance also may increase your risk for metabolic syndrome. Insulin resistance is a condition in which the body cant use its insulin properly. Insulin is a hormone that helps move blood sugar into cells where its used for energy. Insulin resistance can lead to high blood sugar levels, and its closely linked to overweight and obesity.Genetics (ethnicity and family history) and older age are other factors that may play a role in causing metabolic syndrome.
                
Outlook
                
Metabolic syndrome is becoming more common due to a rise in obesity rates among adults. In the future, metabolic syndrome may overtake smoking as the leading risk factor for heart disease.
                
It is possible to prevent or delay metabolic syndrome, mainly with lifestyle changes. A healthy lifestyle is a lifelong commitment. Successfully controlling metabolic syndrome requires long-term effort and teamwork with your health care providers.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000090-3" qtype="causes">What causes Metabolic Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Metabolic syndrome has several causes that act together. You can control some of the causes, such as overweight and obesity, an inactive lifestyle, and insulin resistance.
                
You can&apos;t control other factors that may play a role in causing metabolic syndrome, such as growing older. Your risk for metabolic syndrome increases with age.
                
You also can&apos;t control genetics (ethnicity and family history), which may play a role in causing the condition. For example, genetics can increase your risk for insulin resistance, which can lead to metabolic syndrome.
                
People who have metabolic syndrome often have two other conditions: excessive blood clotting and constant, low-grade inflammation throughout the body. Researchers don&apos;t know whether these conditions cause metabolic syndrome or worsen it.
                
Researchers continue to study conditions that may play a role in metabolic syndrome, such as:
                
A fatty liver (excess triglycerides and other fats in the liver)
                
Polycystic ovarian syndrome (a tendency to develop cysts on the ovaries)
                
Gallstones
                
Breathing problems during sleep (such as sleep apnea)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000090-4" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Metabolic Syndrome? ?</Question>
			<Answer>People at greatest risk for metabolic syndrome have these underlying causes:
                
Abdominal obesity (a large waistline)
                
An inactive lifestyle
                
Insulin resistance
                
Some people are at risk for metabolic syndrome because they take medicines that cause weight gain or changes in blood pressure, blood cholesterol, and blood sugar levels. These medicines most often are used to treat inflammation, allergies, HIV, and depression and other types of mental illness.
                
Populations Affected
                
Some racial and ethnic groups in the United States are at higher risk for metabolic syndrome than others. Mexican Americans have the highest rate of metabolic syndrome, followed by whites and blacks.
                
Other groups at increased risk for metabolic syndrome include:
                
People who have a personal history of diabetes
                
People who have a sibling or parent who hasdiabetes
                
Women when compared with men
                
Women who have a personal history of polycystic ovarian syndrome (a tendency to develop cysts on the ovaries)
                
Heart Disease Risk
                
Metabolic syndrome increases your risk for coronary heart disease. Other risk factors, besides metabolic syndrome, also increase your risk for heart disease. For example, a high LDL (bad) cholesterol level and smoking are major risk factors for heart disease. For details about all of the risk factors for heart disease, go to the Coronary Heart Disease Risk Factors HealthTopic.
                
Even if you dont have metabolic syndrome, you should find out your short-term risk for heart disease. The National Cholesterol Education Program (NCEP) divides short-term heart disease risk into four categories. Your risk category depends on which risk factors you have and how many you have.
                
Your risk factors are used to calculate your 10-year risk of developing heart disease. The NCEP has an online calculator that you can use to estimate your 10-year risk of having a heart attack.
                
High risk: Youre in this category if you already have heart disease or diabetes, or if your 10-year risk score is more than 20 percent.
                
Moderately high risk: Youre in this category if you have two or more risk factors and your 10-year risk score is 10 percent to 20 percent.
                
Moderate risk: Youre in this category if you have two or more risk factors and your 10-year risk score is less than 10 percent.
                
Lower risk: Youre in this category if you have zero or one risk factor.
                
Even if your 10-year risk score isnt high, metabolic syndrome will increase your risk for coronary heart disease over time.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000090-5" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Metabolic Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Metabolic syndrome is a group of risk factors that raises your risk for heart disease and other health problems, such as diabetes and stroke. These risk factors can increase your risk for health problems even if they&apos;re only moderately raised (borderline-high risk factors).
                
Most of the metabolic risk factors have no signs or symptoms, although a large waistline is a visible sign.
                
Some people may have symptoms of high blood sugar if diabetesespecially type 2 diabetesis present. Symptoms of high blood sugar often include increased thirst; increased urination, especially at night; fatigue (tiredness); and blurred vision.
                
High blood pressure usually has no signs or symptoms. However, some people in the early stages of high blood pressure may have dull headaches, dizzy spells, or more nosebleeds than usual.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000090-6" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Metabolic Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your doctor will diagnose metabolic syndrome based on the results of a physical exam and blood tests. You must have at least three of the five metabolic risk factors to be diagnosed with metabolic syndrome.
                
Metabolic Risk Factors
                
A Large Waistline
                
Having a large waistline means that you carry excess weight around your waist (abdominal obesity). This is also called having an &quot;apple-shaped&quot; figure. Your doctor will measure your waist to find out whether you have a large waistline.
                
A waist measurement of 35 inches or more for women or 40 inches or more for men is a metabolic risk factor. A large waistline means you&apos;re at increased risk for heart disease and other health problems.
                
A High Triglyceride Level
                
Triglycerides are a type of fat found in the blood. A triglyceride level of 150 mg/dL or higher (or being on medicine to treat high triglycerides) is a metabolic risk factor. (The mg/dL is milligrams per deciliterthe units used to measure triglycerides, cholesterol, and blood sugar.)
                
A Low HDL Cholesterol Level
                
HDL cholesterol sometimes is called &quot;good&quot; cholesterol. This is because it helps remove cholesterol from your arteries.
                
An HDL cholesterol level of less than 50 mg/dL for women and less than 40 mg/dL for men (or being on medicine to treat low HDL cholesterol) is a metabolic risk factor.
                
High Blood Pressure
                
A blood pressure of 130/85 mmHg or higher (or being on medicine to treat high blood pressure) is a metabolic risk factor. (The mmHg is millimeters of mercurythe units used to measure blood pressure.)
                
If only one of your two blood pressure numbers is high, you&apos;re still at risk for metabolic syndrome.
                
High Fasting Blood Sugar
                
A normal fasting blood sugar level is less than 100 mg/dL. A fasting blood sugar level between 100125 mg/dL is considered prediabetes. A fasting blood sugar level of 126 mg/dL or higher is considered diabetes.
                
A fasting blood sugar level of 100 mg/dL or higher (or being on medicine to treat high blood sugar) is a metabolic risk factor.
                
About 85 percent of people who have type 2 diabetesthe most common type of diabetesalso have metabolic syndrome. These people have a much higher risk for heart disease than the 15 percent of people who have type 2 diabetes without metabolic syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000090-7" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Metabolic Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Heart-healthy lifestyle changes are the first line of treatment for metabolic syndrome. Lifestyle changes include heart-healthy eating, losing and maintaining a healthy weight, managing stress, physical activity, and quittingsmoking.
                
If lifestyle changes arent enough, your doctor may prescribe medicines. Medicines are used to treat and control risk factors, such as high blood pressure, high triglycerides, low HDL (good) cholesterol, and high blood sugar.
                
Goals of Treatment
                
The major goal of treating metabolic syndrome is to reduce the risk of coronary heart disease. Treatment is directed first at lowering LDL cholesterol and high blood pressure and managing diabetes (if these conditions are present).
                
The second goal of treatment is to prevent the onset of type2 diabetes, if it hasnt already developed. Long-term complications of diabetes often include heart and kidney disease, vision loss, and foot or leg amputation. If diabetes is present, the goal of treatment is to reduce your risk for heart disease by controlling all of your risk factors.
                

                
Heart-Healthy Lifestyle Changes
                
Heart-Healthy Eating
                
Heart-healthy eating is an important part of a heart-healthy lifestyle. Your doctor may recommend heart-healthy eating, which should include:
                
Fat-free or low-fat dairy products, such as skim milk
                
Fish high in omega-3 fatty acids, such as salmon, tuna, and trout, about twice a week
                
Fruits, such as apples, bananas, oranges, pears, and prunes
                
Legumes, such as kidney beans, lentils, chickpeas, black-eyed peas, and lima beans
                
Vegetables, such as broccoli, cabbage, and carrots
                
Whole grains, such as oatmeal, brown rice, and corn tortillas
                
When following a heart-healthy diet, you should avoid eating:
                
A lot of red meat
                
Palm and coconut oils
                
Sugary foods and beverages
                
Two nutrients in your diet make blood cholesterol levels rise:
                
Saturated fatfound mostly in foods that come from animals
                
Trans fat (trans fatty acids)found in foods made with hydrogenated oils and fats, such as stick margarine; baked goods, such as cookies, cakes, and pies; crackers; frostings; and coffee creamers. Some trans fats also occur naturally in animal fats and meats.
                
Saturated fat raises your blood cholesterol more than anything else in your diet. When you follow a heart-healthy eating plan, only 5percent to 6percent of your daily calories should come from saturated fat. Food labels list the amounts of saturated fat. To help you stay on track, here are some examples:
                
If you eat:
                
Try to eat no more than:
                
1,200 calories a day                     
                
8 grams of saturated fat a day            
                
1,500 calories a day
                
10 grams of saturated fat a day
                
1,800 calories a day
                
12 grams of saturated fat a day
                
2,000 calories a day
                
13 grams of saturated fat a day
                
2,500 calories a day
                
17 grams of saturated fat a day
                
Not all fats are bad. Monounsaturated and polyunsaturated fats actually help lower blood cholesterol levels. Some sources of monounsaturated and polyunsaturated fats are:
                
Avocados
                
Corn, sunflower, and soybean oils
                
Nuts and seeds, such as walnuts
                
Olive, canola, peanut, safflower, and sesame oils
                
Peanut butter
                
Salmon and trout
                
Tofu
                
Sodium
                
You should try to limit the amount of sodium that you eat. This means choosing and preparing foods that are lower in salt and sodium. Try to use low-sodium and no added salt foods and seasonings at the table or while cooking. Food labels tell you what you need to know about choosing foods that are lower in sodium. Try to eat no more than 2,300milligrams of sodium a day. If you have high blood pressure, you may need to restrict your sodium intake even more.
                
Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension
                
Your doctor may recommend the Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension (DASH) eating plan if you have high blood pressure. The DASH eating plan focuses on fruits, vegetables, whole grains, and other foods that are heart healthy and low in fat, cholesterol, and sodium and salt.
                
The DASH eating plan is a good heart-healthy eating plan, even for those who dont have high blood pressure. Read more about DASH.
                
Limiting Alcohol
                
Try to limit alcohol intake. Too much alcohol can raise your blood pressure and triglyceride levels, a type of fat found in the blood. Alcohol also adds extra calories, which may cause weightgain.
                
Men should have no more than two drinks containing alcohol a day. Women should have no more than one drink containing alcohol a day. One drink is:
                
12 ounces of beer
                
5 ounces of wine
                
1 ounces of liquor
                

                
Maintaining a Healthy Weight
                
If you have metabolic syndrome and are overweight or obese, your doctor will recommend weight loss. He or she can help you create a weight-loss plan and goals. Maintaining a healthy weight can lower your risk for metabolic syndrome, coronary heart disease, and other health problems. Aim for a Healthy Weight by following a heart-healthy eating plan and keeping physically active.
                
Knowing your body mass index (BMI) helps you find out if youre a healthy weight in relation to your height and gives an estimate of your total body fat. To figure out your BMI, check out the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institutes (NHLBI) online BMI calculator or talk to your doctor. A BMI:
                
Below 18.5 is a sign that you are underweight.
                
Between 18.5 and 24.9 is in the normal range.
                
Between 25.0 and 29.9 is considered overweight.
                
Of 30.0 or higher is considered obese.
                
A general goal to aim for is a BMI of less than 25. Your doctor or health care provider can help you set an appropriate BMI goal.
                
Measuring waist circumference helps screen for possible health risks. If most of your fat is around your waist rather than at your hips, youre at a higher risk for heart disease and type2 diabetes. This risk may be higher with a waist size that is greater than 35 inches for women or greater than 40 inches for men.
                
If youre overweight or obese, try to lose weight. A loss of just 3percent to 5percent of your current weight can lower your triglycerides, blood glucose, and the risk of developing type2 diabetes. Greater amounts of weight loss can improve blood pressure readings, lower LDL (bad) cholesterol, and increase HDL cholesterol.
                

                
Managing Stress
                
Learning how to manage stress, relax, and cope with problems can improve your emotional and physical health. Consider healthy stress-reducing activities, such as:
                
A stress management program
                
Meditation
                
Physical activity
                
Relaxation therapy
                
Talking things out with friends or family
                

                
Physical Activity
                
Regular physical activity can lower your risk for metabolic syndrome, coronary heart disease, and other health problems. Everyone should try to participate in moderate-intensity aerobic exercise at least 2hours and 30minutes per week or vigorous aerobic exercise for 1hour and 15minutes per week. Aerobic exercise, such as brisk walking, is any exercise in which your heart beats faster and you use more oxygen than usual. The more active you are, the more you will benefit. Participate in aerobic exercise for at least 10minutes at a time spread throughout the week.
                
Talk with your doctor before you start a new exercise plan. Ask your doctor how much and what kinds of physical activity are safe for you.
                
Read more about physical activity at:
                
Physical Activity and Your Heart
                
U.S. Department of Health and Human Services 2008 Physical Activity Guidelines for Americans
                

                
Quitting Smoking
                
If you smoke, quit. Smoking can raise your risk for heart disease and heart attack and worsen other heart disease risk factors. Talk with your doctor about programs and products that can help you quit smoking. Also, try to avoid secondhand smoke.
                
If you have trouble quitting smoking on your own, consider joining a support group. Many hospitals, workplaces, and community groups offer classes to help people quit smoking. For more information about how to quit smoking, go to the Smoking and Your Heart Health Topic.
                

                
Medicines
                
Sometimes lifestyle changes arent enough to control your risk factors for metabolic syndrome. For example, you may need statin medications to control or lower your cholesterol. By lowering your blood cholesterol level, you can decrease your chance of having a heart attack or stroke. Doctors usually prescribe statins for people who have:
                
Diabetes
                
Heart disease or had a prior stroke
                
High LDL cholesterol levels
                
Doctors may discuss beginning statin treatment with those who have an elevated risk for developing heart disease or having a stroke.
                
Your doctor also may prescribe other medications to:
                
Decrease your chance of having a heart attack or dying suddenly.
                
Lower your blood pressure.
                
Prevent blood clots, which can lead to heart attack or stroke.
                
Reduce your hearts workload and relieve symptoms of coronary heart disease.
                
Take all medicines regularly, as your doctor prescribes. Dont change the amount of your medicine or skip a dose unless your doctor tells you to. You should still follow a heart-healthy lifestyle, even if you take medicines to treat your risk factors for metabolic syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000090-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Metabolic Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Making heart-healthy lifestyle choices is the best way to prevent metabolic syndrome by:
                
Being physically active
                
Following a heart-healthy eating plan
                
Knowing your weight, waist measurement, and body mass index
                
Maintaining a healthy weight
                
Make sure to schedule routine doctor visits to keep track of your cholesterol, blood pressure, and blood sugar levels. Speak with your doctor about a blood test called a lipoprotein panel, which shows your levels of total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol, HDL cholesterol, and triglycerides.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
