<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000366" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/schistosomiasis/">
<Focus>Parasites - Schistosomiasis</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000366-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Parasites - Schistosomiasis ?</Question>
<Answer>Schistosomiasis, also known as bilharzia, is a disease caused by parasitic worms. Infection with Schistosoma mansoni, S. haematobium, and S. japonicum causes illness in humans; less commonly, S. mekongi and S. intercalatum can cause disease. Although the worms that cause schistosomiasis are not found in the United States, more than 200 million people are infected worldwide.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000366-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Parasites - Schistosomiasis? ?</Question>
<Answer>Schistosomiasis is an important cause of disease in many parts of the world, most commonly in places with poor sanitation. School-age children who live in these areas are often most at risk because they tend to spend time swimming or bathing in water containing infectious cercariae.
If you live in, or travel to, areas where schistosomiasis is found and are exposed to contaminated freshwater, you are at risk.
   
Areas where human schistosomiasis is found include:
   
    - Schistosoma mansoni 
     
      - distributed throughout Africa: There is risk of infection in freshwater in southern and sub-Saharan Africa–including the great lakes and rivers as well as smaller bodies of water. Transmission also occurs in the Nile River valley in Sudan and Egypt
      - South America: including Brazil, Suriname, Venezuela
      - Caribbean (risk is low): Dominican Republic, Guadeloupe, Martinique, and Saint Lucia.
     
    - S. haematobium 
     
      - distributed throughout Africa: There is risk of infection in freshwater in southern and sub-Saharan Africa–including the great lakes and rivers as well as smaller bodies of water. Transmission also occurs in the Nile River valley in Egypt and the Mahgreb region of North Africa.
      - found in areas of the Middle East
     
    - S. japonicum 
     
      - found in Indonesia and parts of China and Southeast Asia
     
    - S. mekongi 
     
      - found in Cambodia and Laos
     
    - S. intercalatum 
     
      - found in parts of Central and West Africa.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000366-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parasites - Schistosomiasis ?</Question>
<Answer>Stool or urine samples can be examined microscopically for parasite eggs (stool for S. mansoni or S. japonicum eggs and urine for S. haematobium eggs). The eggs tend to be passed intermittently and in small amounts and may not be detected, so it may be necessary to perform a blood (serologic) test.
    
More on: Resources for Health Professionals: Diagnosis</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000366-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parasites - Schistosomiasis ?</Question>
<Answer>Safe and effective medication is available for treatment of both urinary and intestinal schistosomiasis. Praziquantel, a prescription medication, is taken for 1-2 days to treat infections caused by all Schistosoma species.
    
More on: Resources for Health Professionals: Treatment</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="7">
<Question qid="0000366-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Parasites - Schistosomiasis ?</Question>
<Answer>Prevention
    
No vaccine is available.
    
The best way to prevent schistosomiasis is to take the following steps if you are visiting or live in an area where schistosomiasis is transmitted:
    
     - Avoid swimming or wading in freshwater when you are in countries in which schistosomiasis occurs. Swimming in the ocean and in chlorinated swimming pools is safe.
     - Drink safe water. Although schistosomiasis is not transmitted by swallowing contaminated water, if your mouth or lips come in contact with water containing the parasites, you could become infected. Because water coming directly from canals, lakes, rivers, streams, or springs may be contaminated with a variety of infectious organisms, you should either bring your water to a rolling boil for 1 minute or filter water before drinking it. Bring your water to a rolling boil for at least 1 minute will kill any harmful parasites, bacteria, or viruses present. Iodine treatment alone WILL NOT GUARANTEE that water is safe and free of all parasites.
     - Water used for bathing should be brought to a rolling boil for 1 minute to kill any cercariae, and then cooled before bathing to avoid scalding. Water held in a storage tank for at least 1 - 2 days should be safe for bathing.
     - Vigorous towel drying after an accidental, very brief water exposure may help to prevent the Schistosoma parasite from penetrating the skin. However, do not rely on vigorous towel drying alone to prevent schistosomiasis.
    
    
Those who have had contact with potentially contaminated water overseas should see their health care provider after returning from travel to discuss testing.
    
More on: Schistosomiasis in Travelers
   
  
  
   Control
   
In countries where schistosomiasis causes significant disease, control efforts usually focus on:
   
    - reducing the number of infections in people and/or
    - eliminating the snails that are required to maintain the parasite’s life cycle.
   
   
For all species that cause schistosomiasis, improved sanitation could reduce or eliminate transmission of this disease. In some areas with lower transmission levels, elimination of schistosomiasis is considered a &quot;winnable battle&quot; by public health officials.
   
Control measures can include mass drug treatment of entire communities and targeted treatment of school-age children. Some of the problems with control of schistosomiasis include:
   
    - Chemicals used to eliminate snails in freshwater sources may harm other species of animals in the water and, if treatment is not sustained, the snails may return to those sites afterwards.
    - For certain species of the parasite, such as S. japonicum, animals such as cows or water buffalo can also be infected. Runoff from pastures (if the cows are infected) can contaminate freshwater sources.</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
