<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000418" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/trichinellosis/">
<Focus>Parasites - Trichinellosis (also known as Trichinosis)</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000418-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Parasites - Trichinellosis (also known as Trichinosis) ?</Question>
<Answer>Trichinellosis, also called trichinosis, is caused by eating raw or undercooked meat of animals infected with the larvae of a species of worm called Trichinella. Infection occurs commonly in certain wild carnivorous (meat-eating) animals such as bear or cougar, or omnivorous (meat and plant-eating) animals such as domestic pigs or wild boar.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000418-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Parasites - Trichinellosis (also known as Trichinosis)? ?</Question>
<Answer>People acquire trichinellosis by consuming raw or undercooked meat infected with the Trichinella parasite, particularly wild game meat or pork. Even tasting very small amounts of undercooked meat during preparation or cooking puts you at risk for infection. Outbreaks occur in settings where multiple people consume the same Trichinella-infected meat.
Worldwide, an estimated 10,000 cases of trichinellosis occur every year. Several different species of Trichinella can cause human disease; the most common species is Trichinella spiralis, which has a global distribution and is the species most commonly found in pigs. Other Trichinella species are less commonly reported as the cause of human disease and may be found in different parts of the world, usually infecting wild animals.
In the United States, trichinellosis cases are reported to CDC much less commonly now than in the past (Figure 1). During the late 1940s, when the U.S. Public Health Service began counting cases of trichinellosis, 400 cases in the United States were recorded each year on average. During 2008-2010, 20 cases were reported to CDC each year on average. The overall number of cases reported has decreased because of improved pig-raising practices in the pork industry, commercial and home freezing of pork, and public awareness of the danger of eating raw or undercooked meat products. The number of cases associated with raw or undercooked wild game meats has remained relatively constant over time (Figure 2). Over the past 40 years, few cases of trichinellosis have been reported in the United States, and the risk of trichinellosis from commercially raised and properly prepared pork is very low. However, eating undercooked wild game, particularly bear meat, puts one at risk for acquiring this disease.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000418-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parasites - Trichinellosis (also known as Trichinosis) ?</Question>
<Answer>A diagnosis of trichinellosis is made in patients whose signs and symptoms are compatible with trichinellosis, have a positive laboratory test for Trichinella, and who can recall eating raw or undercooked pork or wild game meat.
    
Laboratory diagnosis of Trichinella infection is most often made by a Trichinella antibody test. In some cases a muscle biopsy may be performed.
    
More on: Resources for Health Professionals: Diagnosis</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000418-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parasites - Trichinellosis (also known as Trichinosis) ?</Question>
<Answer>Safe and effective prescription drugs are available to treat both Trichinella infection and the symptoms that occur as a result of infection. Treatment should begin as soon as possible; a doctor will make the decision to treat based upon symptoms, exposure to raw or undercooked meat, and laboratory test results.
    
More on: Resources For Health Professionals: Treatment</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="7">
<Question qid="0000418-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Parasites - Trichinellosis (also known as Trichinosis) ?</Question>
<Answer>- Wash your hands with warm water and soap after handling raw meat.
    - Curing (salting), drying, smoking, or microwaving meat alone does not consistently kill infective worms; homemade jerky and sausage were the cause of many cases of trichinellosis reported to CDC in recent years.
    - Freeze pork less than 6 inches thick for 20 days at 5°F (-15°C) to kill any worms.
    - Freezing wild game meats, unlike freezing pork products, may not effectively kill all worms because some worm species that infect wild game animals are freeze-resistant.
    - Clean meat grinders thoroughly after each use.
   
   
To help prevent Trichinella infection in animal populations, do not allow pigs or wild animals to eat uncooked meat, scraps, or carcasses of any animals, including rats, which may be infected with Trichinella.</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
