<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000344" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/baylisascaris/index.html">
<Focus>Parasites - Baylisascaris infection</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000344-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Parasites - Baylisascaris infection ?</Question>
<Answer>Baylisascaris worms are intestinal parasites found in a wide variety of animals. Different species of Baylisascaris are associated with different animal hosts. For example, Baylisascaris procyonis is found in raccoons and Baylisascaris columnaris is an intestinal parasite found in skunks. Cases of Baylisascaris infection in people are not frequently reported, but can be severe. Baylisascaris procyonis is thought to pose the greatest risk to humans because of the often close association of raccoons to human dwellings.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000344-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Parasites - Baylisascaris infection? ?</Question>
<Answer>Raccoons are the primary, or definitive, host of Baylisascaris procyonis, a roundworm. Raccoons become infected with Baylisascaris in one of two ways:
    
     - Young raccoons become infected by eating eggs during foraging, feeding, and grooming.
     - Adult raccoons acquire the infection by eating rodents, rabbits, and birds infected with the larvae of Baylisascaris.
    
    
Infected raccoons have been found throughout the United States, mainly in the Midwest, Northeast, Middle Atlantic, and West Coast.
    
Raccoons are peridomestic animals, which means they live in or around areas where people live. Roundworm eggs are passed in the feces of infected raccoons. Raccoons defecate in communal sites, called latrines. Raccoon latrines are often found at bases of trees, unsealed attics, or on flat surfaces such as logs, tree stumps, rocks, decks, and rooftops. As more raccoons move into populated areas, the number and density of their latrines will increase.
    
While raccoons are the roundworm&apos;s primary host, other types of animals can become infected. Birds and small mammals, such as rodents and rabbits, are susceptible to the parasite. Unlike raccoons, these animals sometimes show signs of infection, such as muscle spasms, tremors, and progressive weakness; infection can lead to death. Predator animals, including dogs, may become infected by eating an animal that has been infected with Baylisascaris. In some dogs, Baylisascaris may develop to adult worms and pass eggs in the dogs&apos; feces.
    
The worms develop to maturity in the raccoon intestine, where they produce millions of eggs that are passed in the feces. Eggs that are excreted by raccoons are not immediately infectious. These eggs must develop in the environment for 2 to 4 weeks, after which the eggs are able to cause infection. The eggs are resistant to most environmental conditions and with adequate moisture, can survive for years.
    
     
    
    
Humans become infected by ingesting embryonated (fertile) eggs. Anyone who is exposed to environments where raccoons frequent is potentially at risk. Young children or developmentally disabled persons are at highest risk for infection as they may be more likely to put contaminated fingers, soil, or objects into their mouths.
    
Hunters, trappers, taxidermists, and wildlife handlers may also be at increased risk if they have contact with raccoons or raccoon habitats.
    
Fewer than 25 cases of Baylisascaris disease have been documented in the United States. However, it is possible that some cases are incorrectly diagnosed as other infections or go undiagnosed. Cases that are diagnosed tend to be severe.
    
Cases have been reported in California, Illinois, Louisiana, Massachusetts, Michigan, Minnesota, Missouri, New York, Oregon, and Pennsylvania. As of 2012, there were 16 published human neurological cases in the US; six of the infected persons died.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000344-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parasites - Baylisascaris infection ?</Question>
<Answer>If you suspect you have been infected, consult your health care provider immediately. Be sure to tell your health care provider if you have recently been exposed to raccoons or their feces.
    
Diagnosis is difficult because symptoms depend on the number of infecting larvae and location in the body. Ocular larva migrans, when the larvae migrate to the eye, can cause sensitivity to light, inflammation of the eye, and blindness. Symptoms of visceral larva migrans, when the larvae travel to organs, depend on which organs are affected. For example, an invasion of the liver may cause hepatomegaly (inflammation and enlargement of the liver), while an invasion of the lung may cause pulmonary symptoms such as cough or chest pain. Larvae rarely end up in the nervous system but the most severe cases are neural larva migrans, when the larvae migrate into the brain and cause it to swell (encephalitis). There is no commercially available test for Baylisascaris infection. A health care provider may test blood, cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), and tissue to determine if an individual is infected. Eye examinations may reveal a migrating larva or lesions and are often the most significant clue to infection with Baylisascaris.
    
Diagnosis often is made by ruling out other infections that cause similar symptoms. Information on diagnosis and testing can be obtained through your local or state health department or CDC.
    
More on: Resources for Health Professionals: Diagnosis</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000344-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parasites - Baylisascaris infection ?</Question>
<Answer>No drugs have been shown to be totally effective for the treatment of Baylisascaris infection. Albendazole, a broad spectrum anthelmintic, has been recommended for specific cases.
    
Early treatment might reduce serious damage caused by the infection. Should you suspect you may have ingested raccoon feces, seek immediate medical attention.
    
More on: Resources for Health Professionals: Treatment</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="7">
<Question qid="0000344-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Parasites - Baylisascaris infection ?</Question>
<Answer>Baylisascaris infection can be prevented by avoiding contact with raccoons and their feces. Washing your hands after working or playing outdoors is good practice for preventing a number of diseases.
    
Do not keep, feed, or adopt wild animals, including raccoons, as pets. Infection rarely causes symptoms in raccoons, so you cannot tell if a raccoon is infected by observing its behavior. Roundworm eggs passed in the feces of infected raccoons are not visible to the naked eye. Eggs can only be seen using a microscope.
    
     
    
    
You may discourage raccoons from living in and around your home or parks by taking these steps:
    
     - prevent access to food
     - keep trash containers tightly closed
     - close off access to attics and basements
     - keep sandboxes covered when not in use (raccoons may use sandboxes as a latrine)
     - remove fish ponds -- they eat the fish and drink the water
     - eliminate water sources
     - remove bird feeders
     - clear brush so raccoons are not likely to make a den on your property
    
    
Stay away from areas and materials that might be contaminated by raccoon feces. Raccoons typically defecate at the base of or in raised forks of trees, or on raised horizontal surfaces such as fallen logs, stumps, or large rocks. Raccoon feces also can be found on woodpiles, decks, rooftops, and in attics, garages, and haylofts. Feces usually are dark and tubular, have a pungent odor (usually worse than dog or cat feces), and often contain undigested seeds or other food items.
    
If you have found a raccoon latrine near your home, cleaning the area may prevent possible infection. Newly deposited eggs take at least 2-4 weeks to become infective. Prompt removal and destruction of raccoon feces will reduce risk for exposure and possible infection.
    
More on: Raccoon Latrine Clean-up [PDF, 111 KB, 1 page]
    
     
    
    
If you choose to clean the site yourself, care should be taken to avoid contaminating hands and clothes.
    
     - Wear disposable gloves to help prevent cross contamination.
     - Wear a N95-rated respirator if working in a confined space to prevent accidental ingestion of eggs or other harmful materials.
     - Avoid stirring up dust and debris- you can lightly mist the latrine area with a little water from a spray bottle to reduce the amount of dust.
     - Wear rubber boots that can be scrubbed or cover your shoes with disposable booties that can be thrown away, so that you do not bring eggs into your household.
     - Feces and material contaminated with raccoon feces should be removed and burned, buried, or sent to a landfill.
     - Most chemicals do not kill roundworm eggs; however, heat kills the eggs instantly.
     - Treat feces-soiled decks, patios, and other surfaces with boiling water or a propane torch (please contact your local fire department for regulations and safety practices).
    
    
To help further reduce the risk of possible infection, wash your hands well with soap and warm running water. Clean/launder your clothes thoroughly with hot water and detergent.
    
More on: Handwashing
    
If you are cleaning an indoor raccoon latrine and are not able to use a propane torch, use a damp (but not wet) sponge to wipe the area with hot soapy water. Rinse your sponge frequently. After you are finished, flush dirty water down the toilet. Place the sponge in a plastic bag and put the plastic bag in the garbage.
    
Contact your local animal control office for additional assistance.
    Dogs
    
Dogs may be infected with adult B. procyonis roundworms, but may not show symptoms. Have all pets de-wormed under a veterinarian&apos;s supervision and take precautions to avoid contact with their feces.
    Exotic pets
    
Raccoons and dogs are not the only hosts of Baylisascaris. B. procyonis infection has also been documented in kinkajous. Other animals such as coatis may be susceptible. When wild animals are kept as pets, there can be a risk of disease transmission to humans.</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
