<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000094" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/vpd-vac/varicella/default.htm">
<Focus>Varicella (Chickenpox) Vaccination</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000094-1" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Varicella (Chickenpox) Vaccination ?</Question>
<Answer>At a Glance 
 
Vaccine-preventable disease levels are at or near record lows. Even though most infants and toddlers have received all recommended vaccines by age 2, many under-immunized children remain, leaving the potential for outbreaks of disease. Many adolescents and adults are under-immunized as well, missing opportunities to protect themselves against diseases such as Hepatitis B, influenza, and pneumococcal disease. CDC works closely with public health agencies and private partners to improve and sustain immunization coverage and to monitor the safety of vaccines so that this public health success story can be maintained and expanded in the century to come.  
  
 Vaccine Shortages &amp; Delays 
  
   
   
 
   
  
  
   
   
The latest national information about vaccine supplies and guidance for healthcare providers who are facing vaccine shortages or delays 
     
    
   
  
  
 
  
  
  
 Potential New Vaccines 
  
   
   
 
   
  
  
   
   
Resources for finding information on potential vaccines, research and development status, licensure status, etc. 
       
    
   
  
  
 
  
  
  
 Vaccines: The Basics 
  
   
   
 
   
  
  
   
   
Without vaccines, epidemics of many preventable diseases could return, resulting in increased – and unnecessary – illness, disability, and death. 
          
    
   
  
  
 
  
  
  
 FAQ about Vaccines &amp; Diseases they Prevent 
  
   
   
 
   
  
  
   
          
    
   
  
  
 
  
  
   
  
                
 
                
 
 
 
                
  
 
  
  
Images and logos on this website which are trademarked/copyrighted or used with permission of the trademark/copyright or logo holder are not in the public domain. These images and logos have been licensed for or used with permission in the materials provided on this website. The materials in the form presented on this website may be used without seeking further permission. Any other use of trademarked/copyrighted images or logos requires permission from the trademark/copyright holder...more 
  
  
  
  This graphic notice means that you are leaving an HHS Web site. For more information, please see the Exit Notification and Disclaimer policy.</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
