<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000092" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/vhf/chapare/index.html">
<Focus>Chapare Hemorrhagic Fever (CHHF)</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000092-1" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Chapare Hemorrhagic Fever (CHHF)? ?</Question>
<Answer>Like all arenaviruses, Chapare virus has a rodent host as its reservoir. Humans can contract CHHF through contact with an infected rodent. Contact can be direct or through inhalation of aerosolized Chapare virus from the urine or feces of infected rodents. 
 
Although arenaviruses have been isolated from insects, neither they nor any other intermediary host appear to spread CHHF. 
 
Person-to-person transmission of arenaviruses through aerosolization, although possible, is rare. From the only observed cluster of cases of CHHF, there was no evidence of person-to-person transmission. 
 
Transmission, if it can occur with CHHF, is most likely the result of direct contact with an infected person.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000092-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Chapare Hemorrhagic Fever (CHHF) ?</Question>
<Answer>The symptoms of CHHF, as reported in the only described patient, resemble those of other South American hemorrhagic fevers, such as Argentine HF or Bolivian HF. The incubation period is unknown, but for Argentine hemorrhagic fever (AHF) is 6 to 16 days. 
   
The CHHF clinical course included: 
    
    - fever 
    - headache 
    - articulation and muscle pain 
    - vomiting 
    
   
These symptoms were followed by deterioration with multiple hemorrhagic signs. The only described CHHF patient died 14 days after onset of symptoms. 
   
Since Arenaviruses may enter the fetus through infection of the mother, and anecdotal evidence suggests that infected pregnant women may suffer miscarriages, it is reasonable to assume that both infection of the fetus and miscarriage may be associated with CHHF infection in the mother.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="3">
<Question qid="0000092-3" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Chapare Hemorrhagic Fever (CHHF)? ?</Question>
<Answer>CHHF occurs in the Cochabamba region of Bolivia. 
Field workers 
                
Field workers are at greatest risk because of increased human contact with the reservoir rodent population. Sexual partners of field workers may be at greater risk as well. Laboratory infections have been frequently described with Arenaviruses and Chapare virus can certainly be transmitted to laboratory workers during manipulation of the virus especially during experimental infections of rodents.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="4">
<Question qid="0000092-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Chapare Hemorrhagic Fever (CHHF) ?</Question>
<Answer>CHHF virus has been successfully isolated from both blood and serum during the acute febrile phase of illness. Although not undertaken at the time of the initial cluster, virus can certainly be isolated from tissue obtained post-mortem if available. A subsequent complete genomic analysis of Chapare virus facilitated the development of specific molecular detection (RT-PCR) assays. 
   
Serologic diagnosis of CHHF can be made by indirect immunofluorescent assay and ELISA. However, individuals from endemic areas who show fever, dizziness, and myalgia, accompanied by laboratory findings of low white blood cell and platelet counts and excess protein in the urine, should be suspected of having one of the South American hemorrhagic fever viruses. Clinical specimens should be tested using specific assays.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000092-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Chapare Hemorrhagic Fever (CHHF) ?</Question>
<Answer>Supportive therapy is important in CHHF. This includes: 
    
    - maintenance of hydration 
    - management of shock 
    - sedation 
    - pain relief 
    - usual precautions for patients with bleeding disorders 
    - transfusions (when necessary) 
    
   
Use of convalescent plasma therapy for treatment of AHF reduces mortality significantly and anecdotal evidence shows that the antiviral drug ribavirin may also hold promise for treating AHF. Ribavirin has also been considered for preventing development of disease in people exposed to other arenaviruses. 
   Recovery 
   
The precise mortality of CHHF is unknown and the only described case was fatal. 
   
Patients who have suffered from other arenaviruses may continue to excrete virus in urine or semen for weeks after recovery. For this reason, these fluids should be monitored for infectivity, since convalescent patients have the potential to infect others (particularly sexual partners) via these fluids.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000092-6" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Chapare Hemorrhagic Fever (CHHF) ?</Question>
<Answer>Although rodent control would be desirable, it will not be a successful strategy for preventing Chapare hemorrhagic fever cases caused by exposures outdoors. 
   
As for other hemorrhagic fevers, full barrier nursing procedures should be implemented during management of suspected or confirmed CHHF cases.</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
