<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000144" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/echinococcosis/">
<Focus>Parasites - Echinococcosis</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000144-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Parasites - Echinococcosis ?</Question>
<Answer>Frequently Asked Questions (FAQs)
    
Cystic echinococcosis (CE) disease results from being infected with the larval stage of Echinococcus granulosus, a tiny tapeworm (~2-7 millimeters in length) found in dogs (definitive host), sheep, cattle, goats, foxes, and pigs, amongst others (intermediate hosts). Most infections in humans are asymptomatic, but CE, also known as hydatid disease, causes slowly enlarging masses, most commonly in the liver and the lungs. Treatment can involve both medication and surgery.
    
More on: Cystic Echinococcosis (CE) FAQs
    
Alveolar echinococcosis (AE) disease results from being infected with the larval stage of Echinococcus multilocularis, a tiny tapeworm (~1-4 millimeters in length) found in foxes, coyotes, dogs, and cats (definitive hosts). Although human cases are rare, infection in humans causes parasitic tumors to form in the liver, and, less commonly, the lungs, brain, and other organs. If left untreated, infection with AE can be fatal.
    
More on: Alveolar Echinococcosis (AE) FAQs</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000144-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Parasites - Echinococcosis? ?</Question>
<Answer>Cystic echinococcosis (CE) is caused by infection with the larval stage of Echinococcus granulosus. CE is found in Africa, Europe, Asia, the Middle East, Central and South America, and in rare cases, North America. The parasite is transmitted to dogs when they ingest the organs of other animals that contain hydatid cysts. The cysts develop into adult tapeworms in the dog. Infected dogs shed tapeworm eggs in their feces which contaminate the ground. Sheep, cattle, goats, and pigs ingest tapeworm eggs in the contaminated ground; once ingested, the eggs hatch and develop into cysts in the internal organs. The most common mode of transmission to humans is by the accidental consumption of soil, water, or food that has been contaminated by the fecal matter of an infected dog. Echinococcus eggs that have been deposited in soil can stay viable for up to a year. The disease is most commonly found in people involved in raising sheep, as a result of the sheep&apos;s role as an intermediate host of the parasite and the presence of working dogs that are allowed to eat the offal of infected sheep.
    
Alveolar echinococcosis (AE) is caused by infection with the larval stage of Echinococcus multilocularis. AE is found across the globe and is especially prevalent in the northern latitudes of Europe, Asia, and North America. The adult tapeworm is normally found in foxes, coyotes, and dogs. Infection with the larval stages is transmitted to people through ingestion of food or water contaminated with tapeworm eggs.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000144-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parasites - Echinococcosis ?</Question>
<Answer>The presence of a cyst-like mass in a person with a history of exposure to sheepdogs in an area where E. granulosus is endemic suggests a diagnosis of cystic echinococcosis. Imaging techniques, such as CT scans, ultrasonography, and MRIs, are used to detect cysts. After a cyst has been detected, serologic tests may be used to confirm the diagnosis.
    
Alveolar echinococcosis is typically found in older people. Imaging techniques such as CT scans are used to visually confirm the parasitic vesicles and cyst-like structures and serologic tests can confirm the parasitic infection.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000144-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parasites - Echinococcosis ?</Question>
<Answer>In the past, surgery was the only treatment for cystic echinococcal cysts. Chemotherapy, cyst puncture, and PAIR (percutaneous aspiration, injection of chemicals and reaspiration) have been used to replace surgery as effective treatments for cystic echinococcosis. However, surgery remains the most effective treatment to remove the cyst and can lead to a complete cure. Some cysts are not causing any symptoms and are inactive; those cysts often go away without any treatment.
    
The treatment of alveolar echinococcosis is more difficult than cystic echinococcosis and usually requires radical surgery, long-term chemotherapy, or both.
    
More on: Resources for Health Professionals: Treatment</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="7">
<Question qid="0000144-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Parasites - Echinococcosis ?</Question>
<Answer>Cystic echinococcosis is controlled by preventing transmission of the parasite. Prevention measures include limiting the areas where dogs are allowed and preventing animals from consuming meat infected with cysts.
    
     - Prevent dogs from feeding on the carcasses of infected sheep.
     - Control stray dog populations.
     - Restrict home slaughter of sheep and other livestock.
     - Do not consume any food or water that may have been contaminated by fecal matter from dogs.
     - Wash your hands with soap and warm water after handling dogs, and before handling food.
     - Teach children the importance of washing hands to prevent infection.
    
    
Alveolar echinococcosis can be prevented by avoiding contact with wild animals such as foxes, coyotes, and dogs and their fecal matter and by limiting the interactions between dogs and rodent populations.
    
     - Do not allow dogs to feed on rodents and other wild animals.
     - Avoid contact with wild animals such as foxes, coyotes and stray dogs.
     - Do not encourage wild animals to come close to your home or keep them as pets.
     - Wash your hands with soap and warm water after handling dogs or cats, and before handling food.
     - Teach children the importance of washing hands to prevent infection.
    
    
More on: Handwashing</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
