<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000244" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/h1n1flu/">
<Focus>2009 H1N1 Flu</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000244-1" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose 2009 H1N1 Flu ?</Question>
<Answer>Content on this page was developed during the 2009-2010 H1N1 pandemic and has not been updated. 
    
    - The H1N1 virus that caused that pandemic is now a regular human flu virus and continues to circulate seasonally worldwide. 
    - The English language content on this website is being archived for historic and reference purposes only.  
    
    
  General Information 
    
   
  Information for Health Care Professionals</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="3">
<Question qid="0000244-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for 2009 H1N1 Flu ?</Question>
<Answer>Content on this page was developed during the 2009-2010 H1N1 pandemic and has not been updated. 
    
    - The H1N1 virus that caused that pandemic is now a regular human flu virus and continues to circulate seasonally worldwide. 
    - The English language content on this website is being archived for historic and reference purposes only.  
    
    
   
  General Information 
   
  
Quick Facts for the Public on Antiviral Treatments for 2009 H1N1 (NEW) Nov 23 
  
2009 H1N1 and Seasonal Flu: What You Should Know About Flu Antiviral Drugs (PDF Version) Oct 13 
  
Questions &amp; Answers: Antiviral Drugs, 2009-2010 Flu Season 
  
Questions &amp; Answers: Opening and Mixing Tamiflu® Capsules with Liquids if Child Cannot Swallow Capsules  Nov 16 
  
 Podcast: Take Three Actions to Fight Flu 
  Information for Health Care Professionals 
  
Quick Facts for Clinicians on Antiviral Treatments for 2009 H1N1 Nov 4 
  
Antiviral Recommendations Oct 16 
  
Intravenous Peramivir Oct 24 
  
CDC Podcast: Antiviral Drugs for the 2009-2010 Influenza Season Oct 19 
  
Antiviral Safety Information Nov 3 
  
Pediatric Supplement Recommendations Dec 1 
  
 Information for Pharmacists (including information related to supply of antiviral drugs) Nov 25 
  
 Emergency Use Authorization (EUA) of Medical Products and Devices (including antiviral drugs) 
  
Recommendations for Obstetric Health Care Providers Oct 28 
  
(Video Blog) 2009 H1N1: Who Should Receive Antiviral Therapy? Dec 1 
  
Frontline Questions and Expert Opinion Answers Dec 9</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
