<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000273" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/nczved/divisions/dfbmd/diseases/marine_toxins">
<Focus>Marine Toxins</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="12">
<Question qid="0000273-12" qtype="information">what are marine toxins?</Question>
<Answer>Marine toxins are naturally occurring chemicals that can contaminate certain seafood. The seafood contaminated with these chemicals frequently looks, smells, and tastes normal. When humans eat such seafood, disease can result.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="14">
<Question qid="0000273-14" qtype="exams and tests">how can these diseases be diagnosed for Marine Toxins ?</Question>
<Answer>Diagnosis of marine toxin poisoning is generally based on symptoms and a history of recently eating a particular kind of seafood. Laboratory testing for the specific toxin in patient samples is generally not necessary because this requires special techniques and equipment available in only specialized laboratories. If suspect, leftover fish or shellfish are available, they can be tested for the presence of the toxin more easily. Identification of the specific toxin is not usually necessary for treating patients because there is no specific treatment.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="15">
<Question qid="0000273-15" qtype="treatment">how can these diseases be treated for Marine Toxins ?</Question>
<Answer>Other than supportive care there are few specific treatments for ciguatera poisoning, paralytic shellfish poisoning, neurotoxic shellfish poisoning, or amnesic shellfish poisoning. Antihistamines and epinephrine, however, may sometimes be useful in treating the symptoms of scombrotoxic fish poisoning. Intravenous mannitol has been suggested for the treatment of severe ciguatera poisoning.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="17">
<Question qid="0000273-17" qtype="frequency">how common are these diseases for Marine Toxins ?</Question>
<Answer>Every year, approximately 30 cases of poisoning by marine toxins are reported in the United States. Because healthcare providers are not required to report these illnesses and because many milder cases are not diagnosed or reported, the actual number of poisonings may be much greater. Toxic seafood poisonings are more common in the summer than winter because dinoflagelates grow well in warmer seasons. It is estimated from cases with available data that one person dies every 4 years from toxic seafood poisonings.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="18">
<Question qid="0000273-18" qtype="prevention">what can i do to prevent poisoning by marine toxins?</Question>
<Answer>General guidelines for safe seafood consumption:</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="19">
<Question qid="0000273-19" qtype="information">what is the government doing about these diseases for Marine Toxins ?</Question>
<Answer>Some health departments test shellfish harvested within their jurisdiction to monitor the level of dinoflagellate toxins and asses the risk for contamination. Based on the results of such testing, recreational and commercial seafood harvesting may be prohibited locally during periods of risk. State and federal regulatory agencies monitor reported cases of marine toxin poisoning, and health departments investigate possible outbreaks and devise control measures. The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) provides support to investigators as needed.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="20">
<Question qid="0000273-20" qtype="prevention">what else can be done to prevent these diseases for Marine Toxins ?</Question>
<Answer>It is important to notify public health departments about even one person with marine toxin poisoning. Public health departments can then investigate to determine if a restaurant, oyster bed, or fishing area has a problem. This prevents other illnesses. In any food poisoning occurrence, consumers should note foods eaten and freeze any uneaten portions in case they need to be tested. A commercial test has been developed in Hawaii to allow persons to test sport caught fish for ciguatoxins.</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
