<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<DiseaseFile fid="0000397" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/taeniasis/">
<Focus>Parasites - Taeniasis</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000397-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Parasites - Taeniasis ?</Question>
<Answer>Taeniasis in humans is a parasitic infection caused by the tapeworm species Taenia saginata (beef tapeworm), Taenia solium (pork tapeworm), and Taenia asiatica (Asian tapeworm). Humans can become infected with these tapeworms by eating raw or undercooked beef (T. saginata) or pork (T. solium and T. asiatica). People with taeniasis may not know they have a tapeworm infection because symptoms are usually mild or nonexistent.

T. solium tapeworm infections can lead to cysticercosis, which is a disease that can cause seizures, so it is important seek treatment.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000397-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Parasites - Taeniasis? ?</Question>
<Answer>The tapeworms that cause taeniasis (Taenia saginata, T. solium, and T. asiatica) are found worldwide. Eating raw or undercooked beef or pork is the primary risk factor for acquiring taeniasis. Persons who don&apos;t eat raw or undercooked beef or pork are not likely to get taeniasis.
    
Infections with T. saginata occur wherever contaminated raw beef is eaten, particularly in Eastern Europe, Russia, eastern Africa and Latin America. Taeniasis due to T. saginata is rare in the United States, except in places where cattle and people are concentrated and sanitation is poor, such as around feed lots when cattle can be exposed to human feces. Tapeworm infections due to T. solium are more prevalent in under-developed communities with poor sanitation and where people eat raw or undercooked pork. Higher rates of illness have been seen in people in Latin America, Eastern Europe, sub-Saharan Africa, India, and Asia. Taenia solium taeniasis is seen in the United States, typically among Latin American immigrants. Taenia asiatica is limited to Asia and is seen mostly in the Republic of Korea, China, Taiwan, Indonesia, and Thailand.
    
A disease called cysticercosis can occur when T. solium tapeworm eggs are ingested. For example, people with poor hygiene who have taeniasis -- with or without symptoms -- will shed tapeworm eggs in their feces and might accidentally contaminate their environment. This can lead to transmission of cysticercosis to themselves or others.
    
More on: Cysticercosis</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000397-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parasites - Taeniasis ?</Question>
<Answer>Diagnosis of Taenia tapeworm infections is made by examination of stool samples; individuals should also be asked if they have passed tapeworm segments. Stool specimens should be collected on three different days and examined in the lab for Taenia eggs using a microscope. Tapeworm eggs can be detected in the stool 2 to 3 months after the tapeworm infection is established.
    
Tapeworm eggs of T. solium can also infect humans, causing cysticercosis. It is important to diagnose and treat all tapeworm infections.
    
More on: cysticercosis</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000397-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parasites - Taeniasis ?</Question>
<Answer>Treatment is available after accurate diagnosis. Your doctor will provide prescription medication, either praziquantel or niclosamide, which is taken by mouth. The medication is also available in a children’s dosage. Work with your health care provider for proper treatment options for you and your family.
    
More on: Resources For Health Professionals: Treatment</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="7">
<Question qid="0000397-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Parasites - Taeniasis ?</Question>
<Answer>One way to prevent taeniasis is to cook meat to safe temperatures. A food thermometer should be used to measure the internal temperature of cooked meat. Do not sample meat until it is cooked. USDA recommends the following for meat preparation.
   
    - For Whole Cuts of Meat (excluding poultry) 
     
      - Cook to at least 145° F (63° C) as measured with a food thermometer placed in the thickest part of the meat, then allow the meat to rest* for three minutes before carving or consuming.
     
    - For Ground Meat (excluding poultry) 
     
      - Cook to at least 160° F (71° C); ground meats do not require a rest* time.
     
   
   
*According to USDA, &quot;A &apos;rest time&apos; is the amount of time the product remains at the final temperature, after it has been removed from a grill, oven, or other heat source. During the three minutes after meat is removed from the heat source, its temperature remains constant or continues to rise, which destroys pathogens.&quot;
   
More on: Fight BAC: Safe Food Handling</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</DiseaseFile>
