<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000272" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/vhf/marburg/">
<Focus>Marburg hemorrhagic fever (Marburg HF)</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000272-1" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Marburg hemorrhagic fever (Marburg HF)? ?</Question>
<Answer>It is unknown how Marburg virus first transmits from its animal host to humans; however, for the 2 cases in tourists visiting Uganda in 2008, unprotected contact with infected bat feces or aerosols are the most likely routes of infection. 
  
After this initial crossover of virus from host animal to humans, transmission occurs through person-to-person contact. This may happen in several ways: direct contact to droplets of body fluids from infected persons, or contact with equipment and other objects contaminated with infectious blood or tissues. 
  
In previous outbreaks, persons who have handled infected non-human primates or have come in direct contact with their fluids or cell cultures have become infected. Spread of the virus between humans has occurred in close environments and direct contacts. A common example is through caregivers in the home or in a hospital (nosocomial transmission).</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000272-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Marburg hemorrhagic fever (Marburg HF) ?</Question>
<Answer>After an incubation period of 5-10 days, symptom onset is sudden and marked by fever, chills, headache, and myalgia. Around the fifth day after the onset of symptoms, a maculopapular rash, most prominent on the trunk (chest, back, stomach), may occur. Nausea, vomiting, chest pain, a sore throat, abdominal pain, and diarrhea may then appear. Symptoms become increasingly severe and can include jaundice, inflammation of the pancreas, severe weight loss, delirium, shock, liver failure, massive hemorrhaging, and multi-organ dysfunction. 
 
Because many of the signs and symptoms of Marburg hemorrhagic fever are similar to those of other infectious diseases such as malaria or typhoid fever, clinical diagnosis of the disease can be difficult, especially if only a single case is involved. 
 
The case-fatality rate for Marburg hemorrhagic fever is between 23-90%. For a complete listing of the case fatality rates for previous outbreaks, please see the History of Outbreaks table</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="3">
<Question qid="0000272-3" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Marburg hemorrhagic fever (Marburg HF)? ?</Question>
<Answer>People who have close contact with African fruit bats, humans patients, or non-human primates infected with Marburg virus are at risk. 
                
Historically, the people at highest risk include family members and hospital staff who care for patients infected with Marburg virus and have not used proper barrier nursing techniques. Particular occupations, such as veterinarians and laboratory or quarantine facility workers who handle non-human primates from Africa, may also be at increased risk of exposure to Marburg virus. 
                
Exposure risk can be higher for travelers visiting endemic regions in Africa, including Uganda and other parts of central Africa, and have contact with fruit bats, or enter caves or mines inhabited by fruit bats.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="4">
<Question qid="0000272-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Marburg hemorrhagic fever (Marburg HF) ?</Question>
<Answer>Many of the signs and symptoms of Marburg hemorrhagic fever are similar to those of other more frequent infectious diseases, such as malaria or typhoid fever, making diagnosis of the disease difficult. This is especially true if only a single case is involved. 
 
However, if a person has the early symptoms of Marburg HF and there is reason to believe that Marburg HF should be considered, the patient should be isolated and public health professionals notified. Samples from the patient can then be collected and tested to confirm infection. 
 
Antigen-capture enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) testing, polymerase chain reaction (PCR), and IgM-capture ELISA can be used to confirm a case of Marburg HF within a few days of symptom onset. Virus isolation may also be performed but should only be done in a high containment laboratory with good laboratory practices. The IgG-capture ELISA is appropriate for testing persons later in the course of disease or after recovery. In deceased patients, immunohistochemistry, virus isolation, or PCR of blood or tissue specimens may be used to diagnose Marburg HF retrospectively.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000272-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Marburg hemorrhagic fever (Marburg HF) ?</Question>
<Answer>There is no specific treatment for Marburg hemorrhagic fever. Supportive hospital therapy should be utilized, which includes balancing the patient&apos;s fluids and electrolytes, maintaining oxygen status and blood pressure, replacing lost blood and clotting factors, and treatment for any complicating infections. 
 
Experimental treatments are validated in non-human primates models, but have never been tried in humans.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000272-6" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Marburg hemorrhagic fever (Marburg HF) ?</Question>
<Answer>Preventive measures against Marburg virus infection are not well defined, as transmission from wildlife to humans remains an area of ongoing research. However, avoiding fruit bats, and sick non-human primates in central Africa, is one way to protect against infection. 
 
Measures for prevention of secondary, or person-to-person, transmission are similar to those used for other hemorrhagic fevers. If a patient is either suspected or confirmed to have Marburg hemorrhagic fever, barrier nursing techniques should be used to prevent direct physical contact with the patient. These precautions include wearing of protective gowns, gloves, and masks; placing the infected individual in strict isolation; and sterilization or proper disposal of needles, equipment, and patient excretions. 
 
In conjunction with the World Health Organization, CDC has developed practical, hospital-based guidelines, titled: Infection Control for Viral Haemorrhagic Fevers In the African Health Care Setting. The manual can help health-care facilities recognize cases and prevent further hospital-based disease transmission using locally available materials and few financial resources. 
 
Marburg hemorrhagic fever is a very rare human disease. However, when it occurs, it has the potential to spread to other people, especially health care staff and family members who care for the patient. Therefore, increasing awareness in communities and among health-care providers of the clinical symptoms of patients with Marburg hemorrhagic fever is critical. Better awareness can lead to earlier and stronger precautions against the spread of Marburg virus in both family members and health-care providers. Improving the use of diagnostic tools is another priority. With modern means of transportation that give access even to remote areas, it is possible to obtain rapid testing of samples in disease control centers equipped with Biosafety Level 4 laboratories in order to confirm or rule out Marburg virus infection.</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
