<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000432" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/whipworm/">
<Focus>Parasites - Trichuriasis (also known as Whipworm Infection)</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000432-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Parasites - Trichuriasis (also known as Whipworm Infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>Whipworm (Trichuris trichiura) is an intestinal parasite of humans. The larvae and adult worms live in the intestine of humans and can cause intestinal disease. The name is derived from the worm’s distinctive whip-like shape.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000432-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Parasites - Trichuriasis (also known as Whipworm Infection)? ?</Question>
<Answer>Whipworm is a soil-transmitted helminth (STH) and is the third most common roundworm of humans. Whipworm causes an infection called trichuriasis and often occurs in areas where human feces is used as fertilizer or where defecation onto soil happens. The worms are spread from person to person by fecal-oral transmission or through feces-contaminated food.
    Geographic Distribution
Worldwide, infection occurs more frequently in areas with tropical weather and poor sanitation practices, and among children. In 2002, the estimated number of persons infected with whipworm was 1 billion. Trichuriasis also occurs in the southern United States.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000432-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parasites - Trichuriasis (also known as Whipworm Infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>The standard method for diagnosing the presence of whipworm is by microscopically identifying whipworm eggs in a stool sample. Because eggs may be difficult to find in light infections, a concentration procedure is recommended.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000432-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parasites - Trichuriasis (also known as Whipworm Infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>Anthelminthic medications (drugs that rid the body of parasitic worms), such as albendazole and mebendazole, are the drugs of choice for treatment. Infections are generally treated for 3 days. The recommended medications are effective. Health care providers may decide to repeat a stool exam after treatment. Iron supplements may also be prescribed if the infected person suffers from anemia.
    
More on: Resources for Health Professionals: Treatment</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="7">
<Question qid="0000432-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Parasites - Trichuriasis (also known as Whipworm Infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>The best way to prevent whipworm infection is to always:
    
     - Avoid ingesting soil that may be contaminated with human feces, including where human fecal matter (&quot;night soil&quot;) or wastewater is used to fertilize crops.
     - Wash your hands with soap and warm water before handling food.
     - Teach children the importance of washing hands to prevent infection.
     - Wash, peel, or cook all raw vegetables and fruits before eating, particularly those that have been grown in soil that has been fertilized with manure.
    
    
More on: Handwashing
    
Transmission of infection to others can be prevented by
    
     - Not defecating outdoors.
     - Effective sewage disposal systems.</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
