<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000120" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/cyclosporiasis/">
<Focus>Parasites - Cyclosporiasis (Cyclospora Infection)</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000120-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Parasites - Cyclosporiasis (Cyclospora Infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>Cyclospora cayetanensis is a parasite composed of one cell, too small to be seen without a microscope. This parasite causes an intestinal infection called cyclosporiasis.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000120-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Parasites - Cyclosporiasis (Cyclospora Infection)? ?</Question>
<Answer>People become infected with Cyclospora by ingesting sporulated oocysts, which are the infective form of the parasite. This most commonly occurs when food or water contaminated with feces is consumed. An infected person sheds unsporulated (immature, non-infective) Cyclospora oocysts in the feces. The oocysts are thought to require days to weeks in favorable environmental conditions to sporulate (become infective). Therefore, direct person-to-person transmission is unlikely, as is transmission via ingestion of newly contaminated food or water.
    
More on: Cyclospora Biology
    Geographic Distribution
    
Cyclosporiasis occurs in many countries, but it seems to be most common in tropical and subtropical regions. In areas where cyclosporiasis has been studied, the risk for infection is seasonal. However, no consistent pattern has been identified regarding the time of year or the environmental conditions, such as temperature or rainfall.
    
In the United States, foodborne outbreaks of cyclosporiasis since the mid-1990s have been linked to various types of imported fresh produce, including raspberries, basil, snow peas, and mesclun lettuce; no commercially frozen or canned produce has been implicated.
    
U.S. cases of infection also have occurred in persons who traveled to Cyclospora-endemic areas. To reduce the risk for infection, travelers should take precautions, such as those recommended in CDC&apos;s Health Information for International Travel (Yellow Book). Travelers also should be aware that treatment of water or food with chlorine or iodine is unlikely to kill Cyclospora oocysts.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000120-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parasites - Cyclosporiasis (Cyclospora Infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>Clinical Diagnosis
    
Health care providers should consider Cyclospora as a potential cause of prolonged diarrheal illness, particularly in patients with a history of recent travel to Cyclospora-endemic areas. Testing for Cyclospora is not routinely done in most U.S. laboratories, even when stool is tested for parasites. Therefore, if indicated, health care providers should specifically request testing for Cyclospora.
    
More on: Resources for Health Professionals: Diagnosis
    Laboratory Diagnosis
    
Cyclospora infection is diagnosed by examining stool specimens. Diagnosis can be difficult in part because even persons who are symptomatic might not shed enough oocysts in their stool to be readily detectable by laboratory examinations. Therefore, patients might need to submit several specimens collected on different days.
    
Special techniques, such as acid-fast staining, are often used to make Cyclospora oocysts more visible under the microscope. In addition, Cyclospora oocysts are autofluorescent, meaning that when stool containing the parasite is viewed under an ultraviolet (UV) fluorescence microscope the parasite appears blue or green against a black background. Molecular diagnostic methods, such as polymerase chain reaction (PCR) analysis, are used to look for the parasite&apos;s DNA in the stool.
    
More on: Key points for the laboratory diagnosis of cyclosporiasis</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000120-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parasites - Cyclosporiasis (Cyclospora Infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>Trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole (TMP/SMX), sold under the trade names Bactrim*, Septra*, and Cotrim*, is the usual therapy for Cyclospora infection. No highly effective alternative antibiotic regimen has been identified yet for patients who do not respond to the standard treatment or have a sulfa allergy.
    
More on: Resources for Health Professionals: Treatment
    
Most people who have healthy immune systems will recover without treatment. If not treated, the illness may last for a few days to a month or longer. Symptoms may seem to go away and then return one or more times (relapse). Anti-diarrheal medicine may help reduce diarrhea, but a health care provider should be consulted before such medicine is taken. People who are in poor health or who have weakened immune systems may be at higher risk for severe or prolonged illness.
    
More on: Resources for Health Professionals FAQs
    
* Use of trade names is for identification only and does not imply endorsement by the Public Health Service or by the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="7">
<Question qid="0000120-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Parasites - Cyclosporiasis (Cyclospora Infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>On the basis of the currently available information, avoiding food or water that may have been contaminated with feces is the best way to prevent cyclosporiasis. Treatment with chlorine or iodine is unlikely to kill Cyclospora oocysts. No vaccine for cyclosporiasis is available.
    
The U.S. Food and Drug Administration&apos;s (FDA) Center for Food Safety and Applied Nutrition (CFSAN) publishes detailed food safety recommendations for growers and suppliers. In its Guide to Minimize Microbial Food Safety Hazards for Fresh Fruits and Vegetables, CFSAN describes good agricultural practices (GAPs) and good manufacturing practices (GMPs) for fresh fruits and vegetables. The guidelines address the growing, harvesting, sorting, packaging, and storage processes; following the guidelines can help reduce the overall risk for microbial contamination during these processes. The precise ways that food and water become contaminated with Cyclospora oocysts are not fully understood.
    
CDC monitors the occurrence of cyclosporiasis in the United States and helps state health departments identify and investigate cyclosporiasis outbreaks to prevent additional cases of illness.
    
More on: Surveillance and Outbreak Response</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
