<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000415" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/toxoplasmosis/">
<Focus>Parasites - Toxoplasmosis (Toxoplasma infection)</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000415-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Parasites - Toxoplasmosis (Toxoplasma infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>A single-celled parasite called Toxoplasma gondii causes a disease known as toxoplasmosis. While the parasite is found throughout the world, more than 60 million people in the United States may be infected with the Toxoplasma parasite. Of those who are infected, very few have symptoms because a healthy person’s immune system usually keeps the parasite from causing illness. However, pregnant women and individuals who have compromised immune systems should be cautious; for them, a Toxoplasma infection could cause serious health problems.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000415-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Parasites - Toxoplasmosis (Toxoplasma infection)? ?</Question>
<Answer>Toxoplasmosis is caused by the protozoan parasite Toxoplasma gondii. In the United States it is estimated that 22.5% of the population 12 years and older have been infected with Toxoplasma. In various places throughout the world, it has been shown that up to 95% of some populations have been infected with Toxoplasma. Infection is often highest in areas of the world that have hot, humid climates and lower altitudes. 
    
Toxoplasmosis is not passed from person-to-person, except in instances of mother-to-child (congenital) transmission and blood transfusion or organ transplantation. People typically become infected by three principal routes of transmission. 
         
     
     
       
      
     
    
      
    Foodborne transmission 
    
The tissue form of the parasite (a microscopic cyst consisting of bradyzoites) can be transmitted to humans by food. People become infected by: 
     
     - Eating undercooked, contaminated meat (especially pork, lamb, and venison) 
     - Accidental ingestion of undercooked, contaminated meat after handling it and not washing hands thoroughly (Toxoplasma cannot be absorbed through intact skin) 
     - Eating food that was contaminated by knives, utensils, cutting boards, or other foods that had contact with raw, contaminated meat 
     
    
      
    Animal-to-human (zoonotic) transmission 
    
Cats play an important role in the spread of toxoplasmosis. They become infected by eating infected rodents, birds, or other small animals. The parasite is then passed in the cat&apos;s feces in an oocyst form, which is microscopic. 
    
Kittens and cats can shed millions of oocysts in their feces for as long as 3 weeks after infection. Mature cats are less likely to shed Toxoplasma if they have been previously infected. A Toxoplasma-infected cat that is shedding the parasite in its feces contaminates the litter box. If the cat is allowed outside, it can contaminate the soil or water in the environment as well. 
     
       
      
     
    
People can accidentally swallow the oocyst form of the parasite. People can be infected by: 
     
     - Accidental ingestion of oocysts after cleaning a cat&apos;s litter box when the cat has shed Toxoplasma in its feces 
     - Accidental ingestion of oocysts after touching or ingesting anything that has come into contact with a cat&apos;s feces that contain Toxoplasma 
     - Accidental ingestion of oocysts in contaminated soil (e.g., not washing hands after gardening or eating unwashed fruits or vegetables from a garden) 
     - Drinking water contaminated with the Toxoplasma parasite 
     
    
      
    Mother-to-child (congenital) transmission 
    
A woman who is newly infected with Toxoplasma during pregnancy can pass the infection to her unborn child (congenital infection). The woman may not have symptoms, but there can be severe consequences for the unborn child, such as diseases of the nervous system and eyes. 
    
      
    Rare instances of transmission 
    
Organ transplant recipients can become infected by receiving an organ from a Toxoplasma-positive donor. Rarely, people can also become infected by receiving infected blood via transfusion. Laboratory workers who handle infected blood can also acquire infection through accidental inoculation.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000415-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parasites - Toxoplasmosis (Toxoplasma infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>The diagnosis of toxoplasmosis is typically made by serologic testing. A test that measures immunoglobulin G (IgG) is used to determine if a person has been infected. If it is necessary to try to estimate the time of infection, which is of particular importance for pregnant women, a test which measures immunoglobulin M (IgM) is also used along with other tests such as an avidity test.
    
Diagnosis can be made by direct observation of the parasite in stained tissue sections, cerebrospinal fluid (CSF), or other biopsy material. These techniques are used less frequently because of the difficulty of obtaining these specimens.
    
Parasites can also be isolated from blood or other body fluids (for example, CSF) but this process can be difficult and requires considerable time.
    
Molecular techniques that can detect the parasite&apos;s DNA in the amniotic fluid can be useful in cases of possible mother-to-child (congenital) transmission.
    
Ocular disease is diagnosed based on the appearance of the lesions in the eye, symptoms, course of disease, and often serologic testing.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000415-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parasites - Toxoplasmosis (Toxoplasma infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>Healthy people (nonpregnant)
    
Most healthy people recover from toxoplasmosis without treatment. Persons who are ill can be treated with a combination of drugs such as pyrimethamine and sulfadiazine, plus folinic acid.
    
     
    Pregnant women, newborns, and infants
    
Pregnant women, newborns, and infants can be treated, although the parasite is not eliminated completely. The parasites can remain within tissue cells in a less active phase; their location makes it difficult for the medication to completely eliminate them.
    
     
    Persons with ocular disease
    
Persons with ocular toxoplasmosis are sometimes prescribed medicine to treat active disease by their ophthalmologist. Whether or not medication is recommended depends on the size of the eye lesion, the location, and the characteristics of the lesion (acute active, versus chronic not progressing).
    
     
    Persons with compromised immune systems
    
Persons with compromised immune systems need to be treated until they have improvement in their condition. For AIDS patients, continuation of medication for the rest of their lives may be necessary, or for as long as they are immunosuppressed.
    
More on: Resources for Health Professionals: Treatment</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="7">
<Question qid="0000415-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Parasites - Toxoplasmosis (Toxoplasma infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>People who are healthy should follow the guidelines below to reduce risk of toxoplasmosis. If you have a weakened immune system, please see guidelines for Immunocompromised Persons.
   Reduce Risk from Food
   
To prevent risk of toxoplasmosis and other infections from food:
   
    - Freeze meat for several days at sub-zero (0° F) temperatures before cooking to greatly reduce chance of infection.
    - Peel or wash fruits and vegetables thoroughly before eating. 
     
      
     
    - Wash cutting boards, dishes, counters, utensils, and hands with hot soapy water after contact with raw meat, poultry, seafood, or unwashed fruits or vegetables.
   
   
More on: Handwashing
   
The U.S. Government and the meat industry continue their efforts to reduce T. gondii in meat.
   Reduce Risk from the Environment
   
To prevent risk of toxoplasmosis from the environment:
   
    - Avoid drinking untreated drinking water.
    - Wear gloves when gardening and during any contact with soil or sand because it might be contaminated with cat feces that contain Toxoplasma. Wash hands with soap and warm water after gardening or contact with soil or sand.
    - Teach children the importance of washing hands to prevent infection.
    - Keep outdoor sandboxes covered. 
     
      
     
    - Feed cats only canned or dried commercial food or well-cooked table food, not raw or undercooked meats.
    - Change the litter box daily if you own a cat. The Toxoplasma parasite does not become infectious until 1 to 5 days after it is shed in a cat&apos;s feces. If you are pregnant or immunocompromised: 
     
      - Avoid changing cat litter if possible. If no one else can perform the task, wear disposable gloves and wash your hands with soap and warm water afterwards.
      - Keep cats indoors.
      - Do not adopt or handle stray cats, especially kittens. Do not get a new cat while you are pregnant.</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
