<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000121" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/cysticercosis/">
<Focus>Parasites - Cysticercosis</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000121-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Parasites - Cysticercosis ?</Question>
<Answer>Cysticercosis is an infection caused by the larvae of the parasite Taenia solium.  This infection occurs after a person swallows tapeworm eggs. The larvae get into tissues such as muscle and brain, and form cysts there (these are called cysticerci). When cysts are found in the brain, the condition is called neurocysticercosis.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="3">
<Question qid="0000121-3" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Parasites - Cysticercosis? ?</Question>
<Answer>Cysticercosis is an infection caused by the larvae of the tapeworm, Taenia solium. A person with an adult tapeworm, which lives in the person’s gut, sheds eggs in the stool.  The infection with the adult tapeworm is called taeniasis.  A pig then eats the eggs in the stool.  The eggs develop into larvae inside the pig and form cysts (called cysticerci) in the pig&apos;s muscles or other tissues. The infection with the cysts is called cysticercosis. Humans who eat undercooked or raw infected pork swallow the cysts in the meat. The larvae then come out of their cysts in the human gut and develop into adult tapeworms, completing the cycle.
    
People get cysticercosis when they swallow eggs that are excreted in the stool of people with the adult tapeworm. This may happen when people
    
     - Drink water or eat food contaminated with tapeworm eggs
     - Put contaminated fingers in their mouth
    
    
Cysticercosis is not spread by eating undercooked meat. However, people get infected with tapeworms (taeniasis) by eating undercooked infected pork. People who have tapeworm infections can infect themselves with the eggs and develop cysticercosis (this is called autoinfection). They can also infect other people if they have poor hygiene and contaminate food or water that other people swallow. People who live with someone who has a tapeworm infection in their intestines have a much higher risk of getting cysticercosis than other people.
    
Human cysticercosis is found worldwide, especially in areas where pig cysticercosis is common. Both taeniasis and cysticercosis are most often found in rural areas of developing countries with poor sanitation, where pigs roam freely and eat human feces. Taeniasis and cysticercosis are rare among persons who live in countries where pigs are not raised and in countries where pigs do not have contact with human feces. Although uncommon, cysticercosis can occur in people who have never traveled outside of the United States if they are exposed to tapeworm eggs.
    
More on: Taeniasis</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000121-6" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parasites - Cysticercosis ?</Question>
<Answer>If you think that you may have cysticercosis, please see your health care provider. Your health care provider will ask you about your symptoms, where you have travelled, and what kinds of foods you eat. The diagnosis of neurocysticercosis usually requires MRI or CT brain scans. Blood tests may be useful to help diagnose an infection, but they may not always be positive in light infections.
  
If you have been diagnosed with cysticercosis, you and your family members should be tested for intestinal tapeworm infection. See the taeniasis section for more information on intestinal tapeworm infections.  
  
More on: Taeniasis
  
More on: Resources for Health Professionals: Diagnosis</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="7">
<Question qid="0000121-7" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parasites - Cysticercosis ?</Question>
<Answer>Some people with cysticercosis do not need to be treated. There are medications available to treat cysticercosis for those who do need treatment. Sometimes surgery may be needed. Your doctor will advise you on which treatment is best for you.
    
More on: Resources for Health Professionals: Treatment
    
More on: Taeniasis</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="8">
<Question qid="0000121-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Parasites - Cysticercosis ?</Question>
<Answer>To prevent cysticercosis, the following precautions should be taken:
    
     - Wash your hands with soap and warm water after using the toilet, changing diapers, and before handling food
     - Teach children the importance of washing hands to prevent infection
     - Wash and peel all raw vegetables and fruits before eating
     - Use good food and water safety practices while traveling in developing countries such as: 
      
       - Drink only bottled or boiled (1 minute) water or carbonated (bubbly) drinks in cans or bottles
       - Filter unsafe water through an &quot;absolute 1 micron or less&quot; filter AND dissolve iodine tablets in the filtered water; &quot;absolute 1 micron&quot; filters can be found in camping and outdoor supply stores
      
    
    
More on: Handwashing
    
More on: Food and Water Safety</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
