<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000053" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/lice/body/">
<Focus>Parasites - Lice - Body Lice</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000053-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Parasites - Lice - Body Lice ?</Question>
<Answer>Body lice are parasitic insects that live on clothing and bedding used by infested persons. Body lice frequently lay their eggs on or near the seams of clothing. Body lice must feed on blood and usually only move to the skin to feed. Body lice exist worldwide and infest people of all races. Body lice infestations can spread rapidly under crowded living conditions where hygiene is poor (the homeless, refugees, victims of war or natural disasters). In the United States, body lice infestations are found only in homeless transient populations who do not have access to bathing and regular changes of clean clothes. Infestation is unlikely to persist on anyone who bathes regularly and who has at least weekly access to freshly laundered clothing and bedding.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000053-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Parasites - Lice - Body Lice? ?</Question>
<Answer>Body lice infestation is found worldwide but generally is limited to persons who live under conditions of crowding and poor hygiene who do not have access to regular bathing and changes of clean clothes, such as:
    
     - the homeless,
     - refugees,
     - survivors of war or natural disasters.
    
    
Infestations can spread rapidly under such conditions. Body lice infestation can occur in people of all races.
    
Body lice are spread through direct contact with a person who has body lice or through contact with articles such as clothing, beds, bed linens, or towels that have been in contact with an infested person. However, in the United States, actual infestation with body lice tends to be occur only in homeless, transient persons who do not have access to regular bathing and changes of clean clothes.
    
Body lice can transmit disease. Epidemics of typhus and louse-borne relapsing fever have been caused by body lice (typically in areas where climate, poverty, and social customs or war and social upheaval prevent regular changes and laundering of clothing).</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000053-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parasites - Lice - Body Lice ?</Question>
<Answer>Body lice infestation is diagnosed by finding eggs and crawling lice in the seams of clothing. Sometimes a body louse can be seen crawling or feeding on the skin.
    
Although body lice and nits can be large enough to be seen with the naked eye, a magnifying lens may be necessary to find crawling lice or eggs.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000053-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parasites - Lice - Body Lice ?</Question>
<Answer>A body lice infestation is treated by improving the personal hygiene of the infested person, including assuring a regular (at least weekly) change of clean clothes. Clothing, bedding, and towels used by the infested person should be laundered using hot water (at least 130°F) and machine dried using the hot cycle.
    
Sometimes the infested person also is treated with a pediculicide, a medicine that can kill lice; however, a pediculicide generally is not necessary if hygiene is maintained and items are laundered appropriately at least once a week. A pediculicide should be applied exactly as directed on the bottle or by your physician.
    
If you choose to treat, guidelines for the choice of the pediculicide are the same as for head lice.
    
More on: Head Lice Treatment</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="7">
<Question qid="0000053-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Parasites - Lice - Body Lice ?</Question>
<Answer>Body lice are spread most commonly by direct contact with an infested person or an infested person’s clothing or bedding. Body lice usually infest persons who do not launder and change their clothes regularly.
    
The following are steps that can be taken to help prevent and control the spread of body lice:
    
     - Bathe regularly and change into properly laundered clothes at least once a week; launder infested clothing at least once a week.
     - Machine wash and dry infested clothing and bedding using the hot water (at least 130°F) laundry cycle and the high heat drying cycle. Clothing and items that are not washable can be dry-cleaned OR sealed in a plastic bag and stored for 2 weeks.
     - Do not share clothing, beds, bedding, and towels used by an infested person.
     - Fumigation or dusting with chemical insecticides sometimes is necessary to control and prevent the spread of body lice for certain diseases (epidemic typhus).</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
