<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000001" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/acanthamoeba/">
<Focus>Acanthamoeba - Granulomatous Amebic Encephalitis (GAE); Keratitis</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000001-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Acanthamoeba - Granulomatous Amebic Encephalitis (GAE); Keratitis ?</Question>
<Answer>Acanthamoeba is a microscopic, free-living ameba (single-celled living organism) commonly found in the environment that can cause rare, but severe, illness. Acanthamoeba causes three main types of illness involving the eye (Acanthamoeba keratitis), the brain and spinal cord (Granulomatous Encephalitis), and infections that can spread throughout the entire body (disseminated infection).</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000001-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Acanthamoeba - Granulomatous Amebic Encephalitis (GAE); Keratitis? ?</Question>
<Answer>Acanthamoeba keratitis
  
   
Acanthamoeba keratitis is a rare disease that can affect anyone, but is most common in individuals who wear contact lenses. In the United States, an estimated 85% of cases occur in contact lens users. The incidence of the disease in developed countries is approximately one to 33 cases per million contact lens wearers.
   
For people who wear contact lenses, certain practices can increase the risk of getting Acanthamoeba keratitis:
   
    - Storing and handling lenses improperly
    - Disinfecting lenses improperly (such as using tap water or topping off solutions when cleaning the lenses or lens case)
    - Swimming, using a hot tub, or showering while wearing lenses
    - Coming into contact with contaminated water
    - Having a history of trauma to the cornea
   
   
Contact lens wearers who practice proper lens care and non-contact lens wearers can still develop the infection. For additional information on contact lens care and prevention of Acanthamoeba keratitis visit CDC’s web page on Prevention and Control.
   
There have been no reports of Acanthamoeba keratitis being spread from one person to another.
   Granulomatous Amebic Encephalitis (GAE)
   
Granulomatous Amebic Encephalitis (GAE) and disseminated infection are very rare forms of Acanthamoeba infection and primarily affect people with compromised immune systems. While unusual, disseminated infection can also affect healthy children and adults. Conditions that may increase a patient’s risk for GAE and disseminated infection include:
   
    - AIDS
    - Organ/Tissue transplant
    - Steroids or excessive use of antibiotics
    - Diabetes Mellitus
    - Cancer
    - Disorders in which white blood cells in the lymphatic tissue are over-produced or abnormal
    - Disorders in which blood cells or blood clotting mechanisms do not function properly or are abnormal
    - Liver cirrhosis
    - Lupus</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000001-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Acanthamoeba - Granulomatous Amebic Encephalitis (GAE); Keratitis ?</Question>
<Answer>Early diagnosis is essential for effective treatment of Acanthamoeba keratitis. The infection is usually diagnosed by an eye specialist based on symptoms, growth of the ameba from a scraping of the eye, and/or seeing the ameba by a process called confocal microscopy.
    
Granulomatous Amebic Encephalitis (GAE) and disseminated infection are more difficult to diagnose and are often at advanced stages when they are diagnosed. Tests useful in the diagnosis of GAE include brain scans, biopsies, or spinal taps. In disseminated disease, biopsy of the involved sites (e.g. , skin, sinuses) can be useful in diagnosis.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000001-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Acanthamoeba - Granulomatous Amebic Encephalitis (GAE); Keratitis ?</Question>
<Answer>Early diagnosis is essential for effective treatment of Acanthamoeba keratitis. Several prescription eye medications are available for treatment. However, the infection can be difficult to treat. The best treatment regimen for each patient should be determined by an eye doctor. If you suspect your eye may be infected with Acanthamoeba, see an eye doctor immediately.
    
Skin infections that are caused by Acanthamoeba but have not spread to the central nervous system can be successfully treated. Because this is a serious infection and the people affected typically have weakened immune systems, early diagnosis offers the best chance at cure.
    
Most cases of brain and spinal cord infection with Acanthamoeba (Granulomatous Amebic Encephalitis) are fatal.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="7">
<Question qid="0000001-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Acanthamoeba - Granulomatous Amebic Encephalitis (GAE); Keratitis ?</Question>
<Answer>Topics</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
