<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000399" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/tb">
<Focus>Tuberculosis (TB)</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000399-2" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Tuberculosis (TB) ?</Question>
<Answer>Tuberculosis (TB) is a disease that is spread through the air from one person to another. There are two kinds of tests that are used to determine if a person has been infected with TB bacteria: the tuberculin skin test and TB blood tests. 
  
A positive TB skin test or TB blood test only tells that a person has been infected with TB bacteria. It does not tell whether the person has latent TB infection (LTBI) or has progressed to TB disease. Other tests, such as a chest x-ray and a sample of sputum, are needed to see whether the person has TB disease. 
  
Tuberculin skin test: The TB skin test (also called the Mantoux tuberculin skin test) is performed by injecting a small amount of fluid (called tuberculin) into the skin in the lower part of the arm. A person given the tuberculin skin test must return within 48 to 72 hours to have a trained health care worker look for a reaction on the arm. The health care worker will look for a raised, hard area or swelling, and if present, measure its size using a ruler. Redness by itself is not considered part of the reaction. 
  
The skin test result depends on the size of the raised, hard area or swelling. It also depends on the person’s risk of being infected with TB bacteria and the progression to TB disease if infected. 
   
   - Positive skin test: This 
     means the person’s body was infected with TB bacteria. Additional tests are needed to determine if the person has latent TB infection or TB disease. A health care worker will then provide treatment as needed. 
   - Negative skin test: This means the person’s body did not react to the test, and that latent TB infection or TB disease is not likely. 
   
  
 
     TB blood tests: 
    TB blood tests (also called interferon-gamma release assays or IGRAs) measure how the immune system reacts to the bacteria that cause TB. An IGRA measures how strong a person’s immune system reacts to TB bacteria by testing the person’s blood in a laboratory. 
  
Two IGRAs are approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and are available in the United States: 
   
   - QuantiFERON®–TB Gold In-Tube test (QFT-GIT) 
   - T-SPOT®.TB test (T-Spot) 
   
   
   - Positive IGRA: This means that the person has been infected with TB bacteria. Additional tests are needed to determine if the person has latent TB infection or TB disease. A health care worker will then provide treatment as needed. 
   - Negative IGRA: This means that the person’s blood did not react to the test and that latent TB infection or TB disease is not likely. 
   
  
IGRAs are the preferred method of TB infection testing for the following: 
    
   - People who have a difficult time returning for a second appointment to look for a reaction to the TST. 
   
  
There is no problem with repeated IGRAs. 
    
   
   
     Testing for TB in BCG-Vaccinated Persons 
  
Many people born outside of the United States have been BCG-vaccinated. 
  
People who have had a previous BCG vaccine may receive a TB skin test. In some people, BCG may cause a positive skin test when they are not infected with TB bacteria. If a TB skin test is positive, additional tests are needed. 
  
IGRAs, unlike the TB skin tests, are not affected by prior BCG vaccination and are not expected to give a false-positive result in people who have received BCG. 
   
     Choosing a TB Test 
  
The person’s health care provider should choose which TB test to use. Factors in selecting which test to use include the reason for testing, test availability, and cost. Generally, it is not recommended to test a person with both a TST and an IGRA. 
   
     Diagnosis of Latent TB Infection or TB Disease 
  
If a person is found to be infected with TB bacteria, other tests are needed to see if the person has TB disease. 
  
TB disease can be diagnosed by medical history, physical examination, chest x-ray, and other laboratory tests. TB disease is treated by taking several drugs as recommended by a health care provider. 
  
If a person does not have TB disease, but has TB bacteria in the body, then latent TB infection is diagnosed. The decision about treatment for latent TB infection will be based on a person’s chances of developing TB disease. 
   
     Diagnosis of TB Disease 
  
People suspected of having TB disease should be referred for a medical evaluation, which will include 
   
   - Medical history, 
   - Physical examination, 
   - Test for TB infection (TB skin test or TB blood test), 
   - Chest radiograph (X-ray), and 
   - Appropriate laboratory tests 
   
  
See Diagnosis of TB (Fact sheet) for more information about TB diagnosis. 
   
    
      Related Links 
     
    
   For Patients 
        
    
   For Health Care Providers</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="3">
<Question qid="0000399-3" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Tuberculosis (TB) ?</Question>
<Answer>Infection Control in Health Care Settings
  
Tuberculosis (TB) transmission has been documented in health care settings where health care workers and patients come in contact with people who have TB disease.
  
People who work or receive care in health care settings are at higher risk for becoming infected with TB; therefore, it is necessary to have a TB infection control plan as part of a general infection control program designed to ensure the following:
  
   - prompt detection of infectious patients,
   - airborne precautions, and
   - treatment of people who have suspected or confirmed TB disease.
  
  
In order to be effective, the primary emphasis of a TB infection control program should be on achieving these three goals.
  
In all health care settings, particularly those in which people are at high risk for exposure to TB, policies and procedures for TB control should be developed, reviewed periodically, and evaluated for effectiveness to determine the actions necessary to minimize the risk for transmission of TB.
  
The TB infection control program should be based on a three-level hierarchy of control measures and include:
  
   - Administrative measures
   - Environmental controls
   - Use of respiratory protective equipment
  
  
The first and most important level of the hierarchy, administrative measures, impacts the largest number of people. It is intended primarily to reduce the risk of uninfected people who are exposed to people who have TB disease.
  
The second level of the hierarchy is the use of environmental controls to reduce the amount of TB in the air. The first two control levels of the hierarchy also minimize the number of areas in the health care setting where exposure to TB may occur.
  
The third level of the hierarchy is the use of respiratory protective equipment in situations that pose a high risk of exposure to TB. Use of respiratory protection equipment can further reduce the risk for exposure of health care workers.
  
More: Information about Infection Control in Health Care Settings
  
     TB Prevention
  
Preventing Exposure to TB Disease While Traveling Abroad
Travelers should avoid close contact or prolonged time with known TB patients in crowded, enclosed environments (for example, clinics, hospitals, prisons, or homeless shelters).
  
Travelers who will be working in clinics, hospitals, or other health care settings where TB patients are likely to be encountered should consult infection control or occupational health experts. They should ask about administrative and environmental procedures for preventing exposure to TB. Once those procedures are implemented, additional measures could include using personal respiratory protective devices.
  
Travelers who anticipate possible prolonged exposure to people with TB (for example, those who expect to come in contact routinely with clinic, hospital, prison, or homeless shelter populations) should have a tuberculin skin test (TST) or interferon-gamma release assay (IGRA) test before leaving the United States. If the test reaction is negative, they should have a repeat test 8 to 10 weeks after returning to the United States. Additionally, annual testing may be recommended for those who anticipate repeated or prolonged exposure or an extended stay over a period of years. Because people with HIV infection are more likely to have an impaired response to both the TST and IGRA, travelers who are HIV positive should tell their physicians about their HIV infection status.
  
More: Tuberculosis Information for International Travelers
  
     What to Do If You Have Been Exposed to TB
  
If you think you have been exposed to someone with TB disease, contact your health care provider or local health department to see if you should be tested for TB. Be sure to tell the doctor or nurse when you spent time with someone who has TB disease.
  
More: What to Do If You Have Been Exposed to TB
  
     Preventing Latent TB Infection from Progressing to TB Disease
  
Many people who have latent TB infection never develop TB disease. But some people who have latent TB infection are more likely to develop TB disease than others. Those at high risk for developing TB disease include:
  
   - People with HIV infection
   - People who became infected with TB bacteria in the last 2 years
   - Babies and young children
   - People who inject illegal drugs
   - People who are sick with other diseases that weaken the immune system
   - Elderly people
   - People who were not treated correctly for TB in the past
  
  
If you have latent TB infection and you are in one of these high-risk groups, you should take medicine to keep from developing TB disease. There are several treatment options for latent TB infection. You and your health care provider must decide which treatment is best for you. If you take your medicine as instructed, it can keep you from developing TB disease. Because there are less bacteria, treatment for latent TB infection is much easier than treatment for TB disease. A person with TB disease has a large amount of TB bacteria in the body. Several drugs are needed to treat TB disease.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000399-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Tuberculosis (TB) ?</Question>
<Answer>Tuberculosis (TB) is caused by a bacterium called Mycobacterium tuberculosis. The bacteria usually attack the lungs, but TB bacteria can attack any part of the body such as the kidney, spine, and brain. If not treated properly, TB disease can be fatal.
  
Not everyone infected with TB bacteria becomes sick. As a result, two TB-related conditions exist: latent TB infection and TB disease. Both latent TB infection and TB disease can be treated. Learn more about the difference between latent TB infection and TB disease.
  
     Treatment for Latent TB Infection
  
People with latent TB infection have TB bacteria in their bodies, but they are not sick because the bacteria are not active. People with latent TB infection do not have symptoms, and they cannot spread TB bacteria to others. However, if TB bacteria become active in the body and multiply, the person will go from having latent TB infection to being sick with TB disease. For this reason, people with latent TB infection are often prescribed treatment to prevent them from developing TB disease. Treatment of latent TB infection is essential for controlling and eliminating TB in the United States.
  
Because there are less bacteria in a person with latent TB infection, treatment is much easier. Four regimens are approved for the treatment of latent TB infection. The medications used to treat latent TB infection include:
  
   - isoniazid (INH)
   - rifampin (RIF)
   - rifapentine (RPT)
  
  
Certain groups of people (such as people with weakened immune systems) are at very high risk of developing TB disease once infected with TB bacteria. Every effort should be made to begin appropriate treatment and to ensure completion of the entire course of treatment for latent TB infection.
  
More: Treatment for Latent TB Infection
  
     Treatment for TB Disease
  
TB bacteria become active (multiplying in the body) if the immune system can&apos;t stop them from growing. When TB bacteria are active, this is called TB disease. TB disease will make a person sick. People with TB disease may spread the bacteria to people with whom they spend many hours.
  
TB disease can be treated by taking several drugs for 6 to 9 months. There are 10 drugs currently approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for treating TB. Of the approved drugs, the first-line anti-TB agents that form the core of treatment regimens include:
  
   - isoniazid (INH)
   - rifampin (RIF)
   - ethambutol (EMB)
   - pyrazinamide (PZA)
  
  
Regimens for treating TB disease have an initial phase of 2 months, followed by a choice of several options for the continuation phase of either 4 or 7 months (total of 6 to 9 months for treatment). Learn more about the continuation phase of treatment.
  
It is very important that people who have TB disease finish the medicine, taking the drugs exactly as prescribed. If they stop taking the drugs too soon, they can become sick again; if they do not take the drugs correctly, the TB bacteria that are still alive may become resistant to those drugs. TB that is resistant to drugs is harder and more expensive to treat.
  
More: Treatment for TB Disease
  
     Treatment Completion
  
Treatment completion is determined by the number of doses ingested over a given period of time. Although basic TB regimens are broadly applicable, there are modifications that should be made under special circumstances (such as people with HIV infection, drug resistance, pregnancy, or treatment of children).</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="9">
<Question qid="0000399-9" qtype="information">What is (are) Tuberculosis (TB) ?</Question>
<Answer>The Division of Tuberculosis Elimination (DTBE) Laboratory Branch (LB) provides services for the following tests on mycobacterial cultures. Any local health department, licensed physician&apos;s office, licensed laboratory or licensed health care facility may submit cultures for testing but they must be routed through either their state health department or other authorized facility.
  Genotyping
  State or local TB control programs
  
A genotyping laboratory, in Michigan  is under contract with CDC to provide genotyping services to TB programs in the United States. Three genotyping methods to identify TB strains:
  
   - Spoligotyping
   - Mycobacterial interspersed repetitive unit (MIRU) analysis
   - IS6110-based restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP) analysis
  
  
For more information, view the Guide to the Application of Genotyping to Tuberculosis Prevention and Control.
  
DTBE epidemiologic investigations and surveillance activities
  
   - The LB provides support for DTBE epidemiologic investigations and surveillance activities. TB genotyping results, when combined with epidemiologic data, help to distinguish TB patients who are involved in the same chain of recent transmission.
  
  Drug susceptibility testing
  
The LB performs drug susceptibility testing for selected Mycobacterium species referred from state or other authorized health facilities. Cultures of mycobacteria are tested by the indirect proportion method with antituberculosis drugs incorporated into 7H10 agar plates.
  
  Additional Resources</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="10">
<Question qid="0000399-10" qtype="research">what research is being done for Tuberculosis (TB) ?</Question>
<Answer>TB Epidemiologic Studies Consortium
  
 The TB Epidemiologic Studies Consortium (TBESC) was established to strengthen, focus, and coordinate tuberculosis (TB) research. The TBESC is designed to build the scientific research capacities of state and metropolitan TB control programs, participating laboratories, academic institutions, hospitals, and both non- and for-profit organizations.
                
  TB Trials Consortium
  
 The TB Trials Consortium (TBTC) is a collaboration of North American and international clinical investigators whose mission is to conduct programmatically relevant research concerning the diagnosis, clinical management, and prevention of TB infection and disease.
  Behavioral and Social Science Research
  Behavioral and social science research has the potential to make a tremendous impact on TB elimination efforts. This research is needed to 1) understand how behaviors of both patients and providers affect TB-related care seeking, diagnosis, treatment success, and prevention; and 2) understand how other social, cultural, and environmental influences affect health seeking and treatment outcomes related to TB.</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
