<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000038" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/babesiosis/">
<Focus>Parasites - Babesiosis</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000038-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Parasites - Babesiosis ?</Question>
<Answer>Babesiosis is caused by microscopic parasites that infect red blood cells. Most human cases of Babesia infection in the United States are caused by the parasite Babesia microti. Occasional cases caused by other species (types) of Babesia have been detected. Babesia microti is spread in nature by Ixodes scapularis ticks (also called blacklegged ticks or deer ticks). Tickborne transmission is most common in particular regions and seasons: it mainly occurs in parts of the Northeast and upper Midwest; and it usually peaks during the warm months. Babesia infection can range in severity from asymptomatic to life threatening. The infection is both treatable and preventable.
    Frequently Asked Questions (FAQs)
    
    Podcasts</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000038-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Parasites - Babesiosis? ?</Question>
<Answer>People can get infected with Babesia parasites in several ways:
    
     - The main way is through the bite of an infected tick—during outdoor activities in areas where babesiosis is found (see below).
     - A less common way is by getting a transfusion from a blood donor who has a Babesia infection but does not have any symptoms. (No tests have been licensed yet for screening blood donors for Babesia.)
     - Rare cases of congenital transmission—from an infected mother to her baby (during pregnancy or delivery)—have been reported.
    
    
Babesia parasites are not transmitted from person-to-person like the flu or the common cold.
    
Many different species (types) of Babesia parasites have been found in animals, only a few of which have been found in people. Babesia microti—which usually infects white-footed mice and other small mammals—is the main species that has been found in people in the United States. Occasional (sporadic) cases of babesiosis caused by other Babesia species have been detected.
    
     
    
    
Babesia microti is transmitted in nature by Ixodes scapularis ticks (also called blacklegged ticks or deer ticks).
    
     - Tickborne transmission primarily occurs in the Northeast and upper Midwest, especially in parts of New England, New York state, New Jersey, Wisconsin, and Minnesota.
     - The parasite typically is spread by the young nymph stage of the tick, which is most apt to be found (seeking or &quot;questing&quot; for a blood meal) during warm months (spring and summer), in areas with woods, brush, or grass.
     - Infected people might not recall a tick bite because I. scapularis nymphs are very small (about the size of a poppy seed).</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000038-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parasites - Babesiosis ?</Question>
<Answer>In symptomatic people, babesiosis usually is diagnosed by examining blood specimens under a microscope and seeing Babesia parasites inside red blood cells.
    
To be sure the diagnosis is correct, your health care provider might have specimens of your blood tested by a specialized reference laboratory (such as at CDC or a health department).
    
More on: Resources for Health Professionals: Diagnosis</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000038-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parasites - Babesiosis ?</Question>
<Answer>Effective treatments are available. People who do not have any symptoms or signs of babesiosis usually do not need to be treated.
    
Before considering treatment, the first step is to make sure the diagnosis is correct.
    
For more information, people should talk to their health care provider.
    
More on: Resources for Health Professionals: Treatment</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="7">
<Question qid="0000038-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Parasites - Babesiosis ?</Question>
<Answer>Steps can be taken to reduce the risk for babesiosis and other tickborne infections. The use of prevention measures is especially important for people at increased risk for severe babesiosis (for example, people who do not have a spleen). Avoiding exposure to tick habitats is the best defense.
   
Babesia microti is spread by Ixodes scapularis ticks, which are mostly found in wooded, brushy, or grassy areas, in certain regions and seasons. No vaccine is available to protect people against babesiosis. However, people who live, work, or travel in tick-infested areas can take simple steps to help protect themselves against tick bites and tickborne infections.
   
    
   
   
During outdoor activities in tick habitats, take precautions to keep ticks off the skin.
   
    - Walk on cleared trails and stay in the center of the trail, to minimize contact with leaf litter, brush, and overgrown grasses, where ticks are most likely to be found.
    - Minimize the amount of exposed skin, by wearing socks, long pants, and a long-sleeved shirt. Tuck the pant legs into the socks, so ticks cannot crawl up the inside of the pants. Wear light-colored clothing, to make it easier to see and remove ticks before they attach to skin.
    - Apply repellents to skin and clothing. Follow the instructions on the product label. 
     
      - Products that contain DEET (N,N-diethylmetatoluamide) can be directly applied to exposed skin and to clothing, to help keep ticks away (by repelling them). The product label includes details about how and where to apply the repellent, how often to reapply it, and how to use it safely on children.
      - Permethrin products can be applied to clothing/boots (not to skin), actually kill ticks that come in contact with the treated clothing, and usually stay effective through several washings.
     
   
   
    
   
   
After outdoor activities, conduct daily tick checks and promptly remove any ticks that are found. Thorough, daily tick checks are very important. The I. scapularis nymphs that typically spread B. microti are so small (about the size of a poppy seed) that they are easily overlooked. But they usually must stay attached to a person for more than 36-48 hours to be able to transmit the parasite.
   
    - Remove ticks from clothing and pets before going indoors.
    - Conduct a full-body exam for ticks. Use a hand-held or full-length mirror to view all parts of the body. Be sure to check behind the knees, between the legs (groin/thighs), between the toes, under the arms (armpits), around the waist, inside the belly button, the back of the neck, behind and in the ears, as well as in and around the scalp, hairline, and hair. Remember to check children and pets, too.
   
   
Remove ticks that are attached to the skin as soon as possible, preferably by using pointed (fine-tipped) tweezers. Grab the tick’s mouth parts close to the skin, and slowly pull the tick straight out (with steady outward pressure), until the tick lets go.
   
More on: Removing Ticks
   
More on: Ticks</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
