<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000439" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/nczved/divisions/dfbmd/diseases/yersinia/">
<Focus>Yersinia</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="11">
<Question qid="0000439-11" qtype="information">what is yersiniosis for Yersinia ?</Question>
<Answer>Yersiniosis is an infectious disease caused by a bacterium of the genus Yersinia. In the United States, most human illness is caused by one species, Y. enterocolitica. Infection with Y. enterocolitica can cause a variety of symptoms depending on the age of the person infected. Infection with Y. enterocolitica occurs most often in young children. Common symptoms in children are fever, abdominal pain, and diarrhea, which is often bloody. Symptoms typically develop 4 to 7 days after exposure and may last 1 to 3 weeks or longer. In older children and adults, right-sided abdominal pain and fever may be the predominant symptoms, and may be confused with appendicitis. In a small proportion of cases, complications such as skin rash, joint pains, or spread of bacteria to the bloodstream can occur.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="14">
<Question qid="0000439-14" qtype="frequency">how common is infection with y. enterocolitica for Yersinia ?</Question>
<Answer>Y. enterocolitica is a relatively infrequent cause of diarrhea and abdominal pain. Based on data from the Foodborne Diseases Active Surveillance Network (FoodNet), which measures the burden and sources of specific diseases over time, approximately one culture-confirmed Y. enterocolitica infection per 100,000 persons occurs each year. Children are infected more often than adults, and the infection is more common in the winter.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="15">
<Question qid="0000439-15" qtype="exams and tests">how can y. enterocolitica infections be diagnosed for Yersinia ?</Question>
<Answer>Y. enterocolitica infections are generally diagnosed by detecting the organism in the stools. Many laboratories do not routinely test for Y. enterocolitica,so it is important to notify laboratory personnel when infection with this bacterium is suspected so that special tests can be done. The organism can also be recovered from other sites, including the throat, lymph nodes, joint fluid, urine, bile, and blood.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="16">
<Question qid="0000439-16" qtype="treatment">how can y. enterocolitica infections be treated for Yersinia ?</Question>
<Answer>Uncomplicated cases of diarrhea due to Y. enterocolitica usually resolve on their own without antibiotic treatment. However, in more severe or complicated infections, antibiotics such as aminoglycosides, doxycycline, trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole, or fluoroquinolones may be useful.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="19">
<Question qid="0000439-19" qtype="prevention">what are public health agencies doing to prevent or control yersiniosis for Yersinia ?</Question>
<Answer>The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) monitors the frequency of Y. enterocolitica infections through the foodborne disease active surveillance network (FoodNet). In addition, CDC conducts investigations of outbreaks of yersiniosis to control them and to learn more about how to prevent these infections. CDC has collaborated in an educational campaign to increase public awareness about prevention of Y. enterocolitica infections. The U.S. Food and Drug Administration inspects imported foods and milk pasteurization plants and promotes better food preparation techniques in restaurants and food processing plants. The U.S. Department of Agriculture monitors the health of food animals and is responsible for the quality of slaughtered and processed meat. The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency regulates and monitors the safety of our drinking water supplies.</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
