<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000339" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/lice/pubic/">
<Focus>Parasites - Lice - Pubic "Crab" Lice</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000339-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Parasites - Lice - Pubic "Crab" Lice ?</Question>
<Answer>Also called crab lice or "crabs," pubic lice are parasitic insects found primarily in the pubic or genital area of humans. Pubic lice infestation is found worldwide and occurs in all races, ethnic groups, and levels of society.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000339-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Parasites - Lice - Pubic "Crab" Lice? ?</Question>
<Answer>Pubic (&quot;crab&quot;) lice infestation is found worldwide and occurs in all races and ethnic groups and in all levels of society. Pubic lice usually are spread through sexual contact and are most common in adults. Occasionally pubic lice may be spread by close personal contact or contact with articles such as clothing, bed linens, and towels that have been used by an infested person. Pubic lice found on the head or eyelashes of children may be an indication of sexual exposure or abuse.
    
Pubic lice do not transmit disease; however, secondary bacterial infection can occur from scratching of the skin.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000339-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parasites - Lice - Pubic "Crab" Lice ?</Question>
<Answer>Pubic lice are short and crab-like and appear very different from head and body lice. Pubic lice infestation is diagnosed by finding a “crab” louse or eggs on hair in the pubic region or, less commonly, elsewhere on the body (eyebrows, eyelashes, beard, mustache, armpit, perianal area, groin, trunk, scalp). Although pubic lice and nits can be large enough to be seen with the naked eye, a magnifying lens may be necessary to find lice or eggs.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000339-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parasites - Lice - Pubic "Crab" Lice ?</Question>
<Answer>A lice-killing lotion containing 1% permethrin or a mousse containing pyrethrins and piperonyl butoxide can be used to treat pubic (&quot;crab&quot;) lice. These products are available over-the-counter without a prescription at a local drug store or pharmacy. These medications are safe and effective when used exactly according to the instructions in the package or on the label. 
    
Lindane shampoo is a prescription medication that can kill lice and lice eggs. However, lindane is not recommended as a first-line therapy. Lindane can be toxic to the brain and other parts of the nervous system; its use should be restricted to patients who have failed treatment with or cannot tolerate other medications that pose less risk. Lindane should not be used to treat premature infants, persons with a seizure disorder, women who are pregnant or breast-feeding, persons who have very irritated skin or sores where the lindane will be applied, infants, children, the elderly, and persons who weigh less than 110 pounds. 
    
Malathion* lotion 0.5% (Ovide*) is a prescription medication that can kill lice and some lice eggs; however, malathion lotion (Ovide*) currently has not been approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for treatment of pubic (&quot;crab&quot;) lice. 
    
Both topical and oral ivermectin have been used successfully to treat lice; however, only topical ivermectin lotion currently is approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for treatment of lice. Oral ivermectin is not FDA-approved for treatment of lice. 
    
How to treat pubic lice infestations: (Warning: See special instructions for treatment of lice and nits on eyebrows or eyelashes. The lice medications described in this section should not be used near the eyes.) 
    
   
   
    
    - Wash the infested area; towel dry. 
    - Carefully follow the instructions in the package or on the label. Thoroughly saturate the pubic hair and other infested areas with lice medication. Leave medication on hair for the time recommended in the instructions. After waiting the recommended time, remove the medication by following carefully the instructions on the label or in the box. 
    - Following treatment, most nits will still be attached to hair shafts. Nits may be removed with fingernails or by using a fine-toothed comb. 
    - Put on clean underwear and clothing after treatment. 
    - To kill any lice or nits remaining on clothing, towels, or bedding, machine-wash and machine-dry those items that the infested person used during the 2–3 days before treatment. Use hot water (at least 130°F) and the hot dryer cycle. 
    - Items that cannot be laundered can be dry-cleaned or stored in a sealed plastic bag for 2 weeks. 
    - All sex partners from within the previous month should be informed that they are at risk for infestation and should be treated. 
    - Persons should avoid sexual contact with their sex partner(s) until both they and their partners have been successfully treated and reevaluated to rule out persistent infestation. 
    - Repeat treatment in 9–10 days if live lice are still found. 
    - Persons with pubic lice should be evaluated for other sexually transmitted diseases (STDs). 
    
   
Special instructions for treatment of lice and nits found on eyebrows or eyelashes: 
    
    - If only a few live lice and nits are present, it may be possible to remove these with fingernails or a nit comb. 
    - If additional treatment is needed for lice or nits on the eyelashes, careful application of ophthalmic-grade petrolatum ointment (only available by prescription) to the eyelid margins 2–4 times a day for 10 days is effective. Regular petrolatum (e.g., Vaseline)* should not be used because it can irritate the eyes if applied. 
    
   
*Use of trade names is for identification purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the Public Health Service or by the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. 
    
   
This information is not meant to be used for self-diagnosis or as a substitute for consultation with a health care provider. If you have any questions about the parasites described above or think that you may have a parasitic infection, consult a health care provider.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="7">
<Question qid="0000339-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Parasites - Lice - Pubic "Crab" Lice ?</Question>
<Answer>Pubic (&quot;crab&quot;) lice most commonly are spread directly from person to person by sexual contact. Pubic lice very rarely may be spread by clothing, bedding, or a toilet seat.
    
The following are steps that can be taken to help prevent and control the spread of pubic (&quot;crab&quot;) lice:
    
     - All sexual contacts of the infested person should be examined. All those who are infested should be treated.
     - Sexual contact between the infested person(s)s and their sexual partner(s) should be avoided until all have been examined, treated as necessary, and reevaluated to rule out persistent infestation.
     - Machine wash and dry clothing worn and bedding used by the infested person in the hot water (at least 130°F) laundry cycle and the high heat drying cycle. Clothing and items that are not washable can be dry-cleaned OR sealed in a plastic bag and stored for 2 weeks.
     - Do not share clothing, bedding, and towels used by an infested person.
     - Do not use fumigant sprays or fogs; they are not necessary to control pubic (&quot;crab&quot;) lice and can be toxic if inhaled or absorbed through the skin.
    
    
Persons with pubic lice should be examined and treated for any other sexually transmitted diseases (STDs) that may be present.</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
