<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000199" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/">
<Focus></Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="12">
<Question qid="0000199-12" qtype="prevention">how vaccines prevent disease</Question>
<Answer>Why Are Childhood Vaccines So Important? It is always better to prevent a disease than to treat it after it occurs. Diseases that used to be common in this country and around the world, including polio, measles, diphtheria, pertussis (whooping cough), rubella (German measles), mumps, tetanus, rotavirus and Haemophilus influenzae type b (Hib) can now be prevented by vaccination. Thanks to a vaccine, one of the most terrible diseases in history – smallpox – no longer exists outside the laboratory. Over the years vaccines have prevented countless cases of disease and saved millions of lives. Immunity Protects us From Disease Immunity is the body’s way of preventing disease.  Children are born with an immune system composed of cells, glands, organs, and fluids located throughout the body. The immune system recognizes germs that enter the body as &quot;foreign invaders” (called antigens) and produces proteins called antibodies to fight them. The first time a child is infected with a specific antigen (say measles virus), the immune system produces antibodies designed to fight it. This takes time . . . usually the immune system can’t work fast enough to prevent the antigen from causing disease, so the child still gets sick.  However, the immune system “remembers” that antigen. If it ever enters the body again, even after many years, the immune system can produce antibodies fast enough to keep it from causing disease a second time. This protection is called immunity. It would be nice if there were a way to give children immunity to a disease without their having to get sick first. In fact there is: Vaccines contain the same antigens (or parts of antigens) that cause diseases. For example, measles vaccine contains measles virus. But the antigens in vaccines are either killed, or weakened to the point that they don’t cause disease. However, they are strong enough to make the immune system produce antibodies that lead to immunity. In other words, a vaccine is a safer substitute for a child’s first exposure to a disease. The child gets protection without having to get sick. Through vaccination, children can develop immunity without suffering from the actual diseases that vaccines prevent. Top of Page More Facts Newborn babies are immune to many diseases because they have antibodies they got from their mothers. However, this immunity goes away during the first year of life. If an unvaccinated child is exposed to a disease germ, the child&apos;s body may not be strong enough to fight the disease. Before vaccines, many children died from diseases that vaccines now prevent, such as whooping cough, measles, and polio. Those same germs exist today, but because babies are protected by vaccines, we don’t see these diseases nearly as often. Immunizing individual children also helps to protect the health of our community, especially those people who cannot be immunized (children who are too young to be vaccinated, or those who can’t receive certain vaccines for medical reasons), and the small proportion of people who don’t respond to a particular vaccine. Vaccine-preventable diseases have a costly impact, resulting in doctor&apos;s visits, hospitalizations, and premature deaths. Sick children can also cause parents to lose time from work.   Related Pages Why Immunize? Vaccines: A Safe Choice Parents Guide to Immunizations For Parents: How Vaccines Prevent Diseases Top of Page   Images and logos on this website which are trademarked/copyrighted or used with permission of the trademark/copyright or logo holder are not in the public domain. These images and logos have been licensed for or used with permission in the materials provided on this website. The materials in the form presented on this website may be used without seeking further permission. Any other use of trademarked/copyrighted images or logos requires permission from the trademark/copyright holder...more This graphic notice means that you are leaving an HHS Web site. For more information, please see the Exit Notification and Disclaimer policy.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="14">
<Question qid="0000199-14" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for ? ?</Question>
<Answer>Measles: Make Sure Your Child Is Protected with MMR Vaccine Measles starts with a fever. Soon after, it causes a cough, runny nose, and red eyes. Then a rash of tiny, red spots breaks out. Measles can be serious for young children. Learn about protecting your child from measles with MMR vaccine. Protect your child at every age. Click on your child&apos;s age group for vaccine information. View or print age-specific vaccine information [252 KB, 27 pages] Records &amp; Requirements Recording immunizations Finding immunization records Interpreting abbreviations on records Immunization requirements for child care and schools Making the Vaccine Decision How vaccines prevent diseases Vaccine side effects/risks Vaccine ingredients Ensuring vaccine safety Vaccines and your child’s immune system Learn More About Preteen and Teen Vaccines The Vaccines For Children program has helped prevent diseases and save lives…big time! [enlarged view] Watch The Immunization Baby Book Learn what vaccines your child needs, when they are needed, and why it is so important to follow the CDC’s recommended immunization schedule as you flip through this video baby book (4:04 mins) on CDC-TV or on YouTube. Who &amp; When (Immunization Schedules) Birth through 6 Years Schedule [2 pages] Create a schedule for your child 7 through 18 Years Schedule [2 pages] 19 Years and Older Schedule [2 pages] Learn more about how CDC sets the immunization schedule for your family Knowing the childhood vaccination rates in your community is important. More Diseases and the Vaccines that Prevent Them Learn more about the 16 diseases that can be prevented with vaccines, as well as the benefits and risks of vaccination. Learn More About... Adoption and Vaccines Pregnancy Help Paying for Vaccines Evaluating Information on the Web</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="19">
<Question qid="0000199-19" qtype="prevention">How to prevent  ?</Question>
<Answer>Vaccines and Preventable Diseases On this Page Vaccine Shortages &amp; Delays Potential New Vaccines Vaccines: The Basics FAQ about Vaccines &amp; Diseases they Prevent   VACCINE-PREVENTABLE DISEASES OR, find it by Vaccine Anthrax Cervical Cancer Diphtheria Hepatitis A Hepatitis B Haemophilus influenzae type b (Hib) Human Papillomavirus (HPV) H1N1 Flu (Swine Flu) Influenza (Seasonal Flu) Japanese Encephalitis (JE) Measles Meningococcal Mumps Pertussis (Whooping Cough) Pneumococcal Poliomyelitis (Polio) Rabies Rotavirus Rubella (German Measles) Shingles (Herpes Zoster) Smallpox Tetanus (Lockjaw) Tuberculosis Typhoid Fever Varicella (Chickenpox) Yellow Fever At a Glance Vaccine-preventable disease levels are at or near record lows. Even though most infants and toddlers have received all recommended vaccines by age 2, many under-immunized children remain, leaving the potential for outbreaks of disease. Many adolescents and adults are under-immunized as well, missing opportunities to protect themselves against diseases such as Hepatitis B, influenza, and pneumococcal disease. CDC works closely with public health agencies and private partners to improve and sustain immunization coverage and to monitor the safety of vaccines so that this public health success story can be maintained and expanded in the century to come. Vaccine Shortages &amp; Delays The latest national information about vaccine supplies and guidance for healthcare providers who are facing vaccine shortages or delays Chart of shortages &amp; delays   Potential New Vaccines Resources for finding information on potential vaccines, research and development status, licensure status, etc. New Vaccine Surveillance Network Program evaluates impact of new vaccines and vaccine policies through a network of 6 US sites Status of Licensure and Recs for New Vaccines American Academy of Pediatrics (AAP) Potential New Vaccines Immunization Action Coalition (IAC)   Vaccines: The Basics Without vaccines, epidemics of many preventable diseases could return, resulting in increased – and unnecessary – illness, disability, and death. All about vaccines How vaccines prevent disease List of all vaccine-preventable diseases List of all vaccines used in United States Photos of vaccine-preventable diseases and/or people affected by them View all...   FAQ about Vaccines &amp; Diseases they Prevent What are the ingredients in vaccines? What vaccines do adults need? What vaccines do children need? What vaccines are used in the United States? What diseases do vaccines prevent? View all...   Related Pages Basics and Common Questions Who Should NOT Get These Vaccines? Unprotected Stories Top of Page   Images and logos on this website which are trademarked/copyrighted or used with permission of the trademark/copyright or logo holder are not in the public domain. These images and logos have been licensed for or used with permission in the materials provided on this website. The materials in the form presented on this website may be used without seeking further permission. Any other use of trademarked/copyrighted images or logos requires permission from the trademark/copyright holder...more This graphic notice means that you are leaving an HHS Web site. For more information, please see the Exit Notification and Disclaimer policy.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="20">
<Question qid="0000199-20" qtype="prevention">what diseases are vaccine preventable</Question>
<Answer>List of Vaccine-Preventable Diseases The following links will lead you to the main page that describes both the disease and the vaccine(s). Vaccines are available for all of the following vaccine-preventable diseases (unless otherwise noted): Anthrax Cervical Cancer (Human Papillomavirus) Diphtheria Hepatitis A Hepatitis B Haemophilus influenzae type b (Hib) Human Papillomavirus (HPV) Influenza (Flu) Japanese encephalitis (JE) Measles Meningococcal Mumps Pertussis Pneumococcal Polio Rabies Rotavirus Rubella Shingles (Herpes Zoster) Smallpox Tetanus Typhoid Tuberculosis (TB) Varicella (Chickenpox) Yellow Fever Related Pages For Parents: What You Need to Know List of Vaccines Used in U.S. Photos of diseases Top of Page   Images and logos on this website which are trademarked/copyrighted or used with permission of the trademark/copyright or logo holder are not in the public domain. These images and logos have been licensed for or used with permission in the materials provided on this website. The materials in the form presented on this website may be used without seeking further permission. Any other use of trademarked/copyrighted images or logos requires permission from the trademark/copyright holder...more This graphic notice means that you are leaving an HHS Web site. For more information, please see the Exit Notification and Disclaimer policy.</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
