<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000414" source="CDC" url="http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/toxocariasis/">
<Focus>Parasites - Toxocariasis (also known as Roundworm Infection)</Focus>
<UMLS>
<CUI></CUI>
<SemanticType></SemanticType>
<SemanticGroup></SemanticGroup>
</UMLS>
<QAPairs>
<QAPair pid="1">
<Question qid="0000414-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Parasites - Toxocariasis (also known as Roundworm Infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>Frequently Asked Questions (FAQs)
    
    
                
    Fact Sheets</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="2">
<Question qid="0000414-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Parasites - Toxocariasis (also known as Roundworm Infection)? ?</Question>
<Answer>Infected dogs and cats shed Toxocara eggs in their feces into the environment. Once in the environment, it takes 2 to 4 weeks for Toxocara larvae to develop and for the eggs to become infectious. Humans or other animals can be infected by accidentally ingesting Toxocara eggs. For example, humans can become infected if they work with dirt and accidentally ingest dirt containing Toxocara eggs. Although rare, people can be infected by eating undercooked or raw meat from an infected animal such as a lamb or rabbit. Because dogs and cats are frequently found where people live, there may be large numbers of infected eggs in the environment. Once in the body, the Toxocara eggs hatch and roundworm larvae can travel in the bloodstream to different parts of the body, including the liver, heart, lungs, brain, muscles, or eyes. Most infected people do not have any symptoms. However, in some people, the Toxocara larvae can cause damage to these tissues and organs. The symptoms of toxocariasis, the disease caused by these migrating larvae, include fever, coughing, inflammation of the liver, or eye problems.
    
A U.S. study in 1996 showed that 30% of dogs younger than 6 months deposit Toxocara eggs in their feces; other studies have shown that almost all puppies are born already infected with Toxocara canis. Research also suggests that 25% of all cats are infected with Toxocara cati. Infection rates are higher for dogs and cats that are left outside for more time and allowed to eat other animals. In humans, it has been found that almost 14% of the U.S. population has been infected with Toxocara. Globally, toxocariasis is found in many countries, and prevalence rates can reach as high as 40% or more in parts of the world. There are several factors that have been associated with higher rates of infection with Toxocara. People are more likely to be infected with Toxocara if they own a dog. Children and adolescents under the age of 20 are more likely to test positive for Toxocara infection. This may be because children are more likely to eat dirt and play in outdoor environments, such as sandboxes, where dog and cat feces can be found. This infection is more common in people living in poverty. Geographic location plays a role as well, because Toxocara is more prevalent in hot, humid regions where eggs are kept viable in the soil.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="5">
<Question qid="0000414-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parasites - Toxocariasis (also known as Roundworm Infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>If you think you or your child may have toxocariasis, you should see your health care provider to discuss the possibility of infection and, if necessary, to be examined. Toxocariasis can be difficult to diagnose because the symptoms of toxocariasis are similar to the symptoms of other infections. A blood test is available that looks for evidence of infection with Toxocara larvae. In addition to the blood test, diagnosis of toxocariasis includes identifying the presence of typical clinical signs of VT or OT and a history of exposure to cats and dogs.</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="6">
<Question qid="0000414-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parasites - Toxocariasis (also known as Roundworm Infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>Visceral toxocariasis can be treated with antiparasitic drugs such as albendazole or mebendazole. Treatment of ocular toxocariasis is more difficult and usually consists of measures to prevent progressive damage to the eye.
    
More on: Resources For Health Professionals: Treatment</Answer>
</QAPair>
<QAPair pid="7">
<Question qid="0000414-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Parasites - Toxocariasis (also known as Roundworm Infection) ?</Question>
<Answer>Controlling Toxocara infection in dogs and cats will reduce the number of infectious eggs in the environment and reduce the risk of infection for people. Have your veterinarian treat your dogs and cats, especially young animals, regularly for worms. This is especially important if your pets spend time outdoors and may become infected again.
    
There are several things that you can do around your home to make you and your pets safer:
    
     - Clean your pet’s living area at least once a week. Feces should be either buried or bagged and disposed of in the trash. Wash your hands after handling pet waste.
     - Do not allow children to play in areas that are soiled with pet or other animal feces and cover sandboxes when not in use to make sure that animals do not get inside and contaminate them.
     - Wash your hands with soap and warm water after playing with your pets or other animals, after outdoor activities, and before handling food.
     - Teach children the importance of washing hands to prevent infection.
     - Teach children that it is dangerous to eat dirt or soil.
    
    
More on: Handwashing
    
Toxocara eggs have a strong protective layer which makes the eggs able to survive in the environment for months or even years under the right conditions. Many common disinfectants are not effective against Toxocara eggs but extreme heat has been shown to kill the eggs. Prompt removal of animal feces can help prevent infection since the eggs require 2 to 4 weeks to become infective once they are out of the animal.</Answer>
</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
