<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000039" source="NINDS" url="http://www.ninds.nih.gov/disorders/batten/batten.htm">
<Focus>Batten Disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0751383</CUI>
			<CUI>C0012634</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000039-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Batten Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Batten disease is a fatal, inherited disorder of the nervous system that begins in childhood. In some cases, the early signs are subtle, taking the form of personality and behavior changes, slow learning, clumsiness, or stumbling. Symptoms of Batten disease are linked to a buildup of substances called lipopigments in the body&apos;s tissues. Lipopigments are made up of fats and proteins. Because vision loss is often an early sign, Batten disease may be first suspected during an eye exam. Often, an eye specialist or other physician may refer the child to a neurologist. Diagnostic tests for Batten disease include blood or urine tests, skin or tissue sampling, an electroencephalogram (EEG), electrical studies of the eyes, and brain scans.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000039-2" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Batten Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>As yet, no specific treatment is known that can halt or reverse the symptoms of Batten disease. However, seizures can sometimes be reduced or controlled with anticonvulsant drugs, and other medical problems can be treated appropriately as they arise. Physical therapy and occupational therapy may help patients retain functioning as long as possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000039-3" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Batten Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Over time, affected children suffer cognitive impairment, worsening seizures, and progressive loss of sight and motor skills. Eventually, children with Batten disease become blind, bedridden, and demented. Batten disease is often fatal by the late teens or twenties.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000039-4" qtype="research">what research (or clinical trials) is being done for Batten Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The biochemical defects that underlie several NCLs have recently been discovered. An enzyme called palmitoyl-protein thioesterase has been shown to be insufficiently active in the infantile form of Batten disease (this condition is now referred to as CLN1). In the late infantile form (CLN2), a deficiency of an acid protease, an enzyme that hydrolyzes proteins, has been found as the cause of this condition. A mutated gene has been identified in juvenile Batten disease (CLN3), but the protein for which this gene codes has not been identified. In addition, research scientists are working with NCL animal models to improve understanding and treatment of these disorders. One research team, for example, is testing the usefulness of bone marrow transplantation in a sheep model, while other investigators are working to develop mouse models. Mouse models will make it easier for scientists to study the genetics of these diseases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
