<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000107" source="NINDS" url="http://www.ninds.nih.gov/disorders/schilders/schilders.htm">
<Focus>Schilder's Disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0007795</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000107-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Schilder's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Schilder&apos;s disease is a rare progressive demyelinating disorder which usually begins in childhood. Schilder&apos;s disease is not the same as Addison-Schilder disease (adrenoleukodystrophy). Symptoms may include dementia, aphasia, seizures, personality changes, poor attention, tremors, balance instability, incontinence, muscle weakness, headache, vomiting, and vision and speech impairment. The disorder is a variant of multiple sclerosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000107-2" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Schilder's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment for the disorder follows the established standards in multiple sclerosis and includes corticosteroids, beta-interferon or immunosuppressive therapy, and symptomatic treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000107-3" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Schilder's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>As with multiple sclerosis, the course and prognosis of Schilder&apos;s disease are unpredictable. For some individuals the disorder is progressive with a steady, unremitting course. Others may experience significant improvement and even remission. In some cases, Schilder&apos;s disease is fatal.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000107-4" qtype="research">what research (or clinical trials) is being done for Schilder's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The NINDS supports and conducts an extensive research program on demyelinating disorders such as Schilder&apos;s disease. Much of this research focuses on learning more about these disorders and finding ways to prevent, treat, and cure them.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
