<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000190" source="NINDS" url="http://www.ninds.nih.gov/disorders/melkersson/melkersson.htm">
<Focus>Melkersson-Rosenthal Syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0025235</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000190-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Melkersson-Rosenthal Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Melkersson-Rosenthal syndrome is a rare neurological disorder characterized by recurring facial paralysis, swelling of the face and lips (usually the upper lip), and the development of folds and furrows in the tongue. Onset is in childhood or early adolescence. After recurrent attacks (ranging from days to years in between), swelling may persist and increase, eventually becoming permanent. The lip may become hard, cracked, and fissured with a reddish-brown discoloration. The cause of Melkersson-Rosenthal syndrome is unknown, but there may be a genetic predisposition. It can be symptomatic of Crohn&apos;s disease or sarcoidosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000190-2" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Melkersson-Rosenthal Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment is symptomatic and may include medication therapies with nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) and corticosteroids to reduce swelling, as well as antibiotics and immunosuppressants. Surgery may be recommended to relieve pressure on the facial nerves and to reduce swollen tissue, but its effectiveness has not been established. Massage and electrical stimulation may also be prescribed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000190-3" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Melkersson-Rosenthal Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Melkersson-Rosenthal syndrome may recur intermittently after its first appearance. It can become a chronic disorder. Follow-up care should exclude the development of Crohn&apos;s disease or sarcoidosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000190-4" qtype="research">what research (or clinical trials) is being done for Melkersson-Rosenthal Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The NINDS supports research on neurological disorders such as Melkersson-Rosenthal syndrome. Much of this research is aimed at increasing knowledge of these disorders and finding ways to treat, prevent, and ultimately cure them.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
