<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000008" source="NIHSeniorHealth" url="http://nihseniorhealth.gov/breastcancer/toc.html">
<Focus>Breast Cancer</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0006142</CUI>
			<CUI>C0678222</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000008-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>How Tumors Form The body is made up of many types of cells. Normally, cells grow, divide and produce more cells as needed to keep the body healthy. Sometimes, however, the process goes wrong. Cells become abnormal and form more cells in an uncontrolled way. These extra cells form a mass of tissue, called a growth or tumor. Tumors can be benign, which means not cancerous, or malignant, which means cancerous. Breast cancer occurs when malignant tumors form in the breast tissue. Who Gets Breast Cancer?  Breast cancer is one of the most common cancers in American women. It is most common among women between the ages of 45-85. (Watch the video to learn more about breast cancer survival rates. To enlarge the videos appearing on this page, click the brackets in the lower right-hand corner of the video screen. To reduce the videos, press the Escape (Esc) button on your keyboard.) Men can get breast cancer too, although they account for only 1 percent of all reported cases. Read more about breast cancer in men.  When Breast Cancer Spreads When cancer grows in breast tissue and spreads outside the breast, cancer cells are often found in the lymph nodes under the arm. If the cancer has reached these nodes, it means that cancer cells may have spread, or metastasized, to other parts of the body. When cancer spreads from its original location in the breast to another part of the body such as the brain, it is called metastatic breast cancer, not brain cancer. Doctors sometimes call this &quot;distant&quot; disease.  Learn about different kinds of breast cancer. Breast Cancer is Not Contagious Breast cancer is not contagious. A woman cannot &quot;catch&quot; breast cancer from other women who have the disease. Also, breast cancer is not caused by an injury to the breast. Most women who develop breast cancer do not have any known risk factors or a history of the disease in their families. Treating and Surviving Breast Cancer  Today, more women are surviving breast cancer than ever before. Nearly three million women are breast cancer survivors. (Watch the video to hear a woman discuss surviving breast cancer.) There are several ways to treat breast cancer, but all treatments work best when the disease is found early. As a matter of fact, when it is caught in its earliest stage, 98.5 percent of women with the disease are alive five years later. Every day researchers are working to find new and better ways to detect and treat cancer. Many studies of new approaches for women with breast cancer are under way. With early detection, and prompt and appropriate treatment, the outlook for women with breast cancer can be positive. To learn more about what happens after treatment, see  Surviving Cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000008-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Breast Cancer? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Some women develop breast cancer and others do not, and the risk factors for the disease vary. Breast cancer may affect younger women, but three-fourths of all breast cancers occur in women between the ages of 45 to 85. In Situ and Invasive Breast Cancer Researchers often talk about breast cancer in two ways: in situ and invasive. In situ refers to cancer that has not spread beyond its site of origin. Invasive applies to cancer that has spread to the tissue around it. This chart shows what the approximate chances are of a woman getting invasive breast cancer in her lifetime. Risk Factors Risk factors are conditions or agents that increase a person&apos;s chances of getting a disease. Here are the most common risk factors for breast cancer. -   Older age. The risk of breast cancer in a 70 year old woman is about 10 times that of a 30 year old woman, but risk decreases after age 85.  Older age. The risk of breast cancer in a 70 year old woman is about 10 times that of a 30 year old woman, but risk decreases after age 85. - Personal and family history. A personal history of breast cancer or breast cancer among one or more of your close relatives, such as a sister, mother, or daughter. Personal and family history. A personal history of breast cancer or breast cancer among one or more of your close relatives, such as a sister, mother, or daughter. - Estrogen levels in the body. High estrogen levels over a long time may increase the risk of breast cancer. Estrogen levels are highest during the years a woman is menstruating. Estrogen levels in the body. High estrogen levels over a long time may increase the risk of breast cancer. Estrogen levels are highest during the years a woman is menstruating. - Never being pregnant or having your first child in your mid-30s or later. Never being pregnant or having your first child in your mid-30s or later. - Early menstruation. Having your first menstrual period before age 12. Early menstruation. Having your first menstrual period before age 12. - Breast density. Women with very dense breasts have a higher risk of breast cancer than women with low or normal breast density.  Breast density. Women with very dense breasts have a higher risk of breast cancer than women with low or normal breast density. -  Combination hormone replacement therapy/Hormone therapy. Estrogen, progestin, or both may be given to replace the estrogen no longer made by the ovaries in postmenopausal women or women who have had their ovaries removed. This is called hormone replacement therapy. (HRT) or hormone therapy (HT). Combination HRT/HT is estrogen combined with progestin. This type of HRT/HT can increase the risk of breast cancer.  Combination hormone replacement therapy/Hormone therapy. Estrogen, progestin, or both may be given to replace the estrogen no longer made by the ovaries in postmenopausal women or women who have had their ovaries removed. This is called hormone replacement therapy. (HRT) or hormone therapy (HT). Combination HRT/HT is estrogen combined with progestin. This type of HRT/HT can increase the risk of breast cancer. - Exposure to radiation. Radiation therapy to the chest for the treatment of cancer can increase the risk of breast cancer, starting 10 years after treatment. Radiation therapy to treat cancer in one breast does not appear to increase the risk of cancer in the other breast. Exposure to radiation. Radiation therapy to the chest for the treatment of cancer can increase the risk of breast cancer, starting 10 years after treatment. Radiation therapy to treat cancer in one breast does not appear to increase the risk of cancer in the other breast. - Obesity. Obesity increases the risk of breast cancer, especially in postmenopausal women who have not used hormone replacement therapy.  Obesity. Obesity increases the risk of breast cancer, especially in postmenopausal women who have not used hormone replacement therapy. - Alcohol. Drinking alcohol increases the risk of breast cancer. The level of risk rises as the amount of alcohol consumed rises. Alcohol. Drinking alcohol increases the risk of breast cancer. The level of risk rises as the amount of alcohol consumed rises. - Gaining weight after menopause, especially after natural menopause and/or after age 60. Gaining weight after menopause, especially after natural menopause and/or after age 60. - Race. White women are at greater risk than black women. However, black women diagnosed with breast cancer are more likely to die of the disease. Race. White women are at greater risk than black women. However, black women diagnosed with breast cancer are more likely to die of the disease. - Inherited gene changes. Women who have inherited certain changes in the genes named BRCA1 and BRCA2 have a higher risk of breast cancer, ovarian cancer and maybe colon cancer. The risk of breast cancer caused by inherited gene changes depends on the type of gene mutation, family history of cancer, and other factors. Men who have inherited certain changes in the BRCA2 gene have a higher risk of breast, prostate and pancreatic cancers, and lymphoma. Inherited gene changes. Women who have inherited certain changes in the genes named BRCA1 and BRCA2 have a higher risk of breast cancer, ovarian cancer and maybe colon cancer. The risk of breast cancer caused by inherited gene changes depends on the type of gene mutation, family history of cancer, and other factors. Men who have inherited certain changes in the BRCA2 gene have a higher risk of breast, prostate and pancreatic cancers, and lymphoma. Five percent to 10 percent of all breast cancers are thought to be inherited. Get information about the BRCA1 and BRCA2 genetic mutations and testing for them. Warning Signs When breast cancer first develops, there may be no symptoms at all. But as the cancer grows, it can cause changes that women should watch for. You can help safeguard your health by learning the following warning signs of breast cancer. -  a lump or thickening in or near the breast or in the underarm area  - a change in the size or shape of the breast  - a dimple or puckering in the skin of the breast  -  a nipple turned inward into the breast  -  fluid, other than breast milk, from the nipple, especially if it&apos;s bloody  - scaly, red, or swollen skin on the breast, nipple, or areola (the dark area of skin around the nipple)  - dimples in the breast that look like the skin of an orange. a lump or thickening in or near the breast or in the underarm area a change in the size or shape of the breast a dimple or puckering in the skin of the breast a nipple turned inward into the breast fluid, other than breast milk, from the nipple, especially if it&apos;s bloody scaly, red, or swollen skin on the breast, nipple, or areola (the dark area of skin around the nipple) dimples in the breast that look like the skin of an orange. Don&apos;t Ignore Symptoms You should see your doctor about any symptoms like these. Most often, they are not cancer, but it&apos;s important to check with the doctor so that any problems can be diagnosed and treated as early as possible. Some women believe that as they age, health problems are due to &quot;growing older.&quot; Because of this myth, many illnesses go undiagnosed and untreated. Don&apos;t ignore your symptoms because you think they are not important or because you believe they are normal for your age. Talk to your doctor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000008-3" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Breast Cancer? ?</Question>
			<Answer>What Is Cancer Prevention? Cancer prevention is action taken to lower the chance of getting cancer. By preventing cancer, the number of new cases of cancer in a group or population is lowered. Hopefully, this will lower the number of deaths caused by cancer. When studying ways to prevent cancer, scientists look at risk factors and protective factors. Anything that increases your chance of developing cancer is called a cancer risk factor. Anything that decreases your chance of developing cancer is called a cancer protective factor. Risk Factors Some risk factors for cancer can be avoided, but many cannot. For example, both smoking and inheriting certain genes are risk factors for some types of cancer, but only smoking can be avoided. Regular exercise and a healthy diet may be protective factors for some types of cancer. Avoiding risk factors and increasing protective factors may lower your risk but it does not mean that you will not get cancer. Different ways to prevent cancer are being studied, including - changing lifestyle or eating habits  - avoiding things known to cause cancer  - taking medicine to treat a precancerous condition or to keep cancer from starting.  changing lifestyle or eating habits avoiding things known to cause cancer taking medicine to treat a precancerous condition or to keep cancer from starting. (For more on risk factors, see the chapter on &quot;Risk Factors.&quot;) Here are protective factors for breast cancer. Less Exposure to Estrogen Decreasing the length of time a woman&apos;s breast tissue is exposed to estrogen may help lower her risk of developing breast cancer. Exposure to estrogen is reduced in the following ways. -   Early pregnancy.  Estrogen levels are lower during pregnancy. Women who have a full-term pregnancy before age 20 have a lower risk of breast cancer than women who have not had children or who give birth to their first child after age 35.  -  Breast-feeding. Estrogen levels may remain lower while a woman is breast-feeding. Women who breastfed have a lower risk of breast cancer than women who have had children but did not breastfeed.  -  Surgical removal of the ovaries.  The ovaries make estrogen. The amount of estrogen made by the body can be greatly reduced by removing one or both ovaries. Also, drugs may be taken to lower the amount of estrogen made by the ovaries.  -  Late menstruation. Menstrual periods that start at age 14 or older decreases the number of years the breast tissue is exposed to estrogen.  - Early menopause. The fewer years a woman menstruates, the shorter the time her breast tissue is exposed to estrogen.   Early pregnancy.  Estrogen levels are lower during pregnancy. Women who have a full-term pregnancy before age 20 have a lower risk of breast cancer than women who have not had children or who give birth to their first child after age 35.  Breast-feeding. Estrogen levels may remain lower while a woman is breast-feeding. Women who breastfed have a lower risk of breast cancer than women who have had children but did not breastfeed.  Surgical removal of the ovaries.  The ovaries make estrogen. The amount of estrogen made by the body can be greatly reduced by removing one or both ovaries. Also, drugs may be taken to lower the amount of estrogen made by the ovaries. Late menstruation. Menstrual periods that start at age 14 or older decreases the number of years the breast tissue is exposed to estrogen. Early menopause. The fewer years a woman menstruates, the shorter the time her breast tissue is exposed to estrogen. Exercise Women who exercise four or more hours a week have a lower risk of breast cancer. The effect of exercise on breast cancer risk may be greatest in premenopausal women who have normal or low body weight. Learn more about the benefits of exercise for older adults.  For exercises tailored to older adults, visit Go4Life, the exercise and physical activity campaign from the National Institute on Aging (NIA) at NIH. Estrogen-only Hormone Therapy After Hysterectomy Hormone therapy with estrogen only may be given to women who have had a hysterectomy. In these women, estrogen-only therapy after menopause may decrease the risk of breast cancer. There is an increased risk of stroke and heart and blood vessel disease in postmenopausal women who take estrogen after a hysterectomy. Learn about menopausal hormone therapy and cancer. Selective Estrogen Receptor Modulators (SERMs) Tamoxifen and raloxifene belong to the family of drugs called selective estrogen receptor modulators (SERMs). SERMs act like estrogen on some tissues in the body, but block the effect of estrogen on other tissues. Treatment with tamoxifen or raloxifene lowers the risk of breast cancer in postmenopausal women. Tamoxifen also lowers the risk of breast cancer in high-risk premenopausal women. With either drug, the reduced risk lasts for several years after treatment is stopped. Lower rates of broken bones have been noted in patients taking raloxifene. Prophylactic Mastectomy Some women who have a high risk of breast cancer may choose to have a prophylactic mastectomy (the removal of both breasts when there are no signs of cancer). The risk of breast cancer is much lower in these women and most feel less anxious about their risk of breast cancer. However, it is very important to have cancer risk assessment and counseling about the different ways to prevent breast cancer before making this decision.  Learn more about surgery to reduce the risk of breast cancer. Prophylactic Oophorectomy Premenopausal women who have a high risk of breast cancer due to certain changes in the BRCA1 and BRCA2 genes may choose to have a prophylactic oophorectomy (the removal of both ovaries when there are no signs of cancer). This decreases the amount of estrogen made by the body and lowers the risk of breast cancer. Prophylactic oophorectomy also lowers the risk of breast cancer in normal premenopausal women and in women with an increased risk of breast cancer due to radiation to the chest. However, it is very important to have cancer risk assessment and counseling before making this decision. The sudden drop in estrogen levels may cause the symptoms of menopause to begin. These include hot flashes, trouble sleeping, anxiety, and depression. Long-term effects include decreased sex drive, vaginal dryness, and decreased bone density. Unclear As Risk Factors It is not clear whether the following affect the risk of breast cancer. - Oral contraceptives. Taking oral contraceptives (&quot;the pill&quot;) may slightly increase the risk of breast cancer in current users. This risk decreases over time. Some oral contraceptives contain estrogen. Progestin-only contraceptives that are injected or implanted do not appear to increase the risk of breast cancer.  - Environment. Studies have not proven that being exposed to certain substances in the environment, such as chemicals, increases the risk of breast cancer.  Oral contraceptives. Taking oral contraceptives (&quot;the pill&quot;) may slightly increase the risk of breast cancer in current users. This risk decreases over time. Some oral contraceptives contain estrogen. Progestin-only contraceptives that are injected or implanted do not appear to increase the risk of breast cancer. Environment. Studies have not proven that being exposed to certain substances in the environment, such as chemicals, increases the risk of breast cancer. For More Information Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials can be found at  http://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials on the website of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). Check NCI&apos;s list of cancer clinical trials for breast cancer prevention trials that are now accepting patients.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000008-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most cancers in their early, most treatable stages do not cause any symptoms. That is why it&apos;s important to have regular tests to check for cancer long before you might notice anything wrong. Detecting Breast Cancer Through Screening When breast cancer is found early, it is more likely to be treated successfully. Checking for cancer in a person who does not have any symptoms is called screening. Screening tests for breast cancer include, among others, clinical breast exams and mammograms. Recent studies have shown that ultrasound and MRI&apos;s may also be useful complementary screening tools, particularly in women with mammograms that are not definitive. During a clinical breast exam, the doctor or other health care professional checks the breasts and underarms for lumps or other changes that could be a sign of breast cancer.  A mammogram is a special x-ray of the breast that often can detect cancers that are too small for a woman or her doctor to feel. (Watch the video to learn more about digital mammography and dense breasts. To enlarge the video, click the brackets in the lower right-hand corner. To reduce the video, press the Escape (Esc) button on your keyboard.) Who Should Have a Mammography? Several studies show that mammography screening has reduced the number of deaths from breast cancer. However, some other studies have not shown a clear benefit from mammography. Scientists are continuing to examine the level of benefit that mammography can produce. The U.S. Preventive Services Task Force (USPSTF) recommends a screening mammography for women 50-74 years every two years.  Learn more about the USPSTF mammography recommendations here. Between 5 and 10 percent of mammogram results are abnormal and require more testing. Most of these follow-up tests confirm that no cancer was present. Worried about the cost of a mammogram? Learn about free and low-cost screenings. (Centers for Disease Control and Prevention) How Biopsies are Performed If needed, the most common follow-up test a doctor will recommend is called a biopsy. This is a procedure where a small amount of fluid or tissue is removed from the breast to make a diagnosis. A doctor might perform fine needle aspiration, a needle or core biopsy, or a surgical biopsy. - With fine needle aspiration, doctors numb the area and use a thin needle to remove fluid and/or cells from a breast lump. If the fluid is clear, it may not need to be checked out by a lab.  - For a needle biopsy, sometimes called a core biopsy, doctors use a needle to remove tissue from an area that looks suspicious on a mammogram but cannot be felt. This tissue goes to a lab where a pathologist examines it to see if any of the cells are cancerous.  - In a surgical biopsy, a surgeon removes a sample of a lump or suspicious area. Sometimes it is necessary to remove the entire lump or suspicious area, plus an area of healthy tissue around the edges. The tissue then goes to a lab where a pathologist examines it under a microscope to check for cancer cells.  With fine needle aspiration, doctors numb the area and use a thin needle to remove fluid and/or cells from a breast lump. If the fluid is clear, it may not need to be checked out by a lab. For a needle biopsy, sometimes called a core biopsy, doctors use a needle to remove tissue from an area that looks suspicious on a mammogram but cannot be felt. This tissue goes to a lab where a pathologist examines it to see if any of the cells are cancerous. In a surgical biopsy, a surgeon removes a sample of a lump or suspicious area. Sometimes it is necessary to remove the entire lump or suspicious area, plus an area of healthy tissue around the edges. The tissue then goes to a lab where a pathologist examines it under a microscope to check for cancer cells. Another type of surgical biopsy that removes less breast tissue is called an image-guided needle breast biopsy, or stereotactic biopsy. Eighty percent of U.S. women who have a surgical breast biopsy do not have cancer. However, women who have breast biopsies are at higher risk of developing breast cancer than women who have never had a breast biopsy. Other Detection Methods Magnetic resonance imaging, or MRI, and ultrasound are two other techniques which, as supplements to standard mammography, might help detect breast cancer with greater accuracy. Genetic Detection The most comprehensive study to date of gene mutations in breast cancer, published in September 2012, confirmed that there are four primary subtypes of breast cancer, each with its own biology. The four groups are called intrinsic subtypes of breast cancer and include HER2-enriched (HER2E), Luminal A (LumA), Luminal B (LumB) and Basal-like. The outlook for survival is different for each of these subtypes of breast cancer. Researchers found that one subtype, Basal-like breast cancer, shares many genetic features with a form of ovarian cancer, and that both may respond similarly to drugs that reduce tumor growth or target DNA repair. The authors hope that discovery of these mutations will be an important step in the effort to improve therapies for breast cancer. For the time being, there are no genetic tests that are commercially available based solely on these findings. Soon, however, knowing extensively which breast cancer gene mutations a woman has should help guide precision treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000008-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are many treatment options for women with breast cancer. The choice of treatment depends on your age and general health, the stage of the cancer, whether or not it has spread beyond the breast, and other factors. If tests show that you have cancer, you should talk with your doctor and make treatment decisions as soon as possible. Studies show that early treatment leads to better outcomes. Working With a Team of Specialists People with cancer often are treated by a team of specialists. The team will keep the primary doctor informed about the patient&apos;s progress. The team may include a medical oncologist who is a specialist in cancer treatment, a surgeon, a radiation oncologist who is a specialist in radiation therapy, and others. Before starting treatment, you may want another doctor to review the diagnosis and treatment plan. Some insurance companies require a second opinion. Others may pay for a second opinion if you request it. (Watch the video about this breast cancer survivor&apos;s treatment. To enlarge the video, click the brackets in the lower right-hand corner. To reduce the video, press the Escape (Esc) button on your keyboard.) Clinical Trials for Breast Cancer Some breast cancer patients take part in studies of new treatments. These studies, called clinical trials, are designed to find out whether a new treatment is both safe and effective. Often, clinical trials compare a new treatment with a standard one so that doctors can learn which is more effective. Women with breast cancer who are interested in taking part in a clinical trial should talk to their doctor. The U.S. National Institutes of Health, through its National Library of Medicine and other Institutes, maintains a database of clinical trials at ClinicalTrials.gov. See a list of the current clinical trials on breast cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000008-7" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are a number of treatments for breast cancer, but the ones women choose most often -- alone or in combination -- are surgery, hormone therapy, radiation therapy, and chemotherapy. What Standard Treatments Do Here is what the standard cancer treatments are designed to do. - Surgery takes out the cancer and some surrounding tissue.   - Hormone therapy keeps cancer cells from getting most of the hormones they need to survive and grow.  - Radiation therapy uses high-energy beams to kill cancer cells and shrink tumors and some surrounding tissue.  -  Chemotherapy uses anti-cancer drugs to kill most cancer cells. Surgery takes out the cancer and some surrounding tissue. Hormone therapy keeps cancer cells from getting most of the hormones they need to survive and grow. Radiation therapy uses high-energy beams to kill cancer cells and shrink tumors and some surrounding tissue.  Chemotherapy uses anti-cancer drugs to kill most cancer cells. Treatment for breast cancer may involve local or whole body therapy. Doctors use local therapies, such as surgery or radiation, to remove or destroy breast cancer in a specific area. Whole body, or systemic, treatments like chemotherapy, hormonal, or biological therapies are used to destroy or control cancer throughout the body. Some patients have both kinds of treatment. Treating Early-Stage Breast Cancer If you have early-stage breast cancer, one common treatment available to you is a lumpectomy combined with radiation therapy. A lumpectomy is surgery that preserves a woman&apos;s breast. In a lumpectomy, the surgeon removes only the tumor and a small amount of the surrounding tissue. The survival rate for a woman who has this therapy plus radiation is similar to that for a woman who chooses a radical mastectomy, which is complete removal of a breast. If Cancer Has Spread Locally If you have breast cancer that has spread locally -- just to other parts of the breast -- your treatment may involve a combination of chemotherapy and surgery. Doctors usually first shrink the tumor with chemotherapy and then remove it through surgery. Shrinking the tumor before surgery may allow a woman to avoid a mastectomy and keep her breast. In the past, doctors would remove a lot of lymph nodes near breast tumors to see if the cancer had spread. Some doctors also use a method called sentinel node biopsy. Using a dye or radioactive tracer, surgeons locate the first or sentinel lymph node closest to the tumor, and remove only that node to see if the cancer has spread. If Cancer Has Spread Beyond the Breast If the breast cancer has spread to other parts of the body, such as the lung or bone, you might receive chemotherapy and/or hormonal therapy to destroy cancer cells and control the disease. Radiation therapy may also be useful to control tumors in other parts of the body. Get more information about treatment options for breast cancer  and for  recurrent breast cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000008-8" qtype="research">what research (or clinical trials) is being done for Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>New Technologies Several new technologies offer hope for making future treatment easier for women with breast cancer. - Using a special tool, doctors can today insert a miniature camera through the nipple and into a milk duct in the breast to examine the area for cancer.  Using a special tool, doctors can today insert a miniature camera through the nipple and into a milk duct in the breast to examine the area for cancer. - Researchers are testing another technique to help women who have undergone weeks of conventional radiation therapy. Using a small catheter -- a tube with a balloon tip -- doctors can deliver tiny radioactive beads to a place on the breast where cancer tissue has been removed. This can reduce the therapy time to a matter of days. Researchers are testing another technique to help women who have undergone weeks of conventional radiation therapy. Using a small catheter -- a tube with a balloon tip -- doctors can deliver tiny radioactive beads to a place on the breast where cancer tissue has been removed. This can reduce the therapy time to a matter of days. New Drug Combination Therapies New drug therapies and combination therapies continue to evolve. - A mix of drugs may increase the length of time you will live or the length of time you will live without cancer. It may someday prove useful for some women with localized breast cancer after they have had surgery.  A mix of drugs may increase the length of time you will live or the length of time you will live without cancer. It may someday prove useful for some women with localized breast cancer after they have had surgery. - New research shows women with early-stage breast cancer who took the drug letrozole, an aromatase inhibitor, after they completed five years of tamoxifen therapy significantly reduced their risk of breast cancer recurrence. New research shows women with early-stage breast cancer who took the drug letrozole, an aromatase inhibitor, after they completed five years of tamoxifen therapy significantly reduced their risk of breast cancer recurrence. Treating HER2-Positive Breast Cancer Herceptin is a drug commonly used to treat women who have a certain type of breast cancer. This drug slows or stops the growth of cancer cells by blocking HER2, a protein found on the surface of some types of breast cancer cells. Approximately 20 to 25 percent of breast cancers produce too much HER2. These &quot;HER2 positive&quot; tumors tend to grow faster and are generally more likely to return than tumors that do not overproduce HER2. Results from clinical trials show that those patients with early-stage HER2 positive breast cancer who received Herceptin in combination with chemotherapy had a 52 percent decrease in risk in the cancer returning compared with patients who received chemotherapy treatment alone. Cancer treatments like chemotherapy can be systemic, meaning they affect whole tissues, organs, or the entire body. Herceptin, however, was the first drug used to target only a specific molecule involved in breast cancer. Another drug, Tykerb, was approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration for use for treatment of HER2-positive breast cancer. Because of the availability of these two drugs, an international trial called ALTTO was designed to determine if one drug is more effective, safer, and if taking the drugs separately, in tandem order, or together is better. Unfortunately, the results, released in 2014, showed that taking two HER2-targeted agents together was no better than taking one alone in improving survival. The TAILORx Trial In an attempt to further specialize breast cancer treatment, The Trial Assigning Individualized Options for Treatment, or TAILORx, enrolled 10,000 women to examine whether appropriate treatment can be assigned based on genes that are frequently associated with risk of recurrence of breast cancer. The goal of TAILORx is important because the majority of women with early-stage breast cancer are advised to receive chemotherapy in addition to radiation and hormonal therapy, yet research has not demonstrated that chemotherapy benefits all of them equally. TAILORx seeks to examine many of a woman&apos;s genes simultaneously and use this information in choosing a treatment course, thus sparing women unnecessary treatment if chemotherapy is not likely to be of substantial benefit to them.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000008-10" qtype="information">What is (are) Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>The body is made up of many types of cells. Normally, cells grow, divide, and produce more cells as needed to keep the body healthy. Sometimes, however, the process goes wrong. Cells become abnormal and form more cells in an uncontrolled way. These extra cells form a mass of tissue, called a growth or tumor. Tumors can be benign, which means not cancerous, or malignant, which means cancerous.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000008-11" qtype="information">What is (are) Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Breast cancer occurs when a malignant tumor forms in the breast tissue. The cancer can be found in the breast itself or in the ducts and lymph nodes that surround the breast.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000008-12" qtype="information">What is (are) Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>When cancer spreads from its original location in the breast to another part of the body such as the brain, it is called metastatic breast cancer, not brain cancer. Doctors sometimes call this &quot;distant&quot; disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="13">
			<Question qid="0000008-13" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Breast Cancer? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Did You Know: Breast Cancer Statistics? Breast cancer is one of the most common cancers in American women. It is most common among women between the ages of 45-85. Today, more women are surviving breast cancer than ever before. Over two million women are breast cancer survivors. (Watch the video to learn more about breast cancer survival rates. To enlarge the video, click the brackets in the lower right-hand corner. To reduce the video, press the Escape (Esc) button on your keyboard.) Men can get breast cancer too, although they account for only one percent of all reported cases. Read more about breast cancer in men.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="14">
			<Question qid="0000008-14" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>When breast cancer first develops, there may be no symptoms at all. But as the cancer grows, it can cause changes that women should watch for. You can help safeguard your health by learning the following warning signs of breast cancer. -  a lump or thickening in or near the breast or in the underarm area  - a change in the size or shape of the breast  - a dimple or puckering in the skin of the breast  -  a nipple turned inward into the breast  -  fluid, other than breast milk, from the nipple, especially if it&apos;s bloody  - scaly, red, or swollen skin on the breast, nipple, or areola (the dark area of skin around the nipple)  - dimples in the breast that look like the skin of an orange. a lump or thickening in or near the breast or in the underarm area a change in the size or shape of the breast a dimple or puckering in the skin of the breast a nipple turned inward into the breast fluid, other than breast milk, from the nipple, especially if it&apos;s bloody scaly, red, or swollen skin on the breast, nipple, or areola (the dark area of skin around the nipple) dimples in the breast that look like the skin of an orange. Don&apos;t Ignore Symptoms You should see your doctor about any symptoms like these. Most often, they are not cancer, but it&apos;s important to check with the doctor so that any problems can be diagnosed and treated as early as possible. Some women believe that as they age, health problems are due to &quot;growing older.&quot; Because of this myth, many illnesses go undiagnosed and untreated. Don&apos;t ignore your symptoms because you think they are not important or because you believe they are normal for your age. Talk to your doctor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="15">
			<Question qid="0000008-15" qtype="information">What is (are) Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>One definition of cure is being alive and free of breast cancer for 5 years. If the cancer is found early, a woman&apos;s chances of survival are better. In fact, nearly 98 percent of women who discover their breast cancer when it is near the site of origin and still small in size are alive 5 years later. However, women whose cancer is diagnosed at a late stage, after it has spread to other parts of the body, have only a 23.3 percent chance of surviving 5 years. To learn more about what happens after treatment, see Surviving Cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="16">
			<Question qid="0000008-16" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Breast Cancer? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Risk factors are conditions or agents that increase a person&apos;s chances of getting a disease. Here are the most common risk factors for breast cancer. - Personal and family history. A personal history of breast cancer or breast cancer among one or more of your close relatives, such as a sister, mother, or daughter.  - Estrogen levels in the body. High estrogen levels over a long time may increase the risk of breast cancer. Estrogen levels are highest during the years a woman is menstruating.  - Never being pregnant or having your first child in your mid-30s or later.  - Early menstruation. Having your first menstrual period before age 12.  -  Breast density. Women with very dense breasts have a higher risk of breast cancer than women with low or normal breast density.   -  Combination hormone replacement therapy/Hormone therapy. Estrogen, progestin, or both may be given to replace the estrogen no longer made by the ovaries in postmenopausal women or women who have had their ovaries removed. This is called hormone replacement therapy. (HRT) or hormone therapy (HT). Combination HRT/HT is estrogen combined with progestin. This type of HRT/HT can increase the risk of breast cancer.   - Exposure to radiation. Radiation therapy to the chest for the treatment of cancer can increase the risk of breast cancer, starting 10 years after treatment. Radiation therapy to treat cancer in one breast does not appear to increase the risk of cancer in the other breast.  - Obesity. Obesity increases the risk of breast cancer, especially in postmenopausal women who have not used hormone replacement therapy.   - Alcohol. Drinking alcohol increases the risk of breast cancer. The level of risk rises as the amount of alcohol consumed rises.  - Gaining weight after menopause, especially after natural menopause and/or after age 60.  - Race. White women are at greater risk than black women. However, black women diagnosed with breast cancer are more likely to die of the disease.  - Inherited gene changes. Women who have inherited certain changes in the genes named BRCA1 and BRCA2 have a higher risk of breast cancer, ovarian cancer and maybe colon cancer. The risk of breast cancer caused by inherited gene changes depends on the type of gene mutation, family history of cancer, and other factors. Men who have inherited certain changes in the BRCA2 gene have a higher risk of breast, prostate and pancreatic cancers, and lymphoma.    Five percent to 10 percent of all breast cancers are thought to be inherited.    Personal and family history. A personal history of breast cancer or breast cancer among one or more of your close relatives, such as a sister, mother, or daughter. Estrogen levels in the body. High estrogen levels over a long time may increase the risk of breast cancer. Estrogen levels are highest during the years a woman is menstruating. Never being pregnant or having your first child in your mid-30s or later. Early menstruation. Having your first menstrual period before age 12. Breast density. Women with very dense breasts have a higher risk of breast cancer than women with low or normal breast density. Combination hormone replacement therapy/Hormone therapy. Estrogen, progestin, or both may be given to replace the estrogen no longer made by the ovaries in postmenopausal women or women who have had their ovaries removed. This is called hormone replacement therapy. (HRT) or hormone therapy (HT). Combination HRT/HT is estrogen combined with progestin. This type of HRT/HT can increase the risk of breast cancer. Exposure to radiation. Radiation therapy to the chest for the treatment of cancer can increase the risk of breast cancer, starting 10 years after treatment. Radiation therapy to treat cancer in one breast does not appear to increase the risk of cancer in the other breast. Obesity. Obesity increases the risk of breast cancer, especially in postmenopausal women who have not used hormone replacement therapy. Alcohol. Drinking alcohol increases the risk of breast cancer. The level of risk rises as the amount of alcohol consumed rises. Gaining weight after menopause, especially after natural menopause and/or after age 60. Race. White women are at greater risk than black women. However, black women diagnosed with breast cancer are more likely to die of the disease. Inherited gene changes. Women who have inherited certain changes in the genes named BRCA1 and BRCA2 have a higher risk of breast cancer, ovarian cancer and maybe colon cancer. The risk of breast cancer caused by inherited gene changes depends on the type of gene mutation, family history of cancer, and other factors. Men who have inherited certain changes in the BRCA2 gene have a higher risk of breast, prostate and pancreatic cancers, and lymphoma.    Five percent to 10 percent of all breast cancers are thought to be inherited.   Get information about the BRCA1 and BRCA2 genetic mutations and testing for them. This chart shows what the approximate chances are of a woman getting invasive breast cancer in her lifetime.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="17">
			<Question qid="0000008-17" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>When studying ways to prevent breast cancer, scientists look at risk factors and protective factors. Anything that increases your chance of developing cancer is called a cancer risk factor. Anything that decreases your chance of developing cancer is called a cancer protective factor. Some risk factors for cancer can be avoided, but many cannot. For example, both smoking and inheriting certain genes are risk factors for some types of cancer, but only smoking can be avoided. Regular exercise and a healthy diet may be protective factors for some types of cancer. Avoiding risk factors and increasing protective factors may lower your risk but it does not mean that you will not get cancer. Different ways to prevent cancer are being studied, including - changing lifestyle or eating habits  - avoiding things known to cause cancer  - taking medicine to treat a precancerous condition or to keep cancer from starting. changing lifestyle or eating habits avoiding things known to cause cancer taking medicine to treat a precancerous condition or to keep cancer from starting.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="21">
			<Question qid="0000008-21" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>When breast cancer first develops, there may be no symptoms at all. But as the cancer grows, it can cause changes that women should watch for. You can help safeguard your health by learning the following warning signs of breast cancer. - a lump or thickening in or near the breast or in the underarm area  - a change in the size or shape of the breast  - ridges or pitting of the breast; the skin looks like the skin of an orange  - a change in the way the skin of the breast, areola, or nipple looks or feels; for example, it may be warm, swollen, red, or scaly  - nipple discharge or tenderness, or the nipple is pulled back or inverted into the breast. a lump or thickening in or near the breast or in the underarm area a change in the size or shape of the breast ridges or pitting of the breast; the skin looks like the skin of an orange a change in the way the skin of the breast, areola, or nipple looks or feels; for example, it may be warm, swollen, red, or scaly nipple discharge or tenderness, or the nipple is pulled back or inverted into the breast. You should see your doctor about any symptoms like these. Most often, they are not cancer, but it&apos;s important to check with the doctor so that any problems can be diagnosed and treated as early as possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="25">
			<Question qid="0000008-25" qtype="information">What is (are) Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>A mammogram can often detect breast changes in women who have no signs of breast cancer. Often, it can find a breast lump before it can be felt. If the results indicate that cancer might be present, your doctor will advise you to have a follow-up test called a biopsy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="26">
			<Question qid="0000008-26" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Breast Cancer? ?</Question>
			<Answer>The risks of breast cancer screening tests include the following. - Finding breast cancer may not improve health or help a woman live longer. Screening may not help you if you have fast-growing breast cancer or if it has already spread to other places in your body. Also, some breast cancers found on a screening mammogram may never cause symptoms or become life-threatening. Finding these cancers is called overdiagnosis.  Finding breast cancer may not improve health or help a woman live longer. Screening may not help you if you have fast-growing breast cancer or if it has already spread to other places in your body. Also, some breast cancers found on a screening mammogram may never cause symptoms or become life-threatening. Finding these cancers is called overdiagnosis. - False-negative test results can occur. Screening test results may appear to be normal even though breast cancer is present. A woman who receives a false-negative test result (one that shows there is no cancer when there really is) may delay seeking medical care even if she has symptoms. False-negative test results can occur. Screening test results may appear to be normal even though breast cancer is present. A woman who receives a false-negative test result (one that shows there is no cancer when there really is) may delay seeking medical care even if she has symptoms. - False-positive test results can occur. Screening test results may appear to be abnormal even though no cancer is present. A false-positive test result (one that shows there is cancer when there really isnt) is usually followed by more tests (such as biopsy), which also have risks.  False-positive test results can occur. Screening test results may appear to be abnormal even though no cancer is present. A false-positive test result (one that shows there is cancer when there really isnt) is usually followed by more tests (such as biopsy), which also have risks. - Anxiety from additional testing may result from false positive results. In one study, women who had a false-positive screening mammogram followed by more testing reported feeling anxiety 3 months later, even though cancer was not diagnosed. However, several studies show that women who feel anxiety after false-positive test results are more likely to schedule regular breast screening exams in the future. Anxiety from additional testing may result from false positive results. In one study, women who had a false-positive screening mammogram followed by more testing reported feeling anxiety 3 months later, even though cancer was not diagnosed. However, several studies show that women who feel anxiety after false-positive test results are more likely to schedule regular breast screening exams in the future. - Mammograms expose the breast to radiation. Being exposed to radiation is a risk factor for breast cancer. The risk of breast cancer from radiation exposure is higher in women who received radiation before age 30 and at high doses. For women older than 40 years, the benefits of an annual screening mammogram may be greater than the risks from radiation exposure.  Mammograms expose the breast to radiation. Being exposed to radiation is a risk factor for breast cancer. The risk of breast cancer from radiation exposure is higher in women who received radiation before age 30 and at high doses. For women older than 40 years, the benefits of an annual screening mammogram may be greater than the risks from radiation exposure. - There may be pain or discomfort during a mammogram. During a mammogram, the breast is placed between 2 plates that are pressed together. Pressing the breast helps to get a better x-ray of the breast. Some women have pain or discomfort during a mammogram.  There may be pain or discomfort during a mammogram. During a mammogram, the breast is placed between 2 plates that are pressed together. Pressing the breast helps to get a better x-ray of the breast. Some women have pain or discomfort during a mammogram. Some women worry about radiation exposure, but the risk of any harm from a mammogram is actually quite small. The doses of radiation used are very low and considered safe. The exact amount of radiation used during a mammogram will depend on several factors. For instance, breasts that are large or dense will require higher doses to get a clear image. Learn more about the risks of breast cancer screening.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="29">
			<Question qid="0000008-29" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can seek conventional treatment from a specialized cancer doctor, called an oncologist. The oncologist will usually assemble a team of specialists to guide your therapy. Besides the oncologist, the team may include a surgeon, a radiation oncologist who is a specialist in radiation therapy, and others. Before starting treatment, you may want another doctor to review the diagnosis and treatment plan. Some insurance companies require a second opinion. Others may pay for a second opinion if you request it. You might also be eligible to enroll in a clinical trial to receive treatment that conventional therapies may not offer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="30">
			<Question qid="0000008-30" qtype="research">what research (or clinical trials) is being done for Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Clinical trials are research studies on people to find out whether a new drug or treatment is both safe and effective. New therapies are tested on people only after laboratory and animal studies show promising results. The Food and Drug Administration sets strict rules to make sure that people who agree to be in the studies are treated as safely as possible. Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials can be found at http://www.cancer.gov/clinicaltrials on the website of the National Cancer Institute (NCI). Check NCI&apos;s list of cancer clinical trials for breast cancer prevention trials that are now accepting patients.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="31">
			<Question qid="0000008-31" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Once breast cancer has been found, it is staged. Staging means determining how far the cancer has progressed. Through staging, the doctor can tell if the cancer has spread and, if so, to what parts of the body. More tests may be performed to help determine the stage. Knowing the stage of the disease helps the doctor plan treatment. Staging will let the doctor know - the size of the tumor and exactly where it is in the breast.  - if the cancer has spread within the breast.  - if cancer is present in the lymph nodes under the arm.  - If cancer is present in other parts of the body. the size of the tumor and exactly where it is in the breast. if the cancer has spread within the breast. if cancer is present in the lymph nodes under the arm. If cancer is present in other parts of the body.  Read more details about the stages of breast cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="32">
			<Question qid="0000008-32" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Standard treatments for breast cancer include - surgery that takes out the cancer and some surrounding tissue  - radiation therapy that uses high-energy beams to kill cancer cells and shrink tumors and some surrounding tissue.  - chemotherapy that uses anti-cancer drugs to kill cancer most cells  - hormone therapy that keeps cancer cells from getting most of the hormones they need to survive and grow. surgery that takes out the cancer and some surrounding tissue radiation therapy that uses high-energy beams to kill cancer cells and shrink tumors and some surrounding tissue. chemotherapy that uses anti-cancer drugs to kill cancer most cells hormone therapy that keeps cancer cells from getting most of the hormones they need to survive and grow. (Watch the video to learn about one breast cancer survivor&apos;s story. To enlarge the video, click the brackets in the lower right-hand corner. To reduce the video, press the Escape (Esc) button on your keyboard.)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="34">
			<Question qid="0000008-34" qtype="information">What is (are) Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are two types of breast-conserving surgery -- lumpectomy and partial mastectomy. - Lumpectomy is the removal of the tumor and a small amount of normal tissue around it. A woman who has a lumpectomy almost always has radiation therapy as well. Most surgeons also take out some of the lymph nodes under the arm. Lumpectomy is the removal of the tumor and a small amount of normal tissue around it. A woman who has a lumpectomy almost always has radiation therapy as well. Most surgeons also take out some of the lymph nodes under the arm. - Partial or segmental mastectomy is removal of the cancer, some of the breast tissue around the tumor, and the lining over the chest muscles below the tumor. Often, surgeons remove some of the lymph nodes under the arm. In most cases, radiation therapy follows. Partial or segmental mastectomy is removal of the cancer, some of the breast tissue around the tumor, and the lining over the chest muscles below the tumor. Often, surgeons remove some of the lymph nodes under the arm. In most cases, radiation therapy follows.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="36">
			<Question qid="0000008-36" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Even if the surgeon removes all of the cancer that can be seen at the time of surgery, a woman may still receive follow-up treatment. This may include radiation therapy, chemotherapy, or hormone therapy to try to kill any cancer cells that may be left. Treatment that a patient receives after surgery to increase the chances of a cure is called adjuvant therapy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="38">
			<Question qid="0000008-38" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Radiation therapy uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells and shrink tumors. This therapy often follows a lumpectomy, and is sometimes used after mastectomy. During radiation therapy, a machine outside the body sends high-energy beams to kill the cancer cells that may still be present in the affected breast or in nearby lymph nodes. Doctors sometimes use radiation therapy along with chemotherapy, or before or instead of surgery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="39">
			<Question qid="0000008-39" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chemotherapy is the use of drugs to kill cancer cells. A patient may take chemotherapy by mouth in pill form, or it may be put into the body by inserting a needle into a vein or muscle. Chemotherapy is called whole body or systemic treatment if the drug(s) enter the bloodstream, travel through the body, and kill cancer cells throughout the body. Treatment with standard chemotherapy can be as short as two months or as long as two years. Targeted therapies, usually in pill form, have become more common and focus on either a gene or protein abnormality and usually have few adverse side-effects as they directly affect the abnormality and not other cells or tissues in the body. Sometimes chemotherapy is the only treatment the doctor will recommend. More often, however, chemotherapy is used in addition to surgery, radiation therapy, and/or biological therapy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="40">
			<Question qid="0000008-40" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hormonal therapy keeps cancer cells from getting the hormones they need to grow. This treatment may include the use of drugs that change the way hormones work. Sometimes it includes surgery to remove the ovaries, which make female hormones. Like chemotherapy, hormonal therapy can affect cancer cells throughout the body. Often, women with early-stage breast cancer and those with metastatic breast cancer -- meaning cancer that has spread to other parts of the body -- receive hormone therapy in the form of tamoxifen. Hormone therapy with tamoxifen or estrogens can act on cells all over the body. However, it may increase the chance of developing endometrial cancer. If you take tamoxifen, you should have a pelvic examination every year to look for any signs of cancer. A woman should report any vaginal bleeding, other than menstrual bleeding, to her doctor as soon as possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="41">
			<Question qid="0000008-41" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Certain drugs that have been used successfully in other cancers are now being used to treat some breast cancers. A mix of drugs may increase the length of time you will live, or the length of time you will live without cancer. In addition, certain drugs like Herceptin and Tykerb taken in combination with chemotherapy, can help women with specific genetic breast cancer mutations better than chemotherapy alone.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
