<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000027_2" source="CancerGov" url="https://www.cancer.gov/types/breast/patient/male-breast-treatment-pdq">
<Focus>Male Breast Cancer</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0242787</CUI>
			<CUI>C0238033</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000027_2-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Male Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Key Points
                    - Male breast cancer is a disease in which malignant (cancer) cells form in the tissues of the breast.    - Radiation exposure, high levels of estrogen, and a family history of breast cancer can increase a mans risk of breast cancer.     - Male breast cancer is sometimes caused by inherited gene mutations (changes).    - Men with breast cancer usually have lumps that can be felt.     - Tests that examine the breasts are used to detect (find) and diagnose breast cancer in men.    - If cancer is found, tests are done to study the cancer cells.    - Survival for men with breast cancer is similar to survival for women with breast cancer.    - Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.
                
                
                    Male breast cancer is a disease in which malignant (cancer) cells form in the tissues of the breast.
                    Breast cancer may occur in men. Men at any age may develop breast cancer, but it is usually detected (found) in men between 60 and 70 years of age. Male breast cancer makes up less than 1% of all cases of breast cancer.   The following types of breast cancer are found in men:         -  Infiltrating ductal carcinoma: Cancer that has spread beyond the cells lining ducts in the breast. Most men with breast cancer have this type of cancer.    -  Ductal carcinoma in situ: Abnormal cells that are found in the lining of a duct; also called intraductal carcinoma.    -  Inflammatory breast cancer: A type of cancer in which the breast looks red and swollen and feels warm.     -  Paget disease of the nipple: A tumor that has grown from ducts beneath the nipple onto the surface of the nipple.          Lobular carcinoma in situ (abnormal cells found in one of the lobes or sections of the breast), which sometimes occurs in women, has not been seen in men.
                
                
                    Men with breast cancer usually have lumps that can be felt.
                    Lumps and other signs may be caused by male breast cancer or by other conditions. Check with your doctor if you notice a change in your breasts.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000027_2-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Male Breast Cancer? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Radiation exposure, high levels of estrogen, and a family history of breast cancer can increase a mans risk of breast cancer. Anything that increases your risk of getting a disease is called a risk factor. Having a risk factor does not mean that you will get cancer; not having risk factors doesnt mean that you will not get cancer. Talk with your doctor if you think you may be at risk. Risk factors for breast cancer in men may include the following:         - Being exposed to radiation.     - Having a disease linked to high levels of estrogen in the body, such as cirrhosis (liver disease) or Klinefelter syndrome (a genetic disorder.)    - Having several female relatives who have had breast cancer, especially relatives who have an alteration of the BRCA2 gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000027_2-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Male Breast Cancer inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Male breast cancer is sometimes caused by inherited gene mutations (changes).The genes in cells carry the hereditary information that is received from a persons parents. Hereditary breast cancer makes up about 5% to 10% of all breast cancer. Some mutated genes related to breast cancer are more common in certain ethnic groups. Men who have a mutated gene related to breast cancer have an increased risk of this disease.    There are tests that can detect (find) mutated genes. These genetic tests are sometimes done for members of families with a high risk of cancer. See the following PDQ summaries for more information:         -  Genetics of Breast and Gynecologic Cancers     -  Breast Cancer Prevention     -  Breast Cancer Screening</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000027_2-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Male Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Men with breast cancer usually have lumps that can be felt.Lumps and other signs may be caused by male breast cancer or by other conditions. Check with your doctor if you notice a change in your breasts.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000027_2-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Male Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tests that examine the breasts are used to detect (find) and diagnose breast cancer in men.
                    The following tests and procedures may be used:         -   Physical exam and history : An exam of the body to check general signs of health, including checking for signs of disease, such as lumps or anything else that seems unusual. A history of the patients health habits and past illnesses and treatments will also be taken.    -   Clinical breast exam (CBE): An exam of the breast by a doctor or other health professional. The doctor will carefully feel the breasts and under the arms for lumps or anything else that seems unusual.     -   Ultrasound exam: A procedure in which high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) are bounced off internal tissues or organs and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram. The picture can be printed to be looked at later.    -    MRI (magnetic resonance imaging): A procedure that uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).    -   Blood chemistry studies : A procedure in which a blood sample is checked to measure the amounts of certain substances released into the blood by organs and tissues in the body. An unusual (higher or lower than normal) amount of a substance can be a sign of disease.    -   Biopsy : The removal of cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a microscope by a pathologist to check for signs of cancer. The following are different types of biopsies:                -  Fine-needle aspiration (FNA) biopsy : The removal of tissue or fluid using a thin needle.       -  Core biopsy : The removal of tissue using a wide needle.      -  Excisional biopsy : The removal of an entire lump of tissue.
                
                
                    If cancer is found, tests are done to study the cancer cells.
                    Decisions about the best treatment are based on the results of these tests. The tests give information about:         - How quickly the cancer may grow.    - How likely it is that the cancer will spread through the body.    - How well certain treatments might work.    - How likely the cancer is to recur (come back).        Tests include the following:         -   Estrogen and progesterone receptor test : A test to measure the amount of estrogen and progesterone (hormones) receptors in cancer tissue. If cancer is found in the breast, tissue from the tumor is checked in the laboratory to find out whether estrogen and progesterone could affect the way cancer grows. The test results show whether hormone therapy may stop the cancer from growing.    -   HER2 test: A test to measure the amount of HER2 in cancer tissue. HER2 is a growth factor protein that sends growth signals to cells. When cancer forms, the cells may make too much of the protein, causing more cancer cells to grow. If cancer is found in the breast, tissue from the tumor is checked in the laboratory to find out if there is too much HER2 in the cells. The test results show whether monoclonal antibody therapy may stop the cancer from growing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000027_2-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Male Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Survival for men with breast cancer is similar to survival for women with breast cancer.
                    Survival for men with breast cancer is similar to that for women with breast cancer when their stage at diagnosis is the same. Breast cancer in men, however, is often diagnosed at a later stage. Cancer found at a later stage may be less likely to be cured.
                
                
                    Certain factors affect prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options.
                    The prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options depend on the following:         - The stage of the cancer (whether it is in the breast only or has spread to other places in the body).    - The type of breast cancer.    - Estrogen-receptor and progesterone-receptor levels in the tumor tissue.    - Whether the cancer is also found in the other breast.    - The patients age and general health.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000027_2-7" qtype="stages">What are the stages of Male Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Key Points
                    - After breast cancer has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread within the breast or to other parts of the body.    - There are three ways that cancer spreads in the body.    - Cancer may spread from where it began to other parts of the body.    - The following stages are used for male breast cancer:         - Stage 0 (carcinoma in situ)     - Stage I      - Stage II     - Stage IIIA     - Stage IIIB     - Stage IIIC     - Stage IV
                
                
                    After breast cancer has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread within the breast or to other parts of the body.
                    After breast cancer has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread within the breast or to other parts of the body. This process is called staging. The information gathered from the staging process determines the stage of the disease. It is important to know the stage in order to plan treatment. Breast cancer in men is staged the same as it is in women. The spread of cancer from the breast to lymph nodes and other parts of the body appears to be similar in men and women.   The following tests and procedures may be used in the staging process:         -   Sentinel lymph node biopsy : The removal of the sentinel lymph node during surgery. The sentinel lymph node is the first lymph node to receive lymphatic drainage from a tumor. It is the first lymph node the cancer is likely to spread to from the tumor. A radioactive substance and/or blue dye is injected near the tumor. The substance or dye flows through the lymph ducts to the lymph nodes. The first lymph node to receive the substance or dye is removed. A pathologist views the tissue under a microscope to look for cancer cells. If cancer cells are not found, it may not be necessary to remove more lymph nodes.     -   Chest x-ray : An x-ray of the organs and bones inside the chest. An x-ray is a type of energy beam that can go through the body and onto film, making a picture of areas inside the body.    -   CT scan (CAT scan): A procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, taken from different angles. The pictures are made by a computer linked to an x-ray machine. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.     -   Bone scan : A procedure to check if there are rapidly dividing cells, such as cancer cells, in the bone. A very small amount of radioactive material is injected into a vein and travels through the bloodstream. The radioactive material collects in the bones and is detected by a scanner.    -   PET scan (positron emission tomography scan): A procedure to find malignant tumor cells in the body. A small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into a vein. The PET scanner rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the body. Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells do.
                
                
                    There are three ways that cancer spreads in the body.
                    Cancer can spread through tissue, the lymph system, and the blood:         - Tissue. The cancer spreads from where it began by growing into nearby areas.     - Lymph system. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the lymph system. The cancer travels through the lymph vessels to other parts of the body.     - Blood. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the blood. The cancer travels through the blood vessels to other parts of the body.
                
                
                    Cancer may spread from where it began to other parts of the body.
                    When cancer spreads to another part of the body, it is called metastasis. Cancer cells break away from where they began (the primary tumor) and travel through the lymph system or blood.         - Lymph system. The cancer gets into the lymph system, travels through the lymph vessels, and forms a tumor (metastatic tumor) in another part of the body.    - Blood. The cancer gets into the blood, travels through the blood vessels, and forms a tumor (metastatic tumor) in another part of the body.        The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if breast cancer spreads to the bone, the cancer cells in the bone are actually breast cancer cells. The disease is metastatic breast cancer, not bone cancer.
                
                
                    The following stages are used for male breast cancer:
                    This section describes the stages of breast cancer. The breast cancer stage is based on the results of testing that is done on the tumor and lymph nodes removed during surgery and other tests.     Stage 0 (carcinoma in situ)    There are 3 types of breast carcinoma in situ:            -  Ductal carcinoma in situ (DCIS) is a noninvasive condition in which abnormal cells are found in the lining of a breast duct. The abnormal cells have not spread outside the duct to other tissues in the breast. In some cases, DCIS may become invasive cancer and spread to other tissues. At this time, there is no way to know which lesions could become invasive.     -  Paget disease of the nipple is a condition in which abnormal cells are found in the nipple only.      -  Lobular carcinoma in situ (LCIS) is a condition in which abnormal cells are found in the lobules of the breast. This condition has not been seen in men.               Stage I     In stage I, cancer has formed. Stage I is divided into stages IA and IB.            - In stage IA, the tumor is 2 centimeters or smaller. Cancer has not spread outside the breast.     - In stage IB, small clusters of breast cancer cells (larger than 0.2 millimeter but not larger than 2 millimeters) are found in the lymph nodes and either:                  - no tumor is found in the breast; or       - the tumor is 2 centimeters or smaller.                         Stage II     Stage II is divided into stages IIA and IIB.            - In stage IIA                   - no tumor is found in the breast or the tumor is 2 centimeters or smaller. Cancer (larger than 2 millimeters) is found in 1 to 3 axillary lymph nodes or in the lymph nodes near the breastbone (found during a sentinel lymph node biopsy); or        - the tumor is larger than 2 centimeters but not larger than 5 centimeters. Cancer has not spread to the lymph nodes.                - In stage IIB, the tumor is:                  - larger than 2 centimeters but not larger than 5 centimeters. Small clusters of breast cancer cells (larger than 0.2 millimeter but not larger than 2 millimeters) are found in the lymph nodes; or        - larger than 2 centimeters but not larger than 5 centimeters. Cancer has spread to 1 to 3 axillary lymph nodes or to the lymph nodes near the breastbone (found during a sentinel lymph node biopsy); or        - larger than 5 centimeters. Cancer has not spread to the lymph nodes.                          Stage IIIA    In stage IIIA:            - no tumor is found in the breast or the tumor may be any size. Cancer is found in 4 to 9 axillary lymph nodes or in the lymph nodes near the breastbone (found during imaging tests or a physical exam); or      - the tumor is larger than 5 centimeters. Small clusters of breast cancer cells (larger than 0.2 millimeter but not larger than 2 millimeters) are found in the lymph nodes; or      - the tumor is larger than 5 centimeters. Cancer has spread to 1 to 3 axillary lymph nodes or to the lymph nodes near the breastbone (found during a sentinel lymph node biopsy).               Stage IIIB    In stage IIIB, the tumor may be any size and cancer has spread to the chest wall and/or to the skin of the breast and caused swelling or an ulcer. Also, cancer may have spread to :            - up to 9 axillary lymph nodes; or     - the lymph nodes near the breastbone.           Cancer that has spread to the skin of the breast may also be inflammatory breast cancer. See the section on Inflammatory Male Breast Cancer for more information.       Stage IIIC    In stage IIIC, no tumor is found in the breast or the tumor may be any size. Cancer may have spread to the skin of the breast and caused swelling or an ulcer and/or has spread to the chest wall. Also, cancer has spread to:             - 10 or more axillary lymph nodes; or     -  lymph nodes above or below the collarbone; or     - axillary lymph nodes and lymph nodes near the breastbone.           Cancer that has spread to the skin of the breast may also be inflammatory breast cancer. See the section on Inflammatory Male Breast Cancer for more information.    For treatment, stage IIIC breast cancer is divided into operable and inoperable stage IIIC.        Stage IV    In stage IV, cancer has spread to other organs of the body, most often the bones, lungs, liver, or brain.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000027_2-8" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Male Breast Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Key Points
                    - There are different types of treatment for men with breast cancer.    - Five types of standard treatment are used to treat men with breast cancer:         - Surgery      - Chemotherapy      - Hormone therapy      - Radiation therapy     - Targeted therapy        - Treatment for male breast cancer may cause side effects.
                
                
                    There are different types of treatment for men with breast cancer.
                    Different types of treatment are available for men with breast cancer. Some treatments are standard (the currently used treatment), and some are being tested in clinical trials. A treatment clinical trial is a research study meant to help improve current treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients with cancer. When clinical trials show that a new treatment is better than the standard treatment, the new treatment may become the standard treatment.   For some patients, taking part in a clinical trial may be the best treatment choice. Many of today&apos;s standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first to receive a new treatment.   Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.   Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the side effects of cancer treatment.   Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. Information about clinical trials is available from the NCI website. Choosing the most appropriate cancer treatment is a decision that ideally involves the patient, family, and health care team.
                
                
                    Five types of standard treatment are used to treat men with breast cancer:
                    Surgery      Surgery for men with breast cancer is usually a modified radical mastectomy (removal of the breast, many of the lymph nodes under the arm, the lining over the chest muscles, and sometimes part of the chest wall muscles).         Breast-conserving surgery, an operation to remove the cancer but not the breast itself, is also used for some men with breast cancer. A lumpectomy is done to remove the tumor (lump) and a small amount of normal tissue around it. Radiation therapy is given after surgery to kill any cancer cells that are left.          Chemotherapy      Chemotherapy is a cancer treatment that uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or injected into a vein or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (systemic chemotherapy). When chemotherapy is placed directly into the cerebrospinal fluid, an organ, or a body cavity such as the abdomen, the drugs mainly affect cancer cells in those areas (regional chemotherapy). The way the chemotherapy is given depends on the type and stage of the cancer being treated.    See Drugs Approved for Breast Cancer for more information.       Hormone therapy      Hormone therapy is a cancer treatment that removes hormones or blocks their action and stops cancer cells from growing. Hormones are substances made by glands in the body and circulated in the bloodstream. Some hormones can cause certain cancers to grow. If tests show that the cancer cells have places where hormones can attach (receptors), drugs, surgery, or radiation therapy is used to reduce the production of hormones or block them from working.     See Drugs Approved for Breast Cancer for more information.       Radiation therapy    Radiation therapy is a cancer treatment that uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. There are two types of radiation therapy:            -  External radiation therapy uses a machine outside the body to send radiation toward the cancer.     -  Internal radiation therapy uses a radioactive substance sealed in needles, seeds, wires, or catheters that are placed directly into or near the cancer.           The way the radiation therapy is given depends on the type and stage of the cancer being treated. External radiation therapy is used to treat male breast cancer.        Targeted therapy     Targeted therapy is a type of treatment that uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells without harming normal cells. Monoclonal antibody therapy is a type of targeted therapy used to treat men with breast cancer.     Monoclonal antibody therapy uses antibodies made in the laboratory from a single type of immune system cell. These antibodies can identify substances on cancer cells or normal substances that may help cancer cells grow. The antibodies attach to the substances and kill the cancer cells, block their growth, or keep them from spreading. Monoclonal antibodies are given by infusion. They may be used alone or to carry drugs, toxins, or radioactive material directly to cancer cells. Monoclonal antibodies are also used with chemotherapy as adjuvant therapy (treatment given after surgery to lower the risk that the cancer will come back).      Trastuzumab is a monoclonal antibody that blocks the effects of the growth factor protein HER2.     See Drugs Approved for Breast Cancer for more information.
                
                
                    Treatment for male breast cancer may cause side effects.
                    For information about side effects caused by treatment for cancer, see our Side Effects page.
                
		        
		            Treatment Options for Male Breast Cancer
		            
		                
		                    Initial Surgery
		                    Treatment for men diagnosed with breast cancer is usually modified radical mastectomy. Breast-conserving surgery with lumpectomy may be used for some men.
		                
		                
		                    Adjuvant Therapy
		                    Therapy given after an operation when cancer cells can no longer be seen is called adjuvant therapy. Even if the doctor removes all the cancer that can be seen at the time of the operation, the patient may be given radiation therapy, chemotherapy, hormone therapy, and/or targeted therapy after surgery, to try to kill any cancer cells that may be left.         -  Node-negative: For men whose cancer is node-negative (cancer has not spread to the lymph nodes), adjuvant therapy should be considered on the same basis as for a woman with breast cancer because there is no evidence that response to therapy is different for men and women.     -  Node-positive: For men whose cancer is node-positive (cancer has spread to the lymph nodes), adjuvant therapy may include the following:                - Chemotherapy plus tamoxifen (to block the effect of estrogen).      - Other hormone therapy.      - Targeted therapy with a monoclonal antibody (trastuzumab).                 These treatments appear to increase survival in men as they do in women. The patients response to hormone therapy depends on whether there are hormone receptors (proteins) in the tumor. Most breast cancers in men have these receptors. Hormone therapy is usually recommended for male breast cancer patients, but it can have many side effects, including hot flashes and impotence (the inability to have an erection adequate for sexual intercourse).
		                
		                
		                    Distant Metastases
		                    Treatment for men with distant metastases (cancer that has spread to other parts of the body) may be hormone therapy, chemotherapy, or both. Hormone therapy may include the following:         -  Orchiectomy (the removal of the testicles to decrease the amount of hormone made).    -  Luteinizing hormone-releasing hormone agonist with or without total androgen blockade (to decrease the the amount of sex hormones made).    -  Tamoxifen for cancer that is estrogen-receptor positive.    -  Progestin (a female hormone made in a laboratory).    -  Aromatase inhibitors (to decrease the amount of estrogen made).        Hormone therapies may be used in sequence (one after the other). Standard chemotherapy regimens may be used if hormone therapy does not work. Men usually respond to therapy in the same way as women who have breast cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
