<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000019_1" source="CancerGov" url="https://www.cancer.gov/types/ovarian/patient/ovarian-epithelial-treatment-pdq">
<Focus>Ovarian Epithelial, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1299307</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000019_1-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ovarian Epithelial, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Key Points
                    - Ovarian epithelial cancer, fallopian tube cancer, and primary peritoneal cancer are diseases in which malignant (cancer) cells form in the tissue covering the ovary or lining the fallopian tube or peritoneum.     - Ovarian epithelial cancer, fallopian tube cancer, and primary peritoneal cancer form in the same type of tissue and are treated the same way.    - Women who have a family history of ovarian cancer are at an increased risk of ovarian cancer.    - Some ovarian, fallopian tube, and primary peritoneal cancers are caused by inherited gene mutations (changes).    - Women with an increased risk of ovarian cancer may consider surgery to lessen the risk.    - Signs and symptoms of ovarian, fallopian tube, or peritoneal cancer include pain or swelling in the abdomen.    - Tests that examine the ovaries and pelvic area are used to detect (find) and diagnose ovarian, fallopian tube, and peritoneal cancer.    - Certain factors affect treatment options and prognosis (chance of recovery).
                
                
                    Ovarian epithelial cancer, fallopian tube cancer, and primary peritoneal cancer are diseases in which malignant (cancer) cells form in the tissue covering the ovary or lining the fallopian tube or peritoneum.
                    The ovaries are a pair of organs in the female reproductive system. They are in the pelvis, one on each side of the uterus (the hollow, pear-shaped organ where a fetus grows). Each ovary is about the size and shape of an almond. The ovaries make eggs and female hormones (chemicals that control the way certain cells or organs work).    The fallopian tubes are a pair of long, slender tubes, one on each side of the uterus. Eggs pass from the ovaries, through the fallopian tubes, to the uterus. Cancer sometimes begins at the end of the fallopian tube near the ovary and spreads to the ovary.   The peritoneum is the tissue that lines the abdominal wall and covers organs in the abdomen. Primary peritoneal cancer is cancer that forms in the peritoneum and has not spread there from another part of the body. Cancer sometimes begins in the peritoneum and spreads to the ovary.       Ovarian epithelial cancer is one type of cancer that affects the ovary. See the following PDQ treatment summaries for information about other types of ovarian tumors:         -  Ovarian Germ Cell Tumors     -  Ovarian Low Malignant Potential Tumors     -  Unusual Cancers of Childhood Treatment (ovarian cancer in children)
                
                
                    Ovarian epithelial cancer, fallopian tube cancer, and primary peritoneal cancer form in the same type of tissue and are treated the same way.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000019_1-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Ovarian Epithelial, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Women who have a family history of ovarian cancer are at an increased risk of ovarian cancer. Anything that increases your risk of getting a disease is called a risk factor. Having a risk factor does not mean that you will get cancer; not having risk factors doesn&apos;t mean that you will not get cancer. Talk with your doctor if you think you may be at risk.   Women who have one first-degree relative (mother, daughter, or sister) with a history of ovarian cancer have an increased risk of ovarian cancer. This risk is higher in women who have one first-degree relative and one second-degree relative (grandmother or aunt) with a history of ovarian cancer. This risk is even higher in women who have two or more first-degree relatives with a history of ovarian cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000019_1-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Ovarian Epithelial, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Some ovarian, fallopian tube, and primary peritoneal cancers are caused by inherited gene mutations (changes). The genes in cells carry the hereditary information that is received from a persons parents. Hereditary ovarian cancer makes up about 20% of all cases of ovarian cancer. There are three hereditary patterns: ovarian cancer alone, ovarian and breast cancers, and ovarian and colon cancers.    Fallopian tube cancer and peritoneal cancer may also be caused by certain inherited gene mutations.   There are tests that can detect gene mutations. These genetic tests are sometimes done for members of families with a high risk of cancer. See the following PDQ summaries for more information:          -  Ovarian, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer Prevention     -  Genetics of Breast and Gynecologic Cancers (for health professionals)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000019_1-4" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Ovarian Epithelial, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Women with an increased risk of ovarian cancer may consider surgery to lessen the risk. Some women who have an increased risk of ovarian cancer may choose to have a risk-reducing oophorectomy (the removal of healthy ovaries so that cancer cannot grow in them). In high-risk women, this procedure has been shown to greatly decrease the risk of ovarian cancer. (See the PDQ summary on Ovarian, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer Prevention for more information.)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000019_1-5" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ovarian Epithelial, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Signs and symptoms of ovarian, fallopian tube, or peritoneal cancer include pain or swelling in the abdomen. Ovarian, fallopian tube, or peritoneal cancer may not cause early signs or symptoms. When signs or symptoms do appear, the cancer is often advanced. Signs and symptoms may include the following:         - Pain, swelling, or a feeling of pressure in the abdomen or pelvis.    -  Vaginal bleeding that is heavy or irregular, especially after menopause.    - Vaginal discharge that is clear, white, or colored with blood.    - A lump in the pelvic area.    -  Gastrointestinal problems, such as gas, bloating, or constipation.        These signs and symptoms also may be caused by other conditions and not by ovarian, fallopian tube, or peritoneal cancer. If the signs or symptoms get worse or do not go away on their own, check with your doctor so that any problem can be diagnosed and treated as early as possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000019_1-6" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Ovarian Epithelial, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tests that examine the ovaries and pelvic area are used to detect (find) and diagnose ovarian, fallopian tube, and peritoneal cancer. The following tests and procedures may be used:         -   Physical exam and history : An exam of the body to check general signs of health, including checking for signs of disease, such as lumps or anything else that seems unusual. A history of the patients health habits and past illnesses and treatments will also be taken.    -   Pelvic exam : An exam of the vagina, cervix, uterus, fallopian tubes, ovaries, and rectum. A speculum is inserted into the vagina and the doctor or nurse looks at the vagina and cervix for signs of disease. A Pap test of the cervix is usually done. The doctor or nurse also inserts one or two lubricated, gloved fingers of one hand into the vagina and places the other hand over the lower abdomen to feel the size, shape, and position of the uterus and ovaries. The doctor or nurse also inserts a lubricated, gloved finger into the rectum to feel for lumps or abnormal areas.    -   CA 125 assay : A test that measures the level of CA 125 in the blood. CA 125 is a substance released by cells into the bloodstream. An increased CA 125 level can be a sign of cancer or another condition such as endometriosis.    -   Ultrasound exam: A procedure in which high-energy sound waves (ultrasound) are bounced off internal tissues or organs in the abdomen, and make echoes. The echoes form a picture of body tissues called a sonogram. The picture can be printed to be looked at later. Some patients may have a transvaginal ultrasound.    -   CT scan (CAT scan): A procedure that makes a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body, taken from different angles. The pictures are made by a computer linked to an x-ray machine. A dye may be injected into a vein or swallowed to help the organs or tissues show up more clearly. This procedure is also called computed tomography, computerized tomography, or computerized axial tomography.     -   PET scan (positron emission tomography scan): A procedure to find malignant tumor cells in the body. A very small amount of radioactive glucose (sugar) is injected into a vein. The PET scanner rotates around the body and makes a picture of where glucose is being used in the body. Malignant tumor cells show up brighter in the picture because they are more active and take up more glucose than normal cells do.    -   MRI (magnetic resonance imaging): A procedure that uses a magnet, radio waves, and a computer to make a series of detailed pictures of areas inside the body. This procedure is also called nuclear magnetic resonance imaging (NMRI).    -   Chest x-ray : An x-ray of the organs and bones inside the chest. An x-ray is a type of energy beam that can go through the body and onto film, making a picture of areas inside the body.    -   Biopsy : The removal of cells or tissues so they can be viewed under a microscope by a pathologist to check for signs of cancer. The tissue is usually removed during surgery to remove the tumor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000019_1-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Ovarian Epithelial, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Certain factors affect treatment options and prognosis (chance of recovery). The prognosis (chance of recovery) and treatment options depend on the following:         - The type of ovarian cancer and how much cancer there is.    - The stage and grade of the cancer.    - Whether the patient has extra fluid in the abdomen that causes swelling.    - Whether all of the tumor can be removed by surgery.    - Whether there are changes in the  BRCA1  or  BRCA2  genes.    - The patients age and general health.    - Whether the cancer has just been diagnosed or has recurred (come back).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000019_1-8" qtype="stages">What are the stages of Ovarian Epithelial, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Key Points
                    - After ovarian, fallopian tube, or peritoneal cancer has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread within the ovaries or to other parts of the body.     - There are three ways that cancer spreads in the body.    - Cancer may spread from where it began to other parts of the body.    - The following stages are used for ovarian epithelial, fallopian tube, and primary peritoneal cancer:         - Stage I     - Stage II     - Stage III     - Stage IV        - Ovarian epithelial, fallopian tube, and primary peritoneal cancers are grouped for treatment as early or advanced cancer.
                
                
                    After ovarian, fallopian tube, or peritoneal cancer has been diagnosed, tests are done to find out if cancer cells have spread within the ovaries or to other parts of the body.
                    The process used to find out whether cancer has spread within the organ or to other parts of the body is called staging. The information gathered from the staging process determines the stage of the disease. It is important to know the stage in order to plan treatment. The results of the tests used to diagnose cancer are often also used to stage the disease. (See the General Information section.)
                
                
                    There are three ways that cancer spreads in the body.
                    Cancer can spread through tissue, the lymph system, and the blood:         - Tissue. The cancer spreads from where it began by growing into nearby areas.     - Lymph system. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the lymph system. The cancer travels through the lymph vessels to other parts of the body.     - Blood. The cancer spreads from where it began by getting into the blood. The cancer travels through the blood vessels to other parts of the body.
                
                
                    Cancer may spread from where it began to other parts of the body.
                    When cancer spreads to another part of the body, it is called metastasis. Cancer cells break away from where they began (the primary tumor) and travel through the lymph system or blood.         - Lymph system. The cancer gets into the lymph system, travels through the lymph vessels, and forms a tumor (metastatic tumor) in another part of the body.    - Blood. The cancer gets into the blood, travels through the blood vessels, and forms a tumor (metastatic tumor) in another part of the body.        The metastatic tumor is the same type of cancer as the primary tumor. For example, if ovarian epithelial cancer spreads to the lung, the cancer cells in the lung are actually ovarian epithelial cancer cells. The disease is metastatic ovarian epithelial cancer, not lung cancer.
                
                
                    The following stages are used for ovarian epithelial, fallopian tube, and primary peritoneal cancer:
                    Stage I     In stage I, cancer is found in one or both ovaries or fallopian tubes. Stage I is divided into stage IA, stage IB, and stage IC.            -  Stage IA: Cancer is found inside a single ovary or fallopian tube.     -  Stage IB: Cancer is found inside both ovaries or fallopian tubes.     -  Stage IC: Cancer is found inside one or both ovaries or fallopian tubes and one of the following is true:                   - cancer is also found on the outside surface of one or both ovaries or fallopian tubes; or       - the capsule (outer covering) of the ovary ruptured (broke open) before or during surgery; or       - cancer cells are found in the fluid of the peritoneal cavity (the body cavity that contains most of the organs in the abdomen) or in washings of the peritoneum (tissue lining the peritoneal cavity).                         Stage II     In stage II, cancer is found in one or both ovaries or fallopian tubes and has spread into other areas of the pelvis, or primary peritoneal cancer is found within the pelvis. Stage II ovarian epithelial and fallopian tube cancers are divided into stage IIA and stage IIB.            -  Stage IIA: Cancer has spread from where it first formed to the uterus and/or the fallopian tubes and/or the ovaries.     -  Stage IIB: Cancer has spread from the ovary or fallopian tube to organs in the peritoneal cavity (the space that contains the abdominal organs).               Stage III    In stage III, cancer is found in one or both ovaries or fallopian tubes, or is primary peritoneal cancer, and has spread outside the pelvis to other parts of the abdomen and/or to nearby lymph nodes. Stage III is divided into stage IIIA, stage IIIB, and stage IIIC.            - In stage IIIA, one of the following is true:                  - Cancer has spread to lymph nodes in the area outside or behind the peritoneum only; or       - Cancer cells that can be seen only with a microscope have spread to the surface of the peritoneum outside the pelvis. Cancer may have spread to nearby lymph nodes.                 -  Stage IIIB: Cancer has spread to the peritoneum outside the pelvis and the cancer in the peritoneum is 2 centimeters or smaller. Cancer may have spread to lymph nodes behind the peritoneum.     -  Stage IIIC: Cancer has spread to the peritoneum outside the pelvis and the cancer in the peritoneum is larger than 2 centimeters. Cancer may have spread to lymph nodes behind the peritoneum or to the surface of the liver or spleen.              Stage IV     In stage IV, cancer has spread beyond the abdomen to other parts of the body. Stage IV is divided into stage IVA and stage IVB.            -  Stage IVA: Cancer cells are found in extra fluid that builds up around the lungs.     -  Stage IVB: Cancer has spread to organs and tissues outside the abdomen, including lymph nodes in the groin.
                
                
                    Ovarian epithelial, fallopian tube, and primary peritoneal cancers are grouped for treatment as early or advanced cancer.
                    Stage I ovarian epithelial and fallopian tube cancers are treated as early cancers.   Stages II, III, and IV ovarian epithelial, fallopian tube, and primary peritoneal cancers are treated as advanced cancers.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000019_1-9" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Ovarian Epithelial, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Key Points
                    - There are different types of treatment for patients with ovarian epithelial cancer.    - Three kinds of standard treatment are used.         - Surgery      - Chemotherapy     - Targeted therapy        - New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.          - Radiation therapy     - Immunotherapy        - Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.    - Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.    - Follow-up tests may be needed.
                
                
                    There are different types of treatment for patients with ovarian epithelial cancer.
                    Different types of treatment are available for patients with ovarian epithelial cancer. Some treatments are standard, and some are being tested in clinical trials. A treatment clinical trial is a research study meant to help improve current treatments or obtain information on new treatments for patients with cancer. When clinical trials show that a new treatment is better than the treatment currently used as standard treatment, the new treatment may become the standard treatment. Patients with any stage of ovarian cancer may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial. Some clinical trials are open only to patients who have not started treatment.
                
                
                    Three kinds of standard treatment are used.
                    Surgery     Most patients have surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible. Different types of surgery may include:            -  Hysterectomy: Surgery to remove the uterus and, sometimes, the cervix. When only the uterus is removed, it is called a partial hysterectomy. When both the uterus and the cervix are removed, it is called a total hysterectomy. If the uterus and cervix are taken out through the vagina, the operation is called a vaginal hysterectomy. If the uterus and cervix are taken out through a large incision (cut) in the abdomen, the operation is called a total abdominal hysterectomy. If the uterus and cervix are taken out through a small incision (cut) in the abdomen using a laparoscope, the operation is called a total laparoscopic hysterectomy.     -  Unilateral salpingo-oophorectomy: A surgical procedure to remove one ovary and one fallopian tube.     -  Bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy: A surgical procedure to remove both ovaries and both fallopian tubes.     -  Omentectomy: A surgical procedure to remove the omentum (tissue in the peritoneum that contains blood vessels, nerves, lymph vessels, and lymph nodes).      - Lymph node biopsy: The removal of all or part of a lymph node. A pathologist views the tissue under a microscope to look for cancer cells.              Chemotherapy     Chemotherapy is a cancer treatment that uses drugs to stop the growth of cancer cells, either by killing the cells or by stopping them from dividing. When chemotherapy is taken by mouth or injected into a vein or muscle, the drugs enter the bloodstream and can reach cancer cells throughout the body (systemic chemotherapy). When chemotherapy is placed directly into the cerebrospinal fluid, an organ, or a body cavity such as the abdomen, the drugs mainly affect cancer cells in those areas (regional chemotherapy).     A type of regional chemotherapy used to treat ovarian cancer is intraperitoneal (IP) chemotherapy. In IP chemotherapy, the anticancer drugs are carried directly into the peritoneal cavity (the space that contains the abdominal organs) through a thin tube.     Treatment with more than one anticancer drug is called combination chemotherapy.    The way the chemotherapy is given depends on the type and stage of the cancer being treated.    See Drugs Approved for Ovarian, Fallopian Tube, or Primary Peritoneal Cancer for more information.       Targeted therapy     Targeted therapy is a type of treatment that uses drugs or other substances to identify and attack specific cancer cells without harming normal cells.     Monoclonal antibody therapy is a type of targeted therapy that uses antibodies made in the laboratory, from a single type of immune system cell. These antibodies can identify substances on cancer cells or normal substances that may help cancer cells grow. The antibodies attach to the substances and kill the cancer cells, block their growth, or keep them from spreading. Monoclonal antibodies are given by infusion. They may be used alone or to carry drugs, toxins, or radioactive material directly to cancer cells.     Bevacizumab is a monoclonal antibody that may be used with chemotherapy to treat ovarian epithelial cancer, fallopian tube cancer, or primary peritoneal cancer that has recurred (come back).     Poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase inhibitors (PARP inhibitors) are targeted therapy drugs that block DNA repair and may cause cancer cells to die. Olaparib and niraparib are PARP inhibitors that may be used to treat advanced ovarian cancer.     See Drugs Approved for Ovarian, Fallopian Tube, or Primary Peritoneal Cancer for more information.
                
                
                    New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.
                    This summary section describes treatments that are being studied in clinical trials. It may not mention every new treatment being studied. Information about clinical trials is available from the NCI website.     Radiation therapy     Radiation therapy is a cancer treatment that uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. Some women receive a treatment called intraperitoneal radiation therapy, in which radioactive liquid is put directly in the abdomen through a catheter. Intraperitoneal radiation therapy is being studied to treat advanced ovarian cancer.       Immunotherapy     Immunotherapy is a treatment that uses the patients immune system to fight cancer. Substances made by the body or made in a laboratory are used to boost, direct, or restore the bodys natural defenses against cancer. This type of cancer treatment is also called biotherapy or immunotherapy.     Vaccine therapy uses a substance to stimulate the immune system to destroy a tumor. Vaccine therapy is being studied to treat advanced ovarian cancer.
                
                
                    Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.
                    For some patients, taking part in a clinical trial may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer treatments are safe and effective or better than the standard treatment.   Many of today&apos;s standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first to receive a new treatment.   Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.
                
                
                    Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.
                    Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the side effects of cancer treatment.   Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. See the Treatment Options section that follows for links to current treatment clinical trials. These have been retrieved from NCI&apos;s listing of clinical trials.
                
                
                    Follow-up tests may be needed.
                    Some of the tests that were done to diagnose the cancer or to find out the stage of the cancer may be repeated. Some tests will be repeated in order to see how well the treatment is working. Decisions about whether to continue, change, or stop treatment may be based on the results of these tests.   Some of the tests will continue to be done from time to time after treatment has ended. The results of these tests can show if your condition has changed or if the cancer has recurred (come back). These tests are sometimes called follow-up tests or check-ups.
                
		        
		            Treatment Options by Stage
		            
		                
		                    Early Ovarian Epithelial and Fallopian Tube Cancer
		                    Treatment of early ovarian epithelial cancer or fallopian tube cancer may include the following:         -  Hysterectomy, bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy, and omentectomy. Lymph nodes and other tissues in the pelvis and abdomen are removed and checked under a microscope for cancer cells. Chemotherapy may be given after surgery.    -  Unilateral salpingo-oophorectomy may be done in certain women who wish to have children. Chemotherapy may be given after surgery.        Check the list of NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now accepting patients with stage I ovarian epithelial cancer and fallopian tube cancer. For more specific results, refine the search by using other search features, such as the location of the trial, the type of treatment, or the name of the drug. Talk with your doctor about clinical trials that may be right for you. General information about clinical trials is available from the NCI website.
		                
		                
		                    Advanced Ovarian Epithelial, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer
		                    Treatment of advanced ovarian epithelial cancer, fallopian tube cancer, or primary peritoneal cancer may include the following:         -  Hysterectomy, bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy, and omentectomy. Lymph nodes and other tissues in the pelvis and abdomen are removed and checked under a microscope to look for cancer cells. Surgery is followed by one of the following:               -  Intravenous chemotherapy.      -  Intraperitoneal chemotherapy.      -  Chemotherapy and targeted therapy (bevacizumab, olaparib, or niraparib).             - Chemotherapy followed by hysterectomy, bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy, and omentectomy.     - Chemotherapy alone for patients who cannot have surgery.    - A clinical trial of intraperitoneal radiation therapy, immunotherapy (vaccine therapy), or targeted therapy.        Check the list of NCI-supported cancer clinical trials that are now accepting patients with stage II ovarian epithelial cancer, stage III ovarian epithelial cancer, stage IV ovarian epithelial cancer, fallopian tube cancer and primary peritoneal cavity cancer. For more specific results, refine the search by using other search features, such as the location of the trial, the type of treatment, or the name of the drug. Talk with your doctor about clinical trials that may be right for you. General information about clinical trials is available from the NCI website.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000019_1-10" qtype="research">what research (or clinical trials) is being done for Ovarian Epithelial, Fallopian Tube, and Primary Peritoneal Cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>New types of treatment are being tested in clinical trials.
                    This summary section describes treatments that are being studied in clinical trials. It may not mention every new treatment being studied. Information about clinical trials is available from the NCI website.     Radiation therapy     Radiation therapy is a cancer treatment that uses high-energy x-rays or other types of radiation to kill cancer cells or keep them from growing. Some women receive a treatment called intraperitoneal radiation therapy, in which radioactive liquid is put directly in the abdomen through a catheter. Intraperitoneal radiation therapy is being studied to treat advanced ovarian cancer.       Immunotherapy     Immunotherapy is a treatment that uses the patients immune system to fight cancer. Substances made by the body or made in a laboratory are used to boost, direct, or restore the bodys natural defenses against cancer. This type of cancer treatment is also called biotherapy or immunotherapy.     Vaccine therapy uses a substance to stimulate the immune system to destroy a tumor. Vaccine therapy is being studied to treat advanced ovarian cancer.
                
                
                    Patients may want to think about taking part in a clinical trial.
                    For some patients, taking part in a clinical trial may be the best treatment choice. Clinical trials are part of the cancer research process. Clinical trials are done to find out if new cancer treatments are safe and effective or better than the standard treatment.   Many of today&apos;s standard treatments for cancer are based on earlier clinical trials. Patients who take part in a clinical trial may receive the standard treatment or be among the first to receive a new treatment.   Patients who take part in clinical trials also help improve the way cancer will be treated in the future. Even when clinical trials do not lead to effective new treatments, they often answer important questions and help move research forward.
                
                
                    Patients can enter clinical trials before, during, or after starting their cancer treatment.
                    Some clinical trials only include patients who have not yet received treatment. Other trials test treatments for patients whose cancer has not gotten better. There are also clinical trials that test new ways to stop cancer from recurring (coming back) or reduce the side effects of cancer treatment.   Clinical trials are taking place in many parts of the country. See the Treatment Options section that follows for links to current treatment clinical trials. These have been retrieved from NCI&apos;s listing of clinical trials.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
