<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000114" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/521/acute-febrile-neutrophilic-dermatosis">
<Focus>Acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0085077</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Sweet syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>SS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Neutrophilic dermatosis, acute febrile</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Gomm Button disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000114-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis - also known as Sweet syndrome - is a skin condition marked by fever, inflammation of the joints (arthritis), and painful skin lesions that appear mainly on the face, neck, back and arms. Although middle-aged women are most likely to develop this condition, it may also affect men, older adults and even infants. The exact cause of acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis often isn&apos;t known. In some people, it&apos;s triggered by an infection, illness or certain medications. This condition can also occur with some types of cancer and other serious health problems. Most often, it isn&apos;t serious and will clear on its own in a few months. Healing is much more rapid, however, with treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000114-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis? The most obvious signs of acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis are distinctive skin lesions that usually develop according to a specific pattern. Typically, a series of small red bumps appear suddenly on the back, neck, arms and face, often after a fever or upper respiratory infection. The bumps grow quickly in size, spreading into clusters called plaques that may be a centimeter in diameter or larger. The eruptions are tender or painful and may develop blisters, pustules or even ulcers. Lesions may persist for weeks to months and then disappear on their own, without medication. With medical treatment, the skin lesions may resolve in just a few days. Other signs and symptoms of acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis may include: Moderate to high fever Pink eye (conjunctivitis) or sore eyes Tiredness Aching joints and headache Mouth ulcers The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of temperature regulation 90% Arthralgia 90% Hypermelanotic macule 90% Leukocytosis 90% Migraine 90% Myalgia 90% Skin rash 90% Skin ulcer 90% Splenomegaly 90% Hyperkeratosis 50% Abnormal blistering of the skin 7.5% Abnormality of the oral cavity 7.5% Anemia 7.5% Glomerulopathy 7.5% Hematuria 7.5% Inflammatory abnormality of the eye 7.5% Malabsorption 7.5% Proteinuria 7.5% Pulmonary infiltrates 7.5% Pustule 7.5% Recurrent respiratory infections 7.5% Renal insufficiency 7.5% Thrombocytopenia 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000114-3" qtype="causes">What causes Acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis? In many cases, the cause of acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis is unknown (idiopathic). But sometimes, it can be a sign of an immune system response to one of the following: An upper respiratory tract infection, such as a chest infection or strep throat Blood disorders, especially acute myelogenous leukemia, a cancer of the blood and bone marrow Inflammatory bowel disease, such as ulcerative colitis or Crohn&apos;s disease Bowel or breast cancer Pregnancy Rheumatoid arthritis An injury at the site where the rash appears, such as an insect bite or needle prick Certain medications, including nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000114-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis be treated?  Left untreated, acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis not associated with a more serious condition may disappear on its own within one to three months. Medications can improve skin lesions and associated symptoms in just two or three days, with the worst of the lesions disappearing within one to four weeks. Doctors usually prescribe systemic corticosteroids (prednisone or prednisolone) to treat this condition. These oral anti-inflammatory medications reduce redness, itching, swelling and allergic reactions.  In the pediatric population, long-term use of corticosteroids can cause problems with linear growth, blood pressure, and blood glucose levels. Children may also have social sequelae associated with their use. Therefore, attempts are usually made to treat children with steroid-sparing drugs. Other treatment options include indomethacin, colchicine, potassium iodide, dapsone, cyclosporine, etretinate, pentoxifylline, clofazimine, doxycycline, metronidazole, isotretinoin, methotrexate, cyclophosphamide, chlorambucil, and interferon alpha, all of which have shown some success in the resolution of symtpoms.   With or without treatment, the lesions rarely leave a mark or scar when they eventually disappear. Even after the lesions have resolved, treatment may continue, as recurrence of the condition is common. If an underlying cause can be identified, it should be treated (i.e. resection of solid tumors, treatment of infections, and discontinuation of causative medication). Successful therapy of the underlying disorder may promote resolution of acute febrile neutrophilic dermatosis and prevent recurrences.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
