<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000589" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4552/autosomal-recessive-pseudohypoaldosteronism-type-1">
<Focus>Autosomal recessive pseudohypoaldosteronism type 1</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0033805</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pseudohypoaldosteronism type 1 autosomal recessive</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pseudohypoaldosteronism type 1, recessive</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Generalized pseudohypoaldosteronism type 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Generalized PHA1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>PHA1B</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000589-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Autosomal recessive pseudohypoaldosteronism type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Autosomal recessive pseudohypoaldosteronism type 1 is a disorder of electrolyte metabolism characterized by excess loss of salt in the urine and high concentrations of sodium in sweat, stool, and saliva. The disorder involves multiple organ systems and is especially dangerous in the newborn period. Laboratory tests may show hyponatremia, hyperkalemia, and increased plasma renin activity with high levels of aldosterone in the blood. Respiratory tract infections are common in affected children. Treatment involves aggressive salt replacement and control of hyperkalemia. The disorder may become less severe with age. Autosomal recessive pseudohypoaldosteronism type 1 (PHA1B) is transmitted in an autosomal recessive manner and is caused by mutations in the genes coding for the subunits of the amiloride-sensitive sodium channel (SCNN1A, SCNN1B and SCNN1G).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000589-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Autosomal recessive pseudohypoaldosteronism type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Autosomal recessive pseudohypoaldosteronism type 1? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Autosomal recessive pseudohypoaldosteronism type 1. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal recessive inheritance - Dehydration - Diarrhea - Failure to thrive - Feeding difficulties in infancy - Hyperactive renin-angiotensin system - Hyperaldosteronism - Hyperkalemia - Hyponatremia - Hypotension - Infantile onset - Metabolic acidosis - Pseudohypoaldosteronism - Recurrent respiratory infections - Renal salt wasting - Vomiting - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
