<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000693" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4767/benign-schwannoma">
<Focus>Benign schwannoma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0027809</CUI>
			<CUI>C0854906</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Neurilemoma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Neurilemmoma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Neurolemmoma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Peripheral fibroblastoma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Benign peripheral nerve sheath tumor</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000693-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Benign schwannoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Schwannomas are tumors of the tissue that covers the nerves (nerve sheath). These tumors develop from a type of cell called a Schwann cell, which gives these tumors their name. They are usually benign (not cancerous). Although schwannomas can arise from any nerve in the body, the most common areas include the nerves of the head and neck and those involved with moving the arms and legs. Common symptoms include a slow-growing mass and Tinel&apos;s sign (an electric-like shock when the affected area is touched). The cause of schwannomas is unknown, but they sometimes occur in people with certain disorders including some types of neurofibromatosis. Benign schwannomas are typically treated with surgery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000693-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Benign schwannoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of schwannomas? Common signs and symptoms of schwannomas include a slow-growing mass and Tinel shock (electric-like shock when affected area is touched). Some people may experience numbness or other neurological symptoms depending on the size and location of the tumor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000693-3" qtype="causes">What causes Benign schwannoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes schwannomas? The cause of schwannomas is unknown. They sometimes occur in people with certain disorders including some types of neurofibromatosis (neurofibromatosis type 2 and schwannomatosis). In these cases, affected people have multiple tumors that are due to changes (mutations) in a gene. For example, neurofibromatosis type 2 is caused by mutations in the NF2 gene and schwannomatosis is caused by mutations in the SMARCB1 gene and the LZTR1 gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000693-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Benign schwannoma inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Are schwannomas inherited? Most schwannomas are not inherited. The vast majority of schwannomas occur by chance (sporadically) and as a single tumor. In these cases, people typically do not have affected family members. Around 5-10% of people develop multiple schwannomas. In these cases, the schwannomas may be due to an inherited condition which can be passed from parent to child. For example, neurofibromatosis type 2 and schwannomatosis are two conditions known to cause multiple schwannomas. Both of these conditions are inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. This means that to be affected, a person only needs a change (mutation) in one copy of the responsible gene in each cell. In some cases, an affected person inherits the mutation from an affected parent. Other cases may result from new (de novo) mutations in the gene. These cases occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family. A person with neurofibromatosis type 2 or schwannomatosis has a 50% chance with each pregnancy of passing along the altered gene to his or her child.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000693-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Benign schwannoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is genetic testing available for schwannomas? Genetic testing is not available for many individuals with schwannomas since most of these tumors occur sporadically (by chance) and are not caused by a genetic mutation. However, genetic testing is an option for people with an inherited condition that predisposes to schwannomas such as certain types of neurofibromatosis (neurofibromatosis type 2 and schwannomatosis). Carrier testing for at-risk relatives and prenatal testing are possible if the disease-causing mutation in the family is known. The Genetic Testing Registry (GTR) is a centralized online resource for information about genetic tests. It provides a list of laboratories performing genetic testing for neurofibromatosis type 2 and schwannomatosis. The intended audience for the GTR is health care providers and researchers. Patients and consumers with specific questions about a genetic test should contact a health care provider or a genetics professional. How are schwannomas diagnosed? In addition to a complete physical exam and medical history, the following tests may be necessary to diagnose a schwannoma: x-ray, ultrasound, and/or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). Some people may also need a biopsy of the tumor to confirm the diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000693-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Benign schwannoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might schwannoma be treated? The best treatment options for schwannoma depends on several factors, including the size and location of the tumor; whether the tumor is benign or malignant (cancerous); and the age and overall health of the affected person. For example, standard treatment for benign schwannomas is surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible. People with malignant schwannomas may also be treated with radiation therapy and/or chemotherapy in addition to surgery.  Because there is a chance that a schwannoma may return following surgery or treatment, regular follow-up with physical examinations and imaging should be discussed with a physician.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
