<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000517" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8702/atypical-hemolytic-uremic-syndrome">
<Focus>Atypical hemolytic uremic syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2931788</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>AHUS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Atypical HUS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>HUS, atypical</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000517-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Atypical hemolytic uremic syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Atypical hemolytic-uremic syndrome (aHUS) is a disease that causes abnormal blood clots to form in small blood vessels in the kidneys. These clots can cause serious medical problems if they restrict or block blood flow, including hemolytic anemia, thrombocytopenia, and kidney failure. It can occur at any age and is often caused by a combination of environmental and genetic factors. Genetic factors involve genes that code for proteins that help control the complement system (part of your bodys immune system). Environmental factors include certain medications (such as anticancer drugs), chronic diseases (e.g., systemic sclerosis and malignant hypertension), viral or bacterial infections, cancers, organ transplantation, and pregnancy.  Most cases are sporadic. Less than 20 percent of all cases have been reported to run in families. When the disorder is familial, it can have an autosomal dominant or an autosomal recessive pattern of inheritance. Atypical hemolytic-uremic syndrome differs from a more common condition called typical hemolytic-uremic syndrome. The two disorders have different causes and different signs and symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000517-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Atypical hemolytic uremic syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Atypical hemolytic uremic syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Atypical hemolytic uremic syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Acute kidney injury - Anuria - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Cognitive impairment - Coma - Decreased serum complement C3 - Decreased serum complement factor B - Decreased serum complement factor H - Decreased serum complement factor I - Diarrhea - Dysphasia - Elevated serum creatinine - Fever - Hemiparesis - Hemolytic-uremic syndrome - Hyperlipidemia - Hypertension - Increased blood urea nitrogen (BUN) - Microangiopathic hemolytic anemia - Purpura - Reticulocytosis - Schistocytosis - Seizures - Thrombocytopenia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000517-3" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Atypical hemolytic uremic syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is genetic testing available for atypical hemolytic-uremic syndrome? GeneTests lists the names of laboratories that are performing genetic testing for atypical hemolytic-uremic syndrome. To view the contact information for the clinical laboratories conducting testing click here and follow the &quot;testing&quot; link pertaining to each gene. Please note:  Most of the laboratories listed through GeneTests do not accept direct contact from patients and their families; therefore, if you are interested in learning more, you will need to work with a health care provider or a genetics professional.  In the Genetic Services section of this letter we provide a list of online resources that can assist you in locating a genetics professional near you.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
