<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000309" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5786/amyotrophic-lateral-sclerosis">
<Focus>Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0002736</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>ALS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lou Gehrig disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis type 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>ALS1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis type 10</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis type 11</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis type 2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis type 3</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis type 4</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000309-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS), also referred to as &quot;Lou Gehrig&apos;s disease,&quot; is a progressive motor neuron disease which leads to problems with muscle control and movement. There are various types of ALS, which are distinguished by their signs and symptoms and their cause. Early symptoms may include muscle twitching, cramping, stiffness, or weakness, eventually followed by slurred speech and difficulty chewing or swallowing (dysphagia). As the disease progresses, individuals become weaker are are eventually wheelchair-dependent. Death often results from respiratory failure within 2 to 10 years after the onset of symptoms. Most affected individuals have a sporadic (not inherited) form of ALS; about 5-10% have a familial (inherited) form of the condition. Familial ALS may caused by mutations in any one of several genes and the pattern of inheritance varies depending on the gene involved. Treatment is generally supportive.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000309-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Degeneration of anterior horn cells - Degeneration of the lateral corticospinal tracts - Fasciculations - Heterogeneous - Hyperreflexia - Muscle cramps - Muscle weakness - Pseudobulbar paralysis - Skeletal muscle atrophy - Sleep apnea - Spasticity - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000309-3" qtype="causes">What causes Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes amyotrophic lateral sclerosis? In approximately 90-95% of cases the cause of amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) is unknown and is sporadic (occurring in individuals with no history of the condition in the family). The remaining 5-10% of cases are genetic (familial), often occurring in individuals with a family history of the condition. Mutations in any of several genes, including the C9orf72, SOD1, TARDBP, FUS, ANG, ALS2, SETX, and VAPB genes, can cause familial ALS and may contribute to the development of sporadic ALS. About 60% of individuals with familial ALS have an identifiable genetic mutation; the genetic cause in the remaining cases is unknown. The genes associated with ALS appear to play a role in how neurons function or are involved in regulating the production of various proteins. Over the years, various types of environmental exposures have been proposed as possible contributors to the cause of ALS, including mercury, manganese, products used in farming (fertilizers, insecticides, herbicides), and physical and dietary factors. Exposures have been suggested as a possible explanation for the increased incidence of ALS in Gulf War veterans. Further investigation is ongoing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000309-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) inherited? About 90-95% percent of cases of ALS are not inherited and occur in individuals with no history of the condition in their family. The remaining 5-10% of cases are familial, and are thought to be caused by mutations in any one of several genes. The inheritance pattern associated with familial ALS varies depending on the disease-causing gene involved. Most familial cases are inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. This means that only one altered (mutated) copy of the disease-causing gene in each cell is sufficient to cause the condition. In most of these cases, an affected individual has one parent with the condition. When an individual with an autosomal dominant form of ALS has children, each child has a 50% (1 in 2) risk to inherited the mutated copy of the gene and be affected. Less frequently, ALS is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. In autosomal recessive inheritance, both copies of the disease-causing gene (typically one copy inherited from each parent) must have a mutation for the individual to be affected. The parents of an individual with an autosomal recessive condition, who presumably each carry one mutated copy of the gene, are referred to as carriers. Carriers typically do not have any signs or symptoms of the condition. When two carriers for the same condition are having children, each child has a 25% (1 in 4) risk to have the condition, a 50% (1 in 2) risk to be a carrier like each parent, and a 25% risk to not have the condition and not be a carrier. Autosomal recessive forms of ALS may be mistaken for non-inherited (sporadic) forms due to having a negative family history of the condition. In rare cases, ALS is inherited in an X-linked dominant manner. This occurs when the disease-causing gene is located on the X chromosome (a sex chromosome). Although females have 2 X chromosomes, having a mutation in one X chromosome is still sufficient to cause the condition. Males who have a mutation (and only one X chromosome) will have the condition. Usually, males with an X-linked dominant form of ALS experience more severe symptoms than females with the same form. Some individuals who do inherit a mutation known to cause ALS never develop signs and symptoms of ALS, although the reason for this is unclear. This phenomenon is referred to as reduced penetrance.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000309-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is genetic testing available for amyotrophic lateral sclerosis? Yes. Clinical genetic testing is currently available for several genes in which mutations are known to cause ALS. Genetic testing on a research basis is also available for select susceptibility genes associated with ALS. You can find laboratories offering clinical and research genetic testing for ALS on a Web site called GeneTests. To see GeneTests&apos; list of the types of ALS for which genetic testing is available, click here. Click on &quot;Testing&quot; next to each type of ALS of interest to see a list of the laboratories that offer clinical testing. Click on &quot;Research&quot; next to each type of ALS of interest to see a list of the laboratories that offer research testing. Please note that most of the laboratories listed through GeneTests do not accept direct contact from patients and their families. Therefore, if you are interested in learning more, you will need to work with a health care provider or a genetics professional.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000309-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) be treated? The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has approved the first drug treatment for the diseaseriluzole (Rilutek). Riluzole is believed to reduce damage to motor neurons by decreasing the release of glutamate. Clinical trials with ALS patients showed that riluzole prolongs survival by several months, mainly in those with difficulty swallowing. The drug also extends the time before a patient needs ventilation support. Riluzole does not reverse the damage already done to motor neurons, and patients taking the drug must be monitored for liver damage and other possible side effects. Other treatments for ALS are designed to relieve symptoms and improve the quality of life for patients (palliative care). This supportive care is typically provided by multidisciplinary teams of health care professionals such as physicians; pharmacists; physical, occupational, and speech therapists; nutritionists; social workers; and home care and hospice nurses. Working with patients and caregivers, these teams can design an individualized plan of medical and physical therapy and provide special equipment aimed at keeping patients as mobile and comfortable as possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
