<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000530" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10310/autoimmune-atrophic-gastritis">
<Focus>Autoimmune atrophic gastritis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0443146</CUI>
			<CUI>C0017154</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000530-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Autoimmune atrophic gastritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Autoimmune atrophic gastritis is an autoimmune disorder in which the immune system mistakenly attacks the healthy cells of the stomach lining. Overtime, this can wear away the stomach&apos;s protective barrier and interfere with the absorption of several key vitamins (i.e. vitamin B12, iron, folate). In some cases, autoimmune atrophic gastritis does not cause any obvious signs and symptoms. However, some people may experience nausea, vomiting, a feeling of fullness in the upper abdomen after eating, abdominal pain and/or vitamin deficiencies. The condition is associated with an increased risk of pernicious anemia, gastric polyps and gastric adenocarcinoma. Although the underlying genetic cause has not been identified, studies suggest that the condition may be inherited in an autosomal dominant manner in some families. Treatment is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person, but may include vitamin B12 injections and endoscopic surveillance.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000530-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Autoimmune atrophic gastritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of autoimmune atrophic gastritis? In some cases, autoimmune atrophic gastritis does not cause any obvious signs and symptoms. However, some people may experience nausea, vomiting, a feeling of fullness in the upper abdomen after eating, or abdominal pain. It is often associated with impaired absorption of vitamin B12 and possibly other vitamin deficiencies (such as folate and iron). People with vitamin B12 deficiency are at risk for pernicious anemia, a condition in which the body does not have enough healthy red blood cells. Autoimmune atrophic gastritis is considered a &quot;precancerous&quot; condition and it may be responsible for the development of gastric adenocarcinoma or carcinoids.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000530-3" qtype="causes">What causes Autoimmune atrophic gastritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes autoimmune atrophic gastritis? Autoimmune atrophic gastritis is considered an autoimmune disorder. In people who are affected by this condition, the immune system mistakenly attacks the healthy cells of the stomach lining. Overtime, this can wear away the stomach&apos;s protective barrier and interfere with the absorption of several key vitamins (i.e. vitamin B12, iron, folate). This leads to the signs and symptoms of autoimmune atrophic gastritis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000530-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Autoimmune atrophic gastritis inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is autoimmune atrophic gastritis inherited? In some cases, more than one family member can be affected by autoimmune atrophic gastritis. Although the underlying genetic cause has not been identified, studies suggest that the condition may be inherited in an autosomal dominant manner in these families. In autosomal dominant conditions, an affected person only needs a change (mutation) in one copy of the responsible gene in each cell. In some cases, an affected person inherits the mutation from an affected parent. Other cases may result from new (de novo) mutations in the gene. These cases occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family. A person with the condition has a 50% chance with each pregnancy of passing along the altered gene to his or her child.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000530-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Autoimmune atrophic gastritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is autoimmune atrophic gastritis diagnosed? A diagnosis of autoimmune atrophic gastritis is generally not suspected until characteristic signs and symptoms are present. Additional testing can then be ordered to confirm the diagnosis. This generally includes: A biopsy of the affected tissue obtained through endoscopy Blood work that demonstrates autoantibodies against certain cells of the stomach</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000530-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Autoimmune atrophic gastritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might autoimmune atrophic gastritis be treated? The treatment of autoimmune atrophic gastritis is generally focused on preventing and/or alleviating signs and symptoms of the condition. For example, management is focused on preventing vitamin B12, folate and iron deficiencies in the early stages of the condition. With adequate supplementation of these vitamins and minerals, anemia and other health problems may be avoided. If pernicious anemia is already present at the time of diagnosis, replacement of vitamin B12 is generally recommended via injections. In some cases, endoscopic surveillance may also be recommended due to the increased risk of certain types of cancer. While surgery may be appropriate for the treatment of related cancers, we are not aware of surgical management options or recommendations otherwise. Symptoms of gastritis in general may be managed with prescription or over-the-counter medications (besides antibiotics for H. pylori-associated gastritis) that block or reduce acid production and promote healing. Proton pump inhibitors reduce acid by blocking the action of the parts of cells that produce acid. Examples may include omeprazole, lansoprazole, rabeprazole, esomeprazole, dexlansoprazole and pantoprazole. Histamine (H-2) blockers reduce the amount of acid released into the digestive tract, which relieves gastritis pain and promotes healing. Examples include ranitidine, famotidine, cimetidine and nizatidine. Antacids that neutralize stomach acid and provide pain relief may also be used. We are not aware of dietary guidelines or recommendations for autoimmune atrophic gastritis. Much of the literature on dietary management of gastritis is specific to H. Pylori-associated gastritis. However, people with gastritis in general may find some relief by eating smaller, more-frequent meals; avoiding irritating foods; avoiding alcohol; switching pain relievers; and managing stress.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
