<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000887" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12958/c1q-deficiency">
<Focus>C1q deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3150902</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000887-1" qtype="information">What is (are) C1q deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>C1q deficiency is a rare disorder associated with recurrent skin lesions, chronic infections, systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) or SLE-like diseases. It has also been associated with a kidney disease known as mesangial proliferative glomerulonephritis. C1q is a protein and together with other proteins, C1r and C1s, it forms the C1 complex. This complex is important for the activation of the complement system (a group of proteins that work with the immune system). It also disposes cells that are dead. C1q deficiency presents in 2 different forms, absent C1q protein or abnormal C1q protein. Symptoms include infections (ear infections (otitis media), meningitis, urinary tract infections, oral infections); skin lesions (small blisters (vesicles), dark patches, and atrophic areas) that get worse upon light exposure; cataracts; loss of eyelashes, eyebrows, and scalp hair; blood in urine; and glomerulonephritis. About 93% of cases are associated with systemic lupus erythematosus. It can be caused by mutations in the C1QA, C1QB or C1QC genes and is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern. Treatment depends on the symptoms. Recently, it was shown that C1q production can be restored by allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation, a  procedure in which a person receives blood-forming stem cells (cells from which all blood cells develop) from a genetically similar, but not identical donor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000887-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of C1q deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of C1q deficiency? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for C1q deficiency. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis 7.5% Systemic lupus erythematosus 7.5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Decreased serum complement factor I - Recurrent infections - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
