<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000370" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9518/ankylosing-spondylitis">
<Focus>Ankylosing spondylitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0038013</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Ankylosing spondyloarthritis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Bechterew syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Marie-Strumpell spondylitis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000370-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ankylosing spondylitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ankylosing spondylitis (AS) is a type of chronic, inflammatory arthritis that mainly affects the spine. It usually begins with inflammation of the joints between the pelvic bones and spine, gradually spreading to the joints between the vertebrae. Signs and symptoms usually begin in adolescence or early adulthood and may include back pain and stiffness. Back movement gradually becomes more limited as the vertebrae fuse together. The condition may also affect the shoulders; ribs; hips; knees; and feet; as well as the eyes; bowel; and very rarely, the heart and lungs. AS is likely caused by a combination of genetic and environmental factors; variations in several genes are thought to affect the risk to develop AS. In most cases, treatment involves exercise and medications to relieve pain and inflammation.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000370-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ankylosing spondylitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Ankylosing spondylitis? Ankylosing spondylitis (AS) primarily affects the spine, but may affect other parts of the body too. Signs and symptoms usually begin in adolescence or early adulthood and include back pain and stiffness. Back movement gradually becomes more limited over time as the vertebrae fuse together. Many affected people have mild back pain that comes and goes; others have severe, chronic pain. In very severe cases, the rib cage may become stiffened, making it difficult to breathe deeply. In some people, the condition involves other areas of the body, such as the shoulders, hips, knees, and/or the small joints of the hands and feet. It may affect various places where tendons and ligaments attach to the bones. Sometimes it can affect other organs including the eyes, and very rarely, the heart and lungs. Episodes of eye inflammation may cause eye pain and increased sensitivity to light (photophobia). Neurological complications of AS may include an inability to control urination and bowel movements (incontinence), and the absence of normal reflexes in the ankles due to pressure on the lower portion of the spinal cord (cauda equina). The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Ankylosing spondylitis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 90% Abnormality of the oral cavity 90% Abnormality of the sacroiliac joint 90% Arthralgia 90% Arthritis 90% Diarrhea 90% Enthesitis 90% Inflammatory abnormality of the eye 90% Joint swelling 90% Spinal rigidity 90% Abnormality of the thorax 50% Myalgia 50% Respiratory insufficiency 50% Abdominal pain 7.5% Abnormal tendon morphology 7.5% Abnormality of temperature regulation 7.5% Abnormality of the aortic valve 7.5% Abnormality of the pericardium 7.5% Abnormality of the pleura 7.5% Anorexia 7.5% Arrhythmia 7.5% Autoimmunity 7.5% Cartilage destruction 7.5% Hematuria 7.5% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 7.5% Hyperkeratosis 7.5% Nephrolithiasis 7.5% Nephropathy 7.5% Nephrotic syndrome 7.5% Osteomyelitis 7.5% Proteinuria 7.5% Pulmonary fibrosis 7.5% Pustule 7.5% Recurrent fractures 7.5% Recurrent urinary tract infections 7.5% Renal insufficiency 7.5% Skin rash 7.5% Skin ulcer 7.5% Anterior uveitis - Aortic regurgitation - Back pain - Hip osteoarthritis - Inflammation of the large intestine - Kyphosis - Multifactorial inheritance - Psoriasis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000370-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Ankylosing spondylitis inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is ankylosing spondylitis inherited? Although ankylosing spondylitis (AS) can affect more than one person in a family, it is not a purely genetic disease. While genes seem to play a role, the exact cause of AS is not known. It is considered to be multifactorial, which means that multiple genetic and environmental factors likely interact to affect a person&apos;s risk to develop AS. Most of these factors have not been identified. Inheriting a genetic variation that has been associated with AS does not mean a person will develop AS. Currently, it is not possible to predict the exact likelihood that the children of an affected person will develop the disease. You can find more information about the genetics of AS from Genetics Home Reference, the U.S National Library of Medicine&apos;s Web site for consumer information about genetic conditions and the genes or chromosomes related to those conditions.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000370-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Ankylosing spondylitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might ankylosing spondylitis be treated? The main goal of treatment for people with ankylosing spondylitis (AS) is to maximize long-term quality of life. This may involve easing symptoms of pain and stiffness; retaining function; preventing complications (such as contractures); and minimizing the effects of associated conditions. Education, exercise, and medications are all very important in managing AS. An exercise program is recommended for all affected people, and some may need individual physical therapy. Affected people are encouraged to speak with their health care provider before instituting any changes to an exercise regime. Video demonstrations of exercises tailored for ankylosing spondylitis are available for viewing through the National Ankylosing Spondylitis Society in the UK. Medications may include nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs); pain relievers; sulfasalazine; and anti-tumor necrosis factor drugs. Steroid injections may be helpful for some people. Most people don&apos;t need surgery, but it may be indicated when there is severe, persistent pain or severe limitation in mobility and quality of life. Smoking creates additional problems for people with AS, so affected people who smoke should quit. More detailed information about the treatment of ankylosing spondylitis is available on Medscape&apos;s Web site. You may need to register to view the article, but registration is free.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
