<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000578" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12448/autosomal-recessive-charcot-marie-tooth-disease-with-hoarseness">
<Focus>Autosomal recessive Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease with hoarseness</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0007959</CUI>
			<CUI>C0019825</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>ARCMT2K</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Autosomal recessive axonal CMT4C4</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Autosomal recessive axonal Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2K</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease, axonal, with vocal cord paresis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>CHARCOT-MARIE-TOOTH NEUROPATHY, AXONAL, WITH VOCAL CORD PARESIS, AUTOSOMAL RECESSIVE</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Autosomal recessive axonal Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000578-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Autosomal recessive Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease with hoarseness ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Autosomal recessive Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease with hoarseness? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Autosomal recessive Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease with hoarseness. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Onion bulb formation 7.5% Areflexia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Axonal degeneration/regeneration - Decreased motor nerve conduction velocity - Decreased number of peripheral myelinated nerve fibers - Distal amyotrophy - Distal muscle weakness - Distal sensory impairment - Flexion contracture - Neonatal onset - Pes cavus - Spinal deformities - Split hand - Vocal cord paresis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
