<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000840" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10147/branchiootorenal-syndrome">
<Focus>Branchiootorenal syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265234</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Branchiootorenal dysplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Melnick-Fraser syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Branchio oto renal syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>BOR syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000840-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Branchiootorenal syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Branchiootorenal syndrome is characterized by birth defects or anomalies of tissues in the neck, malformations of the external ear, hearing loss, and kidney malformations. Symptom and symptom severity can vary greatly from person to person. It can be caused by mutations in the EYA1, SIX1, or SIX5 genes. It is passed through families in an autosomal dominant fashion. Treatment may include surgery to remove the anomalies of the neck (i.e., branchial fistulae or cysts), careful assessment and management of hearing loss, and follow-up by a kidney specialist (nephrologist). In some cases dialysis or kidney transplant may be required.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000840-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Branchiootorenal syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Branchiootorenal syndrome? Signs and symptoms of branchiootorenal syndrome can vary greatly from person to person and even between people within the same family. Hearing loss is the most common symptom and is shared by approximately 90% of people with this syndrome. Hearing loss may be conductive, sensorineural, or a combination of both. Other common signs and symptoms include branchial cleft cysts, branchial fistulae, outer, middle, and inner ear malformations, and kidney malformations. Specifically mutations in the EYA1 or SIX1 genes can be associated with kidney malformations. You can find more details regarding the signs and symptoms of branchiootorenal syndrome by visiting the Genetic Home Reference Web site at the following link: http://ghr.nlm.nih.gov/condition=branchiootorenalsyndrome The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Branchiootorenal syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Hearing impairment 90% Preauricular pit 75% Abnormality of the inner ear 50% Abnormality of the middle ear 50% External ear malformation 50% Mixed hearing impairment 50% Preauricular skin tag 50% Renal hypoplasia/aplasia 50% Cupped ear 45% Microtia 45% Stenosis of the external auditory canal 30% Lacrimal duct aplasia 25% Lacrimal duct stenosis 25% Facial palsy 10% Atresia of the external auditory canal 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Lacrimation abnormality 7.5% Multicystic kidney dysplasia 7.5% Renal insufficiency 7.5% Vesicoureteral reflux 7.5% Abnormality of the cerebrum - Abnormality of the renal collecting system - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Bifid uvula - Branchial cyst - Branchial fistula - Cholesteatoma - Congenital hip dislocation - Dilatated internal auditory canal - Euthyroid goiter - Gustatory lacrimation - Heterogeneous - High palate - Hypoplasia of the cochlea - Incomplete partition of the cochlea type II - Incomplete penetrance - Intestinal malrotation - Long face - Microdontia - Narrow face - Overbite - Polycystic kidney dysplasia - Renal agenesis - Renal dysplasia - Renal malrotation - Renal steatosis - Variable expressivity - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000840-3" qtype="causes">What causes Branchiootorenal syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes branchiootorenal syndrome? Mutations in the genes, EYA1, SIX1, and SIX5, are known to cause branchiootorenal syndrome. About 40 percent of people with this condition have a mutation in the EYA1 gene. SIX1 and SIX5 mutations are much less common causes of the disorder. There are likely other genes that have not yet been identified that when mutated can cause this syndrome as well.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000840-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Branchiootorenal syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is branchiootorenal syndrome inherited? Branchiootorenal syndrome may be inherited or occur sporadically. The inheritance pattern of branchiootorenal syndrome is autosomal dominant. Autosomal dominant inheritance is when one mutated copy of the gene that causes a disorder in each cell is needed for a person to be affected. Autosomal dominant conditions may occur for the first time in a person in a family due to a spontaneous gene mutation, or these conditions may be inherited from an affected parent. When a person with an autosomal dominant disorder has a child, there is a 50% chance that their child will inherit the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000840-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Branchiootorenal syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might branchiootorenal syndrome be treated? Hereditary hearing loss conditions, in general, tend to be managed by a team that includes an otolaryngologist, an audiologist, a clinical geneticist, a pediatrician, sometimes an educator of the Deaf, a neurologist, and in case of branchiootorenal syndrome, a nephrologist (kidney doctor). Treatment of hearing loss may include determining which aids would be most helpful, for example hearing aids or vibrotactile devices; cochlear implantation may be considered in children over age 12 months with severe-to-profound hearing loss. Early hearing intervention through amplification, surgery, or cochlear implantation may be recommended for children who are at risk to lose their hearing before they learn to speak. People with hereditary hearing loss often require regular follow-up with a hearing specialist such as an audiologist to monitor stability or progression of the hearing loss. Treatment of branchial fistulae or cysts may require surgery. For people with branchiootorenal syndrome and severe kidney malformations or complications, dialysis or kidney transplant may be required.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
