<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000614" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/812/bangstad-syndrome">
<Focus>Bangstad syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0342284</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Bird-headed dwarfism with progressive ataxia, insulin-resistant diabetes, goiter and primary gonadal insufficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dwarfism</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000614-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Bangstad syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Bangstad syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Bangstad syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the parathyroid gland 90% Abnormality of the teeth 90% Abnormality of the testis 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Convex nasal ridge 90% Deeply set eye 90% Deviation of finger 90% EEG abnormality 90% Hypercortisolism 90% Hyperinsulinemia 90% Hypothyroidism 90% Incoordination 90% Intrauterine growth retardation 90% Microcephaly 90% Polycystic ovaries 90% Seizures 90% Short stature 90% Sloping forehead 90% Type I diabetes mellitus 90% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Brain very small - Cerebral hypoplasia - Goiter - Insulin-resistant diabetes mellitus - Intellectual disability - Large eyes - Narrow face - Pancytopenia - Primary gonadal insufficiency - Progressive cerebellar ataxia - Retrognathia - Severe short stature - Small for gestational age - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
