<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000496" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12860/ataxia-with-oculomotor-apraxia-type-2">
<Focus>Ataxia with Oculomotor Apraxia Type 2</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0271270</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Spinocerebellar ataxia with axonal neuropathy type 2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>SCAN2</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000496-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ataxia with Oculomotor Apraxia Type 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Ataxia with Oculomotor Apraxia Type 2? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Ataxia with Oculomotor Apraxia Type 2. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Impaired distal tactile sensation 57% Tremor 57% Strabismus 30% Conjunctival telangiectasia 5% Areflexia 10/10 Cerebellar atrophy 8/8 Distal amyotrophy 10/10 Distal muscle weakness 10/10 Dysarthria 10/10 Dysphagia 10/10 Elevated alpha-fetoprotein 6/6 Gait ataxia 10/10 Impaired proprioception 10/10 Peripheral axonal neuropathy 8/8 Nystagmus 8/10 Pes cavus 12/18 Oculomotor apraxia 10/18 Scoliosis 7/18 Dystonia 5/18 Head tremor 5/19 Chorea 4/18 Hyporeflexia 4/18 Abnormal pyramidal signs - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Decreased motor nerve conduction velocity - Elevated serum creatine phosphokinase - Gaze-evoked nystagmus - Impaired distal vibration sensation - Increased antibody level in blood - Limb ataxia - Polyneuropathy - Pontocerebellar atrophy - Progressive - Progressive gait ataxia - Saccadic smooth pursuit - Variable expressivity - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
