<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000946" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9146/cardiofaciocutaneous-syndrome">
<Focus>Cardiofaciocutaneous syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1275081</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>CFC syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital heart defects characteristic facial appearance ectodermal abnormalities and growth failure</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cardio-facio-cutaneous syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000946-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Cardiofaciocutaneous syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cardiofaciocutaneous (CFC) syndrome is a disorder that affects many parts of the body, particularly the heart (cardio-), face (facio-), and the skin and hair (cutaneous). People with this condition also have developmental delay and intellectual disability, usually ranging from moderate to severe. The signs and symptoms of cardiofaciocutaneous syndrome overlap significantly with those of two other genetic conditions, Costello syndrome and Noonan syndrome. The three syndromes are part of a group of related conditions called the RASopathies and  they are distinguished by their genetic cause and specific patterns of signs and symptoms; however, it can be difficult to tell these conditions apart in infancy. The CFC syndroeme is caused by mutations in the BRAF (75%-80% of the cases), MAP2K1,  MAP2K2 or KRAS gene (in fewer than 5% of the cases). CFC syndrome is an autosomal dominant condition, however, most cases have resulted from new gene mutations and have occurred in people with no history of the disorder in their family. Treatment is symptomatic and may include surgery to correct the heart problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000946-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Cardiofaciocutaneous syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Cardiofaciocutaneous syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Cardiofaciocutaneous syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the heart valves 90% Abnormality of the pulmonary artery 90% Anteverted nares 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the eyebrow 90% Atria septal defect 90% Coarse facial features 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Dry skin 90% Fine hair 90% Full cheeks 90% Hypertrichosis 90% Long face 90% Long palpebral fissure 90% Muscular hypotonia 90% Neurological speech impairment 90% Palmoplantar keratoderma 90% Short stature 90% Thickened helices 90% Underdeveloped supraorbital ridges 90% Abnormality of the eyelashes 50% Abnormality of the fingernails 50% Abnormality of the ulna 50% Cafe-au-lait spot 50% Cryptorchidism 50% Deep palmar crease 50% Depressed nasal bridge 50% EEG abnormality 50% Epicanthus 50% Frontal bossing 50% Generalized hyperpigmentation 50% High forehead 50% Hyperextensible skin 50% Hypertelorism 50% Hypoplasia of the zygomatic bone 50% Ichthyosis 50% Long philtrum 50% Low posterior hairline 50% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 50% Macrocephaly 50% Macrotia 50% Myopia 50% Narrow forehead 50% Nystagmus 50% Pectus excavatum 50% Premature birth 50% Ptosis 50% Scoliosis 50% Short neck 50% Short nose 50% Slow-growing hair 50% Strabismus 50% Webbed neck 50% Abnormality of the abdominal organs 7.5% Abnormality of the upper urinary tract 7.5% Cerebral cortical atrophy 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Cubitus valgus 7.5% Cutis laxa 7.5% Genu valgum 7.5% Hydrocephalus 7.5% Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy 7.5% Lymphedema 7.5% Optic atrophy 7.5% Peripheral axonal neuropathy 5% Absent eyebrow - Absent eyelashes - Anterior creases of earlobe - Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum - Atopic dermatitis - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Bulbous nose - Cavernous hemangioma - Clinodactyly of the 5th finger - Congenital onset - Constipation - Curly hair - Deep philtrum - Delayed skeletal maturation - Dental malocclusion - Dolichocephaly - Failure to thrive - Feeding difficulties in infancy - Gastroesophageal reflux - Hearing impairment - High palate - Hydronephrosis - Hyperextensibility of the finger joints - Hyperkeratosis - Hypertonia - Hypoplasia of the frontal lobes - Intellectual disability - Low-set ears - Multiple lentigines - Multiple palmar creases - Multiple plantar creases - Oculomotor apraxia - Open bite - Open mouth - Optic nerve dysplasia - Osteopenia - Pectus carinatum - Polyhydramnios - Posteriorly rotated ears - Progressive visual loss - Prominent forehead - Proptosis - Pulmonic stenosis - Relative macrocephaly - Seizures - Sparse hair - Splenomegaly - Submucous cleft hard palate - Tongue thrusting - Vomiting - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000946-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Cardiofaciocutaneous syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might the the itching associated with cardiofaciocutaneous syndrome be treated? Xerosis (dry skin) and pruritus (itching) associated with cardiofaciocutaneous syndrome may be relieved by increasing the amount of moisture in the air or by using hydrating lotions. If signs of infection develop, treatment with antibiotics may be necessary.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
