<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000266" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8644/alveolar-capillary-dysplasia">
<Focus>Alveolar capillary dysplasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2677362</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Congenital alveolar capillary dysplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pulmonary hypertension, familial persistent of the newborn</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Familial persistent pulmonary hypertension of the newborn</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Alveolar capillary dysplasia with pulmonary venous misalignment</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Alveolar capillary dysplasia with misalignment of pulmonary veins</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000266-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Alveolar capillary dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Alveolar capillary dysplasia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Alveolar capillary dysplasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Pulmonary hypertension 90% Respiratory insufficiency 90% Hypoplastic left heart 50% Intestinal malrotation 50% Patent ductus arteriosus 50% Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 7.5% Abnormality of the aorta 7.5% Abnormality of the aortic valve 7.5% Abnormality of the gallbladder 7.5% Abnormality of the pulmonary valve 7.5% Abnormality of the spleen 7.5% Abnormality of the upper urinary tract 7.5% Aganglionic megacolon 7.5% Annular pancreas 7.5% Atria septal defect 7.5% Complete atrioventricular canal defect 7.5% Duodenal stenosis 7.5% Single umbilical artery 7.5% Tetralogy of Fallot 7.5% Tracheoesophageal fistula 7.5% Urogenital fistula 7.5% Ventricular septal defect 7.5% Abnormal lung lobation - Abnormality of the pulmonary veins - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Duodenal atresia - Hydronephrosis - Hydroureter - Hypertension - Meckel diverticulum - Neonatal death - Polyhydramnios - Pulmonary insufficiency - Right-to-left shunt - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
