<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000295" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/429/amniotic-band-syndrome">
<Focus>Amniotic band syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0002636</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Amniotic bands sequence</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Familial amniotic bands</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Streeter anomaly</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital constricting bands</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000295-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Amniotic band syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Amniotic band syndrome refers to a condition in which bands extend from (and originating from) the inner lining of the amnion. The amnion is the sac that surrounds the baby in the womb. As the baby develops in the womb, its extremities may become entangled in the amniotic band resulting in constriction or even amputation. When this happens the baby is said to have amniotic band syndrome. Amniotic bands are thought to happen sporadically or in association with trauma to the abdomen. It can be a complication after an amniocentesis and/or it can indicate early rupture of the amniotic sac.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000295-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Amniotic band syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Amniotic band syndrome? The symptoms of amniotic band syndrome depend on the severity and location of the constrictions. The mildest constrictions affect only the superficial skin and may not require treatment. Deeper constrictions may block lymphatic vessels, impair blood flow, and require immediate surgical care. When the bands affect the limbs, the lower part of the limbs are most often involved, especially the middle, long, and index fingers of the hand. When the feet are involved, the bands most commonly affect the big toe. Pressure from the bands may result in additional abnormalities, such as underdevelopment of a limb, bone abnormalities, amputations, leg-length discrepancy, and club feet. Constriction bands across the head and face may lead to facial clefts. Severe clefts affecting vital organs are often life-threatening. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Amniotic band syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Amniotic constriction ring 90% Finger syndactyly 90% Split hand 90% Talipes 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the lungs 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the radius 50% Lymphedema 50% Oligohydramnios 50% Scoliosis 50% Abnormal lung lobation - Abnormality of the rib cage - Bladder exstrophy - Cleft eyelid - Cleft palate - Cleft upper lip - Ectopia cordis - Encephalocele - Facial cleft - Gastroschisis - Hand polydactyly - Omphalocele - Sporadic - Syndactyly - Talipes equinovarus - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000295-3" qtype="causes">What causes Amniotic band syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes amniotic bands? Amniotic bands are caused by damage to a part of the placenta called the amnion. Damage to the amnion may produce fiber-like bands that can trap parts of the developing baby.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000295-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Amniotic band syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is amniotic band syndrome diagnosed? The earliest reported detection of an amniotic band is at 12 weeks gestation, by vaginal ultrasound. On ultrasound the bands appear as thin, mobile lines, which may be seen attached to or around the baby. However these bands may be difficult to detect by ultrasound, and are more often diagnosed by the results of the fusion, such as missing or deformed limbs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000295-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Amniotic band syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might amniotic band syndrome be treated? Mild cases may not require treatment, however all bands need monitoring as growth occurs to watch for progressive constriction and swelling. Other constrictions may require surgical management; surgical options will vary depending on the abnormality. People with amniotic band syndrome who have amputations may benefit from the use of prosthetics.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
