<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000254" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5784/alpha-1-antitrypsin-deficiency">
<Focus>Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0221757</CUI>
			<CUI>C3501835</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>AAT deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>A1AT deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>AATD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Alpha 1 antitrypsin deficiency</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000254-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency (AATD) is a disorder that causes a deficiency or absence of the alpha-1 antitrypsin (AAT) protein in the blood. AAT is made in the liver and sent through the bloodstream to the lungs, to protect the lungs from damage. Having low levels of ATT (or no ATT) can allow the lungs to become damaged, making breathing hard. Age of onset and severity of AATD can vary based on how much ATT an affected person is missing. In adults, symptoms may include shortness of breath; reduced ability to exercise; wheezing; respiratory infections; fatigue; vision problems; and weight loss. Some people have chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) or asthma. Liver disease (cirrhosis) may occur in affected children or adults. Rarely, AATD can cause a skin condition called panniculitis. AATD is caused by mutations in the SERPINA1 gene and is inherited in a codominant manner. Treatment is based on each person&apos;s symptoms and may include bronchodilators; antibiotics for upper respiratory tract infections; intravenous therapy of AAT; and/or lung transplantation in severe cases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000254-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Emphysema 90% Hepatic failure 90% Hepatomegaly 50% Nephrotic syndrome 7.5% Cirrhosis 5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease - Elevated hepatic transaminases - Hepatocellular carcinoma - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000254-3" qtype="causes">What causes Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency? Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency (AATD) is caused by mutations in the SERPINA1 gene. This gene gives the body instructions to make a protein called alpha-1 antitrypsin (AAT), which protects the body from an enzyme called neutrophil elastase. Neutrophil elastase helps the body fight infections, but it can also attack healthy tissues (especially the lungs) if not controlled by AAT. Mutations that cause AAT can cause a deficiency or absence of AAT, or a form of AAT that does not work well. This allows neutrophil elastase to destroy lung tissue, causing lung disease. In addition, abnormal AAT can build up in the liver and cause damage to the liver. The severity of AATD may also be worsened by environmental factors such as exposure to tobacco smoke, dust, and chemicals.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000254-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency diagnosed? Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency (AATD) may first be suspected in people with evidence of liver disease at any age, or lung disease (such as emphysema), especially when there is no obvious cause or it is diagnosed at a younger age. Confirming the diagnosis involves a blood test showing a low serum concentration of the alpha-1 antitrypsin (AAT) protein, and either: detecting a functionally deficient AAT protein variant by isoelectric focusing (a method for detecting mutations); or detecting SERPINA1 gene mutations on both copies of the gene with molecular genetic testing. (This confirms the diagnosis when the above-mentioned tests are not performed or their results are not in agreement.) Specialists involved in the diagnosis may include primary care doctors, pulmonologists (lung specialists), and/or hepatologists (liver specialists).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000254-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency be treated? Treatment of alpha-1 antitrypsin deficiency (AATD) depends on the symptoms and severity in each person. COPD and other related lung diseases are typically treated with standard therapy. Bronchodilators and inhaled steroids can help open the airways and make breathing easier. Intravenous augmentation therapy (regular infusion of purified, human AAT to increase AAT concentrations) has been recommended for people with established fixed airflow obstruction (determined by a specific lung function test). This therapy raises the level of the AAT protein in the blood and lungs. Lung transplantation may be an appropriate option for people with end-stage lung disease. Liver transplantation is the definitive treatment for advanced liver disease. When present, panniculitis may resolve on its own or after dapsone or doxycycline therapy. When this therapy does not help, it has responded to intravenous augmentation therapy in higher than usual doses. All people with severe AATD should have pulmonary function tests every 6 to 12 months. Those with ATT serum concentrations 10% to 20% of normal should have periodic evaluation of liver function to detect liver disease. People with established liver disease should have periodic ultrasounds of the liver to monitor for fibrotic changes and liver cancer (hepatocellular carcinoma). Yearly vaccinations against influenza and pneumococcus are recommended to lessen the progression of lung disease. Vaccination against hepatitis A and B is recommended to lessen the risk of liver disease. People with AATD should avoid smoking and occupations with exposure to environmental pollutants. Parents, older and younger siblings, and children of a person with severe AATD should be evaluated to identify as early as possible those who would benefit from treatment and preventive measures.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
