<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000943" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8586/cardiocranial-syndrome">
<Focus>Cardiocranial syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1857495</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pfeiffer syndrome 2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pfeiffer cardiocranial syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Craniostenosis, sagittal, with congenital heart disease, mental deficiency, and mandibular ankylosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pfeiffer-type cardiocranial syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pfeiffer Singer Zschiesche syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000943-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Cardiocranial syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Cardiocranial syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Cardiocranial syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Cognitive impairment 90% Craniosynostosis 90% Dolichocephaly 90% External ear malformation 90% Hypertelorism 90% Laryngomalacia 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Short stature 90% Tracheomalacia 90% Trismus 90% Abnormal localization of kidney 50% Atria septal defect 50% Camptodactyly of finger 50% Cryptorchidism 50% Exaggerated cupid&apos;s bow 50% Hypoplasia of penis 50% Limitation of joint mobility 50% Polyhydramnios 50% Ptosis 50% Tetralogy of Fallot 50% Vesicoureteral reflux 50% Renal hypoplasia/aplasia 7.5% Ventricular septal defect 7.5% Abnormality of cardiovascular system morphology - Abnormality of the tracheobronchial system - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Growth delay - Intellectual disability - Micropenis - Microphallus - Sagittal craniosynostosis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
