<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000564" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/11918/autosomal-dominant-nocturnal-frontal-lobe-epilepsy">
<Focus>Autosomal dominant nocturnal frontal lobe epilepsy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3696898</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>ADNFLE</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Epilepsy, nocturnal frontal lobe, 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>ENFL1</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000564-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Autosomal dominant nocturnal frontal lobe epilepsy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Autosomal dominant nocturnal frontal lobe epilepsy (ADNFLE) is an uncommon, inherited form of epilepsy. Signs and symptoms include seizures that usually occur at night during sleep. The seizures that occur in people with ADNFLE can last from a few seconds to a few minutes, and can vary from causing simple arousal from sleep to severe, dramatic muscle spasm events. Some people with ADNFLE also have seizures during the day. Some episodes may be misdiagnosed as nightmares, night terrors, or panic attacks. The onset of ADNFLE ranges from infancy to adulthood, but most cases begin in childhood. Episodes tend to become milder and less frequent with age. ADNFLE is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner and may be caused by a mutation in any of several genes. In many cases, the genetic cause remains unknown. Seizures can usually be controlled with antiseizure medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000564-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Autosomal dominant nocturnal frontal lobe epilepsy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Autosomal dominant nocturnal frontal lobe epilepsy? The seizures that occur in people with autosomal dominant nocturnal frontal lobe epilepsy (ADNFLE) usually occur at night while sleeping, but some affected people also have seizures during the day. The seizures tend to occur in clusters, with each one lasting from a few seconds to a few minutes. In some people, seizures are mild and only cause a person to wake from sleep. In others, severe episodes can cause sudden, dramatic muscle spasms, wandering around, and/or crying out or making other sounds. Episodes of seizures tend to become less frequent and more mild as an affected person ages. Some people with ADNFLE experience aura, which may cause neurological symptoms such as tingling, shivering, a sense of fear, dizziness, and/or a feeling of falling or being pushed. Feelings of breathlessness, hyperventilation, and choking have also been reported. Most people with ADNFLE are intellectually normal. Psychiatric disorders, behavioral problems and intellectual disability have been described in some people with ADNFLE, but it is unclear if these features are directly related to the condition. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Autosomal dominant nocturnal frontal lobe epilepsy. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Intellectual disability 5% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Behavioral abnormality - Focal seizures - Incomplete penetrance - Juvenile onset - Seizures - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000564-3" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Autosomal dominant nocturnal frontal lobe epilepsy ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is autosomal dominant nocturnal frontal lobe epilepsy diagnosed? The diagnosis of autosomal dominant nocturnal frontal lobe epilepsy (ADNFLE) is made on clinical grounds. The key to diagnosis is a detailed history from the affected person, as well as witnesses. Sometimes video-EEG monitoring is necessary. The features that are suggestive of a diagnosis of ADNFLE are: clusters of seizures with a frontal semiology seizures that occur predominantly during sleep normal clinical neurologic exam normal intellect (although reduced intellect, cognitive deficits, or psychiatric disorders may occur) normal findings on neuroimaging ictal EEG (recorded during a seizure) that may be normal or obscured by movement of the cables or electrodes interictal EEG (recorded in between seizures) that shows infrequent epileptiform discharges (distinctive patterns resembling those that occur in people with epilepsy) the presence of the same disorder in other family members, with evidence of autosomal dominant inheritance The diagnosis can be established in a person with the above features, combined with a positive family history and/or genetic testing that detects a mutation in one of the genes known to cause ADNFLE. People who are concerned they may be having seizures or other neurological signs or symptoms should be evaluated by a neurologist.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
