<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000702" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/872/beta-ketothiolase-deficiency">
<Focus>Beta ketothiolase deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1536500</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Alpha-methylacetoaceticaciduria</Synonym>
		<Synonym>2-methyl-3-hydroxybutyricacidemia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mitochondrial acetoacetyl-CoA Thiolase deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>3-oxothiolase deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>3-ketothiolase deficiency</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000702-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Beta ketothiolase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Beta-ketothiolase deficiency is an inherited disorder in which the body cannot effectively process a protein building block (amino acid) called isoleucine. This condition also impairs the body&apos;s ability to process ketones, which are molecules produced during the breakdown of fats. Signs and symptoms typically appear between the ages of 6 months and 24 months. Affected children experience episodes of vomiting, dehydration, difficulty breathing, extreme tiredness (lethargy), and occasionally seizures. These episodes, which are called ketoacidotic attacks, sometimes lead to coma. Ketoacidotic attacks are frequently triggered by infections, periods without food (fasting), or increased intake of protein-rich foods. This condition is inherited in an autosomal recessive fashion and is caused by mutations in the ACAT1 gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000702-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Beta ketothiolase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Beta ketothiolase deficiency? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Beta ketothiolase deficiency. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal recessive inheritance - Dehydration - Episodic ketoacidosis - Intellectual disability - Vomiting - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
