<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000848" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1019/brittle-cornea-syndrome">
<Focus>Brittle cornea syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0268344</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>EDS VIB (formerly)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome type 6B (formerly)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fragilitas oculi with joint hyperextensibility</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Corneal fragility, keratoglobus, blue sclerae, joint hyperextensibility</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dysgenesis mesodermalis corneae et sclerae</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000848-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Brittle cornea syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Brittle cornea syndrome (BCS) is a type of connective tissue disorder that mainly affects the eyes, joints and skin. Signs and symptoms may include rupture of the cornea after only minor trauma; degeneration of the cornea (keratoconus) or thinning and protrusion of the cornea (keratoglobus); bluish tint in the white part of the eyes (blue sclerae); hypermobile joints; hyperelastic skin; hearing defects; and dental abnormalities. There are 2 types of BCS which are distinguished by the mutated gene that causes the condition. BCS type 1 is caused by mutations in the ZNF469 gene and BCS type 2 is caused by mutations in the PRDM5 gene. BCS is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000848-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Brittle cornea syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Brittle cornea syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Brittle cornea syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Corneal dystrophy 90% Decreased corneal thickness 90% Myopia 90% Atypical scarring of skin 50% Blue sclerae 50% Bruising susceptibility 50% Conductive hearing impairment 50% Gait disturbance 50% Joint hypermobility 50% Myalgia 50% Reduced bone mineral density 50% Sensorineural hearing impairment 50% Visual impairment 50% Abnormality of epiphysis morphology 7.5% Abnormality of the hip bone 7.5% Abnormality of the mitral valve 7.5% Abnormality of the pulmonary valve 7.5% Abnormality of the teeth 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Corneal erosion 7.5% Glaucoma 7.5% Hernia 7.5% Recurrent fractures 7.5% Retinal detachment 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Flat cornea 5% Inguinal hernia 5% Megalocornea 5% Sclerocornea 5% Umbilical hernia 5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Congenital hip dislocation - Dentinogenesis imperfecta - Disproportionate tall stature - Epicanthus - Hearing impairment - Joint laxity - Keratoconus - Keratoglobus - Macrocephaly - Mitral valve prolapse - Molluscoid pseudotumors - Palmoplantar cutis laxa - Red hair - Spondylolisthesis - Visual loss - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
