<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000085" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/501/acromegaloid-facial-appearance-syndrome">
<Focus>Acromegaloid facial appearance syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0796280</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>AFA syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Thick lips and oral mucosa</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000085-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Acromegaloid facial appearance syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Acromegaloid facial appearance syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Acromegaloid facial appearance syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal nasal morphology 90% Abnormality of the nasal alae 90% Abnormality of the tongue 90% Blepharophimosis 90% Coarse facial features 90% Gingival overgrowth 90% Hypertelorism 90% Joint hypermobility 90% Large hands 90% Palpebral edema 90% Thick lower lip vermilion 90% Abnormality of the metacarpal bones 50% Cognitive impairment 50% Craniofacial hyperostosis 50% Highly arched eyebrow 50% Sloping forehead 50% Synophrys 50% Thick eyebrow 50% Thickened skin 50% Intellectual disability, mild 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Specific learning disability 7.5% Tapered finger 7.5% Abnormality of the mouth - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Bulbous nose - Large for gestational age - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
