<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000767" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/918/bod-syndrome">
<Focus>BOD syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1862082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Brachymorphism-onychodysplasia-dysphalangism syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Brachymorphism onychodysplasia dysphalangism syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000767-1" qtype="information">What is (are) BOD syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>BOD syndrome is a genetic condition characterized by underdeveloped pinky toenails or fingernails, normal intellect to mild intellectual disability, distinct facial features, and short stature. The cause of the condition is not known. BOD syndrome is thought to be inherited in an autosomal dominant fashion, however in many cases the condition occurs for the first time in a family due to a new mutation. Signs and symptoms of BOD syndrome are similar to, albeit milder than that of, Coffin-Siris syndrome. The relationship between these syndromes is presently unknown.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000767-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of BOD syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of BOD syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for BOD syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the fingernails 90% Anonychia 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the distal phalanges of the toes 90% Aplastic/hypoplastic toenail 90% Brachydactyly syndrome 90% Delayed skeletal maturation 90% Long philtrum 90% Microcephaly 90% Short distal phalanx of finger 90% Short stature 90% Wide nasal bridge 90% Abnormal nasal morphology 50% Epicanthus 50% Frontal bossing 50% Hypoplasia of the zygomatic bone 50% Intrauterine growth retardation 50% Narrow forehead 50% Pointed chin 50% Strabismus 50% Triangular face 50% Wide mouth 50% Abnormality of the mitral valve 7.5% Abnormality of the respiratory system 7.5% Atria septal defect 7.5% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 7.5% Coarse facial features 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% High anterior hairline 7.5% Hypertrichosis 7.5% Symphalangism affecting the phalanges of the hand 7.5% Thick eyebrow 7.5% Umbilical hernia 7.5% Abnormal facial shape - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Congenital cystic adenomatoid malformation of the lung - Nail dysplasia - Short distal phalanx of the 5th finger - Short middle phalanx of the 5th finger - Wide nose - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
