<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000880" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10041/burn-mckeown-syndrome">
<Focus>Burn-Mckeown syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1837822</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Bilateral choanal atresia, cardiac defects, deafness, and dysmorphic appearance</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Choanal atresia deafness cardiac defects dysmorphism</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000880-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Burn-Mckeown syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Burn-Mckeown syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Burn-Mckeown syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Blepharophimosis 90% Choanal atresia 90% Hypertelorism 90% Abnormality of the cardiac septa 50% Prominent nasal bridge 50% Abnormality of the palate 7.5% Short nose 7.5% Short stature 7.5% 2-3 toe syndactyly - Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Atria septal defect - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Bifid uvula - Bilateral choanal atresia/stenosis - Cleft palate - Cleft upper lip - Conductive hearing impairment - Feeding difficulties in infancy - Hypomimic face - Lower eyelid coloboma - Mandibular prognathia - Narrow mouth - Preauricular skin tag - Protruding ear - Renal hypoplasia - Short palpebral fissure - Short philtrum - Thin vermilion border - Underdeveloped nasal alae - Ventricular septal defect - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
