<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000776" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/932/book-syndrome">
<Focus>Book syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0457014</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Premolar aplasia, hyperhidrosis, and canities prematura</Synonym>
		<Synonym>PHC syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000776-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Book syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Book syndrome is a very rare type of ectodermal dysplasia. Signs and symptoms include premolar aplasia (when the premolars fail to develop); excessive sweating (hyperhidrosis); and premature graying of the hair. Other features that have been reported in only one person include a narrow palate (roof of the mouth); hypoplastic (underdeveloped) nails; eyebrow anomalies; a unilateral simian crease; and poorly formed dermatoglyphics (skin patterns on the hands and feet). Book syndrome is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000776-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Book syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Book syndrome? To our knowledge, Book syndrome has only been reported in one, large Swedish family (25 cases in 4 generations) and in one other isolated case. The signs and symptoms reported in the Swedish family included premolar aplasia (when the premolars fail to develop); excessive sweating (hyperhidrosis); and early whitening of the hair. Early whitening of the hair was the most constant symptom, being found in every affected family member. The age of onset of this symptom ranged from age 6 to age 23. In some cases, there was whitening of hair on other parts of the body such as the armipits, genital hair, and eyebrows. Two-thirds of the affected people had an abnormality of the sweat glands. In the isolated case, additional features that were reported include a narrow palate (roof of the mouth); hypoplastic (underdeveloped) nails; eyebrow anomalies; a unilateral simian crease; and poorly formed dermatoglyphics (skin patterns on the hands and feet). The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Book syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Premature graying of hair 90% Short palm 90% Abnormality of the eyebrow 50% Abnormality of the fingernails 50% Abnormality of the palate 50% Single transverse palmar crease 50% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Hypodontia - Palmoplantar hyperhidrosis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000776-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Book syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Book syndrome inherited? To our knowledge, Book syndrome has only been reported in one, large Swedish family (25 cases in 4 generations) and in one other isolated case. In the Swedish family, the syndrome was inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. In autosomal dominant inheritance, having a mutation in only one copy of the responsible gene is enough to cause signs and symptoms of the condition. When a person with an autosomal dominant condition has children, each child has a 50% (1 in 2) risk to inherit the mutated copy of the gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000776-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Book syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Book syndrome diagnosed? Due to the rarity of Book syndrome and scarcity of reports in the medical literature, we are unaware of specific information about diagnosing Book syndrome. In general, ectodermal dysplasias are diagnosed by the presence of specific symptoms affecting the hair, nails, sweat glands, and/or teeth. When a person has at least two types of abnormal ectodermal features (e.g., malformed teeth and extremely sparse hair), the person is typically identified as being affected by an ectodermal dysplasia. Specific genetics tests to diagnose ectodermal dysplasia are available for only a limited number of ectodermal dysplasias. Unfortunately, there currently is no genetic test for Book syndrome because the gene responsible for the condition has not yet been identified. People who are interested in learning more about a diagnosis of ectodermal dysplasia for themselves or family members should speak with their dermatologist and/or dentist. These specialists can help determine whether a person has signs and/or symptoms of ectodermal dysplasia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
