<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000473" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/794/arthrogryposis-renal-dysfunction-cholestasis-syndrome">
<Focus>Arthrogryposis renal dysfunction cholestasis syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0008370</CUI>
			<CUI>C1859722</CUI>
			<CUI>C3279454</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>ARC syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Arthrogryposis multiplex congenita, renal dysfunction, and cholestasis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Arthrogryposis - renal dysfunction - cholestasis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Arthrogryposis-renal dysfunction-cholestasis syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Arthrogryposis multiplex congenita</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000473-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Arthrogryposis renal dysfunction cholestasis syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Arthrogryposis renal dysfunction cholestasis syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Arthrogryposis renal dysfunction cholestasis syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the renal tubule 90% Abnormality of thrombocytes 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Abnormal renal physiology 50% Abnormality of coagulation 50% Abnormality of temperature regulation 50% Aminoaciduria 50% Diabetes insipidus 50% Hepatomegaly 50% Ichthyosis 50% Malabsorption 50% Muscular hypotonia 50% Oligohydramnios 50% Recurrent fractures 50% Rocker bottom foot 50% Skeletal muscle atrophy 50% Talipes 50% Abnormality of the cardiac septa 7.5% Abnormality of the hip bone 7.5% Abnormality of the palate 7.5% Anemia 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 7.5% Cirrhosis 7.5% Convex nasal ridge 7.5% Cutis laxa 7.5% Depressed nasal bridge 7.5% Hypothyroidism 7.5% Kyphosis 7.5% Nephrolithiasis 7.5% Pectus carinatum 7.5% Sensorineural hearing impairment 7.5% Upslanted palpebral fissure 7.5% Abnormal bleeding 5% Lissencephaly 5% Nephrogenic diabetes insipidus 5% Atria septal defect - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Cholestatic liver disease - Conjugated hyperbilirubinemia - Death in infancy - Dehydration - Elevated hepatic transaminases - Failure to thrive - Giant cell hepatitis - Hip dysplasia - Jaundice - Low-set ears - Metabolic acidosis - Microcephaly - Nephrocalcinosis - Nephropathy - Renal tubular acidosis - Right ventricular hypertrophy - Sloping forehead - Talipes calcaneovalgus - Ventricular septal defect - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
