<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000706" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/871/beta-thalassemia">
<Focus>Beta-thalassemia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0005283</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Beta thalassemia major</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cooley's anemia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Beta thalassemia intermedia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Beta thalassemia minor</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Erythroblastic anemia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hemoglobinopathy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Thalassemia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000706-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Beta-thalassemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Beta-thalassemia is a blood disorder that reduces the body&apos;s production of hemoglobin. Low levels of hemoglobin lead to a shortage of mature red blood cells and a lack of oxygen in the body. Affected people have anemia, which can cause paleness, weakness, fatigue, and more serious complications. Severe beta-thalassemia is called thalassemia major or Cooleys anemia. Thalassemia intermedia is a less severe form. Beta-thalassemia is caused by mutations in the HBB gene and is usually inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. People who have only one HBB gene mutation may have no symptoms or develop mild symptoms, and are said to have thalassemia minor. Treatment depends on the severity in each person and may include transfusions, folic acid supplementation, iron chelation, and/or bone marrow transplantation (the only definitive cure).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000706-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Beta-thalassemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Beta-thalassemia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Beta-thalassemia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the heme biosynthetic pathway 90% Hypersplenism 90% Pallor 90% Splenomegaly 90% Abnormality of iron homeostasis 50% Abnormality of temperature regulation 50% Abnormality of the genital system 50% Abnormality of the teeth 50% Behavioral abnormality 50% Biliary tract abnormality 50% Depressed nasal bridge 50% Feeding difficulties in infancy 50% Genu valgum 50% Hepatomegaly 50% Malabsorption 50% Malar prominence 50% Muscle weakness 50% Paresthesia 50% Reduced bone mineral density 50% Respiratory insufficiency 50% Upslanted palpebral fissure 50% Abnormality of color vision 7.5% Abnormality of the thorax 7.5% Anterior hypopituitarism 7.5% Arthralgia 7.5% Bone marrow hypocellularity 7.5% Cataract 7.5% Cirrhosis 7.5% Diabetes mellitus 7.5% Elevated hepatic transaminases 7.5% Hearing impairment 7.5% Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy 7.5% Hypoparathyroidism 7.5% Hypothyroidism 7.5% Neoplasm of the liver 7.5% Nyctalopia 7.5% Primary adrenal insufficiency 7.5% Pulmonary hypertension 7.5% Skeletal dysplasia 7.5% Skin ulcer 7.5% Sudden cardiac death 7.5% Thrombocytopenia 7.5% Thrombophlebitis 7.5% Visual impairment 7.5% Hypochromic microcytic anemia - Reduced beta/alpha synthesis ratio - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000706-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Beta-thalassemia inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is beta-thalassemia inherited? Beta-thalassemia major and beta-thalassemia intermedia are usually inherited in an autosomal recessive manner, which means both copies of the HBB gene in each cell have mutations. The parents of a person with an autosomal recessive condition each carry one copy of the mutated gene and are referred to as carriers. When two carriers have children, each child has a 25% (1 in 4) chance to be affected, a 50% (1 in 2) chance to be a carrier like each parent, and a 25% (1 in 4) chance to be unaffected and not be a carrier. Sometimes, people with only one HBB gene mutation in each cell (carriers) do have mild anemia. These people are said to have &apos;beta-thalassemia minor&apos; or &apos;beta-thalassemia trait.&apos;  In a small percentage of families, the condition is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. In these cases, one mutated copy of the gene in each cell is enough to cause the signs and symptoms of beta-thalassemia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
