<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000796" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/957/brachycephalofrontonasal-dysplasia">
<Focus>Brachycephalofrontonasal dysplasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1840378</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hypertelorism, Teebi type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Teebi hypertelorism syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Craniofrontonasal dysplasia, Teebi type</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000796-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Brachycephalofrontonasal dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Brachycephalofrontonasal dysplasia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Brachycephalofrontonasal dysplasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Highly arched eyebrow 90% Hypertelorism 90% Long philtrum 90% Prominent nasal bridge 90% Thick eyebrow 90% Thin vermilion border 90% Abnormality of periauricular region 50% Abnormality of the helix 50% Brachydactyly syndrome 50% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 50% Cryptorchidism 50% Finger syndactyly 50% Frontal bossing 50% High anterior hairline 50% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 50% Ptosis 50% Round face 50% Shawl scrotum 50% Short nose 50% Short toe 50% Umbilical hernia 50% Abnormal localization of kidney 7.5% Advanced eruption of teeth 7.5% Arrhythmia 7.5% Atria septal defect 7.5% Chin dimple 7.5% Female pseudohermaphroditism 7.5% Omphalocele 7.5% Oral cleft 7.5% Patent ductus arteriosus 7.5% Pectus excavatum 7.5% Proptosis 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Tetralogy of Fallot 7.5% Ventricular septal defect 7.5% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Broad palm - Depressed nasal bridge - Prominent forehead - Wide nasal bridge - Widow&apos;s peak - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
