<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000277" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5791/amelogenesis-imperfecta">
<Focus>Amelogenesis imperfecta</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0002452</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000277-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Amelogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>Amelogenesis imperfecta (AI) (amelogenesis - enamel formation; imperfecta - imperfect) is a disorder that affects the structure and appearance of the enamel of the teeth. This condition causes teeth to be unusually small, discolored, pitted or grooved, and prone to rapid wear and breakage. These dental problems, which vary among affected individuals, can affect both primary (baby) teeth and permanent teeth. There are 4 main types of AI that are classified based on the type of enamel defect. These 4 types are divided further into 14 subtypes, which are distinguished by their specific dental abnormalities and by their pattern of inheritance. AI can be inherited in an autosomal dominant, autosomal recessive or X-linked recessive pattern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000277-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Amelogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of amelogenesis imperfecta? In general, the both primary and permanent teeth are affected. The enamel tends to be soft and weak, and the teeth appear yellow and damage easily. The defects associated with amelogeneis imperfecta are highly variable and include abnormalities classified as hypoplastic (defects in the amount of enamel), hypomaturation (defect in the final growth and development of the tooth enamel), and hypocalcification (defect in the initial stage of enamel formation followed by defective tooth growth). The enamel in the hypomaturation and hypocalcification types is not mineralized and is thus described as hypomineralized. Traditionally, the diagnosis and classification of amelogenesis imperfecta is based on the clinical presentation and the mode of inheritance. There are four principal types based on the defects in the tooth enamel. These types are subdivided into 14 different subtypes based on the clinical presentation and the mode of inheritance. Detailed information about the signs and symptoms associated with the four major types of amelogenesis imperfecta is available from the UNC School of Dentistry.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000277-3" qtype="causes">What causes Amelogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes amelogenesis imperfecta? Amelogenesis imperfecta is caused by mutations in the AMELX, ENAM, and MMP20 genes. These genes provide instructions for making proteins that are essential for normal tooth development. These proteins are involved in the formation of enamel, which is the hard, calcium-rich material that forms the protective outer layer of each tooth. Mutations in any of these genes alter the structure of these proteins or prevent the genes from making any protein at all. As a result, tooth enamel is abnormally thin or soft and may have a yellow or brown color. Teeth with defective enamel are weak and easily damaged. In some cases, the genetic cause of amelogenesis imperfecta can not been identified. Researchers are working to find mutations in other genes that are responsible for this disorder. Click on each gene name to learn more about the role it plays in the development of tooth enamel.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000277-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Amelogenesis imperfecta inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is amelogenesis imperfecta inherited? Amelogenesis imperfecta can have different patterns of inheritance, depending on the gene that is altered. Most cases are caused by mutations in the ENAM gene and are inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern. This type of inheritance means one copy of the altered gene in each cell is sufficient to cause the disorder. Amelogenesis imperfecta may also be inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern; this form of the disorder can result from mutations in the ENAM or MMP20 gene. Autosomal recessive inheritance means two copies of the gene in each cell are altered. About 5 percent of amelogenesis imperfecta cases are caused by mutations in the AMELX gene and are inherited in an X-linked pattern. A condition is considered X-linked if the mutated gene that causes the disorder is located on the X chromosome, one of the two sex chromosomes. In most cases, males with X-linked amelogenesis imperfecta experience more severe dental abnormalities than females with this form of this condition. Other cases of amelogenesis imperfecta result from new mutations in these genes and occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000277-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Amelogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is amelogenesis imperfecta diagnosed? A dentist can identify and diagnose amelogenesis imperfecta on the basis of the patient&apos;s family history and the signs and symptoms present in the affected individual. Extraoral X-rays (X-rays taken outside the mouth) can reveal the presence of teeth that never erupted o that were absorbed. Intraoral X-rays (X-rays taken inside the mouth) show contrast between the enamel and dentin in cases in which mineralization is affected. Genetic testing is available for the genes AMELX, ENAM, and MMP20. You can visit the Genetic Testing Registry to locate laboratories performing genetic testing for these genes. The American Academy of Pediatric Dentistry is a source of information to find a pediatric dentist. The National Dental Association can also assist people in locating a dentist.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000277-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Amelogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might amelogenesis imperfecta be treated? Treatment depends on the type of amelogenesis imperfecta and the type of enamel abnormality. Treatments include preventative measures, various types of crowns, as well as tooth implants or dentures in the most severe cases. The social and emotional impact of this condition should also be addressed. Detailed information on the treatment of amelogenesis imperfecta is available from the UNC School of Dentistry.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
