<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000012" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3/ablepharon-macrostomia-syndrome">
<Focus>Ablepharon macrostomia syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0266574</CUI>
			<CUI>C0024433</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>AMS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital ablepharon, absent eyelashes/eyebrows, macrostomia, auricular, nasal, genital and other systemic anomalies</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000012-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ablepharon macrostomia syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Ablepharon macrostomia syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Ablepharon macrostomia syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal hair quantity 90% Abnormality of the eyelashes 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the eyebrow 90% Cutis laxa 90% Fine hair 90% Hypoplasia of the zygomatic bone 90% Neurological speech impairment 90% Underdeveloped nasal alae 90% Wide mouth 90% Abnormality of female external genitalia 50% Anteverted nares 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the nipples 50% Breast aplasia 50% Camptodactyly of finger 50% Cognitive impairment 50% Cryptorchidism 50% Dry skin 50% Hearing impairment 50% Hypoplasia of penis 50% Microdontia 50% Myopia 50% Opacification of the corneal stroma 50% Thin skin 50% Umbilical hernia 50% Visual impairment 50% Abnormality of skin pigmentation 7.5% Atresia of the external auditory canal 7.5% Corneal erosion 7.5% Depressed nasal bridge 7.5% Omphalocele 7.5% Thin vermilion border 7.5% Toe syndactyly 7.5% Short upper lip 5% Talipes equinovarus 5% Ablepharon - Abnormal nasal morphology - Absent eyebrow - Absent eyelashes - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Cryptophthalmos - Delayed speech and language development - Hypertelorism - Microtia, third degree - Ventral hernia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
