<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000100" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/480/acrorenal-mandibular-syndrome">
<Focus>Acrorenal mandibular syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1860166</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Acro-renal-uterine-mandibular syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Split hand split foot mandibular hypoplasia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000100-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Acrorenal mandibular syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Acrorenal mandibular syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Acrorenal mandibular syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the fibula 90% Abnormality of the tibia 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the radius 90% Renal hypoplasia/aplasia 90% Split foot 90% Split hand 90% Abnormality of female internal genitalia 50% Abnormality of the clavicle 50% Abnormality of the hip bone 50% Abnormality of the palate 50% Abnormality of the ribs 50% Abnormality of the sense of smell 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the lungs 50% Intrauterine growth retardation 50% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 50% Oligohydramnios 50% Pectus carinatum 50% Short neck 50% Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 7.5% Abnormal lung lobation 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the tongue 7.5% Congenital diaphragmatic hernia 7.5% Finger syndactyly 7.5% Kyphosis 7.5% Narrow face 7.5% Oral cleft 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Short philtrum 7.5% Sprengel anomaly 7.5% Tracheoesophageal fistula 7.5% Abnormal sacral segmentation - Abnormality of the cardiovascular system - Abnormality of the ureter - Absent nipple - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Bicornuate uterus - Butterfly vertebrae - Dolichocephaly - Elbow flexion contracture - Epicanthus - Foot polydactyly - Hand polydactyly - Hemivertebrae - High palate - Hip dislocation - Hypoplasia of the radius - Hypoplasia of the ulna - Hypoplastic scapulae - Kyphoscoliosis - Low-set ears - Missing ribs - Narrow chest - Narrow palate - Polycystic kidney dysplasia - Posteriorly rotated ears - Pulmonary hypoplasia - Renal agenesis - Rudimentary fibula - Rudimentary to absent tibiae - Thin ribs - Toe syndactyly - Uterus didelphys - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
