<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000736" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10237/biotin-thiamine-responsive-basal-ganglia-disease">
<Focus>Biotin-thiamine-responsive basal ganglia disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1843807</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Biotin-responsive basal ganglia disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>BBGD</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000736-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Biotin-thiamine-responsive basal ganglia disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Biotin-thiamine-responsive basal ganglia disease is a rare condition that affects the brain and other parts of the nervous system. The severity of the condition and the associated signs and symptoms vary from person to person, even within the same family. Without early diagnosis and treatment, most affected people develop features of the condition between ages 3 and 10 years. Signs and symptoms may include recurrent episodes of confusion, seizures, ataxia (problems coordinating movements), dystonia, facial palsy (weakness of the facial muscles), external ophthalmoplegia (paralysis of the muscles surrounding the eye), and dysphagia. Eventually, these episodes can lead to coma or even death. Biotin-thiamine-responsive basal ganglia disease is caused by changes (mutations) in the SLC19A3 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. As its name suggests, early and lifelong treatment with the vitamins biotin and thiamine may improve the symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000736-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Biotin-thiamine-responsive basal ganglia disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Biotin-thiamine-responsive basal ganglia disease? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Biotin-thiamine-responsive basal ganglia disease. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the basal ganglia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Babinski sign - Coma - Confusion - Craniofacial dystonia - Dysarthria - Dysphagia - Encephalopathy - External ophthalmoplegia - Fever - Gait ataxia - Inability to walk - Irritability - Juvenile onset - Morphological abnormality of the pyramidal tract - Muscular hypotonia of the trunk - Mutism - Nystagmus - Paraparesis - Ptosis - Rigidity - Seizures - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
