<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000966" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1121/carnitine-palmitoyltransferase-2-deficiency">
<Focus>Carnitine palmitoyltransferase 2 deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0342790</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Carnitine palmitoyltransferase deficiency type 2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>CPT2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Carnitine palmitoyltransferase II (CPT II) deficiency</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000966-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Carnitine palmitoyltransferase 2 deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Carnitine palmitoyltransferase 2 (CPT2) deficiency is a condition that prevents the body from using certain fats for energy, particularly during periods without food (fasting). There are three main types of CPT2 deficiency: a lethal neonatal form, a severe infantile hepatocardiomuscular form, and a myopathic form. The neonatal and infantile forms are severe multisystemic diseases characterized by liver failure with hypoketotic hypoglycemia (extremely low levels of ketones (substances produced when fat cells break down in the blood) and low blood sugar), cardiomyopathy, seizures, and early death. The myopathic form is characterized by exercise-induced muscle pain and weakness and occasional myoglobinuria (rust-colored urine indicating breakdown of muscle tissue). Mutations in the CPT2 gene cause CPT2 deficiency. It is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern. Treatment is based on avoidance of prolonged fasting and a low-fat and high-carbohydrate diet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000966-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Carnitine palmitoyltransferase 2 deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Carnitine palmitoyltransferase 2 deficiency? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Carnitine palmitoyltransferase 2 deficiency. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Elevated hepatic transaminases 90% Hepatomegaly 90% Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy 90% Muscle weakness 90% Myalgia 90% Myopathy 90% Seizures 90% Cerebral calcification 50% Multicystic kidney dysplasia 50% Renal insufficiency 50% Encephalitis 7.5% Hypoglycemia 7.5% Reduced consciousness/confusion 7.5% Sudden cardiac death 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
