<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001728" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12844/deafness-and-myopia-syndrome">
<Focus>Deafness and myopia syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
			<CUI>C3806275</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>High myopia-sensorineural deafness syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001728-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Deafness and myopia syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Deafness and myopia syndrome is rare condition that affects both hearing and vision. Beginning at birth or in early infancy, people with this condition have moderate to profound hearing loss in both ears that generally becomes worse over time. Affected people also develop severe myopia (nearsightedness) later in infancy or early childhood. Deafness and myopia syndrome is caused by changes (mutations) in the SLITRK6 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Treatment aims to improve hearing loss and correct myopia. Cochlear implantation may be an option for some affected people.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001728-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Deafness and myopia syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Deafness and myopia syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Deafness and myopia syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal recessive inheritance - Conductive hearing impairment - Hematuria - Intellectual disability - Myopia - Proteinuria - Severe Myopia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
