<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001368" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1392/cleft-palate-short-stature-vertebral-anomalies">
<Focus>Cleft palate short stature vertebral anomalies</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0008925</CUI>
			<CUI>C0349588</CUI>
			<CUI>C0265343</CUI>
			<CUI>C0013336</CUI>
			<CUI>C2240378</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Mathieu-De Broca-Bony syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001368-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Cleft palate short stature vertebral anomalies ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Cleft palate short stature vertebral anomalies? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Cleft palate short stature vertebral anomalies. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 90% Abnormality of the metacarpal bones 90% Aganglionic megacolon 90% Brachydactyly syndrome 90% Carious teeth 90% Cleft palate 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Delayed skeletal maturation 90% Epicanthus 90% Genu recurvatum 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Scoliosis 90% Short neck 90% Short nose 90% Short stature 90% Vertebral segmentation defect 90% Abnormality of bone mineral density 50% Abnormality of the hip bone 50% Abnormality of the ureter 50% Anteverted nares 50% Congenital diaphragmatic hernia 50% Facial asymmetry 50% Joint hypermobility 50% Laryngomalacia 50% Limitation of joint mobility 50% Muscular hypotonia 50% Thin vermilion border 50% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
