<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001443" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10818/combined-malonic-and-methylmalonic-aciduria">
<Focus>Combined malonic and methylmalonic aciduria</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0268583</CUI>
			<CUI>C3280314</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>CMAMMA</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001443-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Combined malonic and methylmalonic aciduria ?</Question>
			<Answer>Combined malonic and methylmalonic aciduria (CMAMMA) is an inherited condition in which certain chemicals accumulate in the blood and urine of affected individuals. People with CMAMMA can have a wide variety of symptoms. Children with CMAMMA can suffer from developmental delays and a failure to gain weight and grow (failure to thrive). In those who were identified as adults, symptoms may include psychiatric features and neurological problems that can mimic Alzheimer&apos;s disease and multiple sclerosis. Recently, researchers have found that mutations in the ACSF3 gene cause CMAMMA.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001443-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Combined malonic and methylmalonic aciduria ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Combined malonic and methylmalonic aciduria? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Combined malonic and methylmalonic aciduria. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal recessive inheritance - Dehydration - Diarrhea - Failure to thrive - Generalized clonic seizures - Ketoacidosis - Methylmalonic aciduria - Vomiting - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
