<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001445" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12892/combined-oxidative-phosphorylation-deficiency-16">
<Focus>Combined oxidative phosphorylation deficiency 16</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3809339</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Infantile hypertrophic cardiomyopathy due to MRPL44 deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Combined oxidative phosphorylation defect type 16</Synonym>
		<Synonym>COXPD16</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001445-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Combined oxidative phosphorylation deficiency 16 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Combined oxidative phosphorylation deficiency 16, also know as infantile hypertrophic cardiomyopathy, is characterized by decreased levels of mitochondrial complexes. The symptoms and signs described include an enlarged heart muscle (hypertrophic cardiomyopathy) and fatty liver (hepatic steatosis), as well as eye problems, headache, paralysis of one side of the body, Leigh-like lesions on brain magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), kidney insufficiency and neurological disease. It is caused by mutations in the MRPL44 gene, which results in mitochondrial dysfunction. The cases described seem to be inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern. Treatment is supportive.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001445-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Combined oxidative phosphorylation deficiency 16 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Combined oxidative phosphorylation deficiency 16? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Combined oxidative phosphorylation deficiency 16. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal recessive inheritance - Elevated hepatic transaminases - Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy - Increased serum lactate - Infantile onset - Microvesicular hepatic steatosis - Variable expressivity - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
