<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001916" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1912/doyne-honeycomb-retinal-dystrophy">
<Focus>Doyne honeycomb retinal dystrophy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1832174</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>DHRD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Doyne honeycomb degeneration of retina</Synonym>
		<Synonym>DHD</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001916-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Doyne honeycomb retinal dystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Doyne honeycomb retinal dystrophy (DHRD) is a condition that affects the eyes and causes vision loss. It is characterized by small, round, white spots known as drusen that accumulate beneath the retinal pigment epithelium (the pigmented layer of the retina). Over time, drusen may grow and come together, creating a honeycomb pattern. It usually begins in early to mid adulthood, but the age of onset varies. The degree of vision loss also varies. DHRD is usually caused by mutations in the EFEMP1 gene and is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001916-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Doyne honeycomb retinal dystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Doyne honeycomb retinal dystrophy? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Doyne honeycomb retinal dystrophy. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal dominant inheritance - Reticular pigmentary degeneration - Retinal dystrophy - Visual impairment - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001916-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Doyne honeycomb retinal dystrophy inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Doyne honeycomb retinal dystrophy inherited? Doyne honeycomb retinal dystrophy (DHRD) is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. This means that having only one changed (mutated) copy of the responsible gene in each cell is enough to cause signs and symptoms of the condition.  When a person with an autosomal dominant condition has children, each child has a 50% (1 in 2) risk to inherit the mutated gene from the affected parent. Children who do not inherit the mutated gene will not develop or pass on the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001916-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Doyne honeycomb retinal dystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Doyne honeycomb retinal dystrophy (DHRD) be treated? There is currently no cure for Doyne honeycomb retinal dystrophy (DHRD) and treatment options are limited. Management of hereditary retinal dystrophies generally focuses on vision rehabilitation, which involves the use of low vision aids, orientation, and mobility training. The goal of visual rehabilitation is to reach maximum function, a sense of well being, a personally satisfying level of independence, and optimum quality of life. Choroidal neovascularization (CNV), the growth of new blood vessels in the choroid, can develop in people with DHRD and has a poor visual prognosis. The authors of a 2011 study reported that 2 people with DHRD and CNV were treated with a course of intravitreal bevacizumab (injected into the eye). This treatment stopped fluid leakage and led to increased visual acuity. They proposed that recovery of visual acuity after treatment of CNV in these cases shows that the loss of retinal function may be reversible. However, this finding needs to be confirmed in more studies with a larger number of participants. There was also a case report of a person with malattia leventinese (a condition very similar to DHRD and sometimes considered the same) who was treated successfully with photodynamic therapy using verteporfin. The treatment reportedly prevented severe visual loss in the patient. The authors of this case report proposed that photodynamic therapy be considered as a possible treatment in patients with malattia leventinese or DHRD who develop CNV.   You may consider participating in a clinical trial for treatment of retinal dystrophy. The U.S. National Institutes of Health, through the National Library of Medicine, developed ClinicalTrials.gov to provide patients, family members, and members of the public with current information on clinical research studies.  There are many clinical trials currently enrolling individuals with hereditary retinal dystrophy. View a list of these studies here. After you click on a study, review its eligibility criteria to determine its appropriateness. We suggest reviewing the list of studies with your physician. Use the studys contact information to learn more. You can check this site often for regular updates. Use &quot;retinal dystrophy&quot; or &quot;Doyne honeycomb retinal dystrophy&quot; as your search term.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
