<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001051" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10424/cerebral-autosomal-recessive-arteriopathy-with-subcortical-infarcts-and-leukoencephalopathy">
<Focus>Cerebral autosomal recessive arteriopathy with subcortical infarcts and leukoencephalopathy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0270612</CUI>
			<CUI>C0021308</CUI>
			<CUI>C0852949</CUI>
			<CUI>C1838577</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>CARASIL</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Maeda syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Subcortical vascular encephalopathy, progressive</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cerebrovascular disease with thin skin, alopecia, and disc disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001051-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Cerebral autosomal recessive arteriopathy with subcortical infarcts and leukoencephalopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cerebral autosomal recessive arteriopathy with subcortical infarcts and leukoencephalopathy, commonly known as CARASIL, is an inherited condition that causes stroke and other impairments. This progressive condition is characterized by muscle stiffness, mood and personality changes, dementia, memory loss, alopecia of the scalp, and attacks of low back pain. CARASIL is caused by mutations in the HTRA1 gene. It is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001051-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Cerebral autosomal recessive arteriopathy with subcortical infarcts and leukoencephalopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Cerebral autosomal recessive arteriopathy with subcortical infarcts and leukoencephalopathy? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Cerebral autosomal recessive arteriopathy with subcortical infarcts and leukoencephalopathy. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Nystagmus 5% Abnormality of extrapyramidal motor function - Alopecia - Arteriosclerosis of small cerebral arteries - Ataxia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Babinski sign - Dementia - Diffuse demyelination of the cerebral white matter - Diffuse white matter abnormalities - Dysarthria - Gait disturbance - Hyperreflexia - Low back pain - Progressive encephalopathy - Pseudobulbar signs - Rigidity - Spasticity - Urinary incontinence - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
