<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001788" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6258/dentinogenesis-imperfecta">
<Focus>Dentinogenesis imperfecta</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0011436</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Dentinogenesis imperfecta without osteogenesis imperfecta</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Capdepont teeth</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dentinogenesis imperfecta type 2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dentinogenesis imperfecta type 3</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001788-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Dentinogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>Dentinogenesis imperfecta is a condition that results in issues with tooth development, causing the teeth to be translucent and discolored (most often a blue-gray or yellow-brown in color). Individuals with this disorder tend to have teeth that are weaker than normal which leads to increased wear, breakage, and loss of the teeth. This can affect both primary (baby) and permanent teeth. Dentinogenesis imperfecta is caused by mutations in the DSPP gene and is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. There are three types of dentinogenesis imperfecta. Type I: occurs in people who have osteogenesis imperfecta, a genetic condition in which bones are brittle, causing them to break easily. Type II and type III: usually occur in people without another inherited disorder. Some families with type II also have progressive hearing loss. Type III was first identified in a population in Brandywine, Maryland. Some researchers believe that dentinogenesis imperfecta type II and type III, along with a similar condition called dentin dysplasia type II, are actually just different forms of a single disorder.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001788-2" qtype="causes">What causes Dentinogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes dentinogenesis imperfecta? Mutations in the DSPP gene cause dentinogenesis imperfecta. The DSPP gene provides instructions for making three proteins that are essential for normal tooth development. These proteins are involved in the formation of dentin, which is a bone-like substance that makes up the protective middle layer of each tooth. DSPP mutations alter the proteins made from the gene, leading to the production of abnormally soft dentin. Teeth with defective dentin are discolored, weak, and more likely to decay and break. It is unclear how DSPP mutations are related to hearing loss in some families with dentinogenesis imperfecta type II.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001788-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Dentinogenesis imperfecta inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How do people inherit dentinogenesis imperfecta? Dentinogenesis imperfecta is inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern, which means one copy of the altered gene in each cell is sufficient to cause the disorder. In most cases, an affected person has one parent with the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001788-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Dentinogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might dentinogenesis imperfecta be treated? The aims of treatment are to remove sources of infection or pain, restore aesthetics and protect posterior teeth from wear. Treatment varies according to the age of the patient, severity of the problem and the presenting complaint. Crowns, caps or other forms of dental care are the most commonly used treatments. Dentures or dental implants may be necessary if the majority of teeth are lost. More detailed information regarding the treatment of dentinogenesis imperfecta can be found by visiting the following web links: https://www.dentistry.unc.edu/dentalprofessionals/resources/defects/di/ http://www.ojrd.com/content/3/1/31</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
