<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001688" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1626/currarino-triad">
<Focus>Currarino triad</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1531773</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Currarino syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Partial sacral agenesis with intact first sacral vertebra, presacral mass and anorectal malformation</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001688-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Currarino triad ?</Question>
			<Answer>Currarino triad or syndrome is an autosomal dominant hereditary condition which is characterized by the triad of sacral agenesis abnormalities (abnormally developed lower spine), anorectal malformation (most commonly in the form of anorectal stenosis) and presacral mass consisting of a teratoma, anterior sacral meningocele or both. However only 1 out of 5 cases of Currarino triad has all three abnormalities present. Currarino triad is considered a spectrum disorder with a wide variation in severity. Up to one-third of the patients are asymptomatic and may only be diagnosed during adulthood only on X-rays and ultrasound examinations that are performed for different reasons. Currarino triad is most often caused by mutations in the MNX1 gene. Treatment depends on the type and severity of abnormalities present, but may involve surgery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001688-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Currarino triad ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Currarino triad? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Currarino triad. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the sacrum 90% Presacral teratoma 90% Hemisacrum (S2-S5) 75% Bifid sacrum 22% Arteriovenous malformation 7.5% Bifid scrotum 7.5% Displacement of the external urethral meatus 7.5% Hypoplasia of penis 7.5% Lower limb asymmetry 7.5% Male pseudohermaphroditism 7.5% Abdominal distention - Anal atresia - Anal fistula - Anal stenosis - Anterior sacral meningocele - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Bicornuate uterus - Chronic constipation - Gastrointestinal obstruction - Horseshoe kidney - Incomplete penetrance - Neurogenic bladder - Perianal abscess - Rectovaginal fistula - Recurrent urinary tract infections - Septate vagina - Tethered cord - Urinary incontinence - Vesicoureteral reflux - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001688-3" qtype="causes">What causes Currarino triad ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Currarino triad? Currarino triad is caused by mutations in the MNX1 gene in nearly all familial and 30% of sporadic cases. These mutations in the gene are called loss of function mutations because the gene can no longer produce working (functional) protein. Less frequently, a complex phenotype of Currarino triad can be caused by microdeletions of 7q containing MNX1 (the long arm of chromosome 7 is missing a small piece of DNA which includes MNX1 and other genes).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001688-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Currarino triad inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Currarino triad inherited? Currarino triad is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. This means that having a change (mutation) in only one copy of the MNX1 gene in each cell is enough to cause features of the condition. In some cases, an affected person inherits the mutated gene from an affected parent. In other cases, the mutation occurs for the first time in a person with no family history of the condition. This is called a de novo mutation. When a person with a mutation that causes an autosomal dominant condition has children, each child has a 50% (1 in 2) chance to inherit that mutation. A significant interfamilial (between different families) and intrafamilial (within the same family) variability in expression has been found without any definite correlation to the genetic mutations. This means in one family, a parent might only have one very mild feature of Currarino triad while one of their children might have severe forms of all three features and yet another child might have a mild form of one feature and a severe form of another.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
