<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001901" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1899/donnai-barrow-syndrome">
<Focus>Donnai-Barrow syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1857277</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Faciooculoacousticorenal syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>DBS/FOAR syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Diaphragmatic hernia exomphalos absent corpus callosum hypertelorism myopia sensorineural deafness and proteinuria</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001901-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Donnai-Barrow syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Donnai Barrow syndrome is an inherited disorder that affects many parts of the body. People with this condition generally have characteristic facial features, severe sensorineural hearing loss, vision problems and an absent or underdeveloped corpus callosum (the tissue connecting the left and right halves of the brain). Other features may include diaphragmatic hernia, omphalocele, and/or other abnormalities of the intestine or heart. Affected people often have mild to moderate intellectual disability and developmental delay. Donnai Barrow syndrome is caused by changes (mutations) in the LRP2 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Treatment of this condition is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person but may include hearing aids and/or cochlear implants for hearing loss, corrective lenses for vision problems and surgery for certain physical abnormalities.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001901-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Donnai-Barrow syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Donnai-Barrow syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Donnai-Barrow syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Low-molecular-weight proteinuria 100% Non-acidotic proximal tubulopathy 100% Abnormality of the fontanelles or cranial sutures 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 90% Broad nasal tip 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Depressed nasal bridge 90% High anterior hairline 90% Hypertelorism 90% Infra-orbital crease 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Myopia 90% Proptosis 90% Proteinuria 90% Sensorineural hearing impairment 90% Short nose 90% Low-set ears 75% Broad forehead 50% Congenital diaphragmatic hernia 50% Diaphragmatic eventration 50% Macrocephaly 50% Omphalocele 50% Retinal detachment 50% Umbilical hernia 50% Visual impairment 50% Progressive visual loss 33% Retinal dystrophy 33% Abnormality of female internal genitalia 7.5% Chorioretinal coloboma 7.5% Hypoplasia of the iris 7.5% Intestinal malrotation 7.5% Iris coloboma 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Ventricular septal defect 7.5% Bicornuate uterus 5% Cataract 1% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 11/11 Hypertelorism 12/12 Sensorineural hearing impairment 5/5 Severe Myopia 5/5 Short nose 9/11 Wide anterior fontanel 9/12 Congenital diaphragmatic hernia 9/13 Posteriorly rotated ears 7/11 Iris coloboma 3/6 Omphalocele 6/12 Intestinal malrotation 3/13 Autosomal recessive inheritance - Hypoplasia of midface - Malar flattening - Partial agenesis of the corpus callosum - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
