<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001325" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10779/chronic-lymphocytic-inflammation-with-pontine-perivascular-enhancement-responsive-to-steroids">
<Focus>Chronic lymphocytic inflammation with pontine perivascular enhancement responsive to steroids</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0333386</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>CLIPPERS</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001325-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Chronic lymphocytic inflammation with pontine perivascular enhancement responsive to steroids ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chronic lymphocytic inflammation with pontine perivascular enhancement responsive to steroids (CLIPPERS) is an inflammatory disease of the central nervous system. The main symptoms of CLIPPERS include double vision, nystagmus, uncoordinated movement (ataxia) and facial numbness or tingling. This condition can be treated by suppressing the immune system with steroids.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001325-2" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Chronic lymphocytic inflammation with pontine perivascular enhancement responsive to steroids ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might CLIPPERS be treated? The signs and symptoms of CLIPPERS typically improve after treatment with steroids. Initial treatment may involve a short course of high dose steroids given intravenously, and then oral steroids. Many patients experience a relapse when steroids are tapered off, so it is usually necessary to continue treatment that suppresses the immune system. Long term treatment may include a low dose of oral steroids and another type of immune suppressant, such as methotrexate or rituximab. Because there have been very few patients with CLIPPERS reported in medical journals, the best course of treatment has not yet been determined.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
