<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001557" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7710/congenital-sucrase-isomaltase-deficiency">
<Focus>Congenital sucrase-isomaltase deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1283620</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>CSID</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital sucrose-isomaltase malabsorption</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Sucrose-isomaltase malabsorption, congenital</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Disaccharide intolerance, 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Sucrose intolerance congenital</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001557-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Congenital sucrase-isomaltase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Congenital sucrase-isomaltase deficiency (CSID) is a genetic condition that affects a person&apos;s ability to digest certain sugars. People with this condition cannot break down the sugars sucrose (a sugar found in fruits, and also known as table sugar) and maltose (the sugar found in grains). CSID usually becomes apparent after an infant begins to consume fruits, juices, and grains. After ingestion of sucrose or maltose, an affected child will typically experience stomach cramps, bloating, excess gas production, and diarrhea. These digestive problems can lead to failure to thrive and malnutrition. Most affected children are better able to tolerate sucrose and maltose as they get older. CSID is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern and is caused by mutations in the SI gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001557-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Congenital sucrase-isomaltase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Congenital sucrase-isomaltase deficiency? Affected infants usually develop symptoms soon after they first ingest sucrose, which is found in modified milk formulas, fruits, or starches. Symptoms may include explosive, watery diarrhea resulting in abnormally low levels of body fluids (dehydration), abdominal swelling (distension), and/or abdominal discomfort. In addition, some affected infants may experience malnutrition, resulting from malabsorption of essential nutrients, and/or failure to thrive, resulting from nutritional deficiencies. In some cases, individuals may exhibit irritability; colic; abrasion and/or irritation (excoriation) of the skin on the buttocks as a result of prolonged diarrhea episodes; and/or vomiting. Symptoms of this disorder vary among affected individuals, but are usually more severe in infants and young children than in adults. Symptoms exhibited in infants and young children are usually more pronounced than those of the affected adults because the diet of younger individuals often includes a higher carbohydrate intake. In addition, the time it takes for intestinal digestion is less in infants or young children. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Congenital sucrase-isomaltase deficiency. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Diarrhea - Malabsorption - Nephrolithiasis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001557-3" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Congenital sucrase-isomaltase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is congenital sucrase-isomaltase deficiency (CSID) diagnosed? CSID can be diagnosed through clinical evaluation, detailed patient history, and tolerance lab tests. Blood tests can be done to look for a flat serum glucose curve after patients are given a dose of sucrose. In addition, blood and urine samples may test positive for sucrose, maltose, or palatinose (a form of maltose) if used during tolerance testing. The feces may also show sucrose, glucose, and fructose, and an acid pH level of below 5.0 or 6.0.  CSID can be confirmed by taking a small sample of tissue (biopsy) from the small intestine and measuring the activity of the enzyme called sucrase-isomaltase. Other tests may include a sucrose hydrogen breath test in which an abnormally high level of hydrogen will be detected in the breath of an affected individual after sucrose ingestion.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001557-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Congenital sucrase-isomaltase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might congenital sucrase-isomaltase deficiency (CSID) be treated? CSID is typically treated by modifying a person&apos;s diet to reduce the amount of sucrose. Because many foods contain sucrose and other complex sugars, it can be difficult to completely remove sucrase from the diet. Sucraid is an oral medication containing the enzyme that does not work properly in people with this condition. By taking this medication, those with CSID can eat sucrose-containing foods because this enzyme will break down sucrose. This medication must be taken with each meal or snack.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
