<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001791" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5576/denys-drash-syndrome">
<Focus>Denys-Drash syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0950121</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Drash syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Wilms tumor and pseudohermaphroditism</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Nephropathy, wilms tumor, and genital anomalies</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pseudohermaphroditism, nephron disorder and Wilms' tumor</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Nephropathy associated with male pseudohermaphroditism and Wilms' tumor</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001791-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Denys-Drash syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Denys-Drash syndrome is a condition that affects the kidneys and genitalia. Kidney disease typically begins in the first few months of life, often leading to kidney failure in childhood. In addition, up to 90 percent of people with this condition develop a rare form of kidney cancer known as Wilms tumor. Males with Denys-Drash syndrome have gonadal dysgenesis, a condition in which the external genitalia do not look clearly male or clearly female (ambiguous genitalia) or the genitalia appear to be completely female. The testes are also undescended, meaning that they remain in the pelvis, abdomen, or groin. Affected females usually have normal genitalia. For this reason, females with this condition may be diagnosed with isolated nephrotic syndrome. Denys-Drash syndrome is caused by mutations in the WT1 gene. This condition is inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern, which means one copy of the altered gene in each cell is sufficient to cause the disorder. However, most cases result from new mutations in the gene and occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001791-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Denys-Drash syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Denys-Drash syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Denys-Drash syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Male pseudohermaphroditism 90% Nephroblastoma (Wilms tumor) 90% Nephropathy 90% Nephrotic syndrome 90% Proteinuria 90% Hypertension 50% Gonadal dysgenesis 7.5% Ambiguous genitalia, female - Ambiguous genitalia, male - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Congenital diaphragmatic hernia - Diffuse mesangial sclerosis - Focal segmental glomerulosclerosis - Gonadal tissue inappropriate for external genitalia or chromosomal sex - Ovarian gonadoblastoma - Somatic mutation - Stage 5 chronic kidney disease - True hermaphroditism - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001791-3" qtype="causes">What causes Denys-Drash syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Denys-Drash syndrome? Denys-Drash syndrome is caused by mutations in the WT1 gene. This gene provides instructions for making a protein (the WT1 protein) that regulates the activity of other genes by attaching (binding) to specific regions of DNA. The WT1 protein plays a role in the development of the kidneys and gonads (ovaries in females and testes in males) before birth. The WT1 gene mutations that cause Denys-Drash syndrome lead to the production of an abnormal protein that cannot bind to DNA. As a result, the activity of certain genes is unregulated, which impairs the development of the kidneys and reproductive organs. Abnormal development of these organs leads to diffuse glomerulosclerosis (where scar tissue forms throughout glomeruli, the tiny blood vessels in the kidney that filter waste from blood) and gonadal dysgenesis, which are characteristic features of Denys-Drash syndrome. The abnormal gene activity caused by the loss of normal WT1 protein also increases the risk of developing Wilms tumor in affected individuals.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001791-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Denys-Drash syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is Denys-Drash syndrome inherited? Denys-Drash syndrome is inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern, which means one copy of the altered gene in each cell is sufficient to cause the disorder. Most cases of Denys-Drash syndrome result from new (de novo) mutations in the gene that occur during the formation of reproductive cells (eggs or sperm) or in early embryonic development. These cases occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
