<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001882" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10983/disseminated-superficial-actinic-porokeratosis">
<Focus>Disseminated superficial actinic porokeratosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265970</CUI>
			<CUI>C1442958</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>DSAP</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001882-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Disseminated superficial actinic porokeratosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Disseminated superficial actinic porokeratosis (DSAP) is a skin condition that causes dry patches. It is characterized by a large number of small, brownish patches with a distinctive border, found most commonly on sun-exposed areas of the skin (particularly the arms and legs). DSAP usually starts during the third or fourth decade of life and rarely affects children. Lesions usually appear in summer and improve or disappear during winter. While it is usually benign (not cancerous), squamous cell carcinoma or Bowens disease may occasionally develop within patches. DSAP may be inherited in an autosomal dominant matter or may occur sporadically (in people with no family history of DSAP). Some cases are caused by a change (mutation) in the MVK or SART3 genes. Treatment is generally not effective long-term but may include sun protection, topical medications, cryotherapy, and/or photodynamic therapy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001882-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Disseminated superficial actinic porokeratosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Disseminated superficial actinic porokeratosis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Disseminated superficial actinic porokeratosis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the skin 90% Hyperkeratosis 90% Hypohidrosis 90% Cutaneous photosensitivity 50% Pruritus 50% Neoplasm of the skin 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
