<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001552" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9900/congenital-pulmonary-lymphangiectasia">
<Focus>Congenital pulmonary lymphangiectasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1849554</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>CPL</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lymphangiomatosis pulmonary</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pulmonary cystic lymphangiectasis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lymphangiectasia pulmonary congenital</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001552-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Congenital pulmonary lymphangiectasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Congenital pulmonary lymphangiectasia is a rare developmental disorder present from birth that affects the lungs. Infants with this condition have abnormally widened lymphatic vessels within the lungs. The lymphatic system, which helps the immune system protect the body against infection and disease, consists of a network of tubular channels that drain a thin watery fluid known as lymph from different areas of the body into the bloodstream. Lymph, which is made up of proteins, fats and certain white blood cells called lymphocytes, accumulates in the tiny spaces between tissue cells. Infants with congenital pulmonary lymphangiectasia often develop severe, potentially life-threatening, respiratory distress shortly after birth. They may also develop cyanosis, a condition caused by low levels of circulating oxygen in the blood which causes the skin to have a bluish tint. The exact cause of the condition is unknown. Congenital pulmonary lymphangiectasia can occur as a primary or secondary disorder. Primary congenital pulmonary lymphangiectasia can occur as an isolated defect within the lungs or as part of a a generalized form of lymphatic vessel malformation that affects the entire body. Secondary congenital pulmonary lymphangiectasia occurs secondary to another condition, often involving the heart.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001552-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Congenital pulmonary lymphangiectasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Congenital pulmonary lymphangiectasia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Congenital pulmonary lymphangiectasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Acrocyanosis 90% Respiratory insufficiency 90% Abnormality of the pericardium 50% Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease 50% Congestive heart failure 50% Hydrops fetalis 50% Abnormality of the tricuspid valve 7.5% Hepatomegaly 7.5% Pulmonary hypertension 7.5% Splenomegaly 7.5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Bronchodysplasia - Chylothorax - Chylous ascites - Depressed nasal bridge - Edema of the lower limbs - Flat face - Hypertelorism - Malar flattening - Mild postnatal growth retardation - Nonimmune hydrops fetalis - Palpebral edema - Pectus excavatum - Pleural effusion - Polyhydramnios - Pulmonary lymphangiectasia - Recurrent respiratory infections - Variable expressivity - Wide nasal bridge - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
