<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001928" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10763/duane-syndrome-type-1">
<Focus>Duane syndrome type 1</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0013261</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Duane retraction syndrome 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>DURS1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Duane syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001928-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Duane syndrome type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Duane syndrome type 1 is the most common type of Duane syndrome, an eye movement disorder that is present at birth. People with Duane syndrome have restricted ability to move the affected eye(s) outward toward the ear (abduction) and/or inward toward the nose (adduction). The different types are distinguished by the eye movements that are most restricted. Duane syndrome type 1 is characterized by absent to very restricted abduction and normal to mildly restricted adduction. The eye opening (palpebral fissure) narrows and the eyeball retracts into the orbit with adduction. With abduction, the reverse occurs. One or both eyes may be affected. The majority of cases are sporadic (not inherited), while about 10% are familial. 70% of affected people do not have any other abnormalities at birth (isolated Duane syndrome).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001928-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Duane syndrome type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Duane syndrome type 1? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Duane syndrome type 1. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Ophthalmoparesis 90% Strabismus 90% Anteverted nares 50% Blepharophimosis 50% Deeply set eye 50% Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 7.5% Abnormal localization of kidney 7.5% Abnormality of the pupil 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the iris 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the radius 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the thumb 7.5% Brachydactyly syndrome 7.5% Chorioretinal coloboma 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% External ear malformation 7.5% Hearing impairment 7.5% Heterochromia iridis 7.5% Microcephaly 7.5% Nystagmus 7.5% Optic atrophy 7.5% Ptosis 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Short neck 7.5% Talipes 7.5% Visual impairment 7.5% Wide nasal bridge 7.5% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Congenital strabismus - Duane anomaly - Impaired convergence - Impaired ocular abduction - Impaired ocular adduction - Palpebral fissure narrowing on adduction - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001928-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Duane syndrome type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Duane syndrome type 1 be treated? Management of Duane syndrome is mainly supportive. It may involve treatment of amblyopia (&quot;lazy eye&quot;); wearing glasses or contact lenses; the use of prisms to correct for abnormal head posture; or possible eye muscle surgery. The majority of people with Duane syndrome do not need surgery. However, surgery may be indicated if necessary to reduce severe misalignment of the eyes (strabismus); improve an unacceptable head position; treat a significant upshoot or downshoot; or fix displacement of the eyeball within the orbit (enophthalmos). Unfortunately, surgery does not restore function to the affected nerve and muscle, and no surgical technique has been completely successful in eliminating the abnormal eye movements. Surgery for Duane syndrome usually involves adjusting the other eye muscles to compensate and allow for better eye alignment. While it cannot fix the underlying problem, it can substantially improve signs or symptoms. Some surgical procedures or combinations of procedures may be successful in improving or eliminating head turns and strabismus.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
