<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001664" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6213/cri-du-chat-syndrome">
<Focus>Cri du chat syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0010314</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Cat cry syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>5p minus syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chromosome 5p deletion syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>5p- syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Monosomy 5p</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001664-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Cri du chat syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cri du chat syndrome, also known as 5p- (5p minus) syndrome or cat cry syndrome, is a genetic condition that is caused by the deletion of genetic material on the small arm (the p arm) of chromosome 5. Infants with this condition often have a high-pitched cry that sounds like that of a cat. The disorder is characterized by intellectual disability and delayed development, small head size, low birth weight, weak muscle tone in infancy, and distinctive facial features. While cri du chat syndrome is a genetic condition, most cases are not inherited.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001664-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Cri du chat syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Cri du chat syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Cri du chat syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of chromosome segregation 90% Abnormality of the voice 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Epicanthus 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Microcephaly 90% Muscular hypotonia 90% Round face 90% Wide nasal bridge 90% Abnormality of the palate 50% Hypertelorism 50% Intrauterine growth retardation 50% Scoliosis 50% Short neck 50% Short palm 50% Short stature 50% Abnormality of bone mineral density 7.5% Finger syndactyly 7.5% Hernia of the abdominal wall 7.5% Joint hypermobility 7.5% Preauricular skin tag 7.5% Recurrent fractures 7.5% Abnormality of cardiovascular system morphology - Abnormality of the kidney - Abnormality of the pinna - Aggressive behavior - Anterior open-bite malocclusion - Anxiety - Autism - Bifid uvula - Cat cry - Cataract - Conspicuously happy disposition - Cryptorchidism - Delayed speech and language development - Diastasis recti - Difficulty walking - Downturned corners of mouth - Echolalia - Facial asymmetry - Facial grimacing - Feeding difficulties in infancy - Functional respiratory abnormality - Gastroesophageal reflux - Growth delay - Hearing impairment - High axial triradius - High palate - Hyperactivity - Hyperacusis - Hypertonia - Hypospadias - Inguinal hernia - Intellectual disability - Long face - Low-set ears - Microretrognathia - Myopia - Narrow face - Neonatal hypotonia - Oppositional defiant disorder - Optic atrophy - Oral cleft - Overfriendliness - Pes planus - Premature graying of hair - Prominent supraorbital ridges - Recurrent infections in infancy and early childhood - Self-mutilation - Short attention span - Short metacarpal - Short metatarsal - Short philtrum - Single transverse palmar crease - Small for gestational age - Sporadic - Stenosis of the external auditory canal - Stereotypic behavior - Strabismus - Syndactyly - Thick lower lip vermilion - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001664-3" qtype="causes">What causes Cri du chat syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes cri du chat syndrome? Cri du chat syndrome is caused by a deletion of the end of the short (p) arm of chromosome 5. This chromosomal change is written as 5p-. The size of the deletion varies among affected individuals but studies suggest that larger deletions tend to result in more severe intellectual disability and developmental delay than smaller deletions. The signs and symptoms of cri du chat syndrome are probably related to the loss of multiple genes on the short arm of chromosome 5. Researchers believe that the loss of a specific gene, CTNND2, is associated with severe intellectual disability in some people with this condition. They are working to determine how the loss of other genes in this region contributes to the characteristic features of cri du chat syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001664-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Cri du chat syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is cri du chat syndrome inherited? Most cases of cri du chat syndrome are not inherited. The deletion occurs most often as a random event during the formation of reproductive cells (eggs or sperm) or in early fetal development. Most affected individuals do not have a history of the disorder in their family.  About 10 percent of people with cri du chat syndrome inherit the chromosome abnormality from an unaffected parent. In these cases, the parent carries a chromosomal rearrangement called a balanced translocation, in which no genetic material is gained or lost. Balanced translocations  usually do not cause any health problems; however, they can become unbalanced as they are passed to the next generation. Children who inherit an unbalanced translocation can have a chromosomal rearrangement with extra or missing genetic material. Individuals with cri du chat syndrome who inherit an unbalanced translocation are missing genetic material from the short arm of chromosome 5. This results in the intellectual disability and other health problems characteristic of the disorder.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001664-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Cri du chat syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might cri du chat syndrome be treated? While there is no specific treatment available for cri du chat syndrome, early intervention is recommended in the areas of physical therapy (achieving physical and motor milestones such as sitting and standing up), communication (speech therapy, sign language instruction), behavioral modification (for hyperactivity, short attention span, aggression), and learning (special education). Because symptoms may vary from individual to individual, we recommend discussing these options with a health care professional to develop a personalized plan for therapy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
