<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001104" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9194/charcot-marie-tooth-disease-type-2f">
<Focus>Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0040435</CUI>
			<CUI>C1847823</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>CMT 2F</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease, axonal, Type 2F</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease, neuronal, Type 2F</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Charcot Marie Tooth disease type 2F</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Charcot-Marie-Tooth neuropathy, type 2F</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001104-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F ?</Question>
			<Answer>Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F (CMT2F) is a genetic disorder of the peripheral nerves. The subtypes of CMT type 2 (including type 2F) have similar features and are distinguished only by their disease-causing genes. Signs and symptoms usually begin between the ages of 5 and 25 and typically include slowly progressive weakness and atrophy of distal muscles in the feet and/or hands, usually associated with decreased tendon reflexes and mild or no sensory loss. Nerve conduction velocities are usually normal or near-normal. CMT2F is caused by mutations in the HSPB1 gene and is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Management may include occupational and physical therapy; special shoes; surgery as needed; mobility aids; and other supportive treatments.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001104-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F? The subtypes of Charcot-Marie-Tooth type 2, including type 2F, have similar signs and symptoms. Affected individuals usually become symptomatic between the ages of 5 and 25, though onset can range from infancy to after the third decade of life. The most common first symptom is weakness of the feet and ankles, followed by slowly progressive weakness and atrophy of distal muscles in the feet and/or hands. Individuals often have decreased tendon reflexes and mild or no sensory loss. Adults with CMT2 often have bilateral foot drop, symmetric atrophy of muscles below the knee (stork leg appearance) and absent tendon reflexes in the legs. Mild sensory deficits of position, vibration, pain or temperature may occur in the feet, or sensation may be intact. Pain (especially in the feet) is reported by about 20%-40% of affected individuals. Other features that may be associated with CMT2 in a few individuals include hearing impairment; vocal cord or phrenic nerve involvement (which may result in difficulty with speech or breathing); restless legs; and sleep apnea. CMT2 is progressive over many years, but affected individuals often experience long periods without obvious progression. In some individuals, the condition may be so mild that it goes unrecognized. Affected individuals have a normal life span. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Areflexia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Chronic axonal neuropathy - Decreased motor nerve conduction velocity - Distal amyotrophy - Distal muscle weakness - Distal sensory impairment - Fasciculations - Foot dorsiflexor weakness - Hyporeflexia - Muscle cramps - Pes cavus - Steppage gait - Ulnar claw - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001104-3" qtype="causes">What causes Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F? Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F (CMT2F) is caused by mutations in the HSPB1 gene. This gene provides instructions for making a protein (heat shock protein beta-1) which helps protect cells under adverse conditions. Heat shock proteins appear to be involved in activities such as cell movement, stabilizing the cell&apos;s framework, folding and stabilizing new proteins, repairing damaged proteins, and muscle contraction. Heat shock protein beta-1 is particularly abundant in nerve and muscle cells. In nerve cells, it helps to organize a network of threads that maintain the diameter of axons (neurofilaments), which are needed to transmit nerve impulses efficiently. It is unclear exactly how HSPB1 mutations lead to the axon abnormalities characteristic of CMT2F. Researchers suggest that mutations lead to an altered protein which clusters together and interferes with nerve cell function. Another possibility is that the altered protein disrupts the assembly of neurofilaments, which in turn may impair the transmission of nerve impulses.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001104-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F inherited? Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. This means that only one mutated copy of the gene in each cell is sufficient to cause the condition. Most affected individuals inherit the mutated gene from an affected parent, but in some cases the mutation occurs for the first time in the affected individual (de novo mutation). When an individual with an autosomal dominant condition has children, each child has a 50% (1 in 2) chance to inherit the mutated gene and have the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001104-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is genetic testing available for Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F? Yes. GeneTests lists the names of laboratories that are performing clincial genetic testing for Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F. To view the contact information for these laboratories, click here. Please note that most of the laboratories listed through GeneTests do not accept direct contact from patients and their families; therefore, if you are interested in learning more, you will need to work with a health care provider or a genetics professional.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001104-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2F be treated? Treatment for Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 2 mainly focuses on the specific symptoms present. Affected individuals are often managed by a team of various specialists that includes neurologists, physiatrists, orthopedic surgeons, and physical and occupational therapists. Depending on the individual&apos;s signs and symptoms, the following may be indicated: Special shoes, including those with good ankle support Ankle/foot orthoses (AFO) to correct foot drop and aid with walking Orthopedic surgery to correct severe pes cavus Forearm crutches or canes for stability (fewer than 5% of affected individuals need wheelchairs) Treatment of sleep apnea or restless legs Treatment of pain and depression as needed</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
