<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001816" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6268/dextrocardia-with-situs-inversus">
<Focus>Dextrocardia with situs inversus</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1395317</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Situs inversus totalis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Heterotaxy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001816-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Dextrocardia with situs inversus ?</Question>
			<Answer>Dextrocardia with situs inversus is a condition that is characterized by abnormal positioning of the heart and other internal organs. In people affected by dextrocardia, the tip of the heart points towards the right side of the chest instead of the left side. Situs inversus refers to the mirror-image reversal of the organs in the chest and abdominal cavity. Some affected people have no obvious signs or symptoms. However, a small percentage of people also have congenital heart defects, usually transposition of the great vessels. Dextrocardia with situs inversus can also be associated with primary ciliary dyskinesia (also known as Kartagener syndrome). Treatment typically depends on the heart or physical problems the person may have in addition to dextrocardia with situs inversus.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001816-2" qtype="causes">What causes Dextrocardia with situs inversus ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes dextrocardia with situs inversus? The exact cause of dextrocardia with situs inversus is not known, but the condition results from the abnormal positioning of the internal organs during fetal development. More than 60 known genes are important for the proper positioning and patterning of the organs in the body. However, a specific genetic cause of dextrocardia with situs inversus has not been identified and inheritance patterns have not been confirmed in most cases. Some people have dextrocardia with situs inversus as part of an underlying condition called primary ciliary dyskinesia. Primary ciliary dyskinesia can result from changes (mutations) in several different genes, including the DNAI1 and DNAH5 gene; however, the genetic cause is unknown in many families.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001816-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Dextrocardia with situs inversus inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is dextrocardia with situs inversus inherited? In most cases of dextrocardia with situs inversus, a specific genetic cause has not been identified and inheritance patterns have not been confirmed. However, approximately 25% of affected people have primary ciliary dyskinesia, which is typically inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. This means that to be affected, a person must have a mutation in both copies of the responsible gene in each cell. The parents of an affected person usually each carry one mutated copy of the gene and are referred to as carriers. Carriers typically do not show signs or symptoms of the condition. When two carriers of an autosomal recessive condition have children, each child has a 25% (1 in 4) risk to have the condition, a 50% (1 in 2) risk to be a carrier like each of the parents, and a 25% chance to not have the condition and not be a carrier.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001816-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Dextrocardia with situs inversus ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is dextrocardia with situs inversus diagnosed? In some cases, a diagnosis of dextrocardia with situs inversus is suspected based on the presence of concerning signs and symptoms; however, it is often discovered by chance when an x-ray or ultrasound is performed to investigate a different condition. Computed tomography (CT) scanning is typically the preferred examination to confirm the diagnosis of dextrocardia with situs inversus. Magnetic resonance imaging may be substituted in cases that are associated with congenital heart defects.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001816-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Dextrocardia with situs inversus ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might dextrocardia with situs inversus be treated? Treatment typically depends on the heart or physical problems the person may have in addition to dextrocardia with situs inversus. For example, infants born with congenital heart defects or other organ malformations may require surgery. The management of people affected by Kartagener syndrome typically includes measures to enhance clearance of mucus, prevent respiratory infections, and treat bacterial infections. GeneReviews offers more specific information on the treatment of Kartagener syndrome and other types of primary ciliary dyskinesia. Please click on the link to access this resource.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
