<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001839" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10734/dicer1-related-pleuropulmonary-blastoma-cancer-predisposition-syndrome">
<Focus>DICER1-related pleuropulmonary blastoma cancer predisposition syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0445223</CUI>
			<CUI>C0006826</CUI>
			<CUI>C1266144</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>DICER1-related pleuropulmonary blastoma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>DICER1 syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001839-1" qtype="information">What is (are) DICER1-related pleuropulmonary blastoma cancer predisposition syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>DICER1-related pleuropulmonary blastoma cancer predisposition syndrome causes a moderately increased risk for certain cancers and tumors. The lungs, kidneys, ovaries, and thyroid are the most commonly involved sites. Pleuropulmonary blastoma is the most commonly associated tumor and often occurs in infants and young children. Cysts in the kidneys (cystic nephroma) are also associated with DICER1 syndrome. These cysts typically develop in childhood, but do not usually cause any health problems. Women with DICER1 syndrome are at an increased risk for Sertoli-Leydig tumors of the ovaries. DICER1 syndrome is also associated with goiter (multiple fluid-filled or solid tumors in the thyroid gland). These goiters typically occur in adulthood and most often do not cause symptoms. This syndrome is caused by mutations in the DICER1 gene. It is passed through families in an autosomal dominant fashion. Affected members in the same family can be very differently affected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001839-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of DICER1-related pleuropulmonary blastoma cancer predisposition syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of DICER1-related pleuropulmonary blastoma cancer predisposition syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for DICER1-related pleuropulmonary blastoma cancer predisposition syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Familial predisposition - Medulloblastoma - Pleuropulmonary blastoma - Rhabdomyosarcoma - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
