<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001132" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/412/cheilitis-glandularis">
<Focus>Cheilitis glandularis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0267034</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001132-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Cheilitis glandularis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cheilitis glandularis is a rare inflammatory disorder of the lip. It is mainly characterized by swelling of the lip with hyperplasia of the salivary glands; secretion of a clear, thick mucus; and variable inflammation. Enlargement and chronic exposure of the mucous membrane on the lower lip becomes affected by the environment, leading to erosion, ulceration, crusting, and, occasionally, infection. Cheilitis glandularis is more common in adult males, although cases have been described in women and children. In Caucasians, it is associated with a relatively high incidence of squamous cell carcinoma of the lip. Although there may be a genetic susceptibility, no definitive cause has been established. Treatment may include surgical excision by vermilionectomy (sometimes called a lip shave), but treatment varies for each individual.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001132-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Cheilitis glandularis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Cheilitis glandularis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Cheilitis glandularis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of immune system physiology 90% Abnormality of the salivary glands 90% Thick lower lip vermilion 90% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Cheilitis - Squamous cell carcinoma - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001132-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Cheilitis glandularis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might cheilitis glandularis be treated? The approach to treatment for cheilitis glandularis is typically based on information obtained from histopathologic analysis (microscopic examination of the tissue); the identification of the likely causes responsible for the condition; and attempts to alleviate or eradicate those causes. Given the relatively small number of reported cases of the condition, there is not sufficient or reliable data that exists with regard to medical approaches. Therefore, treatment generally varies accordingly for each individual. For cases attributable to angioedema (swelling similar to hives beneath the skin), an antihistamine may help with temporary reduction of acute, nonpurulent (lacking pus) swelling. Suppurative cases (those with pus present) typically require management with appropriate antimicrobial treatment as determined by culture and sensitivity testing. Concomitant corticosteroid treatment may increase the effectiveness of antimicrobial therapy in cases with nodularity; however, the potential adverse effects of long-term corticosteroid treatment, and because it can promote local fibrosis and scarring, limit its potential use either as an adjunct to antibiotic treatment or as a single therapeutic modality. Topical 5-fluorouracil is useful for treatment of dysplastic actinic cheilitis and to curtail its progression. In conjunction with clinical supervision, it can be prescribed as an alternative to vermilionectomy (sometimes called a lip shave) or as a preventative measure following vermilionectomy. In cheilitis glandularis cases in which a history of chronic sun exposure exists (especially if the individual is fair skinned or the everted lip surface is chronically eroded, ulcerated, or crusted), biopsy is strongly recommended to rule out actinic cheilitis or carcinoma. Surgical excision is typically not necessary when the diagnosis is actinic cheilitis with atypia or only mild dysplasia; however, individuals require ongoing clinical vigilance at regular intervals and instruction in measures to protect the lips from further sun damage. Treatment options for cases of actinic cheilitis with moderate-to-severe dysplasia include surgical stripping or vermilionectomy, cryosurgery or laser surgery, or topical chemotherapy with 5-fluorouracil. Given the potential for recurrence and the risk for development of carcinoma, sun protective measures and regular clinical monitoring should be instituted. In cases in which eversion, extensive fibrosis, and induration have resulted in lip incompetence with functional and cosmetic compromise, chronic pain, and surface disruption, surgical cheiloplasty (lip reduction) may be indicated to restore normal lip architecture and function. Cheiloplasty is also a prophylactic measure for reducing the risk of actinic injury.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
