<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001853" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6460/diffuse-idiopathic-skeletal-hyperostosis">
<Focus>Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0020498</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>DISH Forestier's disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Forestier disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>DISH</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Forestier-Rotes disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ankylosing vertebral hyperostosis with tylosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001853-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH) is a form of degenerative arthritis in which the ligaments (connective tissues that connect bones) around the spine turn into bone. Many people with this condition do not experience any symptoms. When present, the most common features are pain and stiffness of the upper back; however, other symptoms may also develop when bone spurs press on nearby organs or parts of the body. The exact underlying cause of DISH remains unknown, although risk factors such as age, gender, long-term use of certain medications and chronic health conditions have been identified. Treatment for DISH depends on many factors including the signs and symptoms present in each person and the severity of the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001853-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis? Many people affected by diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH) have no signs or symptoms of the condition. When present, symptoms vary but many include: Stiffness which is most noticeable in the morning Pain when pressure is applied to the affected area Loss of range of motion Difficulty swallowing or a hoarse voice Tingling, numbness, and/or weakness in the legs The upper portion of the back (thoracic spine) is the most commonly affected site; however, people with DISH may also experience symptoms in other places such as the heels, ankles, knees, hips, shoulders, elbows, and/or hands. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Osteoarthritis 90% Obesity 50% Palmoplantar keratoderma 50% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Punctate palmar and solar hyperkeratosis - Vertebral hyperostosis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001853-3" qtype="causes">What causes Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis ? The exact underlying cause of diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH) is poorly understood. However, several factors have been associated with an increased risk of developing the condition. For example, conditions that disturb cartilage metabolism (such as diabetes mellitus, acromegaly, or certain inherited connective tissue disorders) may lead to DISH. Long-term use of medications called retinoids (such as isotretinoin) can increase the risk for DISH. Age (being older than age 50) and sex (being male) may also play a role.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001853-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis diagnosed? A diagnosis of diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH) is often suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. X-rays may then be ordered to confirm the diagnosis. In some cases, a computed tomography (CT scan) and/or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) may also be ordered to rule out other conditions that cause similar features.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001853-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis be treated? Treatment of diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH) is focused on the signs and symptoms present in each person. For example, pain caused by DISH is often treated with pain relievers, such as acetaminophen (Tylenol, others) or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), such as ibuprofen (Advil, Motrin, others). Affected people with severe pain may be treated with corticosteroid injections. Physical therapy and/or exercise may reduce the stiffness associated with DISH and can help increase range of motion in the joints. In rare cases, surgery may be necessary if severe complications develop. For example, people who experience difficulty swallowing may need surgery to remove the bone spurs in the neck. How might severe diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH) be treated? Although diffuse idiopathic skeletal hyperostosis (DISH) affects 25% of men and 15% of women over the age of 50 years old, many affected people do not have symptoms. However some people with DISH have stiffness and pain, most commonly in the spinal region or back.  In rare cases the joint stiffness and pain is severe and the areas of the spine affected by DISH may have very limited movement. Knees, hips, hands and other joints may also be affected, more commonly in the more severe cases. Therapy for DISH is based on symptoms. In general, physical therapy, analgesics, sedation, anti-inflammatory drugs, and muscle relaxants have all been successful in managing the majority of patients with DISH. Even though few studies have focused on indications for surgery, it is generally accepted that surgery is indicated for patients with severe symptoms (such as airway obstruction and/or dysphagia) in whom conservative approach has failed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
