<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001666" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8683/crigler-najjar-syndrome-type-2">
<Focus>Crigler Najjar syndrome, type 2</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0796083</CUI>
			<CUI>C2931132</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Crigler-Najjar syndrome, type II</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001666-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Crigler Najjar syndrome, type 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Crigler Najjar syndrome, type 2 is caused by mutations in the UGT1A1 gene. The gene mutation causes the body to be unable to make adequate enzyme to convert bilirubin into a form that can easily be removed from the body. Without this enzyme, bilirubin can build up in the body and lead to extraordinarily yellow skin and eyes (jaundice). This condition is less severe than the type 1 form, however the severity of type II can vary greatly. Almost all patients with Crigler Najjar syndrome, type 2 develop normally, but there is a risk for some neurologic damage from kernicterus (bilirubin accumulation in the brain). In general people with type 2 Crigler Najjar syndrome have serum bilirubin levels ranging from 20 to 45 mg/dL. Phenobarbital treatment is the standard therapy for this condition and can often help to drastically reduce the bilirubin levels.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001666-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Crigler Najjar syndrome, type 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Crigler Najjar syndrome, type 2? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Crigler Najjar syndrome, type 2. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the liver 90% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Jaundice - Unconjugated hyperbilirubinemia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001666-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Crigler Najjar syndrome, type 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Crigler Najjar syndrome, type 2 be treated? Treatment for Crigler Najjar syndrome, type 2 is based on trying to reduce bilirubin levels. As a result it is commonly treated with aggressive phototherapy and phenobarbitol. For severe disease, calcium gluconate, intravenous fluids, and albumin may be recommended. Severely affected patients have been treated with plasmapheresis and even liver transplantation. These options may be most relevant for individuals with the more severe type I disease. In type II disease, much of the literature supports that long-term reduction in serum bilirubin levels can be achieved with continued administration of phenobarbital. We recommend that you continue to work closely with your primary health care provider in monitoring your bilirubin levels and the effectiveness of the prescribed therapy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
