<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001404" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6124/coffin-siris-syndrome">
<Focus>Coffin-Siris syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265338</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Fifth digit syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Intellectual disability with absent fifth fingernail and terminal phalanx</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001404-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Coffin-Siris syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Coffin-Siris syndrome is a genetic condition that causes variable degrees of learning disability, developmental delays, underdeveloped pinky toenails or fingernails, and distinct facial features. It can be caused by a change (mutation) in any of several genes including the ARID1A, ARID1B, SMARCA4, SMARCB1, or SMARCE1 genes. Coffin-Siris syndrome follows an autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance, however it usually occurs for the first time in a family due to a new mutation. Occupational, physical, and/or speech therapy can help affected individuals reach their full potential.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001404-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Coffin-Siris syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Coffin-Siris syndrome? The signs and symptoms of Coffin-Siris syndrome vary. More commonly described symptoms include: Mild to severe intellectual disability Mild to severe speech delay Mild to severe delay in motor skills, such as sitting and walking Underdeveloped fingertips or toes Missing pinky fingernails or toenails Distinctive facial features, such as a wide mouth, thick lips, thick eyelashes and brows, wide nose, and flat nasal bridge Extra hair growth on the face and body Sparse scalp hair Other symptoms that have been described in infants and children with Coffin-Siris syndrome include: Small head size Frequent respiratory infections in infancy Feeding difficulty in infancy Failure to thrive  Short stature Low muscle tone Loose joints Eye abnormalities Heart abnormalities Brain abnormalities Kidney abnormalities The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Coffin-Siris syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the eyelashes 90% Abnormality of the teeth 90% Anonychia 90% Coarse facial features 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Feeding difficulties in infancy 90% Hypertrichosis 90% Microcephaly 90% Muscular hypotonia 90% Short distal phalanx of finger 90% Short stature 90% Slow-growing hair 90% Thick eyebrow 90% Thick lower lip vermilion 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the cerebellum 50% Cryptorchidism 50% Dandy-Walker malformation 50% Depressed nasal bridge 50% Depressed nasal ridge 50% Elbow dislocation 50% Hearing impairment 50% Intrauterine growth retardation 50% Joint hypermobility 50% Nystagmus 50% Patellar aplasia 50% Recurrent respiratory infections 50% Scoliosis 50% Seizures 50% Strabismus 50% Wide mouth 50% Abnormal localization of kidney 7.5% Abnormality of the clavicle 7.5% Abnormality of the hip bone 7.5% Abnormality of the intervertebral disk 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 7.5% Aplastic/hypoplastic toenail 7.5% Cataract 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Congenital diaphragmatic hernia 7.5% Cutis marmorata 7.5% Epicanthus 7.5% Kyphosis 7.5% Lacrimation abnormality 7.5% Ptosis 7.5% Renal hypoplasia/aplasia 7.5% Short philtrum 7.5% Single transverse palmar crease 7.5% Spina bifida occulta 7.5% Aggressive behavior - Aplasia of the uterus - Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the patella - Astigmatism - Atria septal defect - Autistic behavior - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Broad nasal tip - Choanal atresia - Coxa valga - Delayed eruption of teeth - Delayed skeletal maturation - Dislocated radial head - Duodenal ulcer - Ectopic kidney - Facial hypertrichosis - Gastric ulcer - Hemangioma - High palate - Hydronephrosis - Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum - Hypoplastic fifth fingernail - Hypospadias - Hypotelorism - Inguinal hernia - Intellectual disability - Intestinal malrotation - Intussusception - Joint laxity - Long eyelashes - Lumbosacral hirsutism - Myopia - Partial agenesis of the corpus callosum - Patent ductus arteriosus - Postnatal growth retardation - Preauricular skin tag - Renal hypoplasia - Sacral dimple - Severe expressive language delay - Short distal phalanx of the 5th finger - Short distal phalanx of the 5th toe - Short sternum - Sparse scalp hair - Tetralogy of Fallot - Umbilical hernia - Ventricular septal defect - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001404-3" qtype="causes">What causes Coffin-Siris syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Coffin-Siris syndrome? Coffin-Siris syndrome is caused by a change (mutation) in either the ARID1A, ARID1B, SMARCA4, SMARCB1, or SMARCE1 gene. Exactly how these gene mutations result in the symptoms of Coffin-Siris syndrome is not known, however it is thought that the mutations affect how genetic material is packaged in the cell. Coffin-Siris syndrome is an autosomal dominant condition; as only one gene mutation is needed to cause the syndrome. It usually occurs for the first time in a family due to a new mutation.  In some cases, no genetic mutation can be identified and the cause of Coffin-Siris syndrome in the family remains unknown.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001404-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Coffin-Siris syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Coffin-Siris syndrome diagnosed? Diagnosis of Coffin-Siris syndrome is largely based upon the presence or absence of common signs and symptoms in the individual. While formal diagnostic criteria have not been established, most individuals with a clinical diagnosis of Coffin-Siris syndrome have certain features in common. You can find detailed information on this topic at the following link to GeneReviews. http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK131811/#coffin-siris.Diagnosis Genetic testing may also be used to diagnose or confirm cases of Coffin-Siris syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001404-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Coffin-Siris syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Coffin-Siris syndrome be treated? People with Coffin-Siris syndrome may benefit from occupational, physical, and speech therapy. Developmental pediatricians may be helpful in recommending and coordinating therapeutic and educational interventions. Additional specialty care may be needed depending on the symptoms in the individual, such as by gastrointestinal, eye, kidney, heart, and hearing specialists.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
