<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001478" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9486/congenital-anosmia">
<Focus>Congenital anosmia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0393778</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Isolated congenital anosmia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>ANIC</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001478-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Congenital anosmia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Congenital anosmia is a very rare condition in which people are born with a lifelong inability to smell. It may occur as an isolated abnormality (no additional symptoms) or be associated with a specific genetic disorder (such as Kallmann syndrome and congenital insensitivity to pain). Scientists suspect that isolated congenital anosmia occurs due to abnormal development of the olfactory system (the sensory system used for sense of smell) prior to birth. This may include abnormalities of the nasal cavity, disruptions in the pathway that carries information from the nose to the brain, and/or malformations of the portion of the brain that processes sense of smell. Unfortunately, there is currently no known cure or treatment for congenital anosmia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001478-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Congenital anosmia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Congenital anosmia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Congenital anosmia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Anosmia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001478-3" qtype="causes">What causes Congenital anosmia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes congenital anosmia? Congenital anosmia may occur as an isolated abnormality or be associated with specific genetic disorders (such as Kallmann syndrome and congenital insensitivity to pain). Most cases of isolated congenital anosmia (not associated with additional symptoms) occur sporadically in people with no family history of the condition. In these people, the exact underlying cause of the condition is unknown. Most likely, there is more than one cause. Scientists suspect that the condition occurs due to abnormal development of the olfactory system (the sensory system used for sense of smell) prior to birth. This may include abnormalities of the nasal cavity, disruptions in the pathway that carries information from the nose to the brain, and/or malformations of the portion of the brain that processes sense of smell. Rarely, isolated congenital anosmia can affect more than one family member. This suggests that there may be a genetic component in some cases. One study found that some people affected by isolated congenital anosmia have changes (mutations) in PROKR2 or PROK2, two genes that have previously been reported in people with Kallmann syndrome (an inherited condition associated with congenital anosmia and other symptoms). To date, no other disease-causing genes have been identified.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001478-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Congenital anosmia inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is congenital anosmia inherited? Most cases of isolated congenital anosmia (not associated with additional symptoms) occur sporadically in people with no family history of the condition. Rarely, more than one family member may be affected. In these families, the condition appears to be inherited in an autosomal dominant manner with reduced penetrance. Congenital anosmia can also by associated with specific genetic disorders such as Kallmann syndrome and congenital insensitivity to pain. In these cases, the inheritance varies based on the associated condition. For example, Kallmann syndrome can be inherited in an autosomal dominant, autosomal recessive or X-linked recessive manner depending on the underlying genetic cause (it can be caused by mutations in several different genes). Congenital insensitivity to pain follows an autosomal recessive pattern of inheritance.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001478-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Congenital anosmia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is congenital anosmia diagnosed? Isolated congenital anosmia (not associated with other symptoms) is a diagnosis of exclusion. This means that the diagnosis is made in people with suspicious signs and symptoms once other conditions that cause similar features have been ruled out. When an affected person has no recollection of ever being able to smell, the following tests may be ordered to support a diagnosis of congenital anosmia: A thorough physical examination and medical history to look for other conditions that may interfere with the sense of smell Smell tests, particularly those that determine the smallest amount of odor that someone can detect Brain Imaging (such as CT scan and MRI scan) as some people with congenital anosmia have malformations in the portion of the brian that processes smells Nasal endoscopy to look for abnormalities of the nasal cavity which may interfere with sense of smell Olfactory nerve testing to evaluate disruptions in the pathway that carries information from the nose to the brain</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001478-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Congenital anosmia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might congenital anosmia be treated? Unfortunately, there is currently no known cure or treatment for congenital anosmia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
