<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001315" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10811/chronic-atypical-neutrophilic-dermatosis-with-lipodystrophy-and-elevated-temperature">
<Focus>Chronic atypical neutrophilic dermatosis with lipodystrophy and elevated temperature</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0023787</CUI>
			<CUI>C1142272</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>CANDLE syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chronic atypical neutrophilic dermatosis-lipodystrophy-elevated temperature syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001315-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Chronic atypical neutrophilic dermatosis with lipodystrophy and elevated temperature ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chronic atypical neutrophilic dermatosis with lipodystrophy and elevated temperature, also known as CANDLE syndrome, is a rare autoinflammatory condition. Signs and symptoms generally develop during the first year of life and may include recurrent fevers, purpura, swollen eyelids, joint pain, contractures, developmental delay and progressive lipodystrophy. CANDLE syndrome is often caused by changes (mutations) in the PSMB8 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. In some cases, the underlying genetic cause is unknown. There is currently no cure for the condition. Treatment is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001315-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Chronic atypical neutrophilic dermatosis with lipodystrophy and elevated temperature ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Chronic atypical neutrophilic dermatosis with lipodystrophy and elevated temperature? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Chronic atypical neutrophilic dermatosis with lipodystrophy and elevated temperature. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of temperature regulation 90% Arthralgia 90% Hepatomegaly 90% Hyperostosis 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Lipoatrophy 90% Skin rash 90% Splenomegaly 90% Clubbing of toes 50% Hyperhidrosis 50% Increased antibody level in blood 50% Lymphadenopathy 50% Muscle weakness 50% Skeletal muscle atrophy 50% Abnormal nasal morphology 7.5% Abnormal pyramidal signs 7.5% Abnormality of the tongue 7.5% Arachnodactyly 7.5% Arrhythmia 7.5% Cardiomegaly 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Congestive heart failure 7.5% Macrotia 7.5% Microcytic anemia 7.5% Respiratory insufficiency 7.5% Thick lower lip vermilion 7.5% Seizures 5% Short stature 5% Adipose tissue loss - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Basal ganglia calcification - Bone pain - Camptodactyly of finger - Clubbing of fingers - Conjunctivitis - Elbow flexion contracture - Elevated erythrocyte sedimentation rate - Elevated hepatic transaminases - Episcleritis - Erythema - Failure to thrive - Flexion contracture of toe - Hyperpigmentation of the skin - Hypertriglyceridemia - Intellectual disability, mild - Large eyes - Lipodystrophy - Long fingers - Macroglossia - Osteopenia - Panniculitis - Prominent nose - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
