<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001416" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6131/cold-urticaria">
<Focus>Cold urticaria</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0221207</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Cold contact urticaria</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Primary idiopathic cold urticaria</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Urticaria idiopathic cold</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001416-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Cold urticaria ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cold urticaria is a condition that affects the skin. Signs and symptoms generally include reddish, itchy welts (hives) and/or swelling when skin is exposed to the cold (i.e. cold weather or swimming in cold water). This rash is usually apparent within 2-5 minutes after exposure and can last for 1-2 hours. The exact cause of cold urticaria is poorly understood in most cases. Rarely, it may be associated with an underlying blood condition or infectious disease. Treatment generally consists of patient education, avoiding exposures that may trigger a reaction, and/or medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001416-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Cold urticaria ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of cold urticaria? The signs and symptoms of cold urticaria and the severity of the condition vary. Affected people generally develop reddish, itchy welts (hives) and/or swelling when skin is exposed to the cold (i.e. cold weather or swimming in cold water). This rash is usually apparent within 2-5 minutes after exposure and lasts for 1-2 hours. Other signs and symptoms may include: Headache Anxiety Tiredness Fainting Heart palpitations Wheezing Joint pain Low blood pressure In very severe cases, exposure to cold could lead to loss of consciousness, shock or even death.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001416-3" qtype="causes">What causes Cold urticaria ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes cold urticaria? In most cases of cold urticaria, the underlying cause is poorly understood. Although the symptoms are triggered by exposure of the skin to the cold (most often when the temperature is lower than 39 degrees Fahrenheit), it is unclear why this exposure leads to such a significant reaction. Rarely, cold urticaria is associated with blood conditions or infectious disease such as cryoglobulinemia, chronic lymphocytic leukaemia, lymphosarcoma, chicken pox, viral hepatitis, and mononucleosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001416-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Cold urticaria inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is cold urticaria inherited? Cold urticaria is not thought to be inherited. Most cases occur sporadically in people with no family history of the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001416-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Cold urticaria ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is cold urticaria diagnosed? A diagnosis of cold urticaria is typically suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. Additional testing can then be ordered to confirm the diagnosis and determine if there are other associated conditions. This generally involves a cold simulation test in which a cold object (such as an ice cube) is applied against the skin of the forearm for 1-5 minutes. In people affected by cold urticaria, a distinct red and swollen rash will generally develop within minutes of exposure. A complete blood count and/or metabolic tests may also be performed to determine associated diseases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001416-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Cold urticaria ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might cold urticaria be treated? The treatment of cold urticaria generally consists of patient education, avoiding scenarios that may trigger a reaction (i.e. cold temperatures, cold water), and/or medications. Prophylactic treatment with high-dose antihistimines may be recommended when exposure to cold is expected and can not be avoided. Additionally, affected people are often told to carry an epinephrine autoinjector due to the increased risk of anaphylaxis. Several other therapies have reportedly been used to treat cold urticaria with varying degrees of success. These include: Leukotriene antagonists Ciclosporin Systemic corticosteroids Dapsone Oral antibiotics Synthetic hormones Danazol</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
