<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001337" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6111/churg-strauss-syndrome">
<Focus>Churg Strauss syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0008728</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>CSS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Allergic granulomatous and angiitis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Allergic angiitis and granulomatosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Allergic granulomatosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Churg-Strauss vasculitis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001337-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Churg Strauss syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Churg Strauss syndrome is a condition characterized by asthma, high levels of eosinophils (a type of white blood cell that helps fight infection), and inflammation of small to medium sized blood vessels (vasculitis). The inflamed vessels can affect various organ systems including the lungs, gastrointestinal tract, skin, heart and nervous system. The exact cause of Churg Strauss syndrome is unknown, but it is thought to be an autoimmune disorder. Treatment may involve the use of glucocorticoids and/or other immunosuppressive therapies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001337-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Churg Strauss syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Churg Strauss syndrome? The specific signs and symptoms of Churg Strauss syndrome (CSS) vary from person to person depending on the organ systems involved. The severity, duration and age of onset also vary. CSS is considered to have three distinct phases - prodromal (allergic), eosinophilic and vasculitic - which don&apos;t always occur sequentially. Some people do not develop all three phases. The prodromal (or allergic) phase is characterized by various allergic reactions. Affected people may develop asthma (including a cough, wheezing, and shortness of breath); hay fever (allergic rhinitis); and/or repeated episodes of sinusitis. This phase can last from months to many years. Most people develop asthma-like symptoms before any other symptoms. The eosinophilic phase is characterized by accumulation of eosinophils (a specific type of white blood cell) in various tissues of the body - especially the lungs, gastrointestinal tract and skin. The vasculitic phase is characterized by widespread inflammation of various blood vessels (vasculitis). Chronic vasculitis can cause narrowing of blood vessels, which can block or slow blood flow to organs. Inflamed blood vessels can also become thin and fragile (potentially rupturing) or develop a bulge (aneurysm). People with CSS often develop nonspecific symptoms including fatigue, fever, weight loss, night sweats, abdominal pain, and/or joint and muscle pain. Neurological symptoms (such as pain, tingling or numbness) are common and depend on the specific nerves involved. About half of affected people develop skin abnormalities due to accumulation of eosinophils in skin tissue. Symptoms of skin involvement may include purplish skin lesions, a rash with hives, and/or small bumps, especially on the elbows. Gastrointestinal involvement may cause various symptoms also. Heart problems may include inflammation of heart tissues and in severe cases, heart failure. The kidneys can also become involved, eventually causing glomerulonephritis. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Churg Strauss syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of eosinophils 90% Asthma 90% Autoimmunity 90% Congestive heart failure 90% Polyneuropathy 90% Pulmonary infiltrates 90% Sinusitis 90% Subcutaneous hemorrhage 90% Urticaria 90% Vasculitis 90% Weight loss 90% Abdominal pain 50% Abnormality of the pericardium 50% Abnormality of the pleura 50% Arthralgia 50% Feeding difficulties in infancy 50% Gait disturbance 50% Hematuria 50% Hypertension 50% Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy 50% Hypopigmented skin patches 50% Nausea and vomiting 50% Skin rash 50% Thrombophlebitis 50% Abnormality of temperature regulation 7.5% Abnormality of the endocardium 7.5% Acrocyanosis 7.5% Arthritis 7.5% Cerebral ischemia 7.5% Coronary artery disease 7.5% Cranial nerve paralysis 7.5% Cutis marmorata 7.5% Glomerulopathy 7.5% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 7.5% Hemoptysis 7.5% Intestinal obstruction 7.5% Malabsorption 7.5% Myalgia 7.5% Myositis 7.5% Nasal polyposis 7.5% Proteinuria 7.5% Pulmonary embolism 7.5% Renal insufficiency 7.5% Respiratory insufficiency 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
