<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001566" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1544/congenitally-corrected-transposition-of-the-great-arteries">
<Focus>Congenitally corrected transposition of the great arteries</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0344616</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Transposition of the great arteries, congenitally corrected</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Transposition of the great vessels, congenitally corrected</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenitally corrected transposition of the great vessels</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001566-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Congenitally corrected transposition of the great arteries ?</Question>
			<Answer>Congenitally corrected transposition of the great arteries is a rare heart defect that occurs when the ventricles and attached valves are switched. As a result, the aorta and the pulmonary artery are connected to the wrong lower heart chambers. Click here to visit MayoClinic.com and view an image of this heart defect. While the oxygen-poor blood still flows to the lungs, and oxygen-rich blood still flows out to nourish the body, other heart problems (such as septal defects, pulmonary stenosis, tricuspid regurgitation, and heart block) are often associated with this defect and require treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001566-2" qtype="causes">What causes Congenitally corrected transposition of the great arteries ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes congenitally corrected transposition of the great arteries? Currently the cause of congenitally corrected transposition of the great arteries is not known. Limited data suggests that air pollutants and hair dye may act as environmental risk factors for this rare defect. Also, having a family history of this heart defect is a risk factor. It has been estimated that the recurrence risk in siblings is around 3% to 5%.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
