<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001454" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10597/complete-androgen-insensitivity-syndrome">
<Focus>Complete androgen insensitivity syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0936016</CUI>
			<CUI>C0237677</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>CAIS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Androgen insensitivity syndrome, complete</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001454-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Complete androgen insensitivity syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complete androgen insensitivity syndrome is a condition that affects sexual development before birth and during puberty. People with this condition are genetically male (one X and one Y chromosome) but do not respond to male hormones at all. As a result, they generally have normal female external genitalia and female breasts. However, they do not have a uterus or cervix so are unable to menstruate or conceive children. Other signs and symptoms may include undescended testes and sparse to absent pubic hair. Gender identity is typically female. Complete androgen insensitivity syndrome is caused by changes (mutations) in the AR gene and is inherited in an X-linked manner. Treatment and gender assignment can be a very complex issue, and must be individualized with each affected person. In general, surgery may be required to remove testes that are located in unusual places and estrogen replacement therapy can be prescribed after puberty.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001454-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Complete androgen insensitivity syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Complete androgen insensitivity syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Complete androgen insensitivity syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal hair quantity 90% Cryptorchidism 90% Decreased fertility 90% Male pseudohermaphroditism 90% Primary amenorrhea 90% Tall stature 90% Hernia of the abdominal wall 50% Reduced bone mineral density 50% Flexion contracture 7.5% Gynecomastia 7.5% Testicular neoplasm 7.5% Tremor 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
