<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001490" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5899/congenital-contractural-arachnodactyly">
<Focus>Congenital contractural arachnodactyly</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0220668</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Beals syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Arachnodactyly, contractural Beals type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Contractures, multiple with arachnodactyly</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ear anomalies-contractures-dysplasia of bone with kyphoscoliosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Beals-Hecht syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001490-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Congenital contractural arachnodactyly ?</Question>
			<Answer>Congenital contractural arachnodactyly (CCA) is a genetic disorder that is typically characterized by tall height; skinny, long limbs; long, skinny fingers and toes (arachnodactyly); multiple joint deformities present at birth (congenital contractures), usually of the elbows, knees, hips, fingers and ankles; &quot;crumpled&quot;-looking ears, and curvature of the spine (kyphoscoliosis). Other features might also be present and vary from person to person. CCA is caused by mutations in a gene called FBN2 gene and is inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern. CCA shares similiar signs and symptoms to Marfan syndrome; however, Marfan syndrome is not caused by mutations in the FBN2 gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001490-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Congenital contractural arachnodactyly ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Congenital contractural arachnodactyly? Congenital contractural arachnodactyly represents a broad spectrum of characteristics. The features are quite variable, both within and between families. The classic form is characterized by a Marfan-like appearance (tall and slender with arm span exceeding height), arachnodactyly (long slender fingers and toes), &apos;crumpled&apos; ears, contractures of major joints from birth (particularly knees, elbows, fingers, toes, and hips), bowed long bones, muscular hypoplasia (underdeveloped muscles), kyphosis/scoliosis, aortic root dilation, and various craniofacial abnormalities (such as micrognathia, high arched palate, scaphocephaly (premature fusion of the sagittal suture of the skull leading to a long, narrow head), brachycephaly (premature fusion of the coronal suture, leading to a short skull), and frontal bossing).  At the most severe end of the spectrum is a rare type with very few reported cases. In addition to the typical skeletal findings (arachnodactyly, joint contractures, scoliosis) and abnormally shaped ears, infants with the severe/lethal form have multiple cardiovascular and gastrointestinal abnormalities. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Congenital contractural arachnodactyly. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the helix 90% Abnormality of the palate 90% Arachnodactyly 90% Camptodactyly of finger 90% Disproportionate tall stature 90% External ear malformation 90% Elbow flexion contracture 86% Knee flexion contracture 81% Crumpled ear 78% Kyphoscoliosis 45% Talipes equinovarus 32% Hip contracture 25% Abnormality of the mitral valve 7.5% Aortic dilatation 7.5% Duodenal stenosis 7.5% Ectopia lentis 7.5% Intestinal malrotation 7.5% Tracheoesophageal fistula 7.5% Adducted thumb - Aortic root dilatation - Atria septal defect - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Bicuspid aortic valve - Brachycephaly - Calf muscle hypoplasia - Congenital kyphoscoliosis - Distal arthrogryposis - Dolichocephaly - Frontal bossing - High palate - Mitral regurgitation - Mitral valve prolapse - Motor delay - Myopia - Osteopenia - Patellar dislocation - Patellar subluxation - Patent ductus arteriosus - Pectus carinatum - Short neck - Ulnar deviation of finger - Ventricular septal defect - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001490-3" qtype="causes">What causes Congenital contractural arachnodactyly ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes congenital contractural arachnodactyly? Congenital contractural arachnodactyly is caused by mutations in the FBN2 gene. The FBN2 gene provides instructions for producing the fibrillin-2 protein. Fibrillin-2 binds to other proteins and molecules to form threadlike filaments called microfibrils. Microfibrils become part of the fibers that provide strength and flexibility to connective tissue. Additionally, microfibrils hold molecules called growth factors and release them at the appropriate time to control the growth and repair of tissues and organs throughout the body. A mutation in the FBN2 gene can reduce the amount and/or quality of fibrillin-2 that is available to form microfibrils. As a result, decreased microfibril formation weakens the elastic fibers and allows growth factors to be released inappropriately, causing tall stature, deformities of the fingers and toes, and other characteristic features of congenital contractural arachnodactyly.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001490-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Congenital contractural arachnodactyly inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is congenital contractural arachnodactyly inherited? This condition is inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern, which means one copy of the altered gene in each cell is sufficient to cause the disorder. In some cases, an affected person inherits the mutation from an affected parent. Other cases result from new mutations in the gene and occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001490-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Congenital contractural arachnodactyly ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might congenital contractural arachnodactyly be treated? Physical therapy for joint contractures helps increase joint mobility and ameliorate the effects of muscle hypoplasia (usually in the calf muscles). In severe cases, surgical release may be necessary. Since the kyphosis/scoliosis tends to be progressive, bracing and/or surgical correction is often needed. Consultation with an orthopedist is encouraged. Other symptoms, if present, should be addressed as they arise and in the standard manner. Regular physician visits should be scheduled to monitor symptom progression and development.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
