<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001811" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10283/desmosterolosis">
<Focus>Desmosterolosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1865596</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001811-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Desmosterolosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Desmosterolosis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Desmosterolosis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 90% Cleft palate 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Hypertonia 90% Intrauterine growth retardation 90% Microcephaly 90% Short stature 90% Abnormality of the ribs 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia involving the nose 50% Depressed nasal bridge 50% Large earlobe 50% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 50% Narrow mouth 50% Nystagmus 50% Seizures 50% Strabismus 50% Ventriculomegaly 50% Abnormality of neuronal migration 7.5% Anomalous pulmonary venous return 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the skin 7.5% Epicanthus 7.5% Frontal bossing 7.5% Hydrocephalus 7.5% Increased bone mineral density 7.5% Intestinal malrotation 7.5% Limb undergrowth 7.5% Macrocephaly 7.5% Patent ductus arteriosus 7.5% Renal hypoplasia/aplasia 7.5% Splenomegaly 7.5% Talipes 7.5% Abnormality of cholesterol metabolism 2/2 Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 2/2 Cleft palate 2/2 Alveolar ridge overgrowth 1/2 Ambiguous genitalia, female 1/2 Ambiguous genitalia, male 1/2 Bilateral talipes equinovarus 1/2 Cupped ear 1/2 Epicanthus 1/2 Frontal bossing 1/2 Generalized osteosclerosis 1/2 Gingival fibromatosis 1/2 Hypoplastic nasal bridge 1/2 Joint contracture of the hand 1/2 Low-set ears 1/2 Macrocephaly 1/2 Microcephaly 1/2 Patent ductus arteriosus 1/2 Posteriorly rotated ears 1/2 Rhizomelia 1/2 Total anomalous pulmonary venous return 1/2 Anteverted nares - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Failure to thrive - Partial agenesis of the corpus callosum - Phenotypic variability - Relative macrocephaly - Short nose - Spasticity - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
