<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001859" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3263/dihydrolipoamide-dehydrogenase-deficiency">
<Focus>Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3492932</CUI>
			<CUI>C0268193</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pyruvate dehydrogenase E3 deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>DLD deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>E3-deficient maple syrup urine disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>E3 deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Maple syrup urine disease, type III</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lipoic acid biosynthesis defects</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pyruvate dehydrogenase deficiency</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001859-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) deficiency is a very rare condition that can vary in age of onset, symptoms and severity. The condition may be characterized by early-onset lactic acidosis and delayed development (most commonly); later-onset neurological dysfunction; or adult-onset isolated liver disease. Signs and symptoms may include lactic acidosis shortly after birth; hypotonia and lethargy in infancy; feeding difficulties; seizures; and various other health issues. Liver problems can range from hepatomegaly to life-threatening liver failure. Symptoms often occur in episodes that may be triggered by illness or other stresses on the body. Many affected infants do not survive the first few years of life; those who survive through early childhood often have growth delay and intellectual disability. Some with onset later in childhood may have neurological dysfunction with normal cognitive development. DLD deficiency is caused by mutations in the DLD gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001859-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency? The signs and symptoms of dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) deficiency can vary widely among affected people. Early-onset DLD deficiency typically appears in early infancy with decreased muscle tone (hypotonia), lethargy, and lactic acidosis. Lactic acidosis can cause nausea, vomiting, severe breathing problems, and an abnormal heartbeat. Symptoms typically occur in episodes that may be triggered by illness, injury, or other stresses on the body. Affected infants often do not survive their initial episode or may die within the first few years of life during a recurrent episode. Children who live beyond the first two to three years often have growth delays and neurological problems such as intellectual disability, spasticity, ataxia, and seizures. However, normal intellect has been reported in a few people with the early-onset form of DLD deficiency. Isolated liver involvement, which can range from hepatomegaly (enlarged liver) to life-threatening liver failure, can also occur in the newborn period, or as late as the 3rd decade of life. A few people with DLD deficiency have become affected later in childhood with ataxia and dystonia, with normal cognitive development. Rarely, affected people have muscle weakness (particularly during exercise) or a weakened heart muscle (cardiomyopathy). The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aminoaciduria 90% Cognitive impairment 50% Gait disturbance 50% Hepatomegaly 50% Microcephaly 50% Muscular hypotonia 50% Hepatic failure 7.5% Hypoglycemia 7.5% Decreased liver function 5% Elevated hepatic transaminases 5% Ataxia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Dystonia - Encephalopathy - Feeding difficulties - Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy - Lactic acidosis - Lethargy - Metabolic acidosis - Seizures - Variable expressivity - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001859-3" qtype="causes">What causes Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency? Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) deficiency is caused by changes (mutations) in the DLD gene. This gene gives the body instructions to make an enzyme called dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD). DLD is one part of 3 different groups of enzymes that work together (enzyme complexes). These enzyme complexes are involved in breaking down amino acids commonly found in protein-rich foods, and in other reactions that help to convert energy from food into a form that our cells can use. Mutations in the DLD gene impair the function of DLD, preventing the 3 enzyme complexes from functioning properly. This causes a build-up of molecules that are normally broken down, which in turn leads to tissue damage, lactic acidosis and other chemical imbalances. The brain is especially sensitive to the buildup of molecules and lack of cellular energy, which is why there are neurological problems associated with DLD deficiency.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001859-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency inherited? Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) deficiency is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. This means that a person must have a mutation in both copies of the responsible gene in each cell to be affected. The parents of an affected person usually each carry one mutated copy of the gene and are referred to as carriers. Carriers typically do not have any signs or symptoms of the condition. When two carriers of an autosomal recessive condition have children, each child has a 25% (1 in 4) risk to be affected, a 50% (1 in 2) risk to be a carrier like each of the parents, and a 25% to be unaffected and not be a carrier.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001859-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase deficiency be treated? There are currently no consensus recommendations for the management of dihydrolipoamide dehydrogenase (DLD) deficiency. Management can be hard because various metabolic pathways are affected and 3 enzyme complexes are involved. Deficiencies in enzyme pathways vary depending on the specific mutation(s) each affected person has. Unfortunately, the treatments that have been attempted in children with the early-onset neurologic form do not appear to significantly alter the course of the disease. Even with treatment, children often do not survive infancy or have varying degrees of chronic neurologic impairment if they survive the initial episode. Depending on individual enzyme complex deficiencies, treatment may involve certain dietary restrictions or certain diets; use of medical foods; and/or supplementation of specific amino acids or other substances. There is limited data for the chronic management of people with the primarily hepatic (liver-related) form of the disease. Management typically involves supportive therapy during times of acute liver injury or failure, and may include nutritional support; IV glucose for hypoglycemia; correction of metabolic acidosis; correction of coagulopathy; and avoidance of liver-toxic medications. More detailed information about the management of DLD deficiency can be viewed on the GeneReviews Web site. GeneReviews is intended for use by genetics professionals. Those not familiar with the principles discussed on the GeneReviews Web site are encouraged to speak with a genetics professional or other healthcare provider regarding information of interest.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
