<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001318" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7121/chronic-fatigue-syndrome">
<Focus>Chronic fatigue syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0015674</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Systemic exertion intolerance disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chronic fatigue immune dysfunction syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001318-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Chronic fatigue syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chronic fatigue syndrome, also known as systemic exertion intolerance disease, is a condition that causes extreme, long-lasting fatigue which can limit the ability to participate in ordinary, daily activities.  It generally occurs in young adults between the ages of 20 and 40 and is twice as common in women. The main symptom is disabling fatigue that does not improve with rest. Other signs and symptoms may include muscle pain; joint pain; concentration and memory problems; headaches; sleep problems; fever; sore throat; and/or tender lymph nodes. The cause of chronic fatigue syndrome is not known yet. Some researchers have proposed that this condition is caused by viral infections or by immunological, hormonal or mental or psychiatric problems, but none have been proved. It is also believed that there may be a genetic predisposition for this condition and stress-related events act as triggers. Because the symptoms are similar to many conditions that need to be ruled out, the diagnosis make take some time to be made and patients are frequently misunderstood. Those who are affected are typically highly functioning individuals who are &quot;struck down&quot; with this disease. There is still no cure for this condition but there are several clinical trials. Current treatment consists of cognitive and/or behavioral therapy and focuses on improving symptoms and may include medications to treat pain, sleep disorders and other associated problems. There is significant controversy and debate in the medical literature about the relationship between myalgic encephalomyelitis and chronic fatigue syndrome. Unfortunately there is no consensus on nomenclature or classification for these disorders, and different countries, organizations, and researchers continue to use different names to describe these conditions. Until a global consensus is reached on how to name and classify these disorders, confusion will persist.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001318-2" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Chronic fatigue syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is chronic fatigue syndrome diagnosed? No specific diagnostic tests are available. Though there is no definitive diagnostic test, the diagnosis can be made if the patient has a typical history, and no abnormality can be detected on the exam or in the screening tests.    The Committee on the Diagnostic Criteria for Myalgic Encephalomyelitis/Chronic Fatigue Syndrome, The Board of Select Populations and the Institute of Medicine proposed a diagnosis criteria which requires that the patient have the following three symptoms: 1. A chronic fatigue that interferes with the daily activities and work,  which is often profound, is of new or definite onset (not lifelong), is not the result of ongoing excessive exertion or other medical conditions, and is not greatly alleviated by rest. 2. Post-exertional malaise. 3. Unrefreshing sleep. At least one of the two following symptoms is also required: 1. Cognitive impairment (imparirment of short memory or concentration). 2. Orthostatic intolerance (Onset of symptoms when standing upright that are improved by lying back down). Other  symptoms include post exertion illness lasting more than 24 hours, muscle pain, pain in the joints, headaces, tender lymph nodes and sore throat.   These symptoms should have persisted or recurred during 6 or more consecutive months of illness and they cannot have first appeared before the fatigue. The following tests are expected to be normal in patients with chronic fatigue syndrome:  Complete blood count with differential count;  Chemistry screen;  Thyroid stimulating hormone level;  Other tests based in the patients symptoms like immunologic tests or serologic tests.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001318-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Chronic fatigue syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might chronic fatigue syndrome be treated? Treatment options for chronic fatigue syndrome (CFS) are limited.[9440] Treatment is largely supportive and is focused on the specific symptoms present in each individual. In most cases, symptoms of CFS lessen over time. Many therapies have been tried, but only cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) and graded exercise therapy reportedly appear to produce meaningful benefit. CBT typically involves a series of one-hour sessions designed to alter beliefs and behaviors that might delay recovery. Graded exercise therapy can be beneficial because prolonged lack of exercise may worsen the symptoms of the condition and should be discouraged.[9440] Gradual introduction of regular aerobic exercise, such as walking, swimming, cycling, or jogging, under close medical supervision may reduce fatigue and improve physical function. The goal is to have 30 minutes of light exercise five times a week. To avoid overexertion it is recommended to set a target heart rate range, generally &lt;100 beats per minute. Graded exercise should be always supervised by a physical therapist or exercise therapist. In some studies, women with this condition were found to have low normal fitness on treadmill testing with no indication of heart or lung problems. Maximal testing did not result in worse fatigue or other symptoms. Because many people who have CFS are also depressed, treating the depression can make it easier to cope with the problems associated with CFS. Low doses of some antidepressants may help improve sleep and relieve pain.[6269] A number of medications, special diets and vitamin supplements have been evaluated in individuals with CFS, but none have been proven effective. Although there have been a number of viruses that were initially reported to cause CFS, additional studies have not proven this.[9440] Trials of antiviral agents have been ineffective in relieving the symptoms of CFS. Several clinical trials aiming to find effective treatment are currently ongoing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
