<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001657" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10282/craniosynostosis-mental-retardation-syndrome-of-lin-and-gettig">
<Focus>Craniosynostosis-mental retardation syndrome of Lin and Gettig</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0025362</CUI>
			<CUI>C0010278</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001657-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Craniosynostosis-mental retardation syndrome of Lin and Gettig ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Craniosynostosis-mental retardation syndrome of Lin and Gettig? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Craniosynostosis-mental retardation syndrome of Lin and Gettig. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Agenesis of corpus callosum - Ambiguous genitalia, male - Arnold-Chiari type I malformation - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Blepharophimosis - Camptodactyly - Cleft palate - Craniosynostosis - Cryptorchidism - Decreased palmar creases - Dolichocephaly - Epicanthus - Feeding difficulties in infancy - Glabellar hemangioma - Hand clenching - Hydronephrosis - Hypertelorism - Hypertonia - Hypoplasia of midface - Hypoplastic philtrum - Hypospadias - Hypotelorism - Inguinal hernia - Intellectual disability, progressive - Intellectual disability, severe - Intestinal malrotation - Joint contracture of the hand - Long philtrum - Low-set ears - Malar flattening - Micropenis - Microtia - Multiple joint contractures - Multiple small bowel atresias - Narrow chest - Omphalocele - Pectus carinatum - Pectus excavatum - Ptosis - Sensorineural hearing impairment - Short columella - Short nose - Slender finger - Smooth philtrum - Stenosis of the external auditory canal - Strabismus - Supernumerary nipple - Thin vermilion border - Trigonocephaly - Turricephaly - Umbilical hernia - Upslanted palpebral fissure - Ventricular septal defect - Vesicoureteral reflux - Wide intermamillary distance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
