<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001681" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1620/cryptogenic-organizing-pneumonia">
<Focus>Cryptogenic organizing pneumonia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0242770</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>COP</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Idiopathic bronchiolitis obliterans organizing pneumonia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Idiopathic BOOP</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001681-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Cryptogenic organizing pneumonia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cryptogenic organizing pneumonia (COP) is a form of idiopathic interstitial pneumonia characterized by lung inflammation and scarring that obstructs the small airways and air sacs of the lungs (alveoli). Signs and symptoms may include flu-like symptoms such as cough, fever, malaise, fatigue and weight loss. COP often affects adults in midlife (40 to 60 years of age). The exact underlying cause of the condition is unknown (idiopathic). Treatment varies based on the severity of the condition but generally includes glucocorticoids.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001681-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Cryptogenic organizing pneumonia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of cryptogenic organizing pneumonia? Signs and symptoms of cryptogenic organizing pneumonia (COP) vary but may include: Persistent nonproductive cough Difficult or labored breathing Fever Malaise Weight loss Hemoptysis (rare)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001681-3" qtype="causes">What causes Cryptogenic organizing pneumonia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes cryptogenic organizing pneumonia? The underlying cause of cryptogenic organizing pneumonia (COP) is unknown (idiopathic). Organizing pneumonia is specifically diagnosed as COP when, among other characteristics, no definite cause for the organizing pneumonia is found. In other words, any known cause for the pneumonia must be ruled out before stating that a person is affected by COP. Other forms of organizing pneumonia may result from infection (bacteria, viruses, parasites, or fungi); drugs; or a reaction to radiation therapy for breast cancer. Organizing pneumonia can also be associated with specific disorders such as certain connective tissue disorders, blood malignancies (cancers), or ulcerative colitis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001681-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Cryptogenic organizing pneumonia inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is cryptogenic organizing pneumonia inherited? We are not aware of any familial cases of cryptogenic organizing pneumonia (COP) in the medical literature, and to our knowledge, there is no evidence that some people may be genetically predisposed to developing COP.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001681-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Cryptogenic organizing pneumonia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is cryptogenic organizing pneumonia diagnosed? A diagnosis of cryptogenic organizing pneumonia is often suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms once other conditions that cause similar features have been excluded. This includes ruling out other known causes of organizing pneumonia. Additional testing such as a computed tomography (CT) scan or lung biopsy can confirm the diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001681-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Cryptogenic organizing pneumonia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might cryptogenic organizing pneumonia be treated? The treatment of cryptogenic organizing pneumonia (COP) generally depends on the severity of the condition. For example, people who are mildly affected may simply be monitored as some cases can improve on their own. Unfortunately, the majority of people with COP have persistent and/or progressive symptoms that will require therapy. In these cases, oral or intravenous glucocorticoids can be given which often result in rapid improvement of symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
