<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001321" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6657/chronic-hiccups">
<Focus>Chronic hiccups</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0744898</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Intractable singultus</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Intractable hiccups</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Persistent hiccups</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hiccups, intractable</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001321-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Chronic hiccups ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chronic hiccups are unintentional movements (spasms) of the diaphragm followed by rapid closure of the vocal cords that persist for an extended period of time. Hiccups often develop for no apparent reason and typically go away on their own after a couple minutes. However, chronic hiccups last over two days and in rare cases, may continue for over a month. Hiccups that recur over long periods of time are also considered &quot;chronic.&quot; Depending on how long the hiccups last, affected people may become exhausted, dehydrated and/or lose weight due to interruptions in sleep and normal eating patterns. Other complications may include irregular heart beat and gastroesophageal reflux. The exact underlying cause is often unknown; some cases may be caused by surgery, certain medications and/or a variety of health problems such as central nervous system (brain and spinal cord) abnormalities, psychological problems, conditions that irritate the diaphragm, and metabolic diseases. Treatment of chronic hiccups varies but may include medications and/or surgery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001321-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Chronic hiccups ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Chronic hiccups? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Chronic hiccups. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of movement 90% Functional respiratory abnormality 90% Recurrent singultus 90% Abnormality of temperature regulation 7.5% Cerebral ischemia 7.5% Coronary artery disease 7.5% Dehydration 7.5% Diabetes insipidus 7.5% Neoplasm of the nervous system 7.5% Renal insufficiency 7.5% Sleep disturbance 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001321-3" qtype="causes">What causes Chronic hiccups ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes chronic hiccups? Although the exact underlying cause of chronic hiccups is often unknown, many factors can contribute to the development of hiccups. For example, common triggers for hiccups include hot or spicy foods and liquids; harmful fumes; surgery; and/or certain medications. Chronic hiccups can also be associated with a variety of health problems including: Pneumonia, pleurisy and other conditions that irritate the diaphragm Brain abnormalities (i.e. strokes, tumors, injuries, infections) Metabolic disorders Gastrointestinal (esophagus, stomach, small/large intestines) diseases Psychological problems such as hysteria, shock, fear, and personality disorders Liver abnormalities Kidney disorders For a comprehensive listings of factors that can cause chronic hiccups, please click here.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001321-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Chronic hiccups inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Are chronic hiccups inherited? Chronic hiccups are not thought to be inherited. Most cases occur sporadically in people with no family history of the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001321-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Chronic hiccups ?</Question>
			<Answer>How are chronic hiccups diagnosed? A diagnosis of chronic hiccups is usually obvious based on symptoms. However, a complete physical exam with various laboratory tests and imaging studies (i.e. chest X-ray, CT scan, MRI scan, and/or fluoroscopy of the diaphragm) may be performed to determine the underlying cause. For more information about the workup and diagnosis of chronic hiccups, please click here.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001321-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Chronic hiccups ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might chronic hiccups be treated? Treatment for chronic hiccups often varies based on the underlying cause. In many cases, medications can be prescribed to treat chronic hiccups. These may include: Tranquilizers such as chlorpromazine and haloperidol  Muscle relaxants Anticonvulsant agents including phenytoin, valproic acid, and carbamazepine Sedatives Pain medications Stimulants Rarely, medications may not be effective in the treatment of chronic hiccups. In these cases, surgery to temporarily or permanently block the phrenic nerve may be performed. The phrenic nerve controls the diaphragm.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
