<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001671" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4427/cronkhite-canada-disease">
<Focus>Cronkhite-Canada disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0238386</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Polyposis skin pigmentation alopecia fingernail changes</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001671-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Cronkhite-Canada disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cronkhite-Canada syndrome is a rare gastrointestinal disorder characterized by widespread colon polyps, unhealthy looking (dystrophic) nails, hair loss (alopecia), darkening skin (such as on the hands, arms, neck and face), diarrhea, weight loss, stomach pain, and/or excess fluid accumulation in arms and legs (peripheral edema). The cause of the condition is not known. Treatment aims to control symptoms and provide adequate nutrition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001671-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Cronkhite-Canada disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Cronkhite-Canada disease? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Cronkhite-Canada disease. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of nail color 90% Abnormality of the fingernails 90% Alopecia 90% Generalized hyperpigmentation 90% Hypoplastic toenails 90% Intestinal polyposis 90% Malabsorption 90% Neoplasm of the colon 90% Neoplasm of the stomach 90% Abdominal pain 50% Anemia 50% Anorexia 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the eyebrow 50% Autoimmunity 50% Gastrointestinal hemorrhage 50% Hypopigmented skin patches 50% Lymphedema 50% Neoplasm of the small intestine 50% Abnormality of the sense of smell 7.5% Cataract 7.5% Congestive heart failure 7.5% Decreased body weight 7.5% Feeding difficulties in infancy 7.5% Furrowed tongue 7.5% Glomerulopathy 7.5% Hepatomegaly 7.5% Hypoproteinemia 7.5% Hypothyroidism 7.5% Macrocephaly 7.5% Paresthesia 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Splenomegaly 7.5% Tapered finger 7.5% Cachexia - Clubbing - Clubbing of fingers - Diarrhea - Gastrointestinal carcinoma - Glossitis - Hamartomatous polyposis - Hematochezia - Hyperpigmentation of the skin - Hypocalcemia - Hypokalemia - Hypomagnesemia - Muscle weakness - Nail dysplasia - Nail dystrophy - Protein-losing enteropathy - Sporadic - Thromboembolism - Vomiting - Xerostomia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
