<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001119" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9200/charcot-marie-tooth-disease-type-4b2">
<Focus>Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 4B2</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1858278</CUI>
			<CUI>C0040435</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>CMT 4B2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Charcot Marie Tooth disease type 4B2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>CHARCOT-MARIE-TOOTH DISEASE, WITH FOCALLY FOLDED MYELIN SHEATHS, AUTOSOMAL RECESSIVE, TYPE 4B2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>CHARCOT-MARIE-TOOTH NEUROPATHY, TYPE 4B2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 4</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001119-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 4B2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 4B2? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease type 4B2. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Areflexia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Decreased motor nerve conduction velocity - Decreased number of peripheral myelinated nerve fibers - Difficulty walking - Distal amyotrophy - Distal muscle weakness - Distal sensory impairment - Foot dorsiflexor weakness - Glaucoma - Hammertoe - Hyporeflexia - Juvenile onset - Kyphoscoliosis - Onion bulb formation - Pes cavus - Segmental peripheral demyelination/remyelination - Sensorineural hearing impairment - Steppage gait - Talipes equinovarus - Ulnar claw - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
