<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001399" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1418/codas-syndrome">
<Focus>CODAS syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1838180</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Cerebral, ocular, dental, auricular, and skeletal syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cerebro-oculo-dento-auriculo-skeletal syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001399-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of CODAS syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of CODAS syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for CODAS syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 90% Abnormality of dental enamel 90% Abnormality of dental morphology 90% Abnormality of epiphysis morphology 90% Abnormality of the metacarpal bones 90% Anteverted nares 90% Brachydactyly syndrome 90% Cataract 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Delayed eruption of teeth 90% Delayed skeletal maturation 90% Depressed nasal bridge 90% Epicanthus 90% Malar flattening 90% Midline defect of the nose 90% Overfolded helix 90% Short nose 90% Short stature 90% Abnormality of the hip bone 50% Joint hypermobility 50% Muscular hypotonia 50% Ptosis 50% Scoliosis 50% Sensorineural hearing impairment 50% Abnormality of the upper urinary tract 7.5% Extrahepatic biliary duct atresia 7.5% Nystagmus 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Ventricular septal defect 7.5% Vocal cord paresis 7.5% Anal atresia 5% Cryptorchidism 5% Omphalocele 5% Proximal placement of thumb 5% Rectovaginal fistula 5% Seizures 5% Atria septal defect - Atrioventricular canal defect - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Broad skull - Congenital cataract - Congenital hip dislocation - Coronal cleft vertebrae - Delayed ossification of carpal bones - Genu valgum - Hypoplasia of dental enamel - Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum - Hypoplasia of the odontoid process - Metaphyseal dysplasia - Polyhydramnios - Short humerus - Short metacarpal - Short phalanx of finger - Squared iliac bones - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
