<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001247" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10835/chromosome-19p-deletion">
<Focus>Chromosome 19p deletion</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1442161</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T049</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Deletion 19p</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Monosomy 19p</Synonym>
		<Synonym>19p deletion</Synonym>
		<Synonym>19p monosomy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Partial monosomy 19p</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001247-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Chromosome 19p deletion ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chromosome 19p deletion is a chromosome abnormality that occurs when there is a missing (deleted) copy of genetic material on the short arm (p) of chromosome 19. The severity of the condition and the signs and symptoms depend on the size and location of the deletion and which genes are involved. Features that often occur in people with chromosome 19p deletion include developmental delay, intellectual disability, behavioral problems and distinctive facial features. Chromosome testing of both parents can provide more information on whether or not the deletion was inherited. In most cases, parents do not have any chromosomal anomaly. However, sometimes one parent is found to have a balanced translocation, where a piece of a chromosome has broken off and attached to another one with no gain or loss of genetic material. The balanced translocation normally does not cause any signs or symptoms, but it increases the risk for having an affected child with a chromosomal anomaly like a deletion. Treatment is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person. This page is meant to provide general information about 19p deletions. You can contact GARD if you have questions about a specific deletion on chromosome 19. To learn more about chromosomal anomalies please visit our GARD webpage on FAQs about Chromosome Disorders.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
