<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001633" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1575/craniofacial-dyssynostosis">
<Focus>Craniofacial dyssynostosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1857511</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Craniosynostosis-craniofacial dysostosis syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Craniofacial dyssynostosis and short stature</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001633-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Craniofacial dyssynostosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Craniofacial dyssynostosis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Craniofacial dyssynostosis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Cognitive impairment 90% Craniosynostosis 90% Dolichocephaly 90% Frontal bossing 90% Hypertelorism 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Macrocephaly 90% Atresia of the external auditory canal 50% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 50% Hydrocephalus 50% Open mouth 50% Short philtrum 50% Short stature 50% Strabismus 50% Umbilical hernia 50% Underdeveloped nasal alae 50% Underdeveloped supraorbital ridges 50% Abnormality of the oral cavity 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 7.5% Epicanthus 7.5% Facial asymmetry 7.5% Nystagmus 7.5% Patent ductus arteriosus 7.5% Sacral dimple 7.5% Short neck 7.5% Abnormal location of ears - Abnormal shape of the occiput - Agenesis of corpus callosum - Arnold-Chiari type I malformation - Brachyturricephaly - Cryptorchidism - Esotropia - Flat midface - Generalized hypotonia - Horseshoe kidney - Hypoplasia of midface - Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum - Hypospadias - Intellectual disability - Malar flattening - Narrow forehead - Pyloric stenosis - Seizures - Ventricular septal defect - Ventriculomegaly - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
