<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001163" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1292/chondrocalcinosis-2">
<Focus>Chondrocalcinosis 2</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0856830</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>CCAL2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chondrocalcinosis familial articular</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Familial articular chondrocalcinosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Calcium pyrophosphate arthropathy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>CPPDD</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001163-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Chondrocalcinosis 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chondrocalcinosis 2 is a rare condition characterized by the accumulation of calcium pyrophosphate dihydrate crystals in and around the joints. A buildup of these crystals can lead to progressive (worsening over time) joint damage. Some affected people may not have any signs or symptoms of the condition. Others experience chronic joint pain or sudden, recurrent episodes of pain, stiffness and/or swelling of the joints. Although chondrocalcinosis 2 can affect people of all ages, it is most commonly diagnosed in early adulthood (age 20-40 years). It is caused by changes (mutations) in the ANKH gene and is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. There is no cure for the condition and treatment is symptomatic.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001163-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Chondrocalcinosis 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Chondrocalcinosis 2? The signs and symptoms of chondrocalcinosis 2 vary from person to person. Some affected people may not have any symptoms of the condition aside from the appearance of calcium deposits on joint x-rays. Others experience chronic pain in affected joints and/or the back if calcium deposits develop around the bones of the spine. Chondrocalcinosis 2 can also be associated with sudden, recurrent episodes of joint pain, stiffness and/or swelling that can last anywhere from several hours to several weeks. These episodes can lead to limited range of motion in the affected joint or even ankylosis (fixation of joint in place). Although almost any joint in the body can be affected, symptoms are often confined to a single knee, wrist, hip or shoulder. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Chondrocalcinosis 2. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the intervertebral disk 90% Arthralgia 90% Calcification of cartilage 90% Joint swelling 90% Osteoarthritis 50% Abnormal tendon morphology 7.5% Chondrocalcinosis 7.5% Joint dislocation 7.5% Limitation of joint mobility 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Adult onset - Arthropathy - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Polyarticular chondrocalcinosis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001163-3" qtype="causes">What causes Chondrocalcinosis 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes chondrocalcinosis 2? Chondrocalcinosis 2 is caused by changes (mutations) in the ANKH gene. This gene encodes a protein that helps transport pyrophosphate (a substance that regulates bone formation). Mutations in ANKH can cause high levels of pyrophosphate and calcium pyrophosphate dihydrate crystals to accumulate in the cartilage of joints. The buildup of these crystals weakens cartilage and causes it to break down more easily. This leads to the many signs and symptoms associated with chondrocalcinosis 2.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001163-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Chondrocalcinosis 2 inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is chondrocalcinosis 2 inherited? Chondrocalcinosis 2 is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. This means that to be affected, a person only needs a change (mutation) in one copy of the responsible gene in each cell. In some cases, an affected person inherits the mutation from an affected parent. Other cases may result from new (de novo) mutations in the gene. These cases occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family. A person with chondrocalcinosis 2 has a 50% chance with each pregnancy of passing along the altered gene to his or her child.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001163-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Chondrocalcinosis 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is chondrocalcinosis 2 diagnosed? A diagnosis of chondrocalcinosis 2 is often suspected based on characteristic signs and symptoms. Specialized testing, such as synovial fluid analysis, can then be ordered to confirm the diagnosis. In synovial fluid analysis, a small sample of the fluid that surrounds affected joints is removed and examined to determine if calcium pyrophosphate dihydrate crystals are present. In most cases, x-rays can be used to identify calcium deposits in the cartilage of joints.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001163-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Chondrocalcinosis 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might chondrocalcinosis 2 be treated? There is currently no cure for chondrocalcinosis 2. Unfortunately, the accumulation of calcium pyrophosphate dihydrate crystals can not be prevented and once present, these crystals can not be removed from affected joints. Therapies are available to manage the signs and symptoms of the condition. During episodes of joint pain, stiffness, and/or swelling, the following treatments may be recommended to relieve symptoms: joint aspiration (draining of fluid from the affected joint), corticosteroids injections, and/or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDS) such as aspirin or ibuprofen. Small doses of a medication called colchicine or NSAIDS are sometimes prescribed to people with frequent and severe attacks in an attempt to prevent future episodes; however, this therapy is not effective in all cases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
