<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001147" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8735/childhood-hypophosphatasia">
<Focus>Childhood hypophosphatasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0220743</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Childhood-onset hypophosphatasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Childhood-onset phosphoethanolaminuria</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Childhood-onset Rathburn disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001147-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Childhood hypophosphatasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Childhood hypophosphatasia is a form of hypophosphatasia, a rare condition that affects the bones. Childhood hypophosphatasia, specifically, is generally diagnosed when the condition develops after six months of age but before adulthood. Signs and symptoms vary but may include delayed motor milestones; low bone mineral density for age; early loss of baby teeth (before age 5); bone and joint pain; short stature; a waddling gait; skeletal malformations; and/or unexplained broken bones. The forms of hypophosphatasia that develop during childhood are generally more mild than those that appear in infancy. Childhood hypophosphatasia is caused by changes (mutations) in the ALPL gene and can be inherited in an autosomal dominant or autosomal recessive manner. Treatment is supportive and based on the signs and symptoms present in each person. Recently an enzyme replacement therapy (ERT) called asfotase alfa has been show to improve bone symptoms in people with childhood hypophosphatasia and has been approved by the FDA.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001147-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Childhood hypophosphatasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Childhood hypophosphatasia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Childhood hypophosphatasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal recessive inheritance - Bowing of the legs - Carious teeth - Craniosynostosis - Dolichocephaly - Elevated plasma pyrophosphate - Elevated urine pyrophosphate - Frontal bossing - Low alkaline phosphatase - Myopathy - Phosphoethanolaminuria - Premature loss of primary teeth - Proptosis - Rachitic rosary - Seizures - Short stature - Skin dimple over apex of long bone angulation - Waddling gait - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
