<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001398" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1417/cockayne-syndrome-type-iii">
<Focus>Cockayne syndrome type III</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0751037</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Cockayne syndrome type C</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cockayne syndrome type 3</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cockayne syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001398-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Cockayne syndrome type III ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cockayne syndrome is a rare condition which causes short stature, premature aging (progeria), severe photosensitivity, and moderate to severe learning delay. This syndrome also includes failure to thrive in the newborn, microcephaly, and impaired nervous system development. Other symptoms may include hearing loss, tooth decay, and eye and bone abnormalities.  Cockayne syndrome type 1 (type A) is sometimes called classic or &quot;moderate&quot; Cockayne syndrome and is diagnosed during early childhood. Cockayne syndrome type 2 (type B) is sometimes referred to as the severe or &quot;early-onset&quot; type. This more severe form presents with growth and developmental abnormalities at birth. The third type, Cockayne syndrome type 3 (type C) is a milder form of the disorder. Cockayne syndrome is caused by mutations in either the ERCC8 (CSA) or ERCC6 (CSB) genes and is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern. The typical lifespan for individuals with Cockayne syndrome type 1 is ten to twenty years. Individuals with type 2 usually do not survive past childhood. Those with type 3 live into middle adulthood.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001398-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Cockayne syndrome type III ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Cockayne syndrome type III? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Cockayne syndrome type III. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal auditory evoked potentials - Abnormal CNS myelination - Abnormal peripheral myelination - Abnormality of skin pigmentation - Abnormality of the pinna - Abnormality of visual evoked potentials - Atherosclerosis - Atypical scarring of skin - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Cerebral calcification - Cutaneous photosensitivity - Dementia - Dermal atrophy - Flexion contracture - Gait disturbance - Glomerulosclerosis - Hearing impairment - Hypertension - Intellectual disability - Large hands - Long foot - Mandibular prognathia - Microcephaly - Normal pressure hydrocephalus - Optic atrophy - Prematurely aged appearance - Proteinuria - Retinal degeneration - Retinal pigment epithelial mottling - Severe short stature - Thymic hormone decreased - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
