<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001335" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1358/chudley-rozdilsky-syndrome">
<Focus>Chudley Rozdilsky syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Chudley syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Multicore myopathy with mental retardation, short stature, and hypogonadotropic hypogonadism</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Myopathy congenital</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001335-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Chudley Rozdilsky syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Chudley Rozdilsky syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Chudley Rozdilsky syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal hair quantity 90% Abnormality of the palate 90% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Craniofacial hyperostosis 90% Delayed skeletal maturation 90% Disproportionate tall stature 90% Facial palsy 90% Hyperlordosis 90% Hypertelorism 90% Hypoplasia of penis 90% Myopia 90% Ophthalmoparesis 90% Ptosis 90% Short stature 90% Skeletal muscle atrophy 90% Abnormality of the hip bone 50% Abnormality of the pinna 50% Limitation of joint mobility 50% Microcephaly 50% Prominent nasal bridge 50% Abnormality of the ribs 7.5% Facial asymmetry 7.5% Pectus carinatum 7.5% Tracheoesophageal fistula 7.5% Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Hypogonadotrophic hypogonadism - Intellectual disability, progressive - Intellectual disability, severe - Lumbar hyperlordosis - Myopathy - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
