<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0001661" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12430/crest-syndrome">
<Focus>CREST syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0206138</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>SCLERODERMA, FAMILIAL PROGRESSIVE</Synonym>
		<Synonym>SYSTEMIC SCLEROSIS, SUSCEPTIBILITY TO</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Calcinosis - Raynaud phenomenon - esophageal involvement - sclerodactyly - telangiectasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Calcinosis-Raynaud phenomenon-esophageal involvement-sclerodactyly-telangiectasia syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Limited cutaneous systemic sclerosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001661-1" qtype="information">What is (are) CREST syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>CREST syndrome, also known as limited scleroderma, is a widespread connective tissue disease characterized by changes in the skin, blood vessels, skeletal muscles, and internal organs. The symptoms involved in CREST syndrome are associated with the generalized form of the disease systemic sclerosis (scleroderma). CREST is an acronym for the clinical features that are seen in a patient with this disease.     (C) - Calcinosis (KAL-sin-OH-sis): the formation of calcium deposits in the connective tissues, which can be detected by X ray. They are typically found on the fingers, hands, face, trunk, and on the skin above the elbows and knees. When the deposits break through the skin, painful ulcers can result.   (R) - Raynaud&apos;s (ray-NOHZ) phenomenon: a condition in which the small blood vessels of the hands and/or feet contract in response to cold or anxiety. As the vessels contract, the hands or feet turn white and cold, then blue. As blood flow returns, they become red. Fingertip tissues may suffer damage, leading to ulcers, scars, or gangrene.   (E) - Esophageal (eh-SOFF-uh-GEE-ul) dysfunction: impaired function of the esophagus (the tube connecting the throat and the stomach) that occurs when smooth muscles in the esophagus lose normal movement. In the upper esophagus, the result can be swallowing difficulties; in the lower esophagus, the problem can cause chronic heartburn or inflammation.   (S) - Sclerodactyly (SKLER-oh-DAK-till-ee): thick and tight skin on the fingers, resulting from deposits of excess collagen within skin layers. The condition makes it harder to bend or straighten the fingers. The skin may also appear shiny and darkened, with hair loss.   (T) - Telangiectasia (tel-AN-jee-ek-TAY-zee-uhs): small red spots on the hands and face that are caused by the swelling of tiny blood vessels. While not painful, these red spots can create cosmetic problems.   It is not necessary to have all five symptoms of CREST syndrome to be diagnosed with the disease. Some doctors believe only two of the five are necessary for a diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001661-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of CREST syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of CREST syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for CREST syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the gastric mucosa 90% Acrocyanosis 90% Arthralgia 90% Arthritis 90% Atypical scarring of skin 90% Autoimmunity 90% Chest pain 90% Chondrocalcinosis 90% Edema 90% Hyperkeratosis 90% Lack of skin elasticity 90% Myalgia 90% Nausea and vomiting 90% Skeletal muscle atrophy 90% Weight loss 90% Abnormality of the myocardium 50% Abnormality of the pericardium 50% Carious teeth 50% Feeding difficulties in infancy 50% Gangrene 50% Malabsorption 50% Mucosal telangiectasiae 50% Myositis 50% Pulmonary fibrosis 50% Pulmonary infiltrates 50% Respiratory insufficiency 50% Skin ulcer 50% Telangiectasia of the skin 50% Trismus 50% Xerostomia 50% Abnormal renal physiology 7.5% Abnormal tendon morphology 7.5% Arrhythmia 7.5% Bowel incontinence 7.5% Coronary artery disease 7.5% Erectile abnormalities 7.5% Hypertensive crisis 7.5% Irregular hyperpigmentation 7.5% Migraine 7.5% Narrow mouth 7.5% Osteolysis 7.5% Osteomyelitis 7.5% Peripheral neuropathy 7.5% Pulmonary hypertension 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Abnormality of chromosome stability - Abnormality of the abdomen - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Calcinosis - Sclerodactyly - Scleroderma - Telangiectasia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001661-3" qtype="causes">What causes CREST syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes CREST syndrome? In people with CREST syndrome, the immune system appears to stimulate cells called fibroblasts to produce excess amounts of collagen. Normally, fibroblasts synthesize collagen to help heal wounds, but in this case, the protein is produced even when it&apos;s not needed, forming thick bands of connective tissue around the cells of the skin, blood vessels and in some cases, the internal organs. Although an abnormal immune system response and the resulting production of excess collagen appears to be the main cause of limited scleroderma, researchers suspect that other factors may play a role, including: genetic factors, pregnancy, hormones, and environmental factors.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001661-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose CREST syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is CREST syndrome diagnosed? CREST syndrome can be difficult to diagnose. Signs and symptoms vary widely and often resemble those of other connective tissue and autoimmune diseases. Further complicating matters is that limited scleroderma sometimes occurs with other autoimmune conditions  such as polymyositis, lupus and rheumatoid arthritis.   A blood sample can be tested for antibodies that are frequently found in the blood of people with limited scleroderma. But this isn&apos;t a definitive test because not everyone with limited scleroderma has these antibodies. Sometimes doctors take a small sample of skin that&apos;s then examined under a microscope in a laboratory. Biopsies can be helpful, but they can&apos;t definitively diagnose limited scleroderma either.  Along with a blood test and skin biopsy, additional tests to identify lung, heart or gastrointestinal complications may also be conducted.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
