<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002877" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10439/hidradenocarcinoma">
<Focus>Hidradenocarcinoma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0334344</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Malignant nodular/clear cell hidradenoma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Malignant acrospiroma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Malignant clear cell acrospiroma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Clear cell eccrine carcinoma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Primary mucoepidermoid cutaneous carcinoma</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002877-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hidradenocarcinoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hidradenocarcinoma is a tumor caused by the abnormal growth of cells in a sweat gland.  It is a type of cancer that usually begins as a single spot (lesion) on the skin of the head or neck, but it has also been found on other parts of the body.  This type of tumor typically develops in older individuals (after age 40).  Each hidradenocarcinoma develops differently over time; some may stay the same size and others grow rapidly.  Sometimes it may spread into nearby tissues, or to more distant parts of the body in a process called metastasis.  It is not known why some hidradenocarcinomas progress rapidly while others remain stable.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002877-2" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hidradenocarcinoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might hidradenocarcinoma be treated? Because hidradenocarcinoma is quite rare, there are no established guidelines for treatment.  Treatment is determined by the size and location of each particular cancer and the extent to which cancer cells may have spread to nearby lymph nodes or tissues.  Surgery is often the first step and aims to remove as much of the cancer as possible.  Both a traditional surgical technique, known as wide local excision, and the newer Mohs micrographic surgery have been used to remove hidradenocarcinomas.  Radiation therapy, performed by a doctor known as radiation oncologist, has been used after surgery in patients with hidradenocarcinoma to destroy any cancer cells that may remain at the original location of the tumor or in the lymph nodes.  Chemotherapy, performed by a doctor known as a medical oncologist, has not yet been proven as effective treatment for hidradenocarcinomas.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
