<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002826" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6626/hereditary-hemorrhagic-telangiectasia">
<Focus>Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0039446</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039445</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>HHT</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Osler Weber Rendu syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>ORW disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Osler-Rendu-Weber disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Rendu-Osler-Weber disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia type 2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia type 3</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia type 4</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002826-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia (HHT) is an inherited disorder of the blood vessels that can cause excessive bleeding. People with this condition can develop abnormal blood vessels called arteriovenous malformations (AVMs) in several areas of the body. If they are on the skin, they are called telangiectasias. The AVMs can also develop in other parts of the body, such as the brain, lungs, liver, or intestines. HHT is caused by mutations in the ACVRL1, ENG, and SMAD4 genes. It is inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern, which means one copy of the altered gene in each cell is sufficient to cause the disorder. There is no cure for HHT. Treatment is symptomatic and supportive, with a focus on controlling bleeding, either through surgery or medication.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002826-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Epistaxis 90% Telangiectasia of the skin 90% Cavernous hemangioma 50% Microcytic anemia 50% Migraine 50% Portal hypertension 50% Spontaneous hematomas 50% Visceral angiomatosis 50% Abnormality of coagulation 7.5% Abnormality of the retinal vasculature 7.5% Biliary tract abnormality 7.5% Cerebral ischemia 7.5% Cirrhosis 7.5% Congestive heart failure 7.5% Conjunctival telangiectasia 7.5% Esophageal varix 7.5% Gastrointestinal hemorrhage 7.5% Hematuria 7.5% Hemoptysis 7.5% Hepatic failure 7.5% Intestinal polyposis 7.5% Nephrolithiasis 7.5% Peripheral arteriovenous fistula 7.5% Pulmonary embolism 7.5% Pulmonary hypertension 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Thrombophlebitis 7.5% Visual impairment 7.5% Anemia - Arteriovenous fistulas of celiac and mesenteric vessels - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Brain abscess - Celiac artery aneurysm - Cerebral arteriovenous malformation - Cerebral hemorrhage - Clubbing - Cyanosis - Dyspnea - Fingerpad telangiectases - Gastrointestinal angiodysplasia - Gastrointestinal arteriovenous malformation - Gastrointestinal telangiectasia - Hematemesis - Hematochezia - Hepatic arteriovenous malformation - Heterogeneous - High-output congestive heart failure - Ischemic stroke - Lip telangiectasia - Melena - Mesenteric artery aneurysm - Nail bed telangiectasia - Nasal mucosa telangiectasia - Palate telangiectasia - Polycythemia - Pulmonary arteriovenous malformation - Right-to-left shunt - Spinal arteriovenous malformation - Spontaneous, recurrent epistaxis - Subarachnoid hemorrhage - Tongue telangiectasia - Transient ischemic attack - Venous varicosities of celiac and mesenteric vessels - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002826-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Can hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia (HHT) be treated? Yes. Although there is not yet a way to prevent the telangiectases or AVMs associated with HHT, most can be treated once they occur. Management includes surveillance for undiagnosed AVMs and treatment for identified complications such as nosebleeds, gastrointestinal bleeding, anemia, pulmonary AVMs, cerebral AVMs, and hepatic AVMs. Treatment of nosebleeds with humidification and nasal lubricants, laser ablation, septal dermoplasty, or estrogen-progesterone therapy can prevent anemia and allow individuals with HHT to pursue normal activities. Individuals with GI bleeding are treated with iron therapy to maintain hemoglobin concentration; endoscopic application of a heater probe, bicap, or laser; surgical removal of bleeding sites; and estrogen-progesterone therapy. Iron replacement and red blood cell transfusions are used to treat anemia. Pulmonary AVMs with feeding vessels that exceed 3.0 mm in diameter require occlusion. Cerebral AVMs greater than 1.0 cm in diameter are treated by surgery, embolotherapy, and/or stereotactic radiosurgery. The treatment of choice for hepatic AVMs is liver transplantation. Blood-thinning medications (anticoagulants) and anti-inflammatory agents should be avoided. Some patients may need to take antibiotics during simple dental or surgical procedures. Individual patients and their doctors should make decisions regarding these measures, as necessary. Surveillance includes annual evaluations for anemia and neurologic conditions and re-evaluation for pulmonary AVMs every one to two years during childhood and every five years thereafter. Women with HHT considering pregnancy are screened and treated for pulmonary AVMs; if pulmonary AVMs are discovered during pregnancy, they are treated during the second trimester.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
