<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002837" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5427/hereditary-mucoepithelial-dysplasia">
<Focus>Hereditary mucoepithelial dysplasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0334044</CUI>
			<CUI>C1274795</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Mucoepithelial dysplasia, hereditary</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Urban-Schosser-Spohn syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002837-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hereditary mucoepithelial dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hereditary mucoepithelial dysplasia (HMD) is a condition that affects the skin, hair, mucosa (areas of the body that are lined with mucus), gums (gingiva), eyes, nose and lungs. Symptoms typically begin in infancy and may include development of cataracts (clouding of the eye lens); blindness; hair loss (alopecia); abnormal changes to the perineum (the area between the anus and external genitalia); and small, skin-colored bumps (keratosis pilaris). Terminal lung disease has also been reported. The cause of HMD is thought to be an abnormality in desmosomes and gap junctions, which are structures involved in cell-to-cell contact. HMD typically follows autosomal dominant inheritance, but has occurred sporadically (in an individual who has no family history of the condition). Treatment typically focuses on individual symptoms of the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002837-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hereditary mucoepithelial dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Hereditary mucoepithelial dysplasia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Hereditary mucoepithelial dysplasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Cataract 90% Corneal dystrophy 90% Fine hair 90% Furrowed tongue 90% Gingival overgrowth 90% Hyperkeratosis 90% Tracheoesophageal fistula 90% Abnormality of female internal genitalia 50% Nystagmus 50% Photophobia 50% Pulmonary fibrosis 50% Hematuria 7.5% Chronic diarrhea 5% Melena 5% Nail dysplasia 5% Nail dystrophy 5% Recurrent pneumonia 5% Alopecia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Blindness - Chronic monilial nail infection - Chronic mucocutaneous candidiasis - Coarse hair - Congenital onset - Cor pulmonale - Corneal neovascularization - Eosinophilia - Esotropia - Fibrocystic lung disease - Keratoconjunctivitis - Opacification of the corneal stroma - Pneumonia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
