<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002431" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6466/freeman-sheldon-syndrome">
<Focus>Freeman Sheldon syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265224</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>FSS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Arthrogryposis distal type 2A</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Whistling face-windmill vane hand syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Craniocarpotarsal dystrophy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Craniocarpotarsal dysplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Myosinopathies</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002431-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Freeman Sheldon syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Freeman Sheldon syndrome is an inherited disorder characterized by multiple contractures (i.e., restricted movement around two or more body areas) at birth (congenital), abnormalities of the head and face (craniofacial) area, defects of the hands and feet, and skeletal malformations. Freeman-Sheldon syndrome can be inherited as an autosomal dominant or autosomal recessive genetic trait. However, most cases occur randomly with no apparent cause (sporadically).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002431-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Freeman Sheldon syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Freeman Sheldon syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Freeman Sheldon syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the teeth 90% Camptodactyly of finger 90% Chin dimple 90% Hypertelorism 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Narrow mouth 90% Scoliosis 90% Talipes 90% Trismus 90% Ulnar deviation of finger 90% Underdeveloped nasal alae 90% Wide nasal bridge 90% Abnormality of the nares 50% Cryptorchidism 50% Deeply set eye 50% Hearing impairment 50% Long philtrum 50% Malignant hyperthermia 50% Neurological speech impairment 50% Prenatal movement abnormality 50% Ptosis 50% Short stature 50% Strabismus 50% Intellectual disability 31% Absent palmar crease 7.5% Hernia 7.5% Oligohydramnios 7.5% Polyhydramnios 7.5% Abnormal auditory evoked potentials - Abnormality of the skin - Adducted thumb - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Blepharophimosis - Breech presentation - Camptodactyly - Cerebellar atrophy - Chin with H-shaped crease - Epicanthus - Failure to thrive - Fever - Flat face - Flexion contracture of toe - High palate - Hip contracture - Hip dislocation - Hypoplasia of the brainstem - Inguinal hernia - Joint contracture of the hand - Knee flexion contracture - Kyphoscoliosis - Malar flattening - Mandibular prognathia - Mask-like facies - Microcephaly - Muscle weakness - Nasal speech - Postnatal growth retardation - Prominent forehead - Rocker bottom foot - Seizures - Short neck - Short nose - Shoulder flexion contracture - Small for gestational age - Spina bifida occulta - Talipes equinovarus - Telecanthus - Ulnar deviation of the hand or of fingers of the hand - Whistling appearance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002431-3" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Freeman Sheldon syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Freeman Sheldon syndrome diagnosed? Freeman Sheldon syndrome may be suspected based on medical history and physical examination which reveal characteristic features such as a small mouth, flat mask-like face, club feet, joint contractures, and under-development of the cartilage of the nose. A definitive diagnosis can be made through clinical genetic testing. GeneTests lists laboratories offering clinical genetic testing for this condition. Clinical genetic tests are ordered to help diagnose a person or family and to aid in decisions regarding medical care or reproductive issues. Talk to your health care provider or a genetic professional to learn more about your testing options.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
