<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002126" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/2147/epidermolysis-bullosa-simplex-generalized">
<Focus>Epidermolysis bullosa simplex, generalized</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0079299</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>EBS, generalized</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Generalized EBS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Epidermolysis bullosa simplex, Koebner type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>EBS-K</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Epidermolysis bullosa simplex, generalized non-Dowling-Meara</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Epidermolysis bullosa</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Epidermolysis bullosa simplex</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002126-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Epidermolysis bullosa simplex, generalized ?</Question>
			<Answer>Epidermolysis bullosa simplex, generalized is a form of epidermolysis bullosa, a group of genetic conditions that cause the skin to be fragile and blister easily. This disorder usually presents at birth or during infancy and results in widespread blisters over the body&apos;s surface. Though it is not a common feature of this type, scarring may occur. There may also be mild involvement of mucous membranes, fingernails and toenails, and localized thickening of the skin on the soles of the feet and the palms of the hands that increases with age. All four major types of epidermolysis bullosa simplex, including the genralized type, are caused by mutations in the KRT5 and KRT14 genes. This condition is usually inherited in an autosomal dominant fashion.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002126-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Epidermolysis bullosa simplex, generalized ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Epidermolysis bullosa simplex, generalized? Epidermolysis bullosa simplex, generalized is associated with widespread blisters that appear at birth or in early infancy. While not a common feature of this type of epidermolysis bullosa, scarring may occasionally occur. There may also be mild involvement of the mucous membranes, fingernails and toenails. As individuals age, localized thickening of the skin on the soles of the feet and palms of the hands may occur.   The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Epidermolysis bullosa simplex, generalized. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal blistering of the skin 90% Subcutaneous hemorrhage 90% Abnormal pattern of respiration 50% Abnormality of dental enamel 50% Abnormality of the nail 50% Hyperhidrosis 50% Ophthalmoparesis 50% Palmoplantar keratoderma 50% Ptosis 50% Fatigable weakness 7.5% Respiratory insufficiency 7.5% Milia 5% Nail dysplasia 5% Nail dystrophy 5% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Palmoplantar hyperkeratosis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002126-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Epidermolysis bullosa simplex, generalized ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might epidermolysis bullosa simplex be treated? There is no cure for epidermolysis bullosa simplex and there is no known treatment proven to completely control all of the symptoms. However, many complications can be lessened or avoided through early intervention. Individuals with milder forms of the disease have minimal symptoms and may require little or no treatment. In all cases, treatment is directed towards the symptoms and is largely supportive. This care should focus on prevention of infection, protection of the skin against trauma, attention to nutritional deficiencies and dietary complications, minimization of deformities and contractures, and the need for psychological support for the patient and other family members.  Detailed information regarding prevention of blisters, care of blisters and infections, and management of nutritional problems can be accessed through the National Institute of Arthritis and Musculoskeletal and Skin  Diseases (NIAMS) and article from the eMedicine journal.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
