<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002852" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12328/hereditary-sensory-and-autonomic-neuropathy-type-v">
<Focus>Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type V</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0259749</CUI>
			<CUI>C0020075</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Congenital insensitivity to pain and thermal analgesia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>HSAN5</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type 5</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Neuropathy, hereditary sensory and autonomic, type V</Synonym>
		<Synonym>HSAN V</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002852-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type V ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type V (HSAN5) is a condition that affects the sensory nerve cells. These cells, which are also called sensory neurons, transmit information about sensations such as pain, temperature, and touch. Signs and symptoms of the condition generally develop at birth or during early infancy and may include a loss of pain and temperature sensation. Because of the inability to feel deep pain, affected people suffer repeated severe injuries such as bone fractures and joint injuries that go unnoticed. HSAN5 is caused by changes (mutations) in the NGF gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Medical management is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person and is oriented to control hyperthermia (elevated body temperature) and prevent injury.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002852-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type V ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type V? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type V. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Anhidrosis 7.5% Episodic fever 5% Intellectual disability, mild 5% Acral ulceration and osteomyelitis leading to autoamputation of digits - Acral ulceration and osteomyelitis leading to autoamputation of the digits (feet) - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Infantile onset - Pain insensitivity - Painless fractures due to injury - Self-mutilation - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
