<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002087" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3681/encephalomyopathy">
<Focus>Encephalomyopathy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3554130</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Mitochondrial encephalomyopathy aminoacidopathy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mitochondrial dna depletion syndrome, encephalomyopathic form with methylmalonic aciduria, autosomal recessive</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002087-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Encephalomyopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Encephalomyopathy? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Encephalomyopathy. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal electroretinogram 90% Abnormality of visual evoked potentials 90% Aminoaciduria 90% Behavioral abnormality 90% Cerebral calcification 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Decreased body weight 90% Decreased nerve conduction velocity 90% Hearing impairment 90% Hypertrichosis 90% Incoordination 90% Microcephaly 90% Ptosis 90% Seizures 90% Short stature 90% Skeletal muscle atrophy 90% Ventriculomegaly 90% Visual impairment 90% Abnormality of the basal ganglia - Athetosis - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Cerebral atrophy - Decreased activity of mitochondrial respiratory chain - Delayed gross motor development - Dystonia - Elevated serum creatine phosphokinase - Facial diplegia - Failure to thrive - Feeding difficulties in infancy - Hyporeflexia - Infantile onset - Intellectual disability, progressive - Irritability - Lactic acidosis - Loss of ability to walk in early childhood - Methylmalonic acidemia - Methylmalonic aciduria - Muscular hypotonia - Ophthalmoplegia - Peripheral neuropathy - Progressive encephalopathy - Respiratory insufficiency due to muscle weakness - Sensorineural hearing impairment - Spasticity - Strabismus - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
