<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002595" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6520/glucose-6-phosphate-dehydrogenase-deficiency">
<Focus>Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2939465</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>G6PD deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hemolytic anemia due to G6PD deficiency</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002595-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Glucose 6 phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency is a hereditary condition in which red blood cells break down (hemolysis) when the body is exposed to certain foods, drugs, infections or stress. This condition occurs when a person is missing or doesn&apos;t have enough glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase, an enzyme which helps red blood cells work properly. G6PD deficiency is more likely to occur in males, particularly African Americans, and those from certain parts of Africa, Asia, and the Mediterranean. This condition is inherited in an X-linked recessive manner and is caused by mutations in the G6PD gene. Treatment may involve medicines to treat an infection, stopping drugs that are causing red blood cell destruction, and/or transfusions, in some cases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002595-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency? People with G6PD deficiency do not have signs of the disease unless their red blood cells are exposed to certain chemicals in food or medicine, certain bacterial or viral infections, or to stress. Many people with this condition never experience symptoms. The most common medical problem associated with G6PD deficiency is hemolytic anemia, which occurs when red blood cells are destroyed faster than the body can replace them. This type of anemia leads to paleness, yellowing of the skin and whites of the eyes (jaundice), dark urine, fatigue, shortness of breath, enlarged spleen, and a rapid heart rate. Researchers believe that carriers of a mutation in the G6PD gene may be partially protected against malaria, an infectious disease carried by a certain type of mosquito. A reduction in the amount of functional glucose-6-dehydrogenase appears to make it more difficult for this parasite to invade red blood cells. G6PD deficiency occurs more frequently in areas of the world where malaria is common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002595-3" qtype="causes">What causes Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency?  Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency is caused by mutations in the G6PD gene. This gene gives the body instructions to make an enzyme called G6PD, which is involved in processing carbohydrates. This enzyme also protects red blood cells from potentially harmful molecules called reactive oxygen species. Chemical reactions involving G6PD produce compounds that prevent reactive oxygen species from building up to toxic levels within red blood cells. Mutations in the G6PD gene lower the amount of G6PD or alter its structure, lessening its ability to play its protective role. As a result, reactive oxygen species can accumulate and damage red blood cells. Factors such as infections, certain drugs, or eating fava beans can increase the levels of reactive oxygen species, causing red blood cells to be destroyed faster than the body can replace them. This reduction of red blood cells causes the signs and symptoms of hemolytic anemia in people with G6PD deficiency.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002595-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency inherited? G6PD deficiency is inherited in an X-linked recessive manner. The gene associated with this condition is located on the X chromosome, which is one of the two sex chromosomes. In males (who have only one X chromosome), one changed (mutated) copy of the gene in each cell is enough to cause the condition because they don&apos;t have another X chromosome with a normal copy of the gene. In females (who have two X chromosomes), a mutation would have to occur in both copies of the gene to cause the disorder. Because it is unlikely that females will have two mutated copies of this gene, males are affected by X-linked recessive disorders much more frequently than females. Fathers cannot pass X-linked traits to their sons.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002595-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency be treated? The most important aspect of management for G6PD deficiency is to avoid agents that might trigger an attack. In cases of acute hemolytic anemia, a blood transfusion or even an exchange transfusion may be required. The G6PD Deficiency Association, which is an advocacy group that provides information and supportive resources to individuals and families affected by G6PD deficiency, provides a list of drugs and food ingredients that individuals with this condition should avoid. They also maintain a list of low risk drugs that are generally safe to take in low doses.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
