<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002328" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/61/femoral-facial-syndrome">
<Focus>Femoral facial syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2931183</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Femoral dysgenesis, bilateral</Synonym>
		<Synonym>FFS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Femoral hypoplasia unusual facies syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>FHUFS</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002328-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Femoral facial syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Femoral-facial syndrome is characterized by underdevelopment of the thigh bones and certain facial features, which may include upslanting eyes, short nose with a broad tip, long space between the nose and upper lip (philtrum), thin upper lip, small or underdeveloped lower jaw (micrognathia), and cleft palate. Symptoms may affect one or both sides of the face and limbs. Cleft palate has been reported only in females. Other signs and symptoms occur variably. Intellectual development has been reported as normal. In most cases the cause of the condition is unknown (sporadic). Some cases have been reported in association with diabetes during pregnancy (maternal diabetes). There have been rare reports (three cases) describing a family with more than one affected member.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002328-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Femoral facial syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Femoral facial syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Femoral facial syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the femur 90% Cleft palate 90% Abnormality of the fibula 50% Abnormality of the hip bone 50% Abnormality of the sacrum 50% Abnormality of the tibia 50% Limb undergrowth 50% Long philtrum 50% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 50% Maternal diabetes 50% Preaxial foot polydactyly 50% Short nose 50% Short stature 50% Talipes 50% Thin vermilion border 50% Upslanted palpebral fissure 50% Vertebral segmentation defect 50% Abnormal localization of kidney 7.5% Abnormality of the ribs 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 7.5% Cryptorchidism 7.5% Hernia of the abdominal wall 7.5% Long penis 7.5% Radioulnar synostosis 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Sprengel anomaly 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Ventriculomegaly 7.5% Abnormal facial shape - Abnormality of the pinna - Abnormality of the renal collecting system - Absent vertebrae - Aplasia/hypoplasia of the femur - Dysplastic sacrum - Esotropia - Gastroesophageal reflux - Hemivertebrae - Humeroradial synostosis - Hypoplastic acetabulae - Hypoplastic labia majora - Inguinal hernia - Limited elbow movement - Limited shoulder movement - Low-set ears - Micropenis - Missing ribs - Polycystic kidney dysplasia - Preaxial hand polydactyly - Pulmonic stenosis - Renal agenesis - Rib fusion - Short fifth metatarsal - Short fourth metatarsal - Short humerus - Short third metatarsal - Smooth philtrum - Sporadic - Talipes equinovarus - Toe syndactyly - Truncus arteriosus - Underdeveloped nasal alae - Ventricular septal defect - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002328-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Femoral facial syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is femoral facial syndrome inherited? The vast majority of cases of femoral facial syndrome (FFS) have been sporadic, not inherited. When a condition is sporadic, it means that it occurs in an individual who has no history of the condition in his/her family. Occurrence in more than one family member has been reported in three cases, but no sibling recurrences have been reported. Maternal diabetes has been recognized as a major factor causing FFS in more than 20% of the reported cases. The circumstances of the reported cases in the literature support non-genetic causes of FFS, such as teratogenic exposure. It is theoretically possible that the cause could sometimes be a new gene mutation occurring in the affected individual, or autosomal dominant inheritance with reduced penetrance.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
