<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002081" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6331/empty-sella-syndrome">
<Focus>Empty sella syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0014008</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Empty sella turcica</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002081-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Empty sella syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Empty sella syndrome (ESS) is a condition that involves the sella turcica, a bony structure at the base of the brain that protects the pituitary gland. There is a primary and secondary form of the condition. The primary form occurs when a structural defect above the pituitary gland increases pressure in the sella turcica and causes the gland to flatten. The secondary form occurs when the pituitary gland is damaged due to injury, a tumor, surgery or radiation therapy. Some people with ESS have no symptoms. People with secondary ESS may have symptoms of decreased pituitary function such as absence of menstruation, infertility, fatigue, and intolerance to stress and infection. In children, ESS may be associated with early onset of puberty, growth hormone deficiency, pituitary tumors, or pituitary gland dysfunction. Treatment focuses on the symptoms present in each person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002081-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Empty sella syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Empty sella syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Empty sella syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Atresia of the external auditory canal 90% Conductive hearing impairment 90% Dolichocephaly 90% Dural ectasia 90% Hypoplasia of the zygomatic bone 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Meningocele 90% Narrow face 90% Ptosis 90% Wormian bones 90% Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 50% Abnormality of the teeth 50% Craniofacial hyperostosis 50% Joint hypermobility 50% Low posterior hairline 50% Pectus excavatum 50% Prominent metopic ridge 50% Scoliosis 50% Short neck 50% Short stature 50% Umbilical hernia 50% Arnold-Chiari malformation 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Cryptorchidism 7.5% Epicanthus 7.5% Hyperlordosis 7.5% Hypertelorism 7.5% Iris coloboma 7.5% Kyphosis 7.5% Muscular hypotonia 7.5% Proptosis 7.5% Sensorineural hearing impairment 7.5% Syringomyelia 7.5% Ventricular septal defect 7.5% Abnormality of the middle ear ossicles - Abnormality of the rib cage - Abnormality of the skin - Arachnoid cyst - Arnold-Chiari type I malformation - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Biconcave vertebral bodies - Dental crowding - High palate - Inguinal hernia - Long philtrum - Low-set ears - Malar flattening - Patent ductus arteriosus - Platybasia - Posteriorly rotated ears - Sclerosis of skull base - Short nasal bridge - Smooth philtrum - Vertebral fusion - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002081-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Empty sella syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is empty sella syndrome inherited? Empty sella syndrome (ESS) is typically not inherited. We are aware of one report of familial ESS, occurring in a father and two children. Some researchers believe that a defect present at birth may play a role in the development of the condition, but are unsure whether the defect directly causes ESS or is only a predisposing factor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
