<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002445" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/826/frontometaphyseal-dysplasia">
<Focus>Frontometaphyseal dysplasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265293</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002445-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Frontometaphyseal dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Frontometaphyseal dysplasia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Frontometaphyseal dysplasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of dental morphology 90% Abnormality of frontal sinus 90% Abnormality of the metaphyses 90% Bowing of the long bones 90% Camptodactyly of finger 90% Craniofacial hyperostosis 90% Hypertelorism 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Prominent supraorbital ridges 90% Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 50% Abnormality of the palate 50% Accelerated skeletal maturation 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the thumb 50% Arachnodactyly 50% Conductive hearing impairment 50% Elbow dislocation 50% Scoliosis 50% Sensorineural hearing impairment 50% Skeletal muscle atrophy 50% Synostosis of carpal bones 50% Ulnar deviation of finger 50% Abnormality of the larynx 7.5% Abnormality of the urethra 7.5% Complete atrioventricular canal defect 7.5% Craniosynostosis 7.5% Tracheal stenosis 7.5% Ureteral stenosis 7.5% Ankle contracture - Antegonial notching of mandible - Anteriorly placed odontoid process - Broad phalanges of the hand - Coarse facial features - Coat hanger sign of ribs - Cor pulmonale - Coxa valga - Delayed eruption of teeth - Dental malocclusion - Elbow flexion contracture - Fused cervical vertebrae - Genu valgum - High palate - Hirsutism - Hydronephrosis - Hydroureter - Increased density of long bone diaphyses - Intellectual disability - Knee flexion contracture - Large foramen magnum - Long foot - Long phalanx of finger - Mitral valve prolapse - Partial fusion of carpals - Partial fusion of tarsals - Persistence of primary teeth - Pointed chin - Scapular winging - Selective tooth agenesis - Short chin - Stridor - Wide nasal bridge - Wrist flexion contracture - X-linked recessive inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
