<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002073" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9835/emanuel-syndrome">
<Focus>Emanuel syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1836929</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Supernumerary der(22),t(11;22) syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Supernumerary der(22) syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002073-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Emanuel syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Emanuel syndrome is a chromosome disorder that causes problems with physical and intellectual development. Signs and symptoms can vary but may include severe intellectual disability; small head size (microcephaly); failure to thrive; cleft palate or high-arched palate; small jaw (micrognathia); congenital heart defects; and abnormalities of the ears, kidneys, and/or male genitals. It is caused by having extra material from chromosomes 11 and 22 in each cell. Almost all people with Emanuel syndrome inherit the extra chromosome material from an unaffected parent with a balanced translocation. Treatment focuses on the specific signs and symptoms in each person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002073-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Emanuel syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Emanuel syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Emanuel syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Anal atresia - Aortic valve stenosis - Atria septal defect - Broad jaw - Cerebral atrophy - Cleft palate - Congenital diaphragmatic hernia - Congenital hip dislocation - Constipation - Cryptorchidism - Deeply set eye - Delayed eruption of primary teeth - Delayed speech and language development - Dental crowding - Facial asymmetry - Feeding difficulties - Gastroesophageal reflux - Hearing impairment - High palate - Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum - Inguinal hernia - Intellectual disability - Intrauterine growth retardation - Kyphosis - Long philtrum - Low hanging columella - Low-set ears - Low-set nipples - Macrotia - Microcephaly - Micropenis - Muscular hypotonia - Myopia - Patent ductus arteriosus - Preauricular pit - Preauricular skin tag - Pulmonic stenosis - Recurrent otitis media - Recurrent respiratory infections - Renal agenesis - Renal hypoplasia - Scoliosis - Seizures - Single umbilical artery - Strabismus - Thickened nuchal skin fold - Truncus arteriosus - Upslanted palpebral fissure - Ventricular septal defect - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
