<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002944" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6677/huntington-disease">
<Focus>Huntington disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0020179</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Huntington's chorea</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Huntington's disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>HD</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002944-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Huntington disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Huntington disease (HD) is an inherited condition that causes progressive degeneration of neurons in the brain. Signs and symptoms usually develop between ages 35 to 44 years and may include uncontrolled movements, loss of intellectual abilities, and various emotional and psychiatric problems. People with HD usually live for about 15 to 20 years after the condition begins. It is caused by changes (mutations) in the HTT gene and is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Treatment is based on the symptoms present in each person and may include various medications. There is also a less common, early-onset form of HD which begins in childhood or adolescence. For more information on this form, please visit GARD&apos;s juvenile Huntington disease Web page.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002944-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Huntington disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Huntington disease? Huntington disease (HD) is a progressive disorder that causes motor, cognitive, and psychiatric signs and symptoms. On average, most people begin developing features of HD between ages 35 and 44. Signs and symptoms vary by stage and may include: Early stage: Behavioral disturbances Clumsiness Moodiness Irritability Paranoia Apathy Anxiety Hallucinations Abnormal eye movements Depression Impaired ability to detect odors Middle stage: Dystonia Involuntary movements Trouble with balance and walking Chorea with twisting and writhing motions Unsteady gait (style of walking) Slow reaction time General weakness Weight loss Speech difficulties Stubbornness Late stage: Rigidity (continual tension of the muscles) Bradykinesia (difficulty initiating and continuing movements) Severe chorea Serious weight loss Inability to speak Inability to walk Swallowing problems Inability to care for oneself There is also a less common, early-onset form of HD which begins in childhood or adolescence. For more information on this form, please visit GARD&apos;s juvenile Huntington disease Web page. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Huntington disease. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of movement 50% Abnormality of the voice 50% Behavioral abnormality 50% Cerebral cortical atrophy 50% Developmental regression 50% EEG abnormality 50% Hypertonia 50% Rigidity 7.5% Abnormality of eye movement - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Bradykinesia - Chorea - Dementia - Depression - Gliosis - Hyperreflexia - Neuronal loss in central nervous system - Personality changes - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002944-3" qtype="causes">What causes Huntington disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Huntington disease? Huntington disease (HD) is caused by a change (mutation) in the HTT gene. This gene gives instructions for making a protein called huntingtin. The exact function of this protein is unclear, but it appears to be important to nerve cells (neurons) in the brain. The HTT gene mutation that causes HD involves a DNA segment known as a CAG trinucleotide repeat. This segment is made up of three DNA building blocks that repeat multiple times in a row. The CAG segment in a normal HTT gene repeats about 10 to 35 times. In people with HD, it may repeat from 36 to over 120 times. People with 36 to 39 CAG repeats (an intermediate size) may or may not develop HD, while people with 40 or more repeats almost always develop HD. An increased number of CAG repeats leads to an abnormally long version of the huntingtin protein. The long protein is then cut into smaller, toxic pieces that end up sticking together and accumulating in neurons. This disrupts the function of the neurons, ultimately causing the features of HD.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002944-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Huntington disease inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Huntington disease inherited? Huntington disease (HD) is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. This means that having a change (mutation) in only one of the 2 copies of the HTT gene is enough to cause the condition. When a person with HD has children, each child has a 50% (1 in 2) chance to inherit the mutated gene and develop the condition. Most people with HD have an affected parent. The family history can sometimes appear negative for various reasons even though a parent carries, or carried, a mutation in the HTT gene. In rare cases, HD is caused by a new (de novo) mutation in the HTT gene, in which case the disease occurs for the first time in the affected person and is not inherited from a parent. As HD is passed through generations, the size of the mutation in the HTT gene (called a trinucleotide repeat) often increases. A longer repeat in the HTT gene may cause earlier onset of symptoms. This phenomenon is called anticipation.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002944-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Huntington disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is genetic testing available for Huntington disease? Yes. Testing of adults at risk for Huntington disease (HD) who have no symptoms of the disease is called predictive testing. Whether to have predictive testing requires careful thought, including pre-test and post-test genetic counseling. This is particularly important because there is currently no cure. Furthermore, predictive testing cannot accurately predict the age a person with an HD mutation will develop symptoms, the severity or type of symptoms they will experience, or the future rate of disease progression. A person may want to have predictive testing because they feel they need to know, or to make personal decisions involving having children, finances, and/or career planning. Other people decide they do not want to know whether they will develop HD. Testing is appropriate to consider in symptomatic people of any age in a family with a confirmed diagnosis of HD. However, testing of asymptomatic people younger than age 18 is not considered appropriate. A main reason is that it takes away the choice of whether the person wants to know, while there is no major benefit to knowing at that age. People who are interested in learning more about genetic testing for HD should speak with a genetics professional. How is Huntington disease diagnosed? A diagnosis of Huntington disease is typically suspected in people with characteristic signs and symptoms of the condition and a family history consistent with autosomal dominant inheritance. The diagnosis can then be confirmed with genetic testing that identifies a specific type of change (mutation) in the HTT gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002944-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Huntington disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Huntington disease be treated? Unfortunately, there is currently no cure for Huntington disease (HD). The current goal of treatment is to slow down the course of the disease and help affected people function for as long and as comfortably as possible. Current treatment strategies involve the use of various medications to treat specific symptoms such as abnormal movements and behaviors. Depression and suicide are more common among affected people, so caregivers should monitor for associated symptoms and seek help if necessary. As symptoms of the disease worsen, affected people need more assistance, supervision, and care.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
