<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002392" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10173/florid-cemento-osseous-dysplasia">
<Focus>Florid cemento-osseous dysplasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0555197</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Gigantiform cementoma</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002392-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Florid cemento-osseous dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Florid cemento-osseous dysplasia is characterized by lesions in the upper and/or lower jaw that occur when normal bone is replaced with a mix of connective tissue and abnormal bone. It tends to affect middle aged women, particularly women of African American and Asian descent. The lesions often affect both sides of the jaw and are symmetrical. The number, size, and shape of the lesions vary. Occasionally the lesions expand and may cause discomfort, pain, or mild disfigurement. The radiographic appearance of the lesions are important for diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002392-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Florid cemento-osseous dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Florid cemento-osseous dysplasia? Usually florid cemento-osseous dysplasia causes no signs or symptoms and is identified incidentally during a radiograph taken for some other purpose. Occasionally however, the lesions expand causing discomfort, pain, and/or mild disfigurement. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Florid cemento-osseous dysplasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal dominant inheritance - Cementoma - Misalignment of teeth - Multiple impacted teeth - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002392-3" qtype="causes">What causes Florid cemento-osseous dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes florid cemento-osseous dysplasia? The cause of florid cemento-osseous dysplasia is not known. This condition is usually not familial (i.e., does not tend to run in families), however a rare familial form has been described in a few families. In these families the condition affected younger individuals, and the rate of lesion growth was rapid.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002392-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Florid cemento-osseous dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is florid cemento-osseous dysplasia diagnosed? Diagnosis of cemento-osseous dysplasia relies on the radiographic findings of the lesions as well as the clinical signs and symptoms. Careful assessment and examination must be made to differentiate cemento-osseous dysplasia from other lesions with similar appearance, namely Paget&apos;s disease, chronic diffuse sclerosing osteomyelitis, fibrous dysplasia, osteosarcoma, periapical cemental dysplasia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002392-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Florid cemento-osseous dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might florid cemento-osseous dysplasia be treated? In many cases florid cemento-osseous dysplasia does not require treatment, however careful follow-up may be warranted. When the condition causes discomfort, pain, or disfigurement, the treatment plan is tailored to the patient. The following article describes the treatment of florid cemento-osseous dysplasia in one patient. We recommend that you speak with your dentist to learn more about your treatment options and for referrals to local specialists. Minhas G, Hodge T, Gill DS. Orthodontic treatment and cemento-osseous dysplasia: a case report. J Orthod. 2008 Jun;35(2):90-5. You can also use the following tools to help you find specialists in your area. The Academy of General Dentistry has a tool for finding member dentists in your area.  http://www.knowyourteeth.com/findadentist/ The American Association of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgeons offers the following tool for finding member oral and maxillofacial surgeons in your area. http://www.aaoms.org/findoms.php Sometimes with more rare diseases, it can be helpful to have an evaluation with a specialist at a major university hospital or academic medical center. Such facilities often have access to up-to-date testing and technology, a large group of health care providers and specialists to consult with, and research opportunities.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
