<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002194" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/2207/exstrophy-epispadias-complex">
<Focus>Exstrophy-epispadias complex</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0014588</CUI>
			<CUI>C0015338</CUI>
			<CUI>C0563449</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>BEEC</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Bladder exstrophy-epispadias-cloacal extrophy complex</Synonym>
		<Synonym>EEC</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Exstrophy of the bladder</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Omphalocele, exstrophy of the cloaca, imperforate anus, and spinal defects complex</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002194-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Exstrophy-epispadias complex ?</Question>
			<Answer>Exstrophy-epispadias complex (EEC) comprises a spectrum of congenital abnormalities that includes epispadias, classical bladder exstrophy and exstrophy of the cloaca and several variants. EEC is characterized by a visible defect of the lower abdominal wall and other problems. The defect occurs due to a rupture of a fetal tissue known as the cloacal membrane during the first trimester of pregnancy. This results in the abnormal development of the abdominal wall of the fetus. The exact timing of the rupture determines whether the child is born with isolated epispadias, classic bladder exstrophy or cloacal exstrophy. Therefore, depending on severity, EEC may involve the urinary system, musculoskeletal system, pelvis, pelvic floor, abdominal wall, genitalia, and sometimes the spine and anus. There is no known cause for this condition. Treatment may involve several surgeries to repair the abdominal wall and any associated malformation. The University of Michigan has a webpage about the development of the embryo and its parts, including the formation of the cloaca.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
