<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002934" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9645/human-t-cell-leukemia-virus-type-1">
<Focus>Human T-cell leukemia virus type 1</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0023492</CUI>
			<CUI>C0020094</CUI>
			<CUI>C0596828</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T005</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>HTLV-1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Human T lymphotropic virus type 1</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002934-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Human T-cell leukemia virus type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Human T-cell leukemia virus, type 1 (HTLV-1) is a retroviral infection that affect the T cells (a type of white blood cell). Although this virus generally causes no signs or symptoms, some affected people may later develop adult T-cell leukemia (ATL), HTLV-1 associated myelopathy/tropical spastic paraparesis (HAM/TSP) or other medical conditions. HTLV-1 is spread by blood transfusions, sexual contact and sharing needles. It can also be spread from mother to child during birth or breast-feeding. There is no cure or treatment for HTLV-1 and it is considered a lifelong condition; however, most (95%) infected people remain asymptomatic (show no symptoms) throughout life.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002934-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Human T-cell leukemia virus type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of human T-cell leukemia virus, type 1? Human T-cell leukemia virus, type 1 (HTLV-1) generally causes no signs or symptoms. However, some affected people may later develop adult T-cell leukemia (ATL), HTLV-1 associated myelopathy/tropical spastic paraparesis (HAM/TSP) or other medical conditions. Approximately 2-5% of people with HTLV-1 will develop ATL, a cancer of the T-cells (a type of white blood cell). The signs and symptoms of this condition and the disease progression vary from person to person. Affected people may have the following features: Fatigue Lymphadenopathy (swollen lymph nodes) Thirst Nausea and vomiting Fever Skin and bone abnormalities Enlarged liver and/or spleen Frequent infections Roughly .25-2% of people with HTLV-1 will develop HAM/TSP, a chronic, progressive disease of the nervous system. Signs and symptoms of this condition vary but may include: Progressive weakness Stiff muscles Muscle spasms Backache &apos;Weak&apos; bladder Constipation</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002934-3" qtype="causes">What causes Human T-cell leukemia virus type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes human T-cell leukemia virus, type 1? Human T-cell leukemia virus, type 1 (HTLV-1) occurs when a person is infected by the human T-cell leukemia retrovirus. HTLV-1 is spread by blood transfusions, sexual contact and sharing needles. It can also be spread from mother to child during birth or breast-feeding. It is unclear why some people with HTLV-1 develop adult T-cell leukemia (ATL), HTLV-1 associated myelopathy/tropical spastic paraparesis (HAM/TSP) or other medical conditions, while others remain asymptomatic (show no signs or symptoms) their entire lives.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002934-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Human T-cell leukemia virus type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is human T-cell leukemia virus, type 1 diagnosed? Human T-cell leukemia virus, type 1 (HTLV-1) is usually diagnosed based on blood tests that detect antibodies to the virus. However, HTLV-1 is often never suspected or diagnosed since most people (95%) never develop any signs or symptoms of the infection. Diagnosis may occur during screening for blood donation, testing performed due to a family history of the infection, or a work-up for an HTLV-1-associated condition such as adult T-cell leukemia (ATL) or HTLV-1 associated myelopathy/tropical spastic paraparesis (HAM/TSP).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002934-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Human T-cell leukemia virus type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might human T-cell leukemia virus, type 1 be treated?  No cure or treatment exists for human T-cell leukemia virus, type 1 (HTLV-1). Management is focused on early detection and preventing the spread of HTLV-1 to others. Screening blood doners, promoting safe sex and discouraging needle sharing can decrease the number of new infections. Mother-to-child transmission can be reduced by screening pregnant women so infected mothers can avoid breastfeeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
