<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002063" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/2082/ehlers-danlos-syndrome-vascular-type">
<Focus>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, vascular type</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
			<CUI>C0013720</CUI>
			<CUI>C0268338</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Ehlers Danlos syndrome, ecchymotic type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ehlers Danlos syndrome, arterial type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ehlers Danlos syndrome, Sack-Barabas type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>EDS4 (formerly)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome type 4 (formerly)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002063-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, vascular type ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS), vascular type is an inherited connective tissue disorder that is caused by defects in a protein called collagen. It is generally considered the most severe form of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome. Common symptoms include thin, translucent skin; easy bruising; characteristic facial appearance; and fragile arteries, muscles and internal organs. EDS, vascular type is caused by changes (mutations) in the COL3A1 gene and is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Treatment and management is focused on preventing serious complications and relieving associated signs and symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002063-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, vascular type ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, vascular type? The signs and symptoms of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS), vascular type vary but may include: Fragile tissues (including arteries, muscles and internal organs) that are prone to rupture Thin, translucent skin Characteristic facial appearance (thin lips, small chin, thin nose, large eyes) Acrogeria (premature aging of the skin of the hands and feet) Hypermobility of small joints (i.e. fingers and toes) Early-onset varicose veins Pneumothorax Easy bruising Joint dislocations and subluxations (partial dislocation) Congenital dislocation of the hips Congenital clubfoot Receding gums The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, vascular type. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of coagulation 90% Abnormality of the eyelashes 90% Abnormality of the hip bone 90% Abnormality of the mitral valve 90% Abnormality of the pleura 90% Acrocyanosis 90% Aneurysm 90% Aortic dissection 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the earlobes 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the eyebrow 90% Bladder diverticulum 90% Bruising susceptibility 90% Carious teeth 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Cryptorchidism 90% Epicanthus 90% Flexion contracture 90% Gastrointestinal infarctions 90% Hypermelanotic macule 90% Hypertelorism 90% Hypokalemia 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Melanocytic nevus 90% Pectus excavatum 90% Peripheral arteriovenous fistula 90% Prematurely aged appearance 90% Short stature 90% Sprengel anomaly 90% Telecanthus 90% Thin skin 90% Glaucoma 50% Malar flattening 50% Premature birth 50% Proptosis 50% Respiratory insufficiency 50% Talipes 50% Telangiectasia of the skin 50% Thin vermilion border 50% Venous insufficiency 50% Abnormality of hair texture 7.5% Abnormality of the intestine 7.5% Abnormality of the palate 7.5% Abnormality of the pulmonary artery 7.5% Abnormality of the pupil 7.5% Alopecia 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the abdominal wall musculature 7.5% Apnea 7.5% Arterial dissection 7.5% Atypical scarring of skin 7.5% Blue sclerae 7.5% Cerebral ischemia 7.5% Cutis laxa 7.5% Cystocele 7.5% Decreased corneal thickness 7.5% Deeply set eye 7.5% Dilatation of the ascending aorta 7.5% Displacement of the external urethral meatus 7.5% Gingival overgrowth 7.5% Gingivitis 7.5% Hematuria 7.5% Joint dislocation 7.5% Joint hypermobility 7.5% Microdontia 7.5% Migraine 7.5% Narrow nasal bridge 7.5% Osteoarthritis 7.5% Osteolysis 7.5% Premature loss of primary teeth 7.5% Ptosis 7.5% Reduced consciousness/confusion 7.5% Renovascular hypertension 7.5% Trismus 7.5% Umbilical hernia 7.5% Uterine rupture 7.5% Vertigo 7.5% Abnormality of the urinary system - Absent earlobe - Acroosteolysis (feet) - Alopecia of scalp - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Cerebral aneurysm - Cigarette-paper scars - Fragile skin - Hemoptysis - Hypermobility of distal interphalangeal joints - Inguinal hernia - Keratoconus - Mitral valve prolapse - Molluscoid pseudotumors - Osteolytic defects of the phalanges of the hand - Periodontitis - Premature delivery because of cervical insufficiency or membrane fragility - Premature loss of teeth - Spontaneous pneumothorax - Talipes equinovarus - Uterine prolapse - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002063-3" qtype="causes">What causes Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, vascular type ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, vascular type? Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS), vascular type is caused by changes (mutations) in the COL3A1 gene. The COL3A1 gene provides instructions for making a component of type III collagen. Collagen is a protein that provides structure and strength to connective tissues throughout the body. Type III collagen, specifically, is found in tissues such as the skin, lungs, intestinal walls, and the walls of blood vessels. Mutations in the COL3A1 gene lead to defects in type III collagen molecules and/or reduced amounts of functional type III collagen. This causes the many signs and symptoms associated with EDS, vascular type.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002063-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, vascular type inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, vascular type inherited? Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS), vascular type is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. This means that to be affected, a person only needs a change (mutation) in one copy of the responsible gene in each cell. In some cases, an affected person inherits the mutation from an affected parent. Other cases may result from new (de novo) mutations in the gene. These cases occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family. A person with EDS, vascular type has a 50% chance with each pregnancy of passing along the altered gene to his or her child.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002063-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, vascular type ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, vascular type diagnosed? A diagnosis of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS), vascular type is typically based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. Genetic testing for a change (mutation) in the COL3A1 gene can then be ordered to confirm the diagnosis. Collagen typing performed on a skin biopsy may be recommended if genetic testing is inconclusive. Collagen is a tough, fiber-like protein that makes up about a third of body protein. It is part of the structure of tendons, bones, and connective tissues. People with EDS, vascular type have abnormalities in type III collagen.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002063-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, vascular type ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, vascular type be treated? The treatment and management of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS), vascular type is focused on relieving associated signs and symptoms and preventing serious complications. For example, people with EDS, vascular type have tissue fragility that puts them at high risk for rupture of arteries, muscles and internal organs. It is, therefore, important to seek immediate medical attention for any sudden, unexplained pain as emergency surgery may be indicated. Pregnant women with EDS, vascular type should be followed by a maternal-fetal specialists at a high-risk perinatal center. Periodic screening may be recommended to diagnose aneurysms or other problems that may not be associated with obvious symptoms. People with the EDS, vascular type should also minimize risk of injury by avoiding contact sports, heavy lifting, and weight training. Elective surgery is also discouraged. GeneReview&apos;s Web site offers more specific information about the treatment and management of EDS, vascular type. Please click on the link to access this resource. Please speak to your healthcare provider if you have any questions about your personal medical management plan.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
