<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002441" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6463/froelich-syndrome">
<Focus>Froelich syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Froelich's adiposity</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Froelich's syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Froehlich syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Adiposogenital dystrophy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Babinski-Froelich syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002441-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Froelich syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Froelich syndrome is characterized by obesity and hypogonadism due to a hypothalamic-pituitary disorder. The hypothalamus is a part of the brain where certain functions such as sleep cycles and body temperature are regulated. The pituitary is a gland that makes hormones that affect growth and the functions of other glands in the body. Froehlich syndrome is acquired (i.e., not thought to be inherited or genetic). This syndrome appears to affect males more commonly. The term &apos;Froelich syndrome&apos; is rarely used today.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002441-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Froelich syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Froelich syndrome? Signs and symptoms of Froelich syndrome include obesity, small testes, delay in the onset of puberty, short stature (compared to other family members of the same sex), malformed or undersized fingernails, and headaches. Some children with Froehlich syndrome may have mental retardation, difficulties with vision, and in rare cases diabetes. Other symptoms of the syndrome may include excessive thirst, excessive urination, and very delicate skin.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002441-3" qtype="causes">What causes Froelich syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Froelich syndrome? Froehlich syndrome is usually caused by lesions in the hypothalamic gland or pituitary gland. The lesions may be caused by a tumor (e.g., craniopharyngioma), swelling from an infection (e.g., tuberculosis), encephalitis, or other brain injuries.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002441-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Froelich syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Froelich syndrome be diagnosed? Diagnosis of Froelich syndrome may be difficult and requires cautious and thoughtful clinical examination, testing urine for low levels of pituitary hormones, and likely other additional tests before a definitive diagnosis of Froehlich syndrome can be made.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
