<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002675" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6549/graves-disease">
<Focus>Graves' disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0018213</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Basedow disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Exophthalmic goiter</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Parry disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Graves' hyperthyroidism</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002675-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Graves' disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Graves&apos; disease is an autoimmune disorder that leads to overactivity of the thyroid gland (hyperthyroidism). It is caused by an abnormal immune system response that causes the thyroid gland to produce too much thyroid hormones. Graves disease is the most common cause of hyperthyroidism and occurs most often in women over age 20. However, the disorder may occur at any age and may affect males as well. Treatment may include radioiodine therapy, antithyroid drugs, and/or thyroid surgery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002675-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Graves' disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Graves&apos; disease? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Graves&apos; disease. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Abnormality of the abdomen - Congestive heart failure - Goiter - Graves disease - Hyperactivity - Hyperhidrosis - Hyperreflexia - Irritability - Muscle weakness - Onycholysis - Polyphagia - Pretibial myxedema - Proptosis - Weight loss - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
