<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002962" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/434/hydrocephalus-due-to-congenital-stenosis-of-aqueduct-of-sylvius">
<Focus>Hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0266476</CUI>
			<CUI>C0020255</CUI>
			<CUI>C0265216</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hydrocephalus, X-linked</Synonym>
		<Synonym>HSAS1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Aqueductal stenosis, X-linked</Synonym>
		<Synonym>HSAS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>HYCX</Synonym>
		<Synonym>L1 syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002962-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius (HSAS) is a form of L1 syndrome, which is an inherited disorder that primarily affects the nervous system. Males with HSAS are typically born with severe hydrocephalus and adducted thumbs (bent towards the palm). Other sign and symptoms of the condition include severe intellectual disability and spasticity. HSAS, like all forms of L1 syndrome, is caused by changes (mutations) in the L1CAM gene and is inherited in an X-linked recessive manner. Treatment is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002962-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius? Males with hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius (HSAS) are typically born with severe hydrocephalus and adducted thumbs (bent towards the palm). Other signs and symptoms may include: Seizures Severe intellectual disability Spasticity Of note, HSAS is one form of L1 syndrome, which is an inherited condition that primarily affects the nervous system. Other forms include MASA syndrome, X-linked complicated hereditary spastic paraplegia type 1, and X-linked complicated corpus callosum agenesis. All of the different forms of L1 syndrome may be observed in affected people within the same family. GeneReviews offers more specific information about the signs and symptoms associated with each form of L1 syndrome. Please click on the link to access this resource. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aqueductal stenosis 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 90% Hydrocephalus 90% Increased intracranial pressure 90% Adducted thumb 50% Coarse facial features 7.5% Holoprosencephaly 7.5% Limitation of joint mobility 7.5% Nystagmus 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Absent septum pellucidum - Agenesis of corpus callosum - Corticospinal tract hypoplasia - Intellectual disability - Macrocephaly - Spastic paraplegia - Spasticity - X-linked recessive inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002962-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius inherited? Hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius is inherited in an X-linked recessive manner. A condition is X-linked if the responsible gene is located on the X chromosome. The X chromosome is one of the two sex chromosomes (the other sex chromosome is the Y chromosome). Females have two X chromosomes in each cell and males have an X chromosome and a Y chromosome in each cell. Although females have two X chromosomes, one of the X chromosomes in each cell is &quot;turned off&quot; and all of the genes on that chromosome are inactivated. Females who have a change (mutation) in a gene on one of their X chromosomes are called carriers of the related condition. Carrier females usually do not have symptoms of the condition because the X chromosome with the mutated gene is often turned off and they have another X chromosome with a working copy of the gene. Sometimes, the X chromosome with the working copy of the gene is turned off, which may cause symptoms of the condition. However, females with symptoms are usually much more mildly affected than males. A male has only one X chromosome, so if he inherits a mutation on the X chromosome, he will have signs and symptoms (be affected). Males with an X-linked recessive condition always pass the mutated gene to all of their daughters, who will be carriers. A male cannot pass an X-linked gene to his sons because males always pass their Y chromosome to male offspring. Female carriers of an X-linked recessive condition have a 25% chance with each pregnancy to have a carrier daughter like themselves, a 25% chance to have a non-carrier daughter, a 25% chance to have an affected son, and a 25% chance to have an unaffected son. This also means that each daughter of a carrier mother has a 50% chance of being a carrier, and each son has a 50% chance of having the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002962-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius diagnosed? A diagnosis of hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius is typically suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms on physical examination and/or brain imaging (i.e. CT scan, MRI scan). Identification of a change (mutation) in the L1CAM gene can be used to confirm the diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002962-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius be treated? The treatment of hydrocephalus due to congenital stenosis of aqueduct of sylvius (HSAS) is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person. For example, hydrocephalus is typically treated with shunt surgery. Special education and early intervention may be recommended for children with intellectual disability. Although intervention is rarely necessary for adducted thumbs (bent towards the palms), tendon transfer surgery or splinting may be suggested in some cases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
