<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002770" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10094/hemochromatosis-type-4">
<Focus>Hemochromatosis type 4</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0018995</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>HFE4</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hemochromatosis, autosomal dominant</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hemochromatosis due to defect in ferroportin</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Autosomal dominant hereditary hemochromatosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ferroportin disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hemochromatosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002770-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hemochromatosis type 4 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hemochromatosis type 4 is a disease in which too much iron builds up in the body.  This extra iron is toxic to the body and can damage the organs. Hemochromatosis is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. It is caused by mutations in the SLC40A1 gene. Hemochromatosis may be aquired or hereditary. Hereditary hemochromatosis is classified by type depending on the age of onset and other factors such as genetic cause and mode of inheritance. To learn more about these types click on the disease names below: Hemochromatosis type 1 Hemochromatosis type 2 Hemochromatosis type 3 There is also a neonatal form of hemochromatosis: Neonatal hemochromatosis</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002770-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hemochromatosis type 4 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Hemochromatosis type 4? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Hemochromatosis type 4. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of iron homeostasis 90% Arthralgia 90% Generalized hyperpigmentation 90% Joint swelling 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Abdominal pain 50% Hepatic steatosis 50% Cirrhosis 7.5% Congenital hepatic fibrosis 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
