<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002149" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9732/epithelial-basement-membrane-corneal-dystrophy">
<Focus>Epithelial basement membrane corneal dystrophy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0521723</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Corneal dystrophy, anterior basement membrane</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Microcystic dystrophy of the cornea</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cogan corneal dystrophy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Map-dot-fingerprint dystrophy of cornea</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002149-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Epithelial basement membrane corneal dystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Epithelial basement membrane corneal dystrophy is a condition where the epithelium of the cornea (the outermost region of the cornea) loses its normal clarity due to a buildup of cloudy material. It gets its name from the unusual appearance of the cornea during an eye exam. This dystrophy occurs when the epithelium&apos;s basement membrane develops abnormally, causing the epithelial cells to not properly adhere to it. This leads to recurrent epithelial erosions, which can cause blurred vision and severe pain. This condition is usually not inherited. However, families with autosomal dominant inheritance and mutations in the TGFBI gene have been identified.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002149-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Epithelial basement membrane corneal dystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Epithelial basement membrane corneal dystrophy? A chronic problem seen in this condition is the epithelial erosions. They can alter the cornea&apos;s normal curvature, causing periodic blurred vision. These erosions may also expose the nerve endings that line the tissue, resulting in moderate to severe pain lasting as long as several days. Generally, the pain will be worse upon awakening in the morning. Other symptoms include sensitivity to light, excessive tearing, and foreign body sensation in the eye. This condition usually affects adults between the ages of 40 and 70, although it can develop earlier in life. It gets its name from the unusual appearance of the cornea during an eye exam. Most often, the affected epithelium will have a map-like appearance, i.e., large, slightly gray outlines that look like a continent on a map. There may also be clusters of opaque dots close to the map-like patches. Less frequently, the irregular basement membrane will form concentric lines in the central cornea that resemble small fingerprints. Epithelial basement membrane corneal dystrophy is not a progressive condition. Typically, it will flare up occasionally for a few years and then go away on its own, with no lasting loss of vision. Most people never know that they have this condition, since they do not have any pain or vision loss. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Epithelial basement membrane corneal dystrophy. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal dominant inheritance - Corneal dystrophy - Map-dot-fingerprint corneal dystrophy - Recurrent corneal erosions - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002149-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Epithelial basement membrane corneal dystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might epithelial basement membrane corneal dystrophy be treated? Because most people do not develop noticeable signs or symptoms, treatment usually is not necessary. However, if treatment is needed, doctors will try to control the pain associated with the epithelial erosions. They may patch the eye to immobilize it, or prescribe lubricating eye drops and ointments. With treatment, these erosions usually heal within three days, although periodic flashes of pain may occur for several weeks thereafter. Other treatments include anterior corneal punctures to allow better adherence of cells; corneal scraping to remove eroded areas of the cornea and allow regeneration of healthy epithelial tissue; and use of the excimer laser to remove surface irregularities. An article from eMedicine Journal provides additional information on treatment for epithelial basement membrane corneal dystrophy at the following link. You may need to register to view the article, but registration is free. http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/1193945-treatment#showall</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
