<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002924" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12682/horizontal-gaze-palsy-with-progressive-scoliosis">
<Focus>Horizontal gaze palsy with progressive scoliosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1846496</CUI>
			<CUI>C0522224</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Progressive external ophthalmoplegia and scoliosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>HGPPS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Gaze palsy, horizontal, with progressive scoliosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Gaze Palsy, Familial Horizontal, With Progressive Scoliosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002924-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Horizontal gaze palsy with progressive scoliosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Horizontal gaze palsy with progressive scoliosis (HGPPS) is a rare disorder that affects vision and also causes an abnormal curvature of the spine (scoliosis). People with this condition are unable to move their eyes side-to-side (horizontally) and must turn their head instead of moving their eyes to track moving objects. Scoliosis develops in infancy or childhood and worsens over time. Scoliosis can be painful and may interfere with movement so it is often treated with surgery early in life. HGPPS is caused by changes (mutations) in the ROBO3 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Treatment is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002924-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Horizontal gaze palsy with progressive scoliosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Horizontal gaze palsy with progressive scoliosis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Horizontal gaze palsy with progressive scoliosis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Kyphosis 90% Cognitive impairment 50% Nystagmus 50% Short neck 50% Seizures 7.5% Sensorineural hearing impairment 7.5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Congenital onset - Horizontal supranuclear gaze palsy - Progressive ophthalmoplegia - Thoracolumbar scoliosis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
