<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002424" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5138/frank-ter-haar-syndrome">
<Focus>Frank Ter Haar syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0398650</CUI>
			<CUI>C1855305</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Ter Haar syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Autosomal recessive Melnick-Needles syndrome (formerly)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Megalocornea, multiple skeletal anomalies, and developmental delay</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002424-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Frank Ter Haar syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Frank-Ter Haar syndrome is a rare inherited condition characterized by multiple skeletal abnormalities, developmental delay, and characteristic facial features (unusually large cornea, flattened back of the head, wide fontanels, prominent forehead, widely spaced eyes, prominent eyes, full cheeks, and small chin). Less than 30 cases have been reported worldwide. Protruding ears, prominent coccyx bone (or tail bone), and congenital heart defects are also frequently present. This condition is caused by mutations in the SH3PXD2B gene and is thought to be inherited in an autosomal recessive fashion.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002424-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Frank Ter Haar syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Frank Ter Haar syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Frank Ter Haar syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Motor delay 5% Abnormality of cardiovascular system morphology - Anterior concavity of thoracic vertebrae - Bowing of the long bones - Broad clavicles - Broad nasal tip - Buphthalmos - Coarse facial features - Cortical irregularity - Delayed cranial suture closure - Dental malocclusion - Flared metaphysis - Flat occiput - Full cheeks - Gingival overgrowth - Growth delay - High palate - Hip dysplasia - Hypertelorism - Large eyes - Low-set ears - Osteopenia - Osteoporosis - Pectus excavatum - Prominent coccyx - Prominent forehead - Proptosis - Protruding ear - Short long bone - Short phalanx of finger - Talipes equinovarus - Wide anterior fontanel - Wide mouth - Wormian bones - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
