<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002542" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/2469/giant-congenital-nevus">
<Focus>Giant congenital nevus</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1842036</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>GPHN</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Giant pigmented hairy nevus</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Giant pigmented nevus</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Bathing trunk nevus</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Large congenital melanocytic nevus</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002542-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Giant congenital nevus ?</Question>
			<Answer>A giant congenital nevus is a dark-colored, often hairy patch of skin that is present at birth (congenital). It grows proportionally to the child. A congenital pigmented nevus is considered giant if by adulthood it is larger than 20cm (about 8 inches) in diameter. Giant congenital nevi can occur in people of any racial or ethnic background and on any area of the body. They result from localized genetic changes in the fetus that lead to excessive growth of melanocytes, the cells in the skin that are responsible for skin color. People with giant congenital nevi may experience a number of complications ranging from fragile, dry, or itchy skin to neurological problems like neurocutaneous melanocytosis (excess pigment cells in the brain or spinal cord). They also have an increased risk of developing malignant melanoma, a type of skin cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002542-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Giant congenital nevus ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Giant congenital nevus? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Giant congenital nevus. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Hypertrichosis 50% Hydrocephalus 7.5% Hypopigmented skin patches 7.5% Pruritus 7.5% Sarcoma 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Broad forehead - Broad nasal tip - Congenital giant melanocytic nevus - Cutaneous melanoma - Deep philtrum - Full cheeks - Long philtrum - Narrow nasal ridge - Open mouth - Periorbital fullness - Prominence of the premaxilla - Prominent forehead - Round face - Short nose - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002542-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Giant congenital nevus ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might giant congenital nevus be treated? Treatment for giant congenital nevus depends on the age of the affected individual as well as the size, location, and thickness of the nevus. Surgery may be done to remove the nevus, particularly when there is a concern that it may develop into a melanoma. When small nevi are removed, the surrounding skin can often be pulled together with stitches. Larger nevi may need to be removed in several stages and full-thickness skin grafts may be needed to help the skin heal following surgery. Laser treatments may be used for superficial skin imperfections, including reducing pigment and hair, but cannot completely remove the nevus. Affected individuals should self-monitor and continue to have regular skin examinations to check for benign or malignant tumors. Early awareness will allow their physicians  to adjust treatment protocols  accordingly. Children are most likely to show neurological signs before primary school and can respond well to a range of symptomatic therapies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
