<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002724" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/68/hanhart-syndrome">
<Focus>Hanhart syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0595985</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Aglossia adactylia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hypoglossia-hypodactylia syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Peromelia with micrognathia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002724-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hanhart syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hanhart syndrome is a rare condition that primarily affects the craniofacial region and the limbs (arms and legs). People affected by this condition are often born with a short, incompletely developed tongue; absent or partially missing fingers and/or toes; abnormalities of the arms and/or legs; and an extremely small jaw. The severity of these physical abnormalities varies greatly among affected people, and children with this condition often have some, but not all, of the symptoms. The cause of Hanhart syndrome is not fully understood. Treatment depends on the signs and symptoms present in each person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002724-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hanhart syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Hanhart syndrome? The signs and symptoms of Hanhart syndrome vary, but may include: Small mouth Short, incompletely developed tongue (hypoglossia) Absent, partially missing, or shortened fingers and/or toes Jaw abnormalities such as micrognathia, retrognathia (receding jaw), or partially missing mandible (lower jaw) High-arched, narrow, or cleft palate Absent or unusually formed arms and/or legs Missing teeth Absence of major salivary glands Some infants with Hanhart syndrome may be born with paralysis of certain areas of the face. If the tongue and/or mouth are affected, this can worsen feeding difficulties that are already present due to the craniofacial abnormalities listed above. The severity of the physical abnormalities associated with Hanhart syndrome varies greatly among affected people, and children with this disorder often have some, but not all, of the symptoms. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Hanhart syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Narrow mouth 90% Upper limb phocomelia 90% Abnormality of the fingernails 50% Brachydactyly syndrome 50% Cleft palate 50% Finger syndactyly 50% Reduced number of teeth 50% Short distal phalanx of finger 50% Split hand 50% Telecanthus 50% Wide nasal bridge 50% Abnormality of the cranial nerves 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Facial asymmetry 7.5% Gastroschisis 7.5% Neurological speech impairment 7.5% Urogenital fistula 7.5% Abnormality of oral frenula - Adactyly - Aglossia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Epicanthus - Microglossia - Retrognathia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002724-3" qtype="causes">What causes Hanhart syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Hanhart syndrome syndrome? The exact underlying cause of Hanhart syndrome is currently unknown. However, researchers suspect that there may be genetic and/or environmental factors that contribute to the development of the condition. To date, no specific disease-causing genes have been identified. Possible environmental factors including: Exposure of the pregnant mother to radiation, teratogenic medications, or hypothermia Trauma or disrupted blood flow to the baby in the womb Chorionic villus sampling procedures (when performed too early in the pregnancy)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002724-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hanhart syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Hanhart syndrome diagnosed? A diagnosis of Hanhart syndrome is typically made based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. In some cases, the diagnosis may be suspected before birth if concerning features are seen on ultrasound.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002724-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hanhart syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Hanhart syndrome treated? Because Hanhart syndrome affects many different systems of the body, medical management is often provided by a team of doctors and other healthcare professionals. Treatment for this condition varies because it depends on the signs and symptoms present in each person. For example, limb and/or craniofacial abnormalities may be treated with surgery and/or prostheses. Affected children may also need speech therapy, physical therapy, and/or occupational therapy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
