<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002327" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8234/feltys-syndrome">
<Focus>Felty's syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0015773</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Felty syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Rheumatoid arthritis, splenomegaly and neutropenia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Familial Felty's syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002327-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Felty's syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Felty&apos;s syndrome is a rare, potentially serious disorder that is defined by the presence of three conditions: rheumatoid arthritis (RA), an enlarged spleen (splenomegaly) and a decreased white blood cell count (neutropenia), which causes repeated infections. Although some individuals with Felty&apos;s syndrome are asymptomatic, others can develop serious and life-threatening infections. Symptoms of Felty&apos;s syndrome, in addition to those associated with the three conditions stated above, may include fatigue, fever, weight loss, discoloration of patches of skin, mild hepatomegaly (enlarged liver), lymphadenopathy (swelling of lymph nodes), Sjgren syndrome, vasculitis, lower-extremity ulcers, and other findings. The exact cause is unknown, but several risk factors have been proposed, including autoimmunity. A few familial cases of the condition have been reported. Treatment typically focuses on controlling the underlying RA; immunosuppressive therapy for RA may improve neutropenia and splenomegaly.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002327-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Felty's syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Felty&apos;s syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Felty&apos;s syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of neutrophils 90% Arthralgia 90% Arthritis 90% Autoimmunity 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Osteolysis 90% Abnormality of lymphocytes 50% Anemia 50% Lymphadenopathy 50% Otitis media 50% Recurrent pharyngitis 50% Sinusitis 50% Splenomegaly 50% Weight loss 50% Abnormality of the pericardium 7.5% Abnormality of the pleura 7.5% Bone marrow hypocellularity 7.5% Cellulitis 7.5% Generalized hyperpigmentation 7.5% Hepatomegaly 7.5% Inflammatory abnormality of the eye 7.5% Irregular hyperpigmentation 7.5% Lymphoma 7.5% Peripheral neuropathy 7.5% Pulmonary fibrosis 7.5% Recurrent urinary tract infections 7.5% Sepsis 7.5% Skin ulcer 7.5% Thrombocytopenia 7.5% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Neutropenia - Rheumatoid arthritis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002327-3" qtype="causes">What causes Felty's syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Felty&apos;s syndrome? The exact cause of Felty&apos;s syndrome is unknown, although several causes and risk factors have been proposed. Some experts believe it may be an autoimmune disorder, and that it may sometimes be inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Other proposed risk factors have included: RF (rheumatoid factor) positivity - being positive for a test used to help diagnose rheumatoid arthritis Long-term rheumatoid arthritis Aggressive and erosive synovitis (inflammation of the tissue that lines the joints) HLA-DR4 positivity (having a specific gene for the immune system that is associated with RA) and DR4 homozygosity (having 2 identical copies of this gene) Extra-articular RA manifestations (symptoms that are not joint-related)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002327-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Felty's syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is Felty&apos;s syndrome inherited? It has not been concluded that Felty&apos;s syndrome is an inherited condition; most individuals with Felty&apos;s syndrome have not had a history of the condition in their family. However, there have been a few reports of the condition appearing to be familial. Furthermore, although the condition itself may not be inherited, some of the risk factors associated with Felty&apos;s syndrome may have genetic components. One study found that a family history of rheumatoid arthritis was more common in patients with Felty&apos;s syndrome and that there was a strong association with HLA-DR4 (an immune system gene common in individuals with RA). The authors also stated that there was an increased frequency of another gene as well, suggesting that certain other immune system genes may interact with HLA-DR4 and contribute to individuals developing Felty&apos;s syndrome. In another report, the authors described a family in which 3 siblings had Felty&apos;s syndrome. All of the siblings shared a specific haplotype (a group of immune system genes that may be inherited together). The authors stated that they believe this supports the theory that multiple genetic factors are involved in family members being predisposed to Felty&apos;s syndrome. An earlier article described a family in which the mother and 2 of her 5 children had Felty&apos;s syndrome, which suggested autosomal dominant inheritance (which has not otherwise been reported).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
