<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002061" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9991/ehlers-danlos-syndrome-progeroid-type">
<Focus>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, progeroid type</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0013720</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Proteodermatan sulfate, defective biosynthesis of</Synonym>
		<Synonym>PDS, defective biosynthesis of</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dermatan sulfate proteoglycan</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Xylosylprotein 4-beta-galactosyltransferase deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>XGPT deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002061-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, progeroid type ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome progeroid type is a genetic disorder of the connective tissue, which is the material between the cells of the body that gives tissues form and strength. The disorder primarily affects the skin, hair, and skeletal system. Symptoms usually show up by childhood or adolescence. Like people with other types of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, individuals with the progeroid form have unusually flexible joints, loose elastic skin, and easy scarring. Features that are unique to this type include sparse scalp hair and eyebrows, and loose elastic skin on the face; these features cause affected individuals to look older than their age. Additional symptoms may include bone weakness, weak muscle tone, mild intellectual disability, and delayed growth in affected children. The progeroid type of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome is caused by mutations in the B4GALT7 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002061-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, progeroid type ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, progeroid type? Ehlers-Danlos syndrome refers to a group of connective tissue disorders characterized by stretchy or kneadable skin, double jointedness, and delayed healing of skin wounds. In addition to these traits, individuals with the progeroid type have thin curly hair, sparse eyebrows and eyelashes, loose elastic skin on the face, and may also have uneven facial features. Although progeroid means &quot;appearance similar to old age&quot;, individuals with progeroid Ehlers-Danlos syndrome do not actually have premature aging and are not expected to have a shortened life span. Other symptoms may include poor muscle tone, fragile bones from low bone mineral density, abnormal teeth, and infection of gums around the teeth. Children who are affected may have delayed growth, which can result in short stature as an adult (less than 152cm). Mild intellectual disabilities or learning disabilities have also been associated with this disorder. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, progeroid type. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of adipose tissue 90% Abnormality of the aortic valve 90% Abnormality of the pulmonary valve 90% Cryptorchidism 90% Epicanthus 90% Flexion contracture 90% Gingivitis 90% Muscular hypotonia 90% Prematurely aged appearance 90% Short stature 90% Testicular torsion 90% Thin skin 90% Abnormal facial shape 50% Abnormality of skin pigmentation 50% Alopecia 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the abdominal wall musculature 50% Atypical scarring of skin 50% Reduced bone mineral density 50% Skeletal dysplasia 50% Telecanthus 50% Joint hypermobility 7.5% Absent earlobe - Arachnodactyly - Atrophic scars - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Bifid uvula - Coxa valga - Failure to thrive - Joint laxity - Long toe - Macrocephaly - Narrow chest - Narrow mouth - Osteopenia - Palmoplantar cutis gyrata - Pes planus - Proptosis - Radioulnar synostosis - Short clavicles - Single transverse palmar crease - Slender toe - Small face - Sparse scalp hair - Wide nasal bridge - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002061-3" qtype="causes">What causes Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, progeroid type ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Ehlers-Danlos syndrome progeroid type? Ehlers-Danlos syndrome progeroid type is caused by changes (mutations) in both of an individual&apos;s copies of the B4GALT7 gene, which is located on chromosome 5. This gene provides instructions for making an enzyme that is involved in the production of collagen (the main protein in connective tissue). When not enough enzyme is made by the B4GALT7 genes, collagen is not formed correctly in connective tissue. The symptoms of the disorder are caused by weak connective tissue. Researchers are still studying exactly how mutations in the B4GALT7 gene cause the signs and symptoms of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome progeroid type.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002061-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, progeroid type inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Ehlers-Danlos syndrome progeroid type inherited? Ehlers-Danlos syndrome progeroid type is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern. This means that an individual must have two non-functional copies of the B4GALT7 gene to be affected with the condition. One copy is inherited from each parent. If an individual has only one non-functional B4GALT7 gene (such as each parent), he or she is a &quot;carrier&quot;. Carriers do not typically show any signs or symptoms of a recessive condition. When two carriers for a recessive condition have children, with each pregnancy there is a 25% (1 in 4) risk for the child to be affected, a 50%  (1 in 2) risk for the child to be a carrier (like each parent) and a 25% risk that the child will be unaffected and also not be a carrier. An individual with a recessive condition will generally have unaffected children, except in the rare circumstance where his or her partner is a carrier of a nonfunctional B4GALT7 gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002061-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, progeroid type ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Ehlers-Danlos syndrome progeroid type be treated? Individuals with Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome progeroid type can benefit from a variety of treatments depending on their symptoms. Affected children with weak muscle tone and delayed development might benefit from physiotherapy to improve muscle strength and coordination. Affected individuals with joint pain might benefit from anti-inflammatory drugs. Lifestyle changes or precautions during exercise or intense physical activity may be advised to reduce the chance of accidents to the skin and bone. It is recommended that affected individuals discuss treatment options with their healthcare provider.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
