<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002032" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9705/ectodermal-dysplasia-skin-fragility-syndrome">
<Focus>Ectodermal dysplasia skin fragility syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0013575</CUI>
			<CUI>C1301903</CUI>
			<CUI>C0302113</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T049</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Mcgrath syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ectodermal dysplasia - skin fragility syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Epidermolysis bullosa simplex due to plakophilin deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ectodermal dysplasia-skin fragility syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002032-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ectodermal dysplasia skin fragility syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Ectodermal dysplasia skin fragility syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Ectodermal dysplasia skin fragility syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal blistering of the skin 90% Abnormality of the eyebrow 90% Abnormality of the nail 90% Alopecia 90% Palmoplantar keratoderma 90% Skin ulcer 90% Blepharitis 50% Dry skin 50% Furrowed tongue 50% Malabsorption 50% Pruritus 50% Woolly hair 7.5% Ectodermal dysplasia - Fragile skin - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
