<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002466" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6475/fukuyama-type-muscular-dystrophy">
<Focus>Fukuyama type muscular dystrophy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0026850</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>FCMD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Muscular dystrophy, congenital progressive, with mental retardation</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Muscular dystrophy, congenital, with central nervous system involvement</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Muscular dystrophy, congenital, Fukuyama type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cerebromuscular dystrophy, Fukuyama type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital disorder of glycosylation with developmental anomaly</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital muscular alpha-dystroglycanopathy with brain and eye anomalies</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital muscular dystrophy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital muscular dystrophy due to dystroglycanopathy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002466-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Fukuyama type muscular dystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Fukuyama type muscular dystrophy? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Fukuyama type muscular dystrophy. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Exaggerated startle response 5% Holoprosencephaly 5% Retinal dysplasia 5% Agenesis of corpus callosum - Areflexia - Atria septal defect - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Calf muscle hypertrophy - Cataract - Cerebellar cyst - Cerebellar hypoplasia - Congenital muscular dystrophy - Elevated serum creatine phosphokinase - Encephalocele - Flexion contracture - Hydrocephalus - Hypermetropia - Hypoplasia of the brainstem - Hypoplasia of the pyramidal tract - Infantile onset - Intellectual disability - Microphthalmia - Muscle weakness - Muscular hypotonia - Myocardial fibrosis - Myopia - Optic atrophy - Pachygyria - Polymicrogyria - Pulmonic stenosis - Respiratory insufficiency - Retinal detachment - Scoliosis - Seizures - Skeletal muscle atrophy - Spinal rigidity - Strabismus - Transposition of the great arteries - Type II lissencephaly - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
