<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002464" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/2410/fuhrmann-syndrome">
<Focus>Fuhrmann syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1856728</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Bowing of the femurs, aplasia or hypoplasia of the fibula, and digital anomalies</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fibular aplasia or hypoplasia, femoral bowing and poly-, syn-, and oligodactyly</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002464-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Fuhrmann syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Fuhrmann syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Fuhrmann syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the fibula 90% Adactyly 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the fibula 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the ulna 90% Femoral bowing 90% Hypoplasia of the radius 90% Radial bowing 90% Short stature 90% Talipes 90% Tarsal synostosis 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the 5th finger 75% Aplasia/hypoplasia of the femur 75% Congenital hip dislocation 75% Hypoplastic iliac wing 75% Hypoplastic pelvis 75% Oligodactyly (feet) 75% Patellar aplasia 75% Abnormal finger flexion creases 50% Abnormality of the femur 50% Abnormality of the fingernails 50% Abnormality of the hip bone 50% Abnormality of the metacarpal bones 50% Anonychia 50% Bowing of the long bones 50% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 50% Hypoplastic toenails 50% Postaxial hand polydactyly 50% Sacrococcygeal pilonidal abnormality 50% Single transverse palmar crease 50% Symphalangism affecting the phalanges of the hand 50% Ulnar deviation of finger 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia involving the metacarpal bones 33% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of metatarsal bones 33% Oligodactyly (hands) 33% Talipes equinovarus 33% Toe syndactyly 33% Finger syndactyly 7.5% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 7.5% Macrotia 7.5% Short distal phalanx of finger 7.5% Split hand 7.5% Absent toenail - Amenorrhea - Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the phalanges of the hand - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Fibular aplasia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
