<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002601" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9279/glutamate-formiminotransferase-deficiency">
<Focus>Glutamate formiminotransferase deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0268609</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Formiminotransferase deficiency syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Formiminoglutamicaciduria (FIGLU-uria)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Formiminoglutamic acidemia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Arakawa syndrome 1</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002601-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Glutamate formiminotransferase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Glutamate formiminotransferase deficiency is an inherited metabolic disorder that affects physical and mental development. There are two forms of this condition, a mild form and a sever form. People with the mild form have minor delays in physical and mental development and may have mild intellectual disability. They also have unusually high levels of a molecule called formiminoglutamate (FIGLU) in their urine. Individuals with the severe form have profound intellectual disability, delayed development of motor skills (sitting, standing, and walking) and megaloblastic anemia. In addition to FIGLU in their urine, they have elevated amounts of certain B vitamins (called folates) in their blood. Glutamate formiminotransferase deficiency is caused by mutations in the FTCD gene. It is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002601-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Glutamate formiminotransferase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Glutamate formiminotransferase deficiency? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Glutamate formiminotransferase deficiency. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aminoaciduria - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Growth delay - Hypersegmentation of neutrophil nuclei - Intellectual disability - Megaloblastic anemia - Positive ferric chloride test - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
