<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002371" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/2326/fibromuscular-dysplasia">
<Focus>Fibromuscular dysplasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0016052</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Fibromuscular dysplasia of arteries</Synonym>
		<Synonym>FMD</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002371-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Fibromuscular dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fibromuscular dysplasia (FMD) is the abnormal development or growth of cells in the walls of arteries that can cause the vessels to narrow or bulge. The carotid arteries, which pass through the neck and supply blood to the brain, are commonly affected. Arteries within the brain and kidneys can also be affected. Narrowing and enlarging of arteries can block or reduce blood flow to the brain, causing a stroke. Some patients experience no symptoms of the disease while others may have high blood pressure, dizziness or vertigo, chronic headache, intracranial aneurysm, ringing in the ears, weakness or numbness in the face, neck pain, or changes in vision. FMD is most often seen in people age 25 to 50 years and affects women more often than men. More than one family member may be affected by the disease. The cause of FMD is unknown. Treatment is based on the arteries affected and the progression and severity of the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002371-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Fibromuscular dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Fibromuscular dysplasia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Fibromuscular dysplasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aortic dissection - Arterial fibromuscular dysplasia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Intermittent claudication - Myocardial infarction - Renovascular hypertension - Stroke - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002371-3" qtype="causes">What causes Fibromuscular dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes fibromuscular dysplasia? The cause of fibromuscular dysplasia is unknown. It is likely that there are many factors that contribute to the development of this condition. These factors may include blood vessel abnormalities, tobacco use, hormone levels, and genetic predispositions. Approximately 28 percent of affected individuals have more than one artery with fibromuscular dysplasia. It is not known why some people develop this condition in more than one artery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
