<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002585" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8658/glomus-tympanicum-tumor">
<Focus>Glomus tympanicum tumor</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0474820</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Glomus tympanicum paraganglioma</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002585-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Glomus tympanicum tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Glomus tympanicum tumor? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Glomus tympanicum tumor. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Adrenal pheochromocytoma - Adult onset - Anxiety (with pheochromocytoma) - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Chemodectoma - Conductive hearing impairment - Diaphoresis (with pheochromocytoma) - Elevated circulating catecholamine level - Extraadrenal pheochromocytoma - Glomus jugular tumor - Glomus tympanicum paraganglioma - Headache (with pheochromocytoma) - Hoarse voice (caused by tumor impingement) - Hyperhidrosis - Hypertension associated with pheochromocytoma - Loss of voice - Palpitations - Palpitations (with pheochromocytoma) - Paraganglioma-related cranial nerve palsy - Pulsatile tinnitus (tympanic paraganglioma) - Tachycardia - Tachycardia (with pheochromocytoma) - Vagal paraganglioma - Vocal cord paralysis (caused by tumor impingement) - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
