<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002838" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7035/hereditary-multiple-osteochondromas">
<Focus>Hereditary multiple osteochondromas</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0015306</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>HMO</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary multiple exostoses</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary multiple exostosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Multiple exostoses</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002838-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hereditary multiple osteochondromas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hereditary multiple osteochondromas (HMO) (formerly called hereditary multiple exostoses) is a genetic condition in which people develop multiple benign (noncancerous) bone tumors that are covered by cartilage (called osteochondromas). The number and location of osteochondromas varies greatly among affected individuals. These tumors are not present at birth, but almost all affected people develop multiple osteochondromas by the time they are 12 years old. Once the bones stop growing, the development of new osteochondromas also usually stops. Osteochondromas can cause abnormal growth of the arms, hands, and legs, which can lead to uneven limb lengths (limb length discrepancy) and short stature. These tumors may cause pain, limit joint movement, and exert pressure on nerves, blood vessels, and surrounding tissues. Osteochondromas are typically benign; however, researchers estimate that people with HMO have about a 1% lifetime risk of these tumors becoming a cancerous osteochondrosarcoma. HMO is caused by mutations in the EXT1 and EXT2 genes and is inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002838-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hereditary multiple osteochondromas ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Hereditary multiple osteochondromas? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Hereditary multiple osteochondromas. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the humerus 90% Abnormality of the tibia 90% Abnormality of the femur 50% Abnormality of the metaphyses 50% Abnormality of the teeth 50% Abnormality of the ulna 50% Anteverted nares 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the radius 50% Aseptic necrosis 50% Bone pain 50% Chondrocalcinosis 50% Cranial nerve paralysis 50% Exostoses 50% Genu valgum 50% Madelung deformity 50% Micromelia 50% Muscle weakness 50% Short stature 50% Abnormal pyramidal signs 7.5% Abnormality of pelvic girdle bone morphology 7.5% Abnormality of the pericardium 7.5% Aneurysm 7.5% Elbow dislocation 7.5% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 7.5% Osteoarthritis 7.5% Osteolysis 7.5% Recurrent fractures 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Synostosis of joints 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002838-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Hereditary multiple osteochondromas inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is hereditary multiple osteochondromas inherited? HMO is caused by mutations in the EXT1 and EXT2 genes. It is inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern, which means that one copy of the altered gene in each cell is sufficient to cause this condition. In most cases, an affected individual inherits the mutation from one affected parent. Other cases result from new mutations in the gene and occur in people with no history of the condition in their family. Most affected individuals (96%) that have inherited a gene mutation from their parent show signs and symptoms of this condition. However, the family history may appear negative because of the failure to recognize the disorder in family members and/or reduced penetrance. Reports have suggested that some females may not show clinical features of HMO but still have the gene mutation that causes this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002838-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hereditary multiple osteochondromas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is genetic testing available for hereditary multiple osteochondromas? GeneTests lists the names of laboratories that are performing genetic testing for hereditary multiple osteochondromas. To view the contact information for the clinical laboratories conducting testing for the EXT1 gene, click here.  To view the contact information for the clinical laboratories conducting testing for the EXT2 gene, click here. Please note:  Most of the laboratories listed through GeneTests do not accept direct contact from patients and their families; therefore, if you are interested in learning more, you will need to work with a health care provider or a genetics professional.  Below, we provide a list of online resources that can assist you in locating a genetics professional near you. How might malignant transformation in hereditary multiple exostoses (HME) be diagnosed? Surface irregularities and unorganized chalk deposits with light areas in the middle of the tumor and cartilage cap may be seen on a bone scan, ultrasound or preferably an MRI. However the diagnosis of chondrosarcoma can only be confirmed by a bone biopsy. What are the signs and symptoms of malignant transformation in hereditary multiple exostoses (HME)? A doctor may become suspicious of a malignant transformation if there is an increase in the size of the tumor in adults when bone growth is already complete. In addition, cancer should be suspected if the thickness of the cartilaginous cap of the osteochondroma is over 1-2 centimeters (normally, after bone growth is complete, the cap is only a few millimeters thick). Other signs of a malignant transformation may include bone pain, temporary loss of sensory or motor function due to compression of a nerve (neurapraxia) or pressure related symptoms in nearby organs. Is screening recommended for malignant transformation in hereditary multiple exostoses (HME)? At present, medical researchers agree that more studies need to be performed to determine the best screening protocols for those with HME, including the study of benefit/cost/risk. However a compelling study was published in 2014 by Czajka and DiCaprio which compares the screening of malignant transformation in people with HME to the screening of breast and cervical cancer in women. The authors conclude that screening should be offered to individuals with HME over the age of 16 (or when bone growth has been completed). They propose screening should include a thorough clinical examination and a full body MRI every two years. If an MRI is not possible than a bone scan be performed, followed by an ultrasound of the cartilage cap of any suspicious findings. The Czajka and DiCaprio further recommend that individuals with HME should be made aware of warning signs of malignant transformation and taught self examination techniques.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002838-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hereditary multiple osteochondromas ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might hereditary multiple osteochondromas (HMO) be treated? Currently, there is no known medical treatment for HMO. Osteochondromas are not usually removed because they stop growing around age 12. Another consideration is how close the tumor is to the affected bone&apos;s growth plate, because surgery can affect how the bone grows. Surgery may be considered, however, if an osteochondroma is causing pain, bone fracture, nerve irritation, or if the tumor continues to grow after the person&apos;s bones have stopped growing. The surgical treatment of choice is complete removal of the tumor. Depending on the location of the osteochondroma, this may be relatively simple. However, if an osteochondroma is close to nerves and blood vessels, this may make surgery difficult and risky. Surgery may also be necessary to correct painful limb abnormalities that are caused by multiple osteochondromas. Surgery may be needed to cut and realign the bones that have become deformed, which is known as osteotomy. If the legs are not equal in length, treatment may include a procedure to slow down the growth of the longer leg. Surgery may also be needed to correct the forearm deformity seen in this condition. Adults with this condition who have untreated forearm deformities usually do not have significant functional limitations. Although rare, an osteochondroma can become cancerous (malignant), which usually takes the form of a low grade chondrosarcoma. This type of malignant tumor is unlikely to spread elsewhere in the body. Higher grades of cancer can occur, but this is even more uncommon. In that case, other therapies, such as chemotherapy and radiation, may be used in treatment. GeneReviews provides more information about treatment for hereditary multiple osteochondromas. How might a malignant transformation in hereditary multiple exostoses (HME) be treated? Chondrosarcomas in a person with HME tend to be well differentiated and low grade tumors. The tumors usually grow slowly and do not readily metastasize. Surgical removal is the recommended treatment as the condrosarcomas do not respond to radiation or chemotherapy. The prognosis or long term outlook after surgical removal of the chondrosarcoma for a person with HME is good as long as the tumor has not metastasized.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
