<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002145" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/2178/epiphyseal-dysplasia-hearing-loss-dysmorphism">
<Focus>Epiphyseal dysplasia hearing loss dysmorphism</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0000768</CUI>
			<CUI>C0392476</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Finucane Kurtz Scott syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002145-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Epiphyseal dysplasia hearing loss dysmorphism ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Epiphyseal dysplasia hearing loss dysmorphism? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Epiphyseal dysplasia hearing loss dysmorphism. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal dermatoglyphics 90% Abnormality of the wrist 90% Anteverted nares 90% Behavioral abnormality 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Delayed skeletal maturation 90% Depressed nasal bridge 90% Epicanthus 90% Facial asymmetry 90% Hypertelorism 90% Hypopigmented skin patches 90% Proximal placement of thumb 90% Seizures 90% Sensorineural hearing impairment 90% Short stature 90% Wide mouth 90% Abnormality of the genital system 50% Deep philtrum 50% Finger syndactyly 50% Long philtrum 50% Ptosis 50% Scoliosis 50% Abnormal localization of kidney 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
