<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002442" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10886/frontal-fibrosing-alopecia">
<Focus>Frontal fibrosing alopecia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1274700</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>FFA</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lichen planopilaris</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002442-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Frontal fibrosing alopecia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Frontal fibrosing alopecia (FFA) is a form of lichen planus follicularis that is characterized primarily by slowly progressive hair loss (alopecia) and scarring on the scalp near the forehead. In some cases, the eyebrows, eye lashes and/or other parts of the body may be involved, as well. Although it has been suggested that FFA may be due to hormonal changes or an autoimmune response, the exact cause of this condition is not yet known. There is currently no cure for FFA; however, treatment with certain types of medications may stop or slow hair loss in some cases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002442-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Frontal fibrosing alopecia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of frontal fibrosing alopecia? Frontal fibrosing alopecia (FFA) is characterized primarily by hair loss (alopecia) and scarring on the scalp near the forehead. The band of hair loss on the front and sides of the scalp is usually symmetrical and slowly progressive (worsening over time). The skin in the affected area often looks normal but may be pale, shiny or mildly scarred. Approximately half of all affected people experience loss of eyebrows, as well. Less commonly, the eyelashes may also be involved. Some people with FFA develop hair loss in areas other than the scalp and face. In some cases, women with FFA also have female pattern hair loss, which is associated with thinning of hair on the scalp due to increased hair shedding and/or a reduction in hair volume.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002442-3" qtype="causes">What causes Frontal fibrosing alopecia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes frontal fibrosing alopecia? The exact underlying cause of frontal fibrosing alopecia (FFA) is unknown. FFA is thought to be an autoimmune condition in which an affected person&apos;s immune system mistakenly attacks the hair follicles (structures in the skin that make hair). Scientists also suspect that there may be a hormonal component since the condition most commonly affects post-menopausal women over age 50.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002442-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Frontal fibrosing alopecia inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is frontal fibrosing alopecia inherited? Frontal fibrosing alopecia is not thought to be inherited in most cases. It rarely affects more than one person in a family.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002442-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Frontal fibrosing alopecia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is frontal fibrosing alopecia diagnosed? Frontal fibrosing alopecia is often suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. The diagnosis can be confirmed by examining a small sample of skin (skin biopsy) from the affected area. In some cases, laboratory studies may be ordered to rule out other conditions that cause similar features.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002442-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Frontal fibrosing alopecia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might frontal fibrosing alopecia be treated? Unfortunately, there is currently no cure for frontal fibrosing alopecia (FFA). Because the hair loss associated with this condition is thought to be caused by inflammation of hair follicles, treatment often involves using anti-inflammatory medications or ointments, such as corticosteroids or hydroxychloroquine (brand name Plaquenil), to reduce inflammation and suppress the body&apos;s immune system. Medications that block the production of the male hormone 5-alpha reductase have been reported to stop further hair loss in some women. Researchers continue to question whether treatment is effective or if hair loss in FFA just stops naturally.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
