<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002286" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4133/familial-osteochondritis-dissecans">
<Focus>Familial osteochondritis dissecans</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3665488</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Osteochondritis dissecans, short stature, and early-onset osteoarthritis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002286-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Familial osteochondritis dissecans ?</Question>
			<Answer>Osteochondritis dissecans is a joint condition that occurs when a piece of cartilage and the thin layer of bone beneath it, separates from the end of the bone. If the piece of cartilage and bone remain close to where they detached, they may not cause any symptoms. However, affected people may experience pain, weakness and/or decreased range of motion in the affected joint if the cartilage and bone travel into the joint space. Although osteochondritis dissecans can affect people of all ages, it is most commonly diagnosed in people between the ages of 10 and 20 years. In most cases, the exact underlying cause is unknown. Rarely, the condition can affect more than one family member (called familial osteochondritis dissecans); in these cases, osteochondritis dissecans is caused by changes (mutations) in the ACAN gene and is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Treatment for the condition varies depending on many factors, including the age of the affected person and the severity of the symptoms, but may include rest; casting or splinting; surgery and/or physical therapy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002286-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Familial osteochondritis dissecans ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Familial osteochondritis dissecans? The signs and symptoms of osteochondritis dissecans vary from person to person. If the piece of cartilage and bone remain close to where they detached, they may not cause any symptoms. However, affected people may experience the following if the cartilage and bone travel into the joint space: Pain, swelling and/or tenderness Joint popping Joint weakness Decreased range of motion Although osteochondritis dissecans can develop in any joint of the body, the knee, ankle and elbow are most commonly affected. Most people only develop the condition in a single joint. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Familial osteochondritis dissecans. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal dominant inheritance - Exostoses - Growth abnormality - Osteoarthritis - Osteochondrosis dissecans - Short stature - Waddling gait - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002286-3" qtype="causes">What causes Familial osteochondritis dissecans ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes osteochondritis dissecans? In most cases, the exact underlying cause of osteochondritis dissecans is not completely understood. Scientists suspect that it may be due to decreased blood flow to the end of the affected bone, which may occur when repetitive episodes of minor injury and/or stress damage a bone overtime. In some families, osteochondritis dissecans is caused by changes (mutations) in the ACAN gene. In these cases, which are referred to as familial osteochondritis dissecans, the condition generally affects multiple joints and is also associated with short stature and early-onset osteoarthritis. The ACAN gene encodes a protein that is important to the structure of cartilage. Mutations in this gene weaken cartilage, which leads to the various signs and symptoms of familial osteochondritis disssecans.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002286-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Familial osteochondritis dissecans ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is osteochondritis dissecans diagnosed? A diagnosis of osteochondritis dissecans is usually suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. Additional testing can then be ordered to confirm the diagnosis. These test may include x-rays, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and/or computed tomography (CT scan). For more information about the diagnosis of osteochondritis dissecans, please click here.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002286-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Familial osteochondritis dissecans ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might osteochondritis dissecans be treated? The primary aim of treatment for osteochondritis dissecans is to restore normal function of the affected joint, relieve pain and prevent osteoarthritis. Treatment for the condition varies depending on many factors including the age of the affected person and the severity of the symptoms. In children and young teens, osteochondritis dissecans often heals overtime without surgical treatment. These cases are often managed with rest and in some cases, crutches and/or splinting to relieve pain and swelling. If non-surgical treatments are not successful or the case is particularly severe (i.e. the cartilage and bone are moving around within the joint space), surgery may be recommended. Following surgery, physical therapy is often necessary to improve the strength and range of motion of the affected joint.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
