<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002861" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6643/hermansky-pudlak-syndrome">
<Focus>Hermansky-Pudlak syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0079504</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>HPS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Albinism with hemorrhagic diathesis and pigmented reticuloendothelial cells</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Delta storage pool disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hermansky Pudlak syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002861-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hermansky-Pudlak syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hermansky-Pudlak syndrome is a multisystem, genetic condition characterized by blood platelet dysfunction with prolonged bleeding, visual impairment, and abnormally light coloring of the skin, hair, and eyes (oculocutaneous albinism). Long-term sun exposure greatly increases the risk of skin damage and skin cancers. Some individuals have colitis, kidney failure, and pulmonary fibrosis. Symptoms of pulmonary fibrosis usually appear during the early thirties and rapidly worsen. This condition is inherited in an autosomal recessive fashion. Treatment is symptomatic and supportive. There are nine different types of Hermansky-Pudlak syndrome, which can be distinguished by their signs and symptoms and underlying genetic cause. Types 1 and 4 are the most severe forms. Types 1, 2, and 4 are the only types associated with pulmonary fibrosis. Individuals with type 3, 5, or 6 have the mildest symptoms of all the types. Little is known about the signs, symptoms, and severity of types 7, 8 and 9.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002861-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hermansky-Pudlak syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Hermansky-Pudlak syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Hermansky-Pudlak syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of coagulation 90% Generalized hypopigmentation 90% Nystagmus 90% Ocular albinism 90% Visual impairment 90% Abnormality of the macula 50% Abnormality of the menstrual cycle 50% Abnormality of visual evoked potentials 50% Astigmatism 50% Bruising susceptibility 50% Cataract 50% Epistaxis 50% Hypopigmentation of hair 50% Myopia 50% Optic atrophy 50% Photophobia 50% Pulmonary fibrosis 50% Renal insufficiency 50% Strabismus 50% Abdominal pain 7.5% Abnormality of dental enamel 7.5% Abnormality of neutrophils 7.5% Abnormality of the eyelashes 7.5% Abnormality of thrombocytes 7.5% Gastrointestinal hemorrhage 7.5% Hyperkeratosis 7.5% Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy 7.5% Inflammation of the large intestine 7.5% Malabsorption 7.5% Melanocytic nevus 7.5% Neoplasm of the skin 7.5% Respiratory insufficiency 7.5% Weight loss 7.5% Abnormality of the hair - Albinism - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Cardiomyopathy - Freckles in sun-exposed areas - Freckling - Gingival bleeding - Hematochezia - Heterogeneous - Prolonged bleeding time - Restrictive lung disease - Severe visual impairment - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
