<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002175" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5910/essential-tremor">
<Focus>Essential tremor</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3543433</CUI>
			<CUI>C0270736</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Benign essential tremor</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Presenile tremor syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Familial essential tremor</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Tremor, hereditary essential, 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary essential tremor</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002175-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Essential tremor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Essential tremor is the most common movement disorder.  It is characterized by involuntary and rhythmic shaking (tremor), especially in the hands, without any other signs or symptoms. It is distinguished from tremor that results from other disorders or known causes, such as tremors seen with Parkinson disease or head trauma. Most cases of essential tremor are hereditary. There are five forms of essential tremor that are based on different genetic causes. Several genes as well as lifestyle and environmental factors likely play a role in a person&apos;s risk of developing this complex condition. In mild cases, treatment may not be necessary. In cases where symptoms interfere with daily living, medications may help to relieve symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002175-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Essential tremor ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Essential tremor? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Essential tremor. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal dominant inheritance - Dysarthria - Hand tremor - Postural tremor - Progressive - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002175-3" qtype="causes">What causes Essential tremor ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes essential tremor? The causes of essential tremor are unknown. Researchers are studying several areas (loci) on particular chromosomes that may be linked to essential tremor, but no specific genetic associations have been confirmed. Several genes, as well as environmental factors, are likely involved in an individual&apos;s risk of developing this complex condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002175-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Essential tremor inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is essential tremor inherited? About half of all cases of essential tremor appear to occur because of a genetic mutation. This is referred to as familial tremor. In these cases, essential tremor appears to be passed through generations in families, but the inheritance pattern varies. In many affected families, the condition appears to be inherited in an autosomal dominant manner, which means one copy of an altered gene in each cell is sufficient to cause the disorder. In other families, the inheritance pattern is unclear. Essential tremor may also appear in people with no history of the disorder in their family. In some families, there are individuals who have essential tremor while others have other movement disorders, such as involuntary muscle tensing (dystonia). The potential genetic connection between essential tremor and other movement disorders is an active area of research..</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002175-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Essential tremor ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might essential tremor be treated? Treatment for essential tremor may not be necessary unless the tremors interfere with daily activities or cause embarrassment. Although there is no definitive cure for essential tremor, medicines may help relieve symptoms. How well medicines work depend on the individual patient. Two medications used to treat tremors include: Propranolol, a drug that blocks the action of stimulating substances called neurotransmitters, particularly those related to adrenaline Primidone, an antiseizure drug that also control the function of some neurotransmitters These drugs can have significant side effects. Eliminating tremor &quot;triggers&quot; such as caffeine and other stimulants from the diet is often recommended. Physical therapy may help to reduce tremor and improve coordination and muscle control for some patients.   More details about the management of essential tremor can be accessed through the following web links: http://www.mayoclinic.com/print/essential-tremor/DS00367/METHOD=print&amp;DSECTION=all  http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/1150290-treatment</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
