<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002854" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/11927/hereditary-sensory-neuropathy-type-ie">
<Focus>Hereditary sensory neuropathy type IE</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0151313</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hereditary sensory neuropathy with hearing loss and dementia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy type IE</Synonym>
		<Synonym>DNMT1-Related Dementia, Deafness, and Sensory Neuropathy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>HSNIE</Synonym>
		<Synonym>HSAN IE</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary sensory neuropathy type 1</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002854-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hereditary sensory neuropathy type IE ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hereditary sensory neuropathy type IE (HSNIE) is a progressive disorder of the central and peripheral nervous systems. Symptoms typically begin by age 20 to 35 and include sensory impairment of the lower legs and feet; loss of sweating in the hands and feet; sensorineural hearing loss; and gradual decline of mental ability (dementia). The severity of symptoms and age of onset vary, even within the same family. HSNIE is caused by a mutation in the DNMT1 gene and is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. There is no effective treatment, but management may include injury prevention, the use of hearing aids, and sedative or antipsychotic medications for symptoms of dementia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002854-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hereditary sensory neuropathy type IE ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Hereditary sensory neuropathy type IE? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Hereditary sensory neuropathy type IE. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Apathy - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Cerebral atrophy - Decreased number of peripheral myelinated nerve fibers - Dementia - Hyporeflexia - Impulsivity - Irritability - Memory impairment - Osteomyelitis - Progressive - Sensorineural hearing impairment - Sensory neuropathy - Somnolence - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002854-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Hereditary sensory neuropathy type IE inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is hereditary sensory neuropathy type IE inherited? Hereditary sensory neuropathy type IE (HSNIE) is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. This means that having only one changed (mutated) copy of the responsible gene in each cell is enough to cause features of the condition. When a person with a mutation that causes HSNIE has children, each child has a 50% (1/2) chance to inherit the mutated gene. A person who does not inherit the mutation from an affected parent is not at risk to pass the condition on to his/her children.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002854-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hereditary sensory neuropathy type IE ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might hereditary sensory neuropathy type IE be treated? There is currently no effective treatment for any type of hereditary sensory neuropathy. Management of symptoms may include: meticulous care of the distal limbs, which includes proper fit of shoes, prevention and treatment of callus formation, cleaning and protection of wounds, and avoidance of trauma to the hands and feet injury prevention when sensory impairment is significant the use of hearing aids and/or assistive communication methods as needed sedative or antipsychotic medications to help reduce the restlessness, roaming behavior, delusions, and hallucinations associated with dementia psychological support for caregivers</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
