<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002716" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/2586/hall-riggs-mental-retardation-syndrome">
<Focus>Hall Riggs mental retardation syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0025362</CUI>
			<CUI>C1856198</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002716-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hall Riggs mental retardation syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Hall Riggs mental retardation syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Hall Riggs mental retardation syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Anteverted nares 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Epicanthus 90% Microcephaly 90% Neurological speech impairment 90% Short stature 90% Thick lower lip vermilion 90% Wide nasal bridge 90% Abnormality of epiphysis morphology 50% Abnormality of the metaphyses 50% Brachydactyly syndrome 50% Coarse hair 50% Delayed skeletal maturation 50% Downturned corners of mouth 50% Hypertelorism 50% Limb undergrowth 50% Nausea and vomiting 50% Platyspondyly 50% Scoliosis 50% Seizures 50% Slow-growing hair 50% Wide mouth 50% Abnormality of dental enamel 7.5% Delayed eruption of teeth 7.5% Limitation of joint mobility 7.5% Absent speech - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Depressed nasal bridge - Failure to thrive - Feeding difficulties in infancy - Hypoplasia of dental enamel - Hypoplasia of the primary teeth - Intellectual disability - Intrauterine growth retardation - Irregular vertebral endplates - Kyphosis - Metaphyseal dysplasia - Microdontia of primary teeth - Osteoporosis - Prominent nose - U-Shaped upper lip vermilion - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
