<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002120" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/2137/epidermolysa-bullosa-simplex-with-muscular-dystrophy">
<Focus>Epidermolysa bullosa simplex with muscular dystrophy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0026850</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>EBS-MD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MDEBS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MD-EBS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Epidermolysa bullosa simplex and limb girdle muscular dystrophy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Epidermolysis bullosa simplex - limb girdle muscular dystrophy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Epidermolysis bullosa simplex</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Limb-girdle muscular dystrophy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002120-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Epidermolysa bullosa simplex with muscular dystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Epidermolysa bullosa simplex with muscular dystrophy? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Epidermolysa bullosa simplex with muscular dystrophy. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal blistering of the skin 90% Abnormality of the fingernails 90% Alopecia 90% Myopathy 90% Neurological speech impairment 90% Ophthalmoparesis 90% Abnormality of dental enamel 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the skin 50% Ptosis 50% Fatigable weakness 7.5% Anemia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Carious teeth - Hypoplasia of dental enamel - Increased connective tissue - Keratitis - Milia - Muscular dystrophy - Nail dysplasia - Nail dystrophy - Neonatal respiratory distress - Palmoplantar hyperkeratosis - Punctate keratitis - Scarring alopecia of scalp - Short stature - Urethral stricture - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
