<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002833" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10096/hereditary-leiomyomatosis-and-renal-cell-cancer">
<Focus>Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0206654</CUI>
			<CUI>C1708350</CUI>
			<CUI>C0007134</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>LRCC</Synonym>
		<Synonym>HLRCC</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Familial leiomyomatosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Multiple cutaneous and uterine leiomyomata</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MCUL</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002833-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC) is a condition that causes benign tumors of smooth muscle tissue in the skin (cutaneous leiomyomas) and in the uterus in females (uterine leiomyomas, or fibroids). The condition also increases the risk of kidney cancer. Signs and symptoms usually begin in adulthood as skin growths appear on the torso, arms, legs, and occasionally on the face. They tend to increase in size and number over time. About 10% to 16% of people with HLRCC develop a type of kidney cancer called renal cell cancer; symptoms of this cancer may include lower back pain, blood in the urine, and/or a mass in the kidney that can be felt by a physician. Some people have no symptoms until the cancer is advanced. HLRCC is caused by mutations in the FH gene and is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002833-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer? Signs and symptoms of hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC) typically begin in adulthood at an average age of 25. The skin growths (cutaneous leiomyomata) appear as skin-colored or light brown bumps on the torso and extremities, and occasionally on the face. They usually increase in size and number with age. They may be more sensitive than the surrounding skin and be painful. Uterine leiomyomata (fibroids) also occur in almost all affected women and tend to be large and numerous. Most women with these have irregular or heavy periods and pelvic pain. A renal tumor occurs in about 10% to 16% of affected individuals (at an average age of 44 years) and may cause blood in the urine, lower back pain, and a palpable mass. Some people with renal cell cancer have no symptoms until the cancer is advanced. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the musculature 90% Neoplasm of the skin 90% Pruritus 50% Cataract 7.5% Esophageal neoplasm 7.5% Uterine neoplasm 7.5% Vaginal neoplasm 7.5% Cutaneous leiomyosarcoma 5% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Cutaneous leiomyoma - Decreased fumarate hydratase activity - Incomplete penetrance - Multiple cutaneous leiomyomas - Renal cell carcinoma - Uterine leiomyoma - Uterine leiomyosarcoma - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002833-3" qtype="causes">What causes Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer? Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC) is caused by changes (mutations) in the FH gene. This gene gives the body instructions for making an enzyme called fumarase which is needed for a series of reactions that lets cells use oxygen and energy (the citric acid cycle, or Krebs cycle). People with HLRCC are born with one mutated copy of the FH gene in each cell. The second copy of the gene in some cells can mutate later on from factors in the environment, such as radiation from the sun or an error during cell division. A mutation can interfere with fumarase&apos;s role in the citric acid cycle, which may affect the regulation of oxygen levels in cells. Long-term oxygen deficiency in cells with two mutated copies of the FH gene may contribute to tumors growth and the tendency to develop leiomyomas and/or renal cell cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002833-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer inherited? Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC) is inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern, which means that having one mutated copy of the gene in each cell is enough to cause symptoms of the condition. In some cases, an affected person inherits the mutated copy of the gene from an affected parent. Other cases result from new mutations in the gene and that occur for the first time in in the affected individual. When an individual with an autosomal dominant condition has children, each child has a 50% (1 in 2) risk to inherit the mutated gene. This is the case regardless of which parent has the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002833-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer be treated? Skin growths (cutaneous leiomyomas) associated with hereditary leiomyomatosis and renal cell cancer (HLRCC) should be examined by a dermatologist. Treatment of these may include surgery to remove a painful growth; cryoablation and/or lasers; and/or medications such as calcium channel blockers, alpha blockers, nitroglycerin, antidepressants, and/or antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), which have been reported to reduce pain. Uterine fibroids should be evaluated by a gynecologist. These are typically treated in the same manner as those that occur in the general population. However, most women with HLRCC need medication and/or surgical removal of the fibroids (myomectomy) at a younger age. Medications may include gonadotropin-releasing hormone agonists (GnRHa), antihormonal drugs, and pain relievers. Hysterectomy should be performed only when necessary. Early detection of kidney tumors in HLRCC is important because they grow aggressively. Total nephrectomy may be strongly considered in individuals with a detectable renal mass.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
