<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002480" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/65/galloway-mowat-syndrome">
<Focus>Galloway-Mowat syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0795949</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Galloway Mowat syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Galloway syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Microcephaly nephrosis syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Nephrosis neuronal dysmigration syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hiatal Hernia-Microcephaly-Nephrosis, Galloway Type</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002480-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Galloway-Mowat syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Galloway-Mowat syndrome is a rare, neurodegenerative disorder characterized by various developmental and physical abnormalities. Signs and symptoms may include small head size (microcephaly); developmental delay; seizures; nephrotic syndrome; hiatal hernia; optic atrophy; movement disorders; and intellectual disability. Other physical abnormalities may also be present. Galloway-Mowat syndrome may be caused by changes (mutations) in the WDR73 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Other, unknown genes may also be responsible. Affected children often do not survive beyond the first few years of life. Treatment is aimed at the specific signs and symptoms present.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002480-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Galloway-Mowat syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Galloway-Mowat syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Galloway-Mowat syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Cognitive impairment 90% Hypoplasia of the ear cartilage 90% Microcephaly 90% Nephropathy 90% Nephrotic syndrome 90% Proteinuria 90% Abnormality of neuronal migration 50% EEG abnormality 50% Intrauterine growth retardation 50% Macrotia 50% Premature birth 50% Seizures 50% Short stature 50% Abnormality of immune system physiology 7.5% Abnormality of the intervertebral disk 7.5% Abnormality of the teeth 7.5% Adducted thumb 7.5% Aqueductal stenosis 7.5% Camptodactyly of finger 7.5% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 7.5% Hypertelorism 7.5% Hypertonia 7.5% Hypotelorism 7.5% Muscular hypotonia 7.5% Ataxia 5% Dandy-Walker malformation 5% Dystonia 5% Feeding difficulties 5% Spastic tetraplegia 5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Camptodactyly - Cataract - Cerebellar atrophy - Cerebral atrophy - Diffuse mesangial sclerosis - Epicanthus - Flat occiput - Focal segmental glomerulosclerosis - Hand clenching - Hiatus hernia - High palate - Hyperreflexia - Hypoalbuminemia - Hypopigmentation of the skin - Hypoplasia of midface - Hypoplasia of the brainstem - Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum - Hypoplasia of the iris - Infantile onset - Intellectual disability - Joint contracture of the hand - Low-set ears - Microphthalmia - Narrow nasal ridge - Nystagmus - Oligohydramnios - Opacification of the corneal stroma - Optic atrophy - Pachygyria - Pes cavus - Prominent nose - Ptosis - Slender finger - Sloping forehead - Small for gestational age - Small nail - Strabismus - Talipes equinovarus - Wide mouth - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002480-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Galloway-Mowat syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Galloway-Mowat syndrome inherited? Galloway-Mowat syndrome is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. This means that to be affected, a person must have a mutation in both copies of the responsible gene in each cell. Affected people inherit one mutated copy of the gene from each parent, who is referred to as a carrier. Carriers of an autosomal recessive condition typically do not have any signs or symptoms (they are unaffected). When 2 carriers of an autosomal recessive condition have children, each child has a: 25% (1 in 4) chance to be affected 50% (1 in 2) chance to be an unaffected carrier like each parent 25% chance to be unaffected and not be a carrier</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002480-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Galloway-Mowat syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is genetic testing available for Galloway-Mowat syndrome? Yes. The Genetic Testing Registry (GTR) provides information about the labs that offer clinical genetic testing for Galloway-Mowat syndrome. While it is known to be caused by mutations in the WDR73 gene, it has been suggested that other, unidentified genes may also be responsible. In some cases, carrier testing for unaffected relatives may only be available if the specific mutation in the affected family member is known. The intended audience for the GTR is health care providers and researchers. Patients and consumers with specific questions about a genetic test should contact a health care provider or a genetics professional.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
