<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002594" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9265/glucose-transporter-type-1-deficiency-syndrome">
<Focus>Glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1847501</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>GLUT1 deficiency syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Encephalopathy due to GLUT1 deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Glucose transport defect, blood-brain barrier</Synonym>
		<Synonym>De Vivo disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>GLUT-1 deficiency syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002594-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome (GLUT1 deficiency syndrome) is an inherited condition that affects the nervous system. Signs and symptoms generally develop within the first few months of life and may include recurrent seizures (epilepsy) and involuntary eye movements. Affected people may also have microcephaly (unusually small head size) that develops after birth, developmental delay, intellectual disability and other neurological problems such as spasticity, ataxia (difficulty coordinating movements), and dysarthria. Approximately 10% of affected people have the &quot;non-epileptic&quot; form of GLUT1 deficiency syndrome which is associated with all the typical symptoms of the condition without seizures. GLUT1 deficiency syndrome is caused by changes (mutations) in the SLC2A1 gene and is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Although there is currently no cure for GLUT1 deficiency syndrome, a special diet (called a ketogenic diet) may help alleviate symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002594-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome? The most common form of glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome (GLUT1 deficiency syndrome), called the classic type, may be characterized by: Recurrent seizures (epilepsy) beginning in the first months of life Microcephaly (unusually small head size) that develops after birth Developmental delay Intellectual disability Speech and language impairment Movement abnormalities (i.e. involuntary eye movements, spasticity, ataxia, dystonia) Behavioral problems Other signs and symptoms may include headaches, confusion, loss of energy and/or myoclonus (muscle twitches). Approximately 10% of affected people have the non-epileptic form of GLUT1 deficiency syndrome. This form is associated with all the typical symptoms of the condition without seizures. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Seizures 75% Autosomal recessive inheritance 5% Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Ataxia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Babinski sign - Choreoathetosis - Confusion - Delayed speech and language development - Dysarthria - EEG abnormality - Hemiparesis - Hyperreflexia - Hypoglycorrhachia - Infantile onset - Intellectual disability - Myoclonus - Paralysis - Paroxysmal dystonia - Paroxysmal involuntary eye movements - Paroxysmal lethargy - Phenotypic variability - Postnatal microcephaly - Sleep disturbance - Spasticity - Specific learning disability - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002594-3" qtype="causes">What causes Glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome? Glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome (GLUT1 deficiency syndrome) is caused by changes (mutations) in the SLC2A1 gene. This gene encodes a protein that helps transport glucose (a simple sugar) into cells where it is used as fuel. The protein is particularly important in the central nervous system since glucose is the brain&apos;s main source of energy. SLC2A1 mutations impair the function of the protein. This significantly reduces the amount of glucose available to brain cells leading to the many signs and symptoms associated with GLUT1 deficiency syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002594-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome inherited? Glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome (GLUT1 deficiency syndrome) is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. This means that to be affected, a person only needs a change (mutation) in one copy of the responsible gene in each cell. In some cases, an affected person inherits the mutation from an affected parent. Other cases may result from new (de novo) mutations in the gene. These cases occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family. A person with GLUT1 deficiency syndrome has a 50% chance with each pregnancy of passing along the altered gene to his or her child.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002594-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome diagnosed? A diagnosis of glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome (GLUT1 deficiency syndrome) is often suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. Additional testing can then be ordered to confirm the diagnosis. This may include a lumbar puncture, specialized blood tests to measure the blood concentration of glucose and genetic testing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002594-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome be treated? There is currently no cure for glucose transporter type 1 deficiency syndrome (GLUT1 deficiency syndrome); however, a special diet (called a ketogenic diet) may help control symptoms in some affected people. The GLUT1 Deficiency Foundation offers an information page with detailed information regarding the ketogenic diet. Please click on the link to access this resource.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
