<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002622" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6529/glycogen-storage-disease-type-6">
<Focus>Glycogen storage disease type 6</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0017919</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>GSD6</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Glycogen storage disease 6</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hers disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Phosphorylase deficiency glycogen-storage disease of liver</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002622-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Glycogen storage disease type 6 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Glycogen storage disease type 6 is a genetic disease in which the liver cannot process sugar properly.  Symptoms usually begin in infancy or childhood and include low blood sugar (hypoglycemia), an enlarged liver (hepatomegaly), or an increase in the amount of lactic acid in the blood (lactic acidosis) particularly when an individual does not eat for a long time.  Symptoms improve significantly as individuals with this condition get older.  Glycogen storage disease type 6 is caused by mutations in the PYGL gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002622-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Glycogen storage disease type 6 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Glycogen storage disease type 6? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Glycogen storage disease type 6. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Hypoglycemia 90% Short stature 90% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Hepatomegaly - Increased hepatic glycogen content - Postnatal growth retardation - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
