<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002146" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5589/epiphyseal-dysplasia-multiple-with-early-onset-diabetes-mellitus">
<Focus>Epiphyseal dysplasia multiple with early-onset diabetes mellitus</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0011849</CUI>
			<CUI>C1833334</CUI>
			<CUI>C0392476</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Wolcott Rallison syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MED-IDDM syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>IDDM-MED syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002146-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Epiphyseal dysplasia multiple with early-onset diabetes mellitus ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Epiphyseal dysplasia multiple with early-onset diabetes mellitus? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Epiphyseal dysplasia multiple with early-onset diabetes mellitus. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the metaphyses 90% Short stature 90% Type II diabetes mellitus 90% Abnormality of immune system physiology 50% Abnormality of neutrophils 50% Acute hepatic failure 50% Brachydactyly syndrome 50% Chronic hepatic failure 50% Cognitive impairment 50% Delayed skeletal maturation 50% Elevated hepatic transaminases 50% Gait disturbance 50% Genu valgum 50% Hepatomegaly 50% Platyspondyly 50% Short thorax 50% Abnormality of neuronal migration 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the pancreas 7.5% Exocrine pancreatic insufficiency 7.5% Hyperlordosis 7.5% Hypoglycemia 7.5% Hypothyroidism 7.5% Intrauterine growth retardation 7.5% Kyphosis 7.5% Microcephaly 7.5% Nephropathy 7.5% Recurrent fractures 7.5% Renal insufficiency 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Barrel-shaped chest - Carpal bone hypoplasia - Cone-shaped epiphyses of the phalanges of the hand - Coxa valga - Depressed nasal bridge - Epiphyseal dysplasia - Flattened epiphysis - High palate - Hip dislocation - Hip Subluxation - Hypertelorism - Hypertonia - Hypoplasia of the odontoid process - Infantile onset - Insulin-resistant diabetes mellitus - Irregular carpal bones - Irregular tarsal ossification - Irregular vertebral endplates - Ivory epiphyses of the phalanges of the hand - Ivory epiphyses of the toes - Multiple epiphyseal dysplasia - Narrow iliac wings - Osteoporosis - Preauricular pit - Reduced pancreatic beta cells - Shortening of all middle phalanges of the fingers - Small epiphyses - Upslanted palpebral fissure - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
