<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002529" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/413/geroderma-osteodysplastica">
<Focus>Geroderma osteodysplastica</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0432255</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>GO</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Walt Disney dwarfism</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Gerodermia osteodysplastica</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Geroderma osteodysplasticum</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002529-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Geroderma osteodysplastica ?</Question>
			<Answer>Geroderma osteodysplastica is an autosomal recessive disorder characterized by lax, wrinkled skin, loose joints and a typical face with a prematurely aged appearance. Skeletal signs include severe osteoporosis leading to frequent fractures, malar and mandibular hypoplasia (underdeveloped cheekbones and jaw) and a variable degree of growth deficiency. This condition is caused by mutations in the GORAB gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002529-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Geroderma osteodysplastica ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Geroderma osteodysplastica? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Geroderma osteodysplastica. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Cutis laxa 90% Hyperextensible skin 90% Joint hypermobility 90% Recurrent fractures 90% Reduced bone mineral density 90% Short stature 90% Thin skin 90% Abnormality of the hip bone 50% Muscular hypotonia 50% Scoliosis 50% Abnormality of epiphysis morphology 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Hernia 7.5% Hypoplasia of the zygomatic bone 7.5% Mandibular prognathia 7.5% Microcornea 7.5% Pectus carinatum 7.5% Pes planus 7.5% Platyspondyly 7.5% Prematurely aged appearance 7.5% Talipes 7.5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Beaking of vertebral bodies - Biconcave vertebral bodies - Camptodactyly - Deeply set eye - Delayed speech and language development - Femoral bowing - Hyperextensibility of the finger joints - Hypoplasia of the maxilla - Intellectual disability - Malar flattening - Microcephaly - Osteopenia - Osteoporosis - Periodontitis - Severe short stature - Tibial bowing - Vertebral compression fractures - Wormian bones - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
