<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002046" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/2076/eec-syndrome">
<Focus>EEC syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0406704</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Ectrodactyly-ectodermal dysplasia-clefting (EEC) syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Rudiger syndrome 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Walker-Clodius syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ectrodactyly-ectodermal dysplasia-cleft lip/cleft palate</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ectrodactyly-cleft lip/palate syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002046-1" qtype="information">What is (are) EEC syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>EEC syndrome (Ectrodactyly-Ectodermal Dysplasia-Cleft Lip/Palate) is a rare form of ectodermal dysplasia. The symptoms can vary from mild to severe and most commonly include missing or irregular fingers and/or toes (ectrodactyly or split hand/foot malformation); abnormalities of the hair and glands; cleft lip and/or palate; distinctive facial features; and abnormalities of the eyes and urinary tract. EEC syndrome can be divided into two different types defined by the underlying cause. More than 90% of individuals have EEC syndrome type 3 (EEC3), caused by mutations in the TP63 gene. The of individuals with EEC syndrome are thought to have a mutation in a region on chromosome 7, known as EEC syndrome type 1 (EEC1). EEC syndrome is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Management typically requires evaluation by various specialists. Treatment varies depending on the signs and symptoms present in the affected individual.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002046-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of EEC syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of EEC syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for EEC syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of dental enamel 90% Abnormality of the fingernails 90% Abnormality of the toenails 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the eyebrow 90% Coarse hair 90% Dry skin 90% Lacrimation abnormality 90% Reduced number of teeth 90% Taurodontia 90% Thick eyebrow 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the skin 50% Corneal erosion 50% Inflammatory abnormality of the eye 50% Renal hypoplasia/aplasia 50% Slow-growing hair 50% Abnormality of the eyelid 7.5% Abnormality of the middle ear 7.5% Anterior hypopituitarism 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the nipples 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the thumb 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the thymus 7.5% Breast aplasia 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Displacement of the external urethral meatus 7.5% External ear malformation 7.5% Fine hair 7.5% Finger syndactyly 7.5% Hypohidrosis 7.5% Lymphoma 7.5% Proximal placement of thumb 7.5% Sensorineural hearing impairment 7.5% Short stature 7.5% Intellectual disability 7% Abnormality of the nasopharynx - Absence of Stensen duct - Anal atresia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Bicornuate uterus - Bladder diverticulum - Blepharitis - Blepharophimosis - Blue irides - Broad nasal tip - Carious teeth - Central diabetes insipidus - Choanal atresia - Cleft palate - Cleft upper lip - Coarse facial features - Conductive hearing impairment - Cryptorchidism - Dacrocystitis - Death in infancy - Depressed nasal bridge - Depressed nasal tip - Duplicated collecting system - Ectodermal dysplasia - Fair hair - Flexion contracture - Frontal bossing - Generalized hypopigmentation - Growth hormone deficiency - Hand polydactyly - Hearing impairment - Heterogeneous - High axial triradius - Hoarse voice - Hydronephrosis - Hydroureter - Hyperkeratosis - Hypertelorism - Hypogonadotrophic hypogonadism - Hypoplasia of the maxilla - Hypoplastic fingernail - Hypoplastic nipples - Inguinal hernia - Malar flattening - Microcephaly - Microdontia - Micropenis - Microtia - Nail dystrophy - Nail pits - Oligodontia - Ovarian cyst - Photophobia - Prominent forehead - Rectovaginal fistula - Recurrent respiratory infections - Renal agenesis - Renal dysplasia - Selective tooth agenesis - Semilobar holoprosencephaly - Short digit - Single transverse palmar crease - Sparse axillary hair - Sparse eyebrow - Sparse eyelashes - Sparse pubic hair - Sparse scalp hair - Split foot - Split hand - Telecanthus - Thin skin - Toe syndactyly - Transverse vaginal septum - Ureterocele - Ureterovesical stenosis - Vesicoureteral reflux - Xerostomia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002046-3" qtype="causes">What causes EEC syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes EEC syndrome? Approximately 90% of individuals with EEC syndrome have a causative mutation identified in the TP63 gene. The TP63 gene codes for the p63 protein, which plays a critical role in early development of the ectoderm-the layers of tissue that develop into the skin, hair, teeth, and nails. The p63 protein is additionally thought to play a role in the development of the limbs, facial features, urinary system, and other organs. Individuals that have EEC syndrome due to a mutation in the TP63 gene are classified as having EEC syndrome type 3 (EEC3). In approximately 10% of individuals, EEC syndrome is caused by a mutation on a region of the q (long) arm of chromosome 7. Individuals that have EEC syndrome due to a mutation on the q arm of chromosome 7 are classified as having EEC syndrome type 1 (EEC1). Rarely, EEC syndrome can be found in individuals that do not have mutations in either the TP63 gene or the q arm of chromosome 7.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002046-4" qtype="inheritance">Is EEC syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is EEC syndrome inherited? EEC syndrome is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.This means that having a change (mutation) in only one copy of the responsible gene in each cell is enough to cause features of the condition. In some cases, an affected person inherits the mutated gene from an affected parent. In other cases, the mutation occurs for the first time in a person with no family history of the condition. This is called a de novo mutation. When a person with a mutation that causes an autosomal dominant condition has children, each child has a 50% (1 in 2) chance to inherit that mutation. EEC can appear to be caused by a de novo mutation in some instances when an unaffected parent of an affected child has germline mosaicism. Germline mosaicism affects the genetic make-up of the egg and sperm cell only. It is estimated that unaffected parents of a child with EEC syndrome have a 4% risk of having another affected child. EEC syndrome additionally shows reduced penetrance and variable expressivity. Reduced penetrance means that not all individuals with a mutation in the disease-causing gene will have signs and symptoms of the condition; however, in this condition, it has been reported that up to 93-98% of individuals with a mutation will have the condition. Variable expressivity means that there is a range of signs and symptoms that can occur in different people with the condition (i.e. the expression of the condition varies).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002046-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose EEC syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is genetic testing available for EEC syndrome? It is estimated that greater than 90% of cases of EEC syndrome are caused by mutations in the TP63 gene. The remainder are suspected to be caused by different mutations in a region on chromosome 7. Genetic testing is available to detect both mutations in the TP63 gene and in the implicated region on chromosome 7.  Genetic Testing Registry lists the names of laboratories that are performing genetic testing for EEC syndrome. To view the contact information for the clinical laboratories conducting testing click here. Testing for individuals with a family history of EEC syndrome who may have a mutation but do not exhibit signs and symptoms of the condition may be available if the mutation in the affected family member(s) is known. Prenatal diagnosis for pregnancies at risk may also be available if the mutation in the family is known. Please note that most of the laboratories listed through GeneTests do not accept direct contact from patients and their families; therefore, if you are interested in learning more, you will need to work with a health care provider or a genetics professional.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
