<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002511" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/2449/geleophysic-dwarfism">
<Focus>Geleophysic dwarfism</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3489726</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Geleophysic dysplasia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002511-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Geleophysic dwarfism ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Geleophysic dwarfism? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Geleophysic dwarfism. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the femur 90% Abnormality of the metacarpal bones 90% Anteverted nares 90% Brachydactyly syndrome 90% Cone-shaped epiphysis 90% Delayed skeletal maturation 90% Full cheeks 90% Hypertelorism 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Long philtrum 90% Round face 90% Short nose 90% Short stature 90% Short toe 90% Thin vermilion border 90% Abnormality of the aortic valve 50% Abnormality of the tricuspid valve 50% Abnormality of the voice 50% Atria septal defect 50% Blepharophimosis 50% Hearing impairment 50% Hepatomegaly 50% Intrauterine growth retardation 50% Micromelia 50% Mitral stenosis 50% Otitis media 50% Platyspondyly 50% Recurrent respiratory infections 50% Respiratory insufficiency 50% Round ear 50% Thickened skin 50% Abnormality of the larynx 7.5% Apnea 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Pulmonary hypertension 7.5% Tracheal stenosis 7.5% Aortic valve stenosis - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Camptodactyly of finger - Congestive heart failure - Coxa valga - High pitched voice - Hypoplasia of the capital femoral epiphysis - Irregular capital femoral epiphysis - Joint stiffness - J-shaped sella turcica - Lack of skin elasticity - Osteopenia - Pectus excavatum - Seizures - Short foot - Short long bone - Short metacarpals with rounded proximal ends - Short palm - Small nail - Smooth philtrum - Thickened helices - Tricuspid stenosis - Upslanted palpebral fissure - Wide mouth - Wrist flexion contracture - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
