<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002378" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/2622/fibular-aplasia-tibial-campomelia-and-oligosyndactyly-syndrome">
<Focus>Fibular aplasia, tibial campomelia, and oligosyndactyly syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1855499</CUI>
			<CUI>C0243065</CUI>
			<CUI>C1968667</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>FATCO syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Terminal transverse defects of the limbs associated with congenital heart malformations</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hecht-Scott syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Limb deficiency-heart malformation syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fibular aplasia-tibial campomelia-oligosyndactyly syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002378-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Fibular aplasia, tibial campomelia, and oligosyndactyly syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Fibular aplasia, tibial campomelia, and oligosyndactyly syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Fibular aplasia, tibial campomelia, and oligosyndactyly syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the fibula 90% Abnormality of the tibia 90% Absent hand 90% Abnormality of the cardiovascular system 50% Finger syndactyly 50% Premature birth 50% Respiratory insufficiency 50% Short stature 50% Split hand 50% Tarsal synostosis 50% Abnormality of the hand - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Fibular aplasia - Oligodactyly (feet) - Oligodactyly (hands) - Phenotypic variability - Shortening of the tibia - Syndactyly - Tibial bowing - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
