<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002792" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10030/hemorrhagic-shock-and-encephalopathy-syndrome">
<Focus>Hemorrhagic shock and encephalopathy syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0085584</CUI>
			<CUI>C0036982</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>HSES</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hemorrhagic shock and encephalopathy syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002792-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hemorrhagic shock and encephalopathy syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hemorrhagic shock and encephalopathy syndrome (HSES) is a rare disease that occurs suddenly in previously healthy children. This condition is characterized by severe shock, coagulopathy, encephalopathy, and liver and kidney dysfunction. Most cases of HSES occur in infants from age 3 to 8 months, although it can also occur in older children. Individuals with HSES have extremely high body temperatures and multiple organ failures. This condition often causes long term neurological problems or death. The cause of the HSES is unknown.hs</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002792-2" qtype="causes">What causes Hemorrhagic shock and encephalopathy syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes hemorrhagic shock and encephalopathy syndrome? The cause of hemorrhagic shock and encephalopathy syndrome is unknown. Some researchers believe that this condition is caused by a complex combination of genetic and environmental factors. Researchers have proposed various factors that may contribute to the development of this condition, including infection, exposure to toxins in the environment, and overwrapping of infants with a fever. Hemorrhagic shock and encephalopathy syndrome has not been reported to be associated with a specific ethnic group or religious background.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
