<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002049" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6322/ehlers-danlos-syndrome">
<Focus>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0013720</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>ED syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>EDS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ehlers Danlos syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Brittle cornea syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome type 5</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome with periventricular heterotopia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, arthrochalasia type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, cardiac valvular type</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002049-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ehlers-Danlos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS) is a group of inherited connective tissue disorders that is caused by abnormalities in the structure, production, and/or processing of collagen. There are 6 major forms of EDS: hypermobility type, classic type, vascular type, kyphoscoliosis type, arthrochalasia type, and dermatosparaxis type. Although other forms of the condition exist, they are extremely rare and are not well-characterized. The signs and symptoms of EDS vary by type and range from mildly loose joints to life-threatening complications. Features shared by many types include joint hypermobility and soft, velvety skin that is highly elastic (stretchy) and bruises easily. Changes (mutations) in a variety of genes may lead to EDS; however, the underlying genetic cause in some families is unknown. Depending on the subtype, EDS may be inherited in an autosomal dominant or an autosomal recessive manner. There is no specific cure for EDS. The treatment and management is focused on preventing serious complications and relieving associated signs and symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002049-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome? There are six major types of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS). Although there is significant overlap in associated features, the subtypes are classified based on their unique signs and symptoms: Hypermobility type - characterized primarily by joint hypermobility affecting both large (elbows, knees) and small (fingers, toes) joints which may lead to recurrent joint dislocations and subluxations (partial dislocation). Affected people generally experience skin involvement (soft, smooth and velvety skin with easy bruising) and chronic pain of the muscles and/or bones, as well. Classic type - associated with extremely elastic (stretchy), smooth skin that is fragile and bruises easily; wide, atrophic scars (flat or depressed scars); and joint hypermobility. Molluscoid pseudotumors (calcified hematomas over pressure points such as the elbow) and spheroids (fat-containing cysts on forearms and shins) are frequently diagnosed in affected people. Hypotonia and delayed motor development may occur, as well. Vascular type - characterized by thin, translucent skin that is extremely fragile and bruises easily. Arteries and certain organs such as the intestines and uterus are also fragile and prone to rupture. Affected people typically have short stature; thin scalp hair; and characteristic facial features including large eyes, a thin nose and lobeless ears. Joint hypermobility is present, but generally confined to the small joints (fingers, toes). Other common features include club foot; tendon and/or muscle rupture; acrogeria (premature aging of the skin of the hands and feet); early onset varicose veins; pneumothorax (collapse of a lung); gingival (gums) recession; and a decreased amount of subcutaneous (under the skin) fat. Kyphoscoliosis type - associated with severe hypotonia at birth, delayed motor development, progressive scoliosis (present from birth), and scleral fragility. Affected people may also have easy bruising; fragile arteries that are prone to rupture; unusually small cornia; and osteopenia (low bone density). Other common features include a &quot;marfanoid habitus&quot; which is characterized by long, slender fingers (arachnodactyly); unusually long limbs; and a sunken chest (pectus excavatum) or protruding chest (pectus carinatum). Arthrochalasia type - characterized by severe joint hypermobility and congenital hip dislocation. Other common features include fragile, elastic skin with easy bruising; hypotonia; kyphoscoliosis (kyphosis and scoliosis); and mild osteopenia. Dermatosparaxis type - associated with extremely fragile skin leading to severe bruising and scarring; saggy, redundant skin, especially on the face; and hernias. For more information on each subtype, please click on the links above. You can also find more detailed information on Medscape Reference&apos;s Web site or the Ehlers-Danlos National Foundation&apos;s Web site. Although other forms of the condition exist, they are extremely rare and are not well-characterized.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002049-3" qtype="causes">What causes Ehlers-Danlos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Ehlers-Danlos syndrome? Ehlers-Danlos syndrome can be caused by changes (mutations) in several different genes (COL5A1, COL5A2, COL1A1, COL3A1, TNXB, PLOD1, COL1A2, and ADAMTS2). However, the underlying genetic cause is unknown in some families. Mutations in these genes usually alter the structure, production, and/or processing of collagen or proteins that interact with collagen. Collagen provides structure and strength to connective tissues throughout the body. A defect in collagen can weaken connective tissues in the skin, bones, blood vessels, and organs resulting in the features of the disorder.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002049-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Ehlers-Danlos syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is Ehlers-Danlos syndrome inherited? The inheritance pattern of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS) varies by subtype. The arthrochalasia, classic, hypermobility, and vascular forms of the disorder usually have an autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance. This means that to be affected, a person only needs a change (mutation) in one copy of the responsible gene in each cell. In some cases, an affected person inherits the mutation from an affected parent. Other cases may result from new (de novo) mutations in the gene. These cases occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family. A person with one of these subtypes has a 50% chance with each pregnancy of passing along the altered gene to his or her child. The dermatosparaxis and kyphoscoliosis types of EDS are inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern. This means that to be affected, a person must have a mutation in both copies of the responsible gene in each cell. The parents of an affected person usually each carry one mutated copy of the gene and are referred to as carriers. Carriers typically do not show signs or symptoms of the condition. When two carriers of an autosomal recessive condition have children, each child has a 25% (1 in 4) risk to have the condition, a 50% (1 in 2) risk to be a carrier like each of the parents, and a 25% chance to not have the condition and not be a carrier.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002049-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Ehlers-Danlos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Ehlers-Danlos syndrome diagnosed? A diagnosis of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome is typically based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. Depending on the subtype suspected, some of the following tests may be ordered to support the diagnosis: Collagen typing performed on a skin biopsy may aid in the diagnosis of vascular type, arthrochalasia type, and dermatosparaxis type. Collagen is a tough, fiber-like protein that makes up about a third of body protein. It is part of the structure of tendons, bones, and connective tissues. People with Ehlers-Danlos syndrome often have abnormalities of certain types of collagen. Genetic testing is available for many subtypes of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome; however, it is not an option for most families with the hypermobility type. Imaging studies such as CT scan, MRI, ultrasound, and angiography may be useful in identifying certain features of the condition. Urine tests to detect deficiencies in certain enzymes that are important for collagen formation may be helpful in diagnosing kyphoscoliosis type.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002049-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Ehlers-Danlos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Ehlers-Danlos syndrome be treated? There is no specific cure for Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS). The treatment and management is focused on preventing serious complications and relieving associated signs and symptoms. Because the features of EDS vary by subtype, management strategies differ slightly. For more specific information on the treatment of each subtype, please click on the links below: Hypermobility type Classic type Vascular type Kyphoscoliosis type Arthrochalasia type Dermatosparaxis type Please speak to your healthcare provider if you have any questions about your personal medical management plan.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
