<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0002280" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6386/familial-mixed-cryoglobulinemia">
<Focus>Familial mixed cryoglobulinemia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0543697</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Meltzer syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002280-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Familial mixed cryoglobulinemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Familial mixed cryoglobulinemia is a rare condition that is characterized by the presence of abnormal proteins (called cryoglobulins) in the blood. These proteins clump together into a &quot;gel-like&quot; consistency at low temperatures, which can lead to inflammation, blocked blood vessels, and a variety of health problems. The associated signs and symptoms vary from person to person depending on which parts of the body or organ systems are affected; however, common features include purpura, joint pain, breathing problems, muscle pain, fatigue, glomerulonephritis, Raynaud&apos;s phenomenon, and skin abnormalities. The underlying genetic cause of familial mixed cryoglobulinemia is currently unknown. Although there are only a few reported families with this condition, it appears to be inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Treatment is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person. In severe cases, medications that suppress the immune system may be necessary.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002280-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Familial mixed cryoglobulinemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Familial mixed cryoglobulinemia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Familial mixed cryoglobulinemia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of temperature regulation 90% Acrocyanosis 90% Mediastinal lymphadenopathy 90% Skin ulcer 90% Subcutaneous hemorrhage 90% Vasculitis 90% Abdominal pain 50% Arthralgia 50% Arthritis 50% Gangrene 50% Gastrointestinal infarctions 50% Glomerulopathy 50% Hematuria 50% Hepatic failure 50% Hepatomegaly 50% Myalgia 50% Polyneuropathy 50% Proteinuria 50% Renal insufficiency 50% Splenomegaly 50% Gastrointestinal hemorrhage 7.5% Keratoconjunctivitis sicca 7.5% Abnormality of blood and blood-forming tissues - Anasarca - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Chronic kidney disease - Cryoglobulinemia - Elevated serum creatinine - Hypertension - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
