<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003396" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10085/klebsiella-infection">
<Focus>Klebsiella infection</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0022729</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Klebsiella</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003396-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Klebsiella infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Klebsiella infections refer to several different types of healthcare-associated infections that are all caused by the Klebsiella bacteria, including pneumonia; bloodstream infections; wound or surgical site infections; and meningitis. Healthy people usually do not get Klebsiella infections. However, people who are hospitalized and receiving treatment for other conditions may be susceptible to these infections. In healthcare settings, people who require long courses of antibiotics and/or devices such as ventilators (breathing machines) or intravenous (vein) catheters are at the most risk for Klebsiella infections. These infections are often treated with antibiotics, although some Klebsiella bacteria may be resistant to certain types of antibiotics.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003396-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Klebsiella infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Klebsiella infections? The signs and symptoms of Klebsiella infections vary since Klebsiella bacteria can cause several different types of conditions. For example, community-acquired pneumonia is one common type of Klebsiella infection which can lead to lung damage and even death in severe cases. Early signs and symptoms of this condition include: High fevers Chills Flu-like symptoms Cough with yellow and/or bloody mucus Shortness of breath Other common Klebsiella infections include bloodstream infections; wound or surgical site infections; and meningitis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003396-3" qtype="causes">What causes Klebsiella infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Klebsiella infections? Klebsiella infections refer to several different types of healthcare-associated infections that are all caused by the Klebsiella bacteria. These bacteria are usually found in human intestines where they do not cause infections. To get a Klebsiella infection, a person must be exposed to the bacteria. For example, Klebsiella must enter the respiratory (breathing) tract to cause pneumonia, or the blood to cause a bloodstream infection. Most healthy people do not get Klebsiella infections. However, people who are hospitalized and receiving treatment for other conditions may be susceptible to these infections. Klebsiella bacteria are usually spread through person-to-person contact. In healthcare settings, people who require long courses of antibiotics and and people whose care requires the use of ventilators (breathing machines) or intravenous (vein) catheters are more at risk for Klebsiella infections. How are Klebsiella bacteria spread? To get a Klebsiella infection, a person must be exposed to the bacteria. For example, Klebsiella must enter the respiratory (breathing) tract to cause pneumonia or the blood to cause a bloodstream infection. In healthcare settings, Klebsiella bacteria can be spread through person-to-person contact or, less commonly, by contamination of the environment. It is not spread through the air. Patients in healthcare settings also may be exposed to Klebsiella when they are on ventilators (breathing machines), or have intravenous (vein) catheters or wounds (caused by injury or surgery). To prevent spreading Klebsiella infections between patients, healthcare personnel must follow specific infection control precautions. These precautions may include frequent hand washing and wearing gowns and gloves when entering the rooms of patients with Klebsiellarelated illnesses. Healthcare facilities should also follow strict cleaning procedures to prevent the spread of Klebsiella. If family members are healthy, they are at very low risk of acquiring a Klebsiella infection. It is still necessary to follow all precautions, particularly hand hygiene. Klebsiella bacteria are spread mostly by person-to-person contact and hand washing is the best way to prevent the spread of germs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003396-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Klebsiella infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>How are Klebsiella infections diagnosed? Klebsiella infections are usually diagnosed by examining a small sample of blood, mucus, and/or urine. Chest x-rays or positron emission tomography (PET scan) may also be used to further evaluate infections that affect the lungs such as community-acquired pneumonia. When a Klebsiella infection is suspected, possible sites of infection including wounds, intravenous (vein) catheters, urinary catheters, and breathing machines should also be tested for the presence of Klebsiella bacteria.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003396-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Klebsiella infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Klebsiella infections be treated? The treatment of Klebsiella infections can be complicated since some Klebsiella bacteria are resistant to certain types of antibiotics. Once a person is diagnosed with one of these infections, a healthcare provider will usually order specialized laboratory testing (susceptibility testing) to determine which antibiotics may be used to treat the Klebsiella infection. If the healthcare provider prescribes an antibiotic, it is important to take the medication exactly as instructed and to continue taking the prescribed course, even if symptoms are gone. If treatment stops too soon, some bacteria may survive and the person may become re-infected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
