<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003986" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3577/methylcobalamin-deficiency-cbl-g-type">
<Focus>Methylcobalamin deficiency cbl G type</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3844614</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Homocystinuria-megaloblastic anemia, cblG complementation type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>cblG</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Methionine synthase deficiency</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003986-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Methylcobalamin deficiency cbl G type ?</Question>
			<Answer>Methylcobalamin deficiency cbl G type is a rare condition that occurs when the body is unable to process certain amino acids (building blocks of protein) properly. In most cases, signs and symptoms develop during the first year of life; however, the age of onset can range from infancy to adulthood. Common features of the condition include feeding difficulties, lethargy, seizures, poor muscle tone (hypotonia), developmental delay, microcephaly (unusually small head size), and megaloblastic anemia. Methylcobalamin deficiency cbl G type is caused by changes (mutations) in the MTR gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Treatment generally includes regular doses of hydroxycobalamin (vitamin B12). Some affected people may also require supplementation with folates and betaine.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003986-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Methylcobalamin deficiency cbl G type ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Methylcobalamin deficiency cbl G type? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Methylcobalamin deficiency cbl G type. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Blindness 5% Nystagmus 5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Cerebral atrophy - Decreased methionine synthase activity - Decreased methylcobalamin - Failure to thrive - Feeding difficulties in infancy - Gait disturbance - Homocystinuria - Hyperhomocystinemia - Hypomethioninemia - Infantile onset - Intellectual disability - Megaloblastic anemia - Muscular hypotonia - Poor coordination - Seizures - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
