<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003957" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4302/mesomelia-synostoses-syndrome">
<Focus>Mesomelia-synostoses syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1838162</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039093</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Mesomelia synostoses</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dominant mesomelic shortness of stature with acral synostoses, umbilical anomalies, and soft palate agenesis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Verloes-David syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003957-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Mesomelia-synostoses syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Mesomelia-synostoses syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Mesomelia-synostoses syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the humerus 90% Abnormality of the metacarpal bones 90% Abnormality of the tibia 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the uvula 90% Brachydactyly syndrome 90% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Micromelia 90% Ptosis 90% Short foot 90% Short stature 90% Short toe 90% Skeletal dysplasia 90% Synostosis of carpal bones 90% Tarsal synostosis 90% Telecanthus 90% Ulnar deviation of finger 90% Abnormality of the femur 50% Abnormal nasal morphology 7.5% Abnormality of the ankles 7.5% Abnormality of the eyebrow 7.5% Abnormality of the upper urinary tract 7.5% Convex nasal ridge 7.5% Genu valgum 7.5% Hearing impairment 7.5% Hypoplasia of the zygomatic bone 7.5% Long philtrum 7.5% Myopia 7.5% Narrow mouth 7.5% Triangular face 7.5% Umbilical hernia 7.5% Short umbilical cord 3/5 Abnormality of the abdomen - Abnormality of the vertebrae - Absent uvula - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Hydronephrosis - Hypertelorism - Mesomelia - Mesomelic short stature - Microretrognathia - Nasal speech - Partial fusion of proximal row of carpal bones - Progressive forearm bowing - Ulnar deviation of the hand or of fingers of the hand - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
