<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003325" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6808/juvenile-myoclonic-epilepsy">
<Focus>Juvenile myoclonic epilepsy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0270853</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Petit mal, impulsive</Synonym>
		<Synonym>JME</Synonym>
		<Synonym>EJM</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Janz syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Myoclonic epilepsy, juvenile, 1</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003325-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Juvenile myoclonic epilepsy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Juvenile myoclonic epilepsy is an epilepsy syndrome characterized by myoclonic jerks (quick jerks of the arms or legs), generalized tonic-clonic seizures (GTCSs), and sometimes, absence seizures. The seizures of juvenile myoclonic epilepsy often occur when people first awaken in the morning. Seizures can be triggered by lack of sleep, extreme fatigue, stress, or alcohol consumption. Onset typically occurs around adolesence in otherwise healthy children. The exact cause of juvenile myoclonic epilepsy remains unknown, but genetics likely plays a role. Although patients usually require lifelong treatment with anticonvulsants, their overall prognosis is generally good.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003325-2" qtype="causes">What causes Juvenile myoclonic epilepsy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes juvenile myoclonic epilepsy? The exact cause of juvenile myoclonic epilepsy remains unknown. It is not associated with conditions such as head trauma, brain tumor, or encephalitis. Several families have specific mutations in various genes and a complex mode of inheritance. In individuals with juvenile myoclonic epilepsy, symptoms can be precipitated by:  Sleep deprivation Psychological stress Alcohol and drug use Noncompliance of medication Photic stimulation Menses Time of day - Usually mornings</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003325-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Juvenile myoclonic epilepsy inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is juvenile myoclonic epilepsy inherited? If I have juvenile myoclonic epilepsy, will my children also have it? Juvenile myoclonic epilepsy is an inherited disorder (about a third of patients with this condition have a positive family history of epilepsy), but the exact mode of inheritance is not clear. A number of studies have indicated that juvenile myoclonic epilepsy is an autosomal dominant condition (i.e. 50% risk of inheritance). However, it exhibits incomplete penetrance, which means that some individuals who inherit the juvenile myoclonic epilepsy gene or genes do not express clinical juvenile myoclonic epilepsy. The children of these individuals who have the gene but do not exhibit symptoms may still inherit the genes and express clinically observable disease. Due to the complex nature of inheritance with this condition, you may benefit from consulting with a genetics professional. This type of healthcare provider can provide you with additional information about diagnosis, natural history, treatment, mode of inheritance, and genetic risks to other family members. To find a genetics clinic, we recommend that you contact your primary doctor for a referral. Click here to learn more about genetic consultations.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003325-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Juvenile myoclonic epilepsy ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might juvenile myoclonic epilepsy be treated? Avoidance of precipitating events such as alcohol use and sleep deprivation may be useful but is not sufficient to control the seizures of juvenile myoclonic epilepsy. Medical therapy with anticonvulsants is typically needed and well tolerated. The majority of patients can be well controlled on a single drug, most commonly valproic acid or lamotrigine or possibly topiramate. More details about the medications used to treat juvenile myoclonic epilepsy can be found at the following link. http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/1185061-treatment</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
