<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003311" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9455/joubert-syndrome-with-oculorenal-anomalies">
<Focus>Joubert syndrome with oculorenal anomalies</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0431399</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Arima syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cerebro-oculo-hepato-renal syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dekaban Arima syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chorioretinal coloboma with cerebellar vermis aplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Joubert syndrome 5</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003311-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Joubert syndrome with oculorenal anomalies ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Joubert syndrome with oculorenal anomalies? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Joubert syndrome with oculorenal anomalies. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the cerebellum 90% Apnea 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Incoordination 90% Muscular hypotonia 90% Nephropathy 90% Chorioretinal coloboma 50% Iris coloboma 50% Long face 50% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 50% Narrow forehead 50% Nystagmus 50% Ptosis 50% Visual impairment 50% Abnormality of neuronal migration 7.5% Abnormality of the hypothalamus-pituitary axis 7.5% Aganglionic megacolon 7.5% Anteverted nares 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 7.5% Encephalocele 7.5% Foot polydactyly 7.5% Hand polydactyly 7.5% Highly arched eyebrow 7.5% Hydrocephalus 7.5% Prominent nasal bridge 7.5% Renal insufficiency 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Agenesis of cerebellar vermis - Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the cerebellar vermis - Ataxia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Blindness - Brainstem dysplasia - Dilated fourth ventricle - Dyspnea - Hepatic fibrosis - Hepatic steatosis - Hepatomegaly - Heterotopia - Hypoplasia of the brainstem - Intellectual disability, progressive - Intellectual disability, severe - Molar tooth sign on MRI - Nephronophthisis - Occipital meningocele - Polycystic kidney dysplasia - Postaxial foot polydactyly - Postaxial hand polydactyly - Renal corticomedullary cysts - Retinal dystrophy - Stage 5 chronic kidney disease - Tachypnea - Tubular atrophy - Tubulointerstitial fibrosis - Undetectable electroretinogram - Wide mouth - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
