<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003881" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10341/megalencephaly-polymicrogyria-and-hydrocephalus-mpph-syndrome">
<Focus>Megalencephaly, polymicrogyria, and hydrocephalus (MPPH) syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0266464</CUI>
			<CUI>C2720434</CUI>
			<CUI>C0020255</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
			<CUI>C0221355</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>MPPH syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Megalencephaly and perisylvian polymicrogyria with postaxial polydactyly and hydrocephalus</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003881-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Megalencephaly, polymicrogyria, and hydrocephalus (MPPH) syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Megalencephaly, polymicrogyria, and hydrocephalus (MPPH) syndrome is a syndrome that is characterized by the presence of polymicrogyria, megalencephaly, mental retardation, seizures, polydactyly, and hydrocephalus. The cause of the condition is currently unknown.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003881-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Megalencephaly, polymicrogyria, and hydrocephalus (MPPH) syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the symptoms of polymicrogyria? A wide variety of symptoms may be observed in people with polymicrogyria, including: Cognitive deficits Epilepsy Paralysis of the face, throat, and tongue Difficulty with speech Drooling</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003881-3" qtype="causes">What causes Megalencephaly, polymicrogyria, and hydrocephalus (MPPH) syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes megalencephaly, polymicrogyria, and hydrocephalus (MPPH) syndrome? The cause of MPPH syndrome is unknown. Infection during pregnancy or fetal accident is thought to be unlikely.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
