<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003530" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8370/leigh-syndrome-french-canadian-type">
<Focus>Leigh syndrome, French Canadian type</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1857355</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
			<CUI>C0238884</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Cox deficiency, French Canadian type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cox deficiency, Saguenay Lac saint Jean type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Leigh syndrome, Saguenay Lac saint Jean type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>LSFC</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cytochrome c oxidase deficiency, French Canadian type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Leigh syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003530-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Leigh syndrome, French Canadian type ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Leigh syndrome, French Canadian type? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Leigh syndrome, French Canadian type. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Seizures 5% Anteverted nares - Ataxia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - CNS demyelination - Delayed speech and language development - Failure to thrive - Gliosis - Highly arched eyebrow - Hirsutism - Hyperglycemia - Hypertelorism - Hypoglycemia - Hypoplasia of midface - Increased CSF lactate - Increased hepatocellular lipid droplets - Increased serum lactate - Infantile onset - Lactic acidosis - Low anterior hairline - Malar flattening - Microvesicular hepatic steatosis - Muscular hypotonia - Peripheral demyelination - Prominent forehead - Strabismus - Tachypnea - Tremor - Wide nasal bridge - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
