<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003968" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3519/metaphyseal-acroscyphodysplasia">
<Focus>Metaphyseal acroscyphodysplasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1855243</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Cupped metaphyses and cone-shaped epiphyses of knees with brachydactyly</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Wedge-shaped epiphyses of knees</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Bellini syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Bellini Chiumello Rimoldi syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Wedge-shaped epiphyses of the knees with mental retardation and short stature</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003968-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Metaphyseal acroscyphodysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Metaphyseal acroscyphodysplasia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Metaphyseal acroscyphodysplasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the femur 90% Abnormality of the hip bone 90% Abnormality of the metacarpal bones 90% Accelerated skeletal maturation 90% Brachydactyly syndrome 90% Cone-shaped epiphysis 90% Genu varum 90% Micromelia 90% Short stature 90% Short toe 90% Cognitive impairment 50% Depressed nasal ridge 50% Epicanthus 50% Frontal bossing 50% Hypertelorism 50% Telecanthus 50% Malar flattening 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Anteverted nares - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Biconcave vertebral bodies - Cone-shaped epiphyses of the phalanges of the hand - Cone-shaped metacarpal epiphyses - Coxa valga - Craniosynostosis - Flat face - Hypoplasia of midface - Hypoplasia of the odontoid process - Intellectual disability - Irregular phalanges - Metaphyseal cupping - Metaphyseal widening - Narrow pelvis bone - Platyspondyly - Prominent forehead - Severe short stature - Short finger - Short humerus - Short metacarpal - Short palm - Short phalanx of finger - Thickened calvaria - Tibial bowing - Wide nasal bridge - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
