<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003798" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3382/marden-walker-like-syndrome">
<Focus>Marden Walker like syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1833136</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Marden Walker like syndrome without psychomotor retardation</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Van den Ende Gupta syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>VDEGS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Blepharophimosis, arachnodactyly, and congenital contractures</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003798-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Marden Walker like syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Marden Walker like syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Marden Walker like syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the eyebrow 90% Abnormality of the ribs 90% Arachnodactyly 90% Blepharophimosis 90% Camptodactyly of finger 90% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 90% Convex nasal ridge 90% Depressed nasal bridge 90% Disproportionate tall stature 90% Hallux valgus 90% Hypoplasia of the zygomatic bone 90% Long toe 90% Macrotia 90% Narrow nasal bridge 90% Abnormality of dental morphology 50% Bowing of the long bones 50% Delayed skeletal maturation 50% Elbow dislocation 50% Hypertelorism 50% Limitation of joint mobility 50% Slender long bone 50% Triphalangeal thumb 50% Underdeveloped nasal alae 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the cerebellum 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Laryngomalacia 7.5% Talipes 7.5% Sclerocornea 5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Camptodactyly of toe - Craniosynostosis - Dental crowding - Dislocated radial head - Distal ulnar hypoplasia - Elbow flexion contracture - Femoral bowing - Glenoid fossa hypoplasia - High palate - Hypoplasia of the maxilla - Joint contracture of the hand - Knee flexion contracture - Lateral clavicle hook - Long hallux - Long metacarpals - Malar flattening - Narrow foot - Narrow nose - Pectus excavatum - Protruding ear - Single umbilical artery - Slender metacarpals - Stridor - Talipes equinovarus - Thin ribs - Ulnar bowing - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
