<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003615" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1053/limited-cutaneous-systemic-sclerosis">
<Focus>Limited cutaneous systemic sclerosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0748540</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Limited cutaneous systemic scleroderma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>CREST syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Systemic scleroderma</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003615-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Limited cutaneous systemic sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Limited cutaneous systemic sclerosis is a subtype of systemic sclerosis characterized by the association of Raynaud&apos;s phenomenon and skin fibrosis on the hands, face, feet and forearms. The exact cause of limited cutaneous systemic sclerosis is unknown, but likely originates from an autoimmune reaction which leads to overproduction of collagen. In some cases, the condition is associated with exposure to certain chemicals. Management is aimed at treating the symptoms present in each affected individual.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003615-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Limited cutaneous systemic sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Limited cutaneous systemic sclerosis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Limited cutaneous systemic sclerosis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Acrocyanosis 90% Autoimmunity 90% Dry skin 90% Hypopigmented skin patches 90% Chondrocalcinosis 50% Feeding difficulties in infancy 50% Mucosal telangiectasiae 50% Nausea and vomiting 50% Skin ulcer 50% Telangiectasia of the skin 50% Camptodactyly of toe 7.5% Pulmonary fibrosis 7.5% Pulmonary hypertension 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003615-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Limited cutaneous systemic sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might CREST syndrome be treated? Unfortunately, CREST syndrome has no known cure. The condition carries both physical and psychological consequences, so a holistic approach to management should be taken. Treatment generally focuses on relieving signs and symptoms and preventing complications. Heartburn may be relieved by antacid medications that reduce the production of stomach acid. Medications that open small blood vessels and increase circulation may help relieve Raynaud&apos;s symptoms and reduce increased pressure in the arteries between the heart and lungs. Drugs that suppress the immune system have shown promise in preventing interstitial lung disease (a condition in which excess collagen collects in the tissue between the lungs&apos; air sacs) in some people with CREST syndrome. To prevent loss of mobility, stretching exercises for the finger joints are important. A physical therapist can also show affected individuals some facial exercises that may help keep the face and mouth flexible. If CREST syndrome is making it difficult to perform daily tasks, an occupational therapist can help individuals learn new ways of doing things. For example, special toothbrushes and flossing devices can make it easier to care for the teeth. Surgery may be necessary for some affected individuals. Large or painful calcium deposits sometimes need to be surgically removed, and amputation of fingertips may be necessary if skin ulcers progress to gangrene. Depression affects approximately 45% of patients with systemic sclerosis and 64% also develop anxiety, so early assessment and treatment of these psychological issues is recommended. For pain management, studies have shown that oxycodone is effective and safe for pain due to severe skin ulcers, while topical lidocaine helps reduce pain of digital ulcers in individuals with systemic scleroderma. ` There are also some lifestyle changes and home remedies that may be helpful for some individuals with CREST syndrome. To reduce Raynaud&apos;s symptoms, individuals may consider wearing gloves or mittens outdoors when the weather is cool, and indoors when reaching into the freezer, for example. To maintain the body&apos;s core temperature, individuals may dress in layers and wear a hat or scarf, thermal socks, and well-fitting boots or shoes that don&apos;t cut off  the circulation. Individuals who smoke should talk to their doctor about the best ways to quit. Nicotine constricts the blood vessels, making Raynaud&apos;s phenomenon worse. Individuals who have difficulty swallowing may consider choosing soft, moist foods and chewing food well. To minimize acid reflux individuals may eat small, frequent meals; avoid spicy or fatty foods, chocolate, caffeine, and alcohol; and avoid exercising immediately before or after eating. Sitting upright for a couple of hours after a meal may also help. To help keep skin soft, individuals may avoid harsh soaps and detergents, while choosing gentle skin cleansers and bath gels with added moisturizers. Individuals may also consider bathing less frequently and taking brief baths and showers, using warm rather than hot water. Moisture levels in the home may be improved by using a humidifier to ease skin and breathing symptoms. For additional information about how CREST syndrome may be treated, the following article from eMedicine may be helpful:  http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/1064663-treatment#showall The information provided here is for general educational purposes only. Individuals interested in learning about specific treatment options for themselves or family members should speak with their healthcare provider.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
