<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003860" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9781/mecp2-duplication-syndrome">
<Focus>MECP2 duplication syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1846058</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>MRXSL</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lubs X-linked mental retardation syndrome (formerly)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>XLMR syndrome, Lubs type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mental retardation, X-linked, Lubs type (formerly)</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003860-1" qtype="information">What is (are) MECP2 duplication syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>MECP2 duplication syndrome is a genetic condition that occurs almost exclusively in males and is characterized by moderate to severe intellectual disability. Other signs and symptoms include infantile hypotonia; delayed motor milestones (i.e. sitting up, crawling); recurrent infections; poor or absent speech; seizures; and/or spasticity. MECP2 duplication syndrome occurs when there is an extra copy (duplication) of the MECP2 gene in each cell. This is generally caused by a duplication of genetic material located on the long (q) arm of the X chromosome. The condition is inherited in an X-linked manner. Treatment is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003860-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of MECP2 duplication syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of MECP2 duplication syndrome? MECP2 duplication syndrome is a condition that occurs almost exclusively in males and is characterized by moderate to severe intellectual disability. Infants affected by this condition are generally diagnosed with severe hypotonia within the first few weeks of life. This reduced muscle tone can lead to feeding difficulties which may require a feeding tube. Trouble swallowing, gastroesophageal reflux, failure to thrive, and extensive drooling are also common symptoms. Distinctive physical features may be noticed shortly after birth which can include brachycephaly (abnormally flat back of the head), midface hypoplasia (underdevelopment of the middle of the face), large ears, deep-set eyes, prominent chin, and a depressed nasal bridge. Due to hypotonia, affected children often have delayed development of motor milestones such as sitting up and crawling. Approximately, one third of affected people never walk independently and those who are able to walk may have an abnormal gait (style of walking). In most cases, hypotonia gives way to spasticity during childhood. Progressive spasticity, which is generally more pronounced in the legs, may lead to the development of mild contractures. Consequently, many affected adults require the use of a wheelchair. The majority of affected people do not develop the ability to talk. Some may have limited speech during early childhood, but frequently this ability is progressively lost during adolescence. Other signs and symptoms associated with MECP2 duplication syndrome may include seizures; autistic features; clinically significant constipation and bladder dysfunction. Many people affected by MECP2 duplication syndrome have recurrent respiratory tract infections. These respiratory infections can be life-threatening and as a result, approximately half of affected people succumb by age 25. In most cases, females with a duplication of the MECP2 gene do not have any symptoms, although depression, anxiety, and autistic features have been described in some. When affected, women with MECP2 duplication syndrome are generally less severely affected than males with the condition. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for MECP2 duplication syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Abnormality of the teeth - Absent speech - Anxiety - Ataxia - Brachycephaly - Bruxism - Chorea - Constipation - Cryptorchidism - Depressed nasal bridge - Depression - Drooling - Dysphagia - Facial hypotonia - Flat midface - Gastroesophageal reflux - Infantile muscular hypotonia - Intellectual disability - Low-set ears - Macrocephaly - Macrotia - Malar flattening - Microcephaly - Narrow mouth - Poor eye contact - Progressive - Progressive spasticity - Recurrent respiratory infections - Rigidity - Seizures - Severe global developmental delay - Tented upper lip vermilion - X-linked recessive inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003860-3" qtype="causes">What causes MECP2 duplication syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes MECP2 duplication syndrome? MECP2 duplication syndrome occurs when there is an extra copy (duplication) of the MECP2 gene in each cell. This is generally caused by a duplication of genetic material located on the long (q) arm of the X chromosome. The size of the duplication can vary; however, this does not appear to affect the severity of the condition. People with larger duplications have signs and symptoms that are similar to people with smaller duplications. The MECP2 gene encodes a protein that is important for normal brain functioning. Although it plays many roles, one of its most important functions is to regulate other genes in the brain by switching them on and off. A duplication of the MECP2 gene leads to the production of excess protein, which is unable to properly regulate the expression of other genes. This results in irregular brain activity, leading to the signs and symptoms of MECP2 duplication syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003860-4" qtype="inheritance">Is MECP2 duplication syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is MECP2 duplication syndrome inherited? MECP2 duplication syndrome is inherited in an X-linked manner. A condition is considered X-linked if the genetic change that causes the condition is located on the X chromosome, one of the two sex chromosomes (the Y chromosome is the other sex chromosome). In males (who have only one X chromosome), a duplication of the MECP2 gene in each cell is sufficient to cause the condition. In females (who have two X chromosomes), a duplication of one of the two copies of the gene typically does not cause the disorder. Early in the development of females, one of the two X chromosomes is randomly and permanently inactivated in each cell (called X-inactivation). X-inactivation prevents female cells from having twice as many functional X chromosomes as males. Because X-inactivation is usually random, the X chromosome inherited from the mother is active in some cells, and the X chromosome inherited from the father is active in other cells. However, when a female has an X chromosome with a duplicated copy of the MECP2 gene, the abnormal chromosome is often preferentially inactivated in many or all cells. This is called &quot;skewed X-inactivation.&quot; It prevents some women with an MECP2 duplication from developing features of the duplication since the extra genetic material is not active. In most cases, MECP2 duplication syndrome is inherited from a mother who has no signs or symptoms of the duplication. Rarely, the condition is not inherited and occurs due to a random event during the formation of the egg or sperm, or in early fetal development. When this happens, it is called a de novo duplication (occurring as a new genetic change for the first time in the affected person).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003860-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose MECP2 duplication syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is MECP2 duplication syndrome diagnosed? A diagnosis of MECP2 duplication syndrome is often suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. Genetic testing can then be ordered to confirm the diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003860-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for MECP2 duplication syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might MECP2 duplication syndrome be treated? Because MECP2 duplication syndrome affects many different systems of the body, medical management is often provided by a team of doctors and other healthcare professionals. Treatment for this condition varies based on the signs and symptoms present in each person. For example, infants with trouble swallowing and/or other feeding difficulties may require a feeding tube. Early developmental interventions may be recommended to help affected children reach their potential. This may include physical therapy, speech therapy and/or occupational therapy. Medications may be prescribed to treat seizures or spasticity. Recurrent infections are usually treated aggressively with appropriate antibiotics. Please speak with a healthcare provider if you have any questions about your personal medical management plan or that of a family member.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
