<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003292" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6799/jejunal-atresia">
<Focus>Jejunal atresia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0266175</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Apple peel syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Apple peel small bowel syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>APSB</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Apple-peel intestinal atresia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Familial apple peel jejunal atresia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003292-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Jejunal atresia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Jejunal atresia is a birth defect that occurs when the membrane that attaches the small intestines to the abdominal wall (called the mesentery) is partially or completely absent. As a result, a portion of the small intestines (the jejunum) twists around an artery that supplies blood to the colon (the marginal artery). This leads to an intestinal blockage or &quot;atresia.&quot; Common symptoms include feeding difficulties, failure to thrive, vomiting bile (a bitter-tasting yellowish-green fluid), abdominal swelling, and/or absence of bowel movements after birth. It typically occurs sporadically in people with no family history of the condition; however, more than one family member can rarely be affected, suggesting that there may be a genetic component in some cases. Jejunal atresia is typically treated with surgery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003292-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Jejunal atresia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Jejunal atresia? Signs and symptoms of jejunal atresia vary but may include: Feeding difficulties Failure to thrive Vomiting bile (a bitter-tasting yellowish-green fluid) Abdominal swelling, especially the upper middle part just below the breast bone Absence of bowel movements after birth The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Jejunal atresia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal recessive inheritance - Jejunal atresia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003292-3" qtype="causes">What causes Jejunal atresia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes jejunal atresia? Jejunal atresia occurs when the membrane that attaches the small intestines to the abdominal wall (called the mesentery) is partially or completely absent. As a result, a portion of the small intestines (the jejunum) twists around an artery that supplies blood to the colon (the marginal artery). This leads to an intestinal blockage or &quot;atresia.&quot; Jejunal atresia typically occurs sporadically in people with no family history of the condition. In these cases, the exact underlying cause is generally unknown; however, scientists suspect that it may be a consequence of disrupted blood flow in the developing fetus. Rarely, more than one family member can be affected by jejunal atresia, suggesting that there may be a genetic component in some cases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003292-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Jejunal atresia inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is jejunal atresia inherited? Most cases of jejunal atresia occur sporadically in people with no family history of the condition. However, it can rarely affect more than one family member. In these families, jejunal atresia is likely due to a genetic cause and appears to be inherited in an autosomal recessive or multifactorial manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003292-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Jejunal atresia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is jejunal atresia diagnosed? In some cases, jejunal atresia may be diagnosed before birth on a prenatal ultrasound. After birth, a diagnosis is often suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. Additional testing such as X-rays with or without contrast can then be ordered to confirm the diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003292-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Jejunal atresia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might jejunal atresia be treated? Jejunal atresia is typically treated with surgery. Total parenteral nutrition (TPN) is generally necessary for a period of time following surgery until normal meals are tolerated.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
