<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003657" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10586/loeys-dietz-syndrome-type-2">
<Focus>Loeys-Dietz syndrome type 2</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2697932</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Loeys-Dietz syndrome 2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Loeys-Dietz syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003657-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Loeys-Dietz syndrome type 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Loeys-Dietz syndrome type 2? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Loeys-Dietz syndrome type 2. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Absent distal phalanges 5% Arnold-Chiari malformation 5% Atria septal defect 5% Bicuspid aortic valve 5% Bicuspid pulmonary valve 5% Cerebral aneurysm 5% Cleft palate 5% Craniosynostosis 5% Descending aortic aneurysm 5% Disproportionate tall stature 5% Hydrocephalus 5% Inguinal hernia 5% Intellectual disability 5% Mitral valve prolapse 5% Osteoporosis 5% Postaxial polydactyly 5% Syndactyly 5% Umbilical hernia 5% Abnormality of the sternum - Arachnodactyly - Ascending aortic aneurysm - Ascending aortic dissection - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Bifid uvula - Blue sclerae - Brachydactyly syndrome - Camptodactyly - Dermal translucency - Exotropia - Generalized arterial tortuosity - Hypertelorism - Joint contracture of the hand - Joint laxity - Malar flattening - Patent ductus arteriosus - Proptosis - Pulmonary artery aneurysm - Retrognathia - Scoliosis - Talipes equinovarus - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
