<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003595" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6906/light-chain-deposition-disease">
<Focus>Light chain deposition disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0238239</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Light-chain deposition disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003595-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Light chain deposition disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Light chain deposition disease (LCDD) involves the immune system, the body&apos;s system of protecting ourselves against infection. The body fights infection with antibodies. Antibodies are made up of small protein segments called light chains and heavy chains. People with LCDD make  too many light chains which get deposited in many different tissues and organs of the body. While LCDD can occur in any organ, the kidneys are always involved. Deposits of light chains can also occur in the liver, heart, small intestine, spleen, skin, nervous system and bone marrow. Additionally, about 50-60% of patients with LCDD have multiple myeloma and 17% have a disease called monoclonal gammopathy of unknown significance (MGUS). Early signs and symptoms of light chain deposition disease may include protein in the urine, high blood pressure, decreased kidney function, and nephrotic syndrome. The goal of treatment in patients with LCDD is to stop/decrease the production of light chains and damage to organs. Treatment options can include: autologous stem cell transplantation; a drug called Bortezomib; a class of drugs called immunomodulatory drugs; and kidney transplant.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003595-2" qtype="inheritance">Is Light chain deposition disease inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is light chain deposition disease a genetic/inheritable disease? Currently, we are not aware of inherited genes or genetic factors that would increase a persons risk for developing light chain deposition disease. You can read more about risk factors for multiple myeloma and monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance at the following links to the MayoClinic.com Website. Multiple myeloma risk factors: http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/multiple-myeloma/DS00415/DSECTION=risk-factors Monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance risk factors: http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/multiple-myeloma/DS00415/DSECTION=risk-factors</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
