<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003833" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10221/maturity-onset-diabetes-of-the-young-type-5">
<Focus>Maturity-onset diabetes of the young, type 5</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0431693</CUI>
			<CUI>C0342276</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>MODY5</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MODY type 5</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Renal cysts and diabetes syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>RCAD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hyperuricemic nephropathy, familial juvenile, atypical</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003833-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Maturity-onset diabetes of the young, type 5 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Maturity-onset diabetes of the young, type 5? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Maturity-onset diabetes of the young, type 5. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Multicystic kidney dysplasia 90% Nephropathy 90% Diabetes mellitus 50% Biliary tract abnormality 33% Elevated hepatic transaminases 33% Elevated serum creatinine 33% Glucose intolerance 33% Glycosuria 33% Gout 33% Proteinuria 33% Stage 5 chronic kidney disease 33% Abnormal localization of kidney 7.5% Abnormality of female internal genitalia 7.5% Abnormality of male internal genitalia 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the pancreas 7.5% Arthritis 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Displacement of the external urethral meatus 7.5% Exocrine pancreatic insufficiency 7.5% Hearing impairment 7.5% Hepatic steatosis 7.5% Hyperuricemia 7.5% Hypothyroidism 7.5% Joint hypermobility 7.5% Mandibular prognathia 7.5% Pyloric stenosis 7.5% Renal hypoplasia/aplasia 7.5% Exocrine pancreatic insufficiency 6/7 Pancreatic hypoplasia 5/6 Renal cyst 19/23 Maturity-onset diabetes of the young 10/13 Abnormality of alkaline phosphatase activity 4/7 Multiple glomerular cysts 4/23 Bicornuate uterus 1/23 Hypoplasia of the uterus 1/23 Renal hypoplasia 1/23 Unilateral renal agenesis 1/23 Autosomal dominant inheritance - Cerebral cortical atrophy - Decreased numbers of nephrons - Epididymal cyst - Hypospadias - Nephrolithiasis - Onset - Phenotypic variability - Ureteropelvic junction obstruction - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
