<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003152" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12312/image-syndrome">
<Focus>IMAGe syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1846009</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>INTRAUTERINE GROWTH RETARDATION, METAPHYSEAL DYSPLASIA, ADRENAL HYPOPLASIA CONGENITA, AND GENITAL ANOMALIES</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Intrauterine growth retardation - metaphyseal dysplasia - adrenal hypoplasia congenita - genital anomalies</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Intrauterine growth retardation-metaphyseal dysplasia-adrenal hypoplasia congenita-genital anomalies syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003152-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of IMAGe syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of IMAGe syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for IMAGe syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the adrenal glands 90% Abnormality of the upper urinary tract 90% Cryptorchidism 90% Depressed nasal bridge 90% Displacement of the external urethral meatus 90% Frontal bossing 90% Intrauterine growth retardation 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Micromelia 90% Muscular hypotonia 90% Macrocephaly 5% Adrenal hypoplasia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Delayed skeletal maturation - Epiphyseal dysplasia - Growth hormone deficiency - Hypercalcemia - Hypercalciuria - Hypospadias - Low-set ears - Metaphyseal dysplasia - Micropenis - Postnatal growth retardation - Prominent forehead - Short nose - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
