<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003762" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3361/malignant-hyperthermia-arthrogryposis-torticollis">
<Focus>Malignant hyperthermia arthrogryposis torticollis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0024591</CUI>
			<CUI>C0040485</CUI>
			<CUI>C0003886</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Froster-Iskenius-Waterson syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Malignant hyperthermia - arthrogryposis - torticollis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003762-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Malignant hyperthermia arthrogryposis torticollis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Malignant hyperthermia arthrogryposis torticollis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Malignant hyperthermia arthrogryposis torticollis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Camptodactyly of finger 90% Congenital muscular torticollis 90% Facial asymmetry 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Long philtrum 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Plagiocephaly 90% Prominent metopic ridge 90% Scoliosis 90% Skeletal muscle atrophy 90% Talipes 90% Tapered finger 90% Ulnar deviation of finger 90% Webbed neck 90% Abnormality of the nipple 50% Abnormality of the voice 50% Amniotic constriction ring 50% Arachnodactyly 50% Cleft palate 50% Conductive hearing impairment 50% Cryptorchidism 50% Downturned corners of mouth 50% Malignant hyperthermia 50% Mask-like facies 50% Narrow mouth 50% Pectus excavatum 50% Prominent nasal bridge 50% Ptosis 50% Scrotal hypoplasia 50% Short stature 50% Abnormality of the fingernails 7.5% Abnormality of the ribs 7.5% Abnormality of the skin 7.5% Advanced eruption of teeth 7.5% Asymmetric growth 7.5% Broad alveolar ridges 7.5% Dolichocephaly 7.5% Exaggerated cupid&apos;s bow 7.5% Finger syndactyly 7.5% Full cheeks 7.5% Hernia of the abdominal wall 7.5% Hypotelorism 7.5% Kyphosis 7.5% Malar flattening 7.5% Muscular hypotonia 7.5% Polyhydramnios 7.5% Prenatal movement abnormality 7.5% Proptosis 7.5% Respiratory insufficiency 7.5% Sloping forehead 7.5% Abnormality of the mandible - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Natal tooth - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
