<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003318" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3062/jung-wolff-back-stahl-syndrome">
<Focus>Jung Wolff Back Stahl syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1832362</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Anterior chamber cleavage disorder, cerebellar hypoplasia, hypothyroidism, and tracheal stenosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003318-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Jung Wolff Back Stahl syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Jung Wolff Back Stahl syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Jung Wolff Back Stahl syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the cerebellum 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Depressed nasal bridge 90% Dry skin 90% Hypothyroidism 90% Low posterior hairline 90% Microcephaly 90% Muscular hypotonia 90% Recurrent respiratory infections 90% Round face 90% Tracheal stenosis 90% Wide nasal bridge 90% Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 50% Abnormality of the genital system 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 50% Telecanthus 50% Abnormality of the hair - Abnormality of the teeth - Abnormality of the thorax - Anterior segment dysgenesis - Cerebellar hypoplasia - Congenital hypothyroidism - Dandy-Walker malformation - Growth delay - Growth hormone deficiency - Hip dysplasia - Hypoplasia of penis - Iris coloboma - Short foot - Short neck - Stenosis of the external auditory canal - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
