<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003758" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10466/malignant-eccrine-spiradenoma">
<Focus>Malignant eccrine spiradenoma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1266063</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Eccrine spiradenoma, malignant</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MES</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003758-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Malignant eccrine spiradenoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Malignant eccrine spiradenoma is a type of tumor that develops from a sweat gland in the skin.  It starts as a rapidly-growing bump on the head or abdomen, and may cause tenderness, redness, or an open wound.  The exact cause of malignant eccrine spiradenoma is unknown, though it is thought that sun exposure or problems with the immune system (immunosuppression) may contribute to the development of this tumor.  Because malignant eccrine spiradenoma is quite rare, there are no established treatment guidelines; however, in practice, surgery is often performed to remove the tumor and additional treatments may follow, depending on the severity and extent of the cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003758-2" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Malignant eccrine spiradenoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might malignant eccrine spiradenoma be treated? Surgery to remove as much of the tumor as possible is usually the first step of treatment for malignant eccrine spiradenoma.  Both a traditional surgical technique known as wide local excision and the newer Mohs micrographic surgery are thought to be effective for treating this cancer.  Additional treatment may include radiation therapy to destroy any cancer cells that might remain after surgery.  Though chemotherapy has been used in cases of malignant eccrine spiradenoma, it is thought to be of limited help in treating this disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
