<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003027" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/2865/hypertrichosis-lanuginosa-congenita">
<Focus>Hypertrichosis lanuginosa congenita</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0235864</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hypertrichosis universalis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital hypertrichosis lanuginosa</Synonym>
		<Synonym>CHL</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hypertrichosis lanuginosa universalis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003027-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hypertrichosis lanuginosa congenita ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypertrichosis lanuginosa congenita is a congenital (present from birth) skin disease characterized by excessive lanugo (very fine, soft, unpigmented) hair covering the entire body, with the exception of the palms, soles, and mucous membranes. The hair can grow to be 3 to 5 cm in length. This condition appears to follow an autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003027-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hypertrichosis lanuginosa congenita ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Hypertrichosis lanuginosa congenita? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Hypertrichosis lanuginosa congenita. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Congenital, generalized hypertrichosis 90% Delayed eruption of teeth 90% Hearing impairment 90% Thick eyebrow 90% Abnormality of skin pigmentation 50% Gingival overgrowth 7.5% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Double eyebrow - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
