<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003099" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9170/hypotrichosis-simplex">
<Focus>Hypotrichosis simplex</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1854310</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>HHS</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003099-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hypotrichosis simplex ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypotrichosis simplex is a rare form of hereditary hair loss without other abnormalities. Affected individuals typically show normal hair at birth, but experience hair loss and thinning of the hair shaft that starts during early childhood and progresses with age. Hypotrichosis simplex can be divided into 2 forms: the scalp-limited form and the generalized form, in which all body hair is affected. The progressive thinning of the hair shaft is a typical feature of androgenetic alopecia. Hypotrichosis simplex can be inherited either as an autosomal dominant or autosomal recessive trait. Some cases are caused by mutations in the APCDD1 gene on chromosome 18p11. To date, there is no treatment for this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003099-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hypotrichosis simplex ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Hypotrichosis simplex? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Hypotrichosis simplex. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Hypotrichosis 100% Abnormality of the eyelashes 90% Alopecia 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the eyebrow 90% Congenital, generalized hypertrichosis 50% Woolly hair 50% Hyperkeratosis 7.5% Pruritus 7.5% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Autosomal recessive inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003099-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hypotrichosis simplex ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is there treatment for hypotrichosis simplex? Is there hope for hair growth in the future? Individuals with hypotrichosis simplex experience a gradual loss of scalp hair that begins during the middle of the first decade and results in almost complete loss of hair by the third decade. A few sparse, fine, short hairs may remain in some individuals. There is currently no treatment for hypotrichosis simplex.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
