<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003360" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6816/kawasaki-syndrome">
<Focus>Kawasaki syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0026691</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Kawasaki disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mucocutaneous lymph node syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Secondary glomerular disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003360-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Kawasaki syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kawasaki syndrome is a condition that involves inflammation of the blood vessels. It is typically diagnosed in young children, but older children and adults can also develop this condition. Kawasaki syndrome often begins with a fever that lasts at least 5 days. Other classic symptoms may include red eyes, lips, and mouth; rash; swollen and red hands and feet; and swollen lymph nodes. Sometimes the condition affects the coronary arteries (which carry oxygen-rich blood to the heart). This can lead to serious heart problems. Kawasaki syndrome occurs most often in people of Asian and Pacific Island descent. The cause of Kawasaki disease is unknown. An infection along with genetic factors may be involved. Treatment includes intravenous gamma globulin and high doses of aspirin in a hospital setting.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003360-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Kawasaki syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Kawasaki syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Kawasaki syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Cheilitis 90% Glossitis 90% Inflammatory abnormality of the eye 90% Lymphadenopathy 90% Proteinuria 90% Recurrent pharyngitis 90% Skin rash 90% Vasculitis 90% Abdominal pain 50% Abnormality of nail color 50% Abnormality of temperature regulation 50% Abnormality of the heart valves 50% Abnormality of the pericardium 50% Arthritis 50% Diarrhea 50% Dry skin 50% Edema 50% Leukocytosis 50% Abnormality of the myocardium 7.5% Arrhythmia 7.5% Arthralgia 7.5% Aseptic leukocyturia 7.5% Behavioral abnormality 7.5% Biliary tract abnormality 7.5% Congestive heart failure 7.5% Coronary artery disease 7.5% Cranial nerve paralysis 7.5% Dilatation of the ascending aorta 7.5% Meningitis 7.5% Migraine 7.5% Nausea and vomiting 7.5% Ptosis 7.5% Restrictive lung disease 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003360-3" qtype="causes">What causes Kawasaki syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What genes are related to Kawasaki syndrome? A variation in the ITPKC gene has been associated with an increased risk of developing Kawasaki syndrome. This gene provides instructions for making an enzyme called inositol 1,4,5-triphosphate 3-kinase C. This enzyme helps limit the activity of immune system cells called T cells, which identify foreign substances and defend the body against infection. Reducing the activity of T cells when appropriate prevents the overproduction of immune proteins called cytokines that lead to inflammation and can, when present in large quantities, can cause tissue damage. Researchers believe that variations in the ITPKC gene may interfere with the body&apos;s ability to reduce T cell activity, leading to inflammation that damages blood vessels and results in the symptoms of this disease. It is likely that other factors, including changes in additional genes, also influence the development of this complex disorder. What causes Kawasaki syndrome? The cause of Kawasaki syndrome isn&apos;t known. The body&apos;s response to a virus or infection combined with genetic factors may cause the disease. However, no specific virus or infection has been found, and the role of genetics is not well understood. Kawasaki syndrome is not contagious; it can&apos;t be passed from one child to another.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003360-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Kawasaki syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is Kawasaki syndrome inherited? A predisposition to Kawasaki syndrome appears to be passed through generations in families, but the inheritance pattern is unknown.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003360-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Kawasaki syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Kawasaki disease be treated? Intravenous gamma globulin is the standard treatment for Kawasaki disease and is administered in high doses. Children with Kawasaki disease usually greatly improve within 24 hours of treatment with IV gamma globulin. Aspirin is often given in combination with the IV gamma globulin as part of the treatment plan. We found limited information on the management of Kawasaki disease specifically in adults, however you may find the following articles to be helpful: Dauphin C. et al., Kawasaki disease is also a disease of adults: report of six cases. Arch Mal Coeur Vaiss [serial online]. 2007;100(5):439-447. Sve P, Stankovic K, Smail A, Durand DV, Marchand G, and Broussolle C. Adult Kawasaki disease: report of two cases and literature review. Semin Arthritis Rheum. 2005;34(6):785-792. Sve P, Bui-Xuan C, Charhon A, and Broussolle C. Adult Kawasaki disease. Rev Med Interne [serial online]. 2003;24(9):577-584.In the article listed above by Dauphin C. et al. the authors describe that of the five adult patients with Kawasaki disease who were treated, all progressed favorably after a course of immunoglobulins.  In addition, in the article by Sve P. et al., the authors comment that &apos;although adult KD often was diagnosed after the acute phase, when a significant beneficial effect from gammaglobulin infusion could not be expected, this treatment did appear to shorten the course of the disease.&apos;</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
