<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003201" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4914/infantile-onset-ascending-hereditary-spastic-paralysis">
<Focus>Infantile-onset ascending hereditary spastic paralysis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0085621</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>IAHSP</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Spastic paralysis, infantile onset ascending</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003201-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Infantile-onset ascending hereditary spastic paralysis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Infantile-onset ascending hereditary spastic paralysis is a motor neuron disease characterized by progressive weakness and stiffness of muscles in the arms, legs, and face. Initial symptoms usually occur within the first 2 years of life and include weakness of the legs, leg muscles that are abnormally tight and stiff, and eventual paralysis of the legs. Over time, muscle weakness and stiffness travels up (ascends) the body from the legs to the head. Infantile-onset ascending hereditary spastic paralysisis caused by mutations in the ALS2 gene, and this condition is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003201-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Infantile-onset ascending hereditary spastic paralysis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Infantile-onset ascending hereditary spastic paralysis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Infantile-onset ascending hereditary spastic paralysis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal pyramidal signs 90% Feeding difficulties in infancy 90% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 90% Hyperreflexia 90% Hypertonia 90% Neurological speech impairment 90% Abnormality of eye movement 50% Pseudobulbar signs 50% Abnormal lower motor neuron morphology - Abnormality of the corticospinal tract - Abnormality of the eye - Abnormality of the face - Achilles tendon contracture - Anarthria - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Babinski sign - Chewing difficulties - Dysarthria - Infantile onset - Motor delay - Muscle weakness - Pes cavus - Progressive - Scoliosis - Slow progression - Spastic paraplegia - Spastic tetraplegia - Tetraplegia - Urinary incontinence - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
