<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003054" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/76/hypohidrotic-ectodermal-dysplasia">
<Focus>Hypohidrotic ectodermal dysplasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0162359</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>HED</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ectodermal dysplasia, hypohidrotic</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Anhidrotic ectodermal dysplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ectodermal dysplasia anhidrotic</Synonym>
		<Synonym>EDA</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003054-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hypohidrotic ectodermal dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypohidrotic ectodermal dysplasia (HED) is a genetic skin disease. Common symptoms include sparse scalp and body hair, reduced ability to sweat, and missing teeth. HED is caused by mutations in the EDA, EDAR, or EDARADD genes. It may be inherited in an X-linked recessive, autosomal recessive, or autosomal dominant manner depending on the genetic cause of the condition. The X-linked form is the most common form. The forms have similar signs and symptoms, however the the autosomal dominant form tends to be the mildest. Treatment of hypohidrotic ectodermal dysplasia may include special hair care formulas or wigs, measures to prevent overheating, removal of ear and nose concretions, and dental evaluations and treatment (e.g., restorations, dental implants, or dentures).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003054-2" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hypohidrotic ectodermal dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is genetic testing available for hypohidrotic ectodermal dysplasia? Yes. Genetic testing for hypohidrotic ectodermal dysplasia is available. In most cases, hypohidrotic ectodermal dysplasia can be diagnosed after infancy based upon the physical features in the affected child. Genetic testing may be ordered to confirm the diagnosis. Other reasons for testing may include to identify carriers or for prenatal diagnosis. Clinical testing is available for detection of disease causing mutations in the EDA, EDAR, and EDARADD genes. We recommend that you speak with a health care provider or a genetics professional to learn more about your testing options. The Genetic Testing Registry (GTR) provides information about the genetic tests for this condition. The intended audience for the GTR is health care providers and researchers. Patients and consumers with specific questions about a genetic test should contact a health care provider or a genetics professional.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003054-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hypohidrotic ectodermal dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might hypohidrotic ectodermal dysplasia be treated? There is no specific treatment for HED. The condition is managed by treating the various symptoms. For patients with abnormal or no sweat glands, it is recommended that they live in places with air conditioning at home, school and work. In order to maintain normal body temperature, they should frequently drink cool liquids and wear cool clothing. Dental defects can be managed with dentures and implants. Artificial tears are used to prevent cornea damage for patients that do not produce enough tears. Surgery to repair a cleft palate is also helpful in improving speech and facial deformities.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
