<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003070" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10917/hypomyelination-with-atrophy-of-basal-ganglia-and-cerebellum">
<Focus>Hypomyelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0544820</CUI>
			<CUI>C0333641</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>H-ABC</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Leukodystrophy, hypomyelinating, 6</Synonym>
		<Synonym>HLD6</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Leukodystrophy, hypomyelinating, with atrophy of the basal ganglia and cerebellum</Synonym>
		<Synonym>HABC</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary ataxia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Leukodystrophy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Spinocerebellar ataxia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003070-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hypomyelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypomyelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum (H-ABC) is a disease that affects certain parts of the brain.  Symptoms usually begin in infancy or early childhood and vary in severity; they include movement difficulties and delay in mental development or learning problems.  These symptoms occur because certain brain cells in individuals with H-ABC are not fully covered by myelin (hypomyelination), a substance that usually surrounds nerve cells to help them work better.  Also, this condition causes the breakdown (atrophy) of two parts of the brain that help to coordinate movement - the basal ganglia and cerebellum.  H-ABC is is caused by a mutation in the TUBB4A gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003070-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hypomyelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Hypomyelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Hypomyelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Hearing impairment 5% Nystagmus 5% Ataxia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Cerebellar atrophy - Cerebral hypomyelination - Choreoathetosis - Delayed speech and language development - Dysarthria - Dystonia - Intellectual disability - Leukodystrophy - Microcephaly - Motor delay - Muscular hypotonia of the trunk - Optic atrophy - Poor speech - Progressive - Rigidity - Seizures - Short stature - Spasticity - Specific learning disability - Sporadic - Tremor - Variable expressivity - Visual impairment - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003070-3" qtype="causes">What causes Hypomyelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes hypomyelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum (H-ABC)? Hypomyelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum (H-ABC) is caused by a mutation in the TUBB4A gene. The mutation usually occurs for the first time in a family as a result of a new mutation in the affected individual. The mutation is rarely inherited from a parent.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003070-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hypomyelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might hypomyelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum (H-ABC) be diagnosed? Hypomyelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum (H-ABC) is diagnosed by a magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) scan of the brain.  When the following three features are identified in the brain of an affected individuals, the diagnosis of H-ABC can be made: Decreased myelin (hypomyelination) in the brain.  Myelin usually forms a protective covering around brain cells.  In H-ABC, this covering is thinner than usual which makes it difficult for nerve cells to work properly. Breakdown (atrophy) of the basal ganglia, a part of the brain that directs and controls movement. Atrophy of the cerebellum, another part of the brain that controls movement.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003070-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hypomyelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might hypomelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum (H-ABC) be treated? Unfortunately, there is no known cure for hypomyelination with atrophy of basal ganglia and cerebellum (H-ABC).  However, there is a case report of one patient&apos;s movement difficulties improving somewhat after he took the medication levodopa-carbidopa.  Another patient showed improvement in movement symptoms after taking folinic acid supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
