<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003590" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10816/lichen-planus-pigmentosus">
<Focus>Lichen planus pigmentosus</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0406366</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>LP pigmentosus</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lichen planus pigmentosa</Synonym>
		<Synonym>LP pigmentosa</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lichen planus pigmentosus inversus</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Rare lichen planus</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003590-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Lichen planus pigmentosus ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lichen planus pigmentosus (LPP) is a rare form of lichen planus. It is characterized by oval or irregularly shaped brown to gray-brown macules and patches on the skin. Areas that are exposed to sun such as the forehead, temples and neck are most commonly affected. However, the macules and patches may also develop on the trunk or in places where two areas of skin touch or rub together (i.e. the armpit, groin, etc). LPP is a chronic, relapsing condition with periods of exacerbations (worsening symptoms) separated by periods of remission (a decrease in or disappearance of symptoms). Although the exact underlying cause of LPP is unknown, studies suggest that UV light, viral infections, and certain topical (applied to the skin) agents such as mustard oil and amla oil, may trigger the condition. Treatment for LPP is symptomatic.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003590-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Lichen planus pigmentosus ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of lichen planus pigmentosus? Lichen planus pigmentosus (LPP), a rare form of lichen planus, is characterized by oval or irregularly shaped brown to gray-brown macules and patches on the skin. Areas that are exposed to sun such as the forehead, temples and neck are most commonly affected. However, the macules and patches may also develop on the trunk or in places where two areas of skin touch or rub together (i.e. the armpit, groin, etc). LPP is a chronic, relapsing condition with periods of exacerbations (worsening symptoms) separated by periods of remission (a decrease in or disappearance of symptoms). Although the skin findings of LPP are usually not associated with any additional symptoms, some affected people may experience mild itching and/or burning or develop other features of lichen planus. Please click here to learn more about the signs and symptoms that may be found in lichen planus. LPP usually affects young to middle-aged adults who have dark skin, especially those of Indian, Latin American, and the Middle Eastern descent.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003590-3" qtype="causes">What causes Lichen planus pigmentosus ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes lichen planus pigmentosus? The exact underlying cause of lichen planus pigmentosus is currently unknown. However, studies suggest that the condition may be triggered by viral infections, UV light or the application of certain oils on the hair or skin (i.e. mustard oil, amla oil).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003590-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Lichen planus pigmentosus ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is lichen planus pigmentosus diagnosed? A diagnosis of lichen planus pigmentosus is usually suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. A skin biopsy may then be ordered to confirm the diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003590-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Lichen planus pigmentosus ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might lichen planus pigmentosus be treated? Treatment for lichen planus pigmentosus is generally symptomatic and may include: Topical (applied to the skin) corticosteroids Topical calcineurin inhibitors (medications that are typically used to treat eczema) Skin lightening agents Laser therapy</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
