<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003351" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3078/kapur-toriello-syndrome">
<Focus>Kapur Toriello syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0796005</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Long columella with cleft lip/palate and eye, heart and intestinal anomalies</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003351-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Kapur Toriello syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Kapur Toriello syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Kapur Toriello syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal nasal morphology 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia affecting the eye 90% Chorioretinal coloboma 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Oral cleft 90% Abnormality of female external genitalia 50% Constipation 50% Hypoplasia of penis 50% Intestinal malrotation 50% Short neck 50% Abnormality of neuronal migration 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 7.5% Atresia of the external auditory canal 7.5% Patent ductus arteriosus 7.5% Preauricular skin tag 7.5% Tetralogy of Fallot 7.5% Ventricular septal defect 7.5% Abnormality of the urinary system - Atria septal defect - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Bilateral single transverse palmar creases - Bulbous nose - Camptodactyly of finger - Cataract - Cleft palate - Cleft upper lip - Clinodactyly of the 5th toe - Conductive hearing impairment - Cryptorchidism - Hypoplastic labia majora - Intellectual disability, progressive - Intellectual disability, severe - Intrauterine growth retardation - Iridoretinal coloboma - Joint contracture of the hand - Low hanging columella - Low posterior hairline - Low-set ears - Micropenis - Microphthalmia - Overlapping fingers - Pachygyria - Polymicrogyria - Scoliosis - Seizures - Short thumb - Single transverse palmar crease - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
