<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003705" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6940/lymphocytic-infiltrate-of-jessner">
<Focus>Lymphocytic infiltrate of Jessner</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0333386</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Benign lymphocytic infiltration</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Jessner disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Jessner-Kanof syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Benign chronic T-cell infiltrative disorder</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003705-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Lymphocytic infiltrate of Jessner ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lymphocytic infiltrate of Jessner is a skin condition characterized by single or multiple small, nonscaly, red, bumps on the face, neck, and upper back. The bumps can enlarge to create a red plaque. Rarely, the skin lesions cause burning or itching. The condition tends to last for several months, sometimes longer. The lesions may fluctuate between periods of worsening and periods of improvement. Currently, the cause is not known.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003705-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Lymphocytic infiltrate of Jessner ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Lymphocytic infiltrate of Jessner? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Lymphocytic infiltrate of Jessner. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of lymphocytes 50% Cutaneous photosensitivity 50% Pruritus 50% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003705-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Lymphocytic infiltrate of Jessner ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might lymphocytic infiltrate of Jessner be treated? Lymphocytic infiltrate of Jessner may require no treatment (since it can resolve spontaneously), but some patients benefit from cosmetic camouflage, photoprotection, excision of small lesions, topical steroids, intralesional steroids, oral hydroxychloroquine, systemic steroids, cryotherapy, methotrexate, thalidomide, and/or oral auranofin. There has been one case report describing treatment with a pulsed-dye laser that worked effectively in this patient after a single treatment without adverse side effects. This and further information on treatment of lymphocytic infiltrate of Jessner is available at the following link to the eMedicine online reference Web site: http://emedicine.medscape.com/article/1098654-treatment</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
