<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003672" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9294/long-qt-syndrome-8">
<Focus>Long QT syndrome 8</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1832916</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>LQT8</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Long QT syndrome with syndactyly</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Timothy syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003672-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Long QT syndrome 8 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Timothy syndrome is a type of long QT syndrome. It affects many parts of the body including the heart, fingers, toes, face, and the nervous system. It is characterized by long QT syndrome, although some people with Timothy syndrome also have other heart defects that affect the hearts ability to pump blood effectively. Other symptoms of Timothy syndrome include fusion of the skin between fingers or toes and distinctive facial features. In addition, many children with this syndrome have developmental delay and characteristic features of autism. Mental retardation and seizures can also occur in children with Timothy syndrome. There are two forms of Timothy syndrome. Type 1 includes all of the characteristic features described. Type 2 causes a more severe form of long QT syndrome and does not appear to cause fusion of skin between fingers or toes. All cases of Timothy syndrome appear to be due to changes in the CACNA1C gene. This syndrome is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. However, most cases are not inherited from an affected parent, but occur for the first time in a family due to a spontaneous or random change in the CACNA1C gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003672-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Long QT syndrome 8 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Long QT syndrome 8? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Long QT syndrome 8. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Prolonged QT interval - Sudden death - Syndactyly - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
