<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003683" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3307/lujan-syndrome">
<Focus>Lujan syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0796022</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Marfanoid habitus, mild general hypotonia, hypernasal voice, normal testicular size and distinct craniofacial anomalies</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003683-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Lujan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lujan syndrome is a condition characterized by intellectual disability, behavioral problems, and poor muscle tone (hypotonia). Affected people also tend to have characteristic physical features such as a tall and thin body; a large head (macrocephaly); and a thin face with distinctive facial features (prominent top of the nose, short space between the nose and the upper lip, narrow roof of the mouth, crowded teeth and a small chin). Most of the cases occur in males. Lujan syndrome is caused by changes (mutations) in the MED12 gene and is inherited in an X-linked manner. Treatment is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person and may include special education; physical therapy, occupational therapy, and speech therapy for developmental delays; and medications to control seizures.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003683-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Lujan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Lujan syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Lujan syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the palate 90% Abnormality of the voice 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Disproportionate tall stature 90% High forehead 90% Macrocephaly 90% Muscular hypotonia 90% Neurological speech impairment 90% Scoliosis 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 50% Arachnodactyly 50% Atria septal defect 50% Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder 50% Hypoplasia of the zygomatic bone 50% Joint hypermobility 50% Macroorchidism 50% Narrow face 50% Pectus excavatum 50% Prominent nasal bridge 50% Short philtrum 50% Abnormality of calvarial morphology 7.5% Abnormality of the pinna 7.5% Abnormality of the teeth 7.5% Brachydactyly syndrome 7.5% Camptodactyly of finger 7.5% Hallucinations 7.5% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Abnormality of the genitourinary system - Abnormality of the rib cage - Abnormally folded helix - Agenesis of corpus callosum - Aggressive behavior - Ascending aortic aneurysm - Autism - Broad thumb - Deep philtrum - Dental crowding - Emotional lability - Flexion contracture - Frontal bossing - Generalized hypotonia - High palate - Hyperactivity - Hypoplasia of the maxilla - Impaired social interactions - Intellectual disability - Joint laxity - Long face - Long nose - Low frustration tolerance - Low-set ears - Narrow nasal bridge - Nasal speech - Obsessive-compulsive behavior - Open mouth - Prominent forehead - Psychosis - Ventricular septal defect - X-linked recessive inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
