<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003221" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3482/intellectual-disability---athetosis---microphthalmia">
<Focus>Intellectual disability - athetosis - microphthalmia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0004158</CUI>
			<CUI>C0026010</CUI>
			<CUI>C3714756</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Bd syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Intellectual disability-athetosis-microphthalmia syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003221-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Intellectual disability - athetosis - microphthalmia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Intellectual disability - athetosis - microphthalmia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Intellectual disability - athetosis - microphthalmia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of movement 90% Abnormality of thumb phalanx 90% Broad forehead 90% Chin dimple 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Facial cleft 90% Frontal bossing 90% Hypertelorism 90% Hypertonia 90% Hypoplasia of the ear cartilage 90% Large earlobe 90% Malar flattening 90% Microcephaly 90% Reduced number of teeth 90% Scoliosis 90% Single transverse palmar crease 90% Supernumerary nipple 90% Telecanthus 90% Abnormality of the palate 50% Abnormality of the thorax 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia affecting the eye 50% Blue sclerae 50% Camptodactyly of finger 50% Facial asymmetry 50% Iris coloboma 50% Lip pit 50% Mandibular prognathia 50% Preauricular skin tag 50% Seizures 50% Strabismus 50% Tapered finger 50% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
