<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003280" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/465/isovaleric-acidemia">
<Focus>Isovaleric acidemia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0268575</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Isovaleric acid CoA dehydrogenase deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>IVA</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Isovaleryl CoA carboxylase deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>IVD deficiency</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003280-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Isovaleric acidemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Isovaleric acidemia (IVA) is a type of organic acid disorder in which affected individuals have problems breaking down an amino acid called leucine from the food they eat. Signs and symptoms may range from very mild to life-threatening. In severe cases, symptoms begin within a few days of birth and include poor feeding, vomiting, seizures, and lack of energy (lethargy); these may progress to more serious medical problems including seizures, coma, and possibly death. In other cases, signs and symptoms appear during childhood and may come and go over time. A characteristic sign of IVA is a distinctive odor of sweaty feet during acute illness. Other features may include failure to thrive or delayed development. IVA is caused by mutations in the IVD gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Treatment involves moderate restriction of proteins in the diet and oral administration of glycine and L-carnitine which helps to rid the body of excess isovaleric acid.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003280-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Isovaleric acidemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Isovaleric acidemia? Health problems related to isovaleric acidemia range from very mild to life-threatening. In severe cases, the features of isovaleric acidemia become apparent within a few days after birth. The initial symptoms include poor feeding, vomiting, seizures, and lack of energy (lethargy). These symptoms sometimes progress to more serious medical problems, including seizures, coma, and possibly death. A characteristic sign of isovaleric acidemia is a distinctive odor of sweaty feet during acute illness. This odor is caused by the buildup of a compound called isovaleric acid in affected individuals. In other cases, the signs and symptoms of isovaleric acidemia appear during childhood and may come and go over time. Children with this condition may fail to gain weight and grow at the expected rate (failure to thrive) and often have delayed development. In these children, episodes of more serious health problems can be triggered by prolonged periods without food (fasting), infections, or eating an increased amount of protein-rich foods. Some people with gene mutations that cause isovaleric acidemia are asymptomatic, which means they never experience any signs or symptoms of the condition. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Isovaleric acidemia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aminoaciduria 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Seizures 50% Cerebellar hemorrhage 5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Bone marrow hypocellularity - Coma - Dehydration - Hyperglycinuria - Ketoacidosis - Lethargy - Leukopenia - Metabolic acidosis - Pancytopenia - Thrombocytopenia - Vomiting - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003280-3" qtype="causes">What causes Isovaleric acidemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes isovaleric acidemia? Isovaleric acidemia is caused by mutations in the IVD gene. The IVD gene provides instructions for making an enzyme that plays an essential role in breaking down proteins from the diet. Specifically, this enzyme helps process the amino acid leucine, which is part of many proteins. If a mutation in the IVD gene reduces or eliminates the activity of this enzyme, the body is unable to break down leucine properly. As a result, an organic acid called isovaleric acid and related compounds build up to harmful levels in the body. This buildup damages the brain and nervous system, causing serious health problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003280-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Isovaleric acidemia inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is isovaleric acidemia inherited? Isovaleric acidemia is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern, which means both copies of the gene in each cell have mutations. The parents of an individual with an autosomal recessive condition each carry one copy of the mutated gene, but they typically do not show signs and symptoms of the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003280-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Isovaleric acidemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might isovaleric acidemia be treated? There is currently no cure for isovaleric acidemia (IVA). Upon diagnosis, immediate treatment is typically necessary in order to prevent metabolic crises and complications that may follow. It is often recommended that affected individuals have a low-leucine / low-protein diet and use medical foods (such as special low-protein flours, pastas, and rice that are made especially for people with organic acid disorders) and leucine-free medical formula. A dietician with knowledge of IVA can help parents create a food plan that contains the right amount of protein, nutrients, and energy to keep the child healthy. Any diet changes should be under the guidance of a dietician. Medications that may be recommended include glycine and L-carnitine, which help rid the body of unwanted isovaleric acid and other harmful substances. No medication or supplement should be used without checking with a metabolic doctor. Children with symptoms of a metabolic crisis need medical treatment right away and may be given bicarbonate, glucose, and other medications by IV. With prompt and careful treatment, children with IVA have a good chance to live healthy lives with normal growth and development. However, some children, even when treated, may have repeated metabolic crises which can lead to life-long learning problems or mental retardation.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
