<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003544" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/87/lenz-microphthalmia-syndrome">
<Focus>Lenz microphthalmia syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0026010</CUI>
			<CUI>C0796016</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Microphthalmia syndromic 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MCOPS1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lenz dysplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Syndromic microphthalmia type 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MAA (formerly)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Microphthalmia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003544-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Lenz microphthalmia syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lenz microphthalmia syndrome is a genetic disorder that causes abnormal development of the eyes and several other parts of the body.  Eye symptoms vary, but may include underdeveloped (small) or absent eyes, cataract, nystagmus, coloboma (a gap or split in structures that make up the eye), and glaucoma. Eye symptoms may affect one or both eyes and may cause vision loss or blindness.  Other signs and symptoms may include abnormalities of the ears, teeth, hands, skeleton, urinary system and occasionally heart defects.  Around 60% of people with this condition have delayed development or intellectual disability ranging from mild to severe. Mutations in the BCOR gene cause some cases of Lenz microphthalmia syndrome. The other causative gene(s) have yet to be identified. This condition is inherited in an X-linked recessive fashion.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003544-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Lenz microphthalmia syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Lenz microphthalmia syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Lenz microphthalmia syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aplasia/Hypoplasia affecting the eye 90% Abnormality of dental morphology 50% Abnormality of the ureter 50% Camptodactyly of finger 50% Chorioretinal coloboma 50% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 50% Cognitive impairment 50% Cryptorchidism 50% Displacement of the external urethral meatus 50% External ear malformation 50% Finger syndactyly 50% Glaucoma 50% Iris coloboma 50% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 50% Microcephaly 50% Microcornea 50% Optic nerve coloboma 50% Oral cleft 50% Preaxial hand polydactyly 50% Renal hypoplasia/aplasia 50% Short stature 50% Abnormality of the clavicle 7.5% Abnormality of the palpebral fissures 7.5% Abnormality of the shoulder 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 7.5% Cataract 7.5% Delayed eruption of teeth 7.5% Hearing impairment 7.5% Hyperlordosis 7.5% Kyphosis 7.5% Long thorax 7.5% Neurological speech impairment 7.5% Nystagmus 7.5% Preauricular skin tag 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Self-injurious behavior 7.5% Visual impairment 7.5% Webbed neck 7.5% Autistic behavior 5% Pulmonary hypoplasia 5% Abnormal palmar dermatoglyphics - Abnormality of the pinna - Aganglionic megacolon - Agenesis of maxillary lateral incisor - Aggressive behavior - Anal atresia - Anophthalmia - Bicuspid aortic valve - Blindness - Camptodactyly - Ciliary body coloboma - Cleft upper lip - Clinodactyly - Dental crowding - Down-sloping shoulders - Growth delay - High palate - Hydroureter - Hypospadias - Intellectual disability - Joint contracture of the hand - Kyphoscoliosis - Low-set ears - Lumbar hyperlordosis - Microphthalmia - Motor delay - Muscular hypotonia - Narrow chest - Overfolded helix - Pectus excavatum - Ptosis - Pyloric stenosis - Radial deviation of finger - Rectal prolapse - Recurrent otitis media - Renal hypoplasia - Self-mutilation - Short clavicles - Spastic diplegia - Syndactyly - X-linked inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
