<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003225" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7890/intellectual-disability-developmental-delay-contractures-syndrome">
<Focus>Intellectual disability-developmental delay-contractures syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0009917</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
			<CUI>C3714756</CUI>
			<CUI>C0424605</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T020</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Contractures of feet, muscle atrophy, and oculomotor apraxia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Apraxia, oculomotor, with congenital contractures and muscle atrophy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Wieacker Wolff syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>WWS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Wieacker syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003225-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Intellectual disability-developmental delay-contractures syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Intellectual disability-developmental delay-contractures syndrome is a rare, slowly progressive genetic disorder that is present at birth. It is characterized by contractures of the joints of the feet (arthrogryposis multiplex congenita), muscle degeneration (atrophy), mild intellectual disability and an impaired ability to move certain muscles of the eyes, face and tongue. Other symptoms might include spasticity and seizures. Intellectual disability-developmental delay-contractures syndrome is caused by mutations in the ZC4H2 gene and is inherited in an X-linked recessive fashion. Most people with intellectual disability-developmental delay-contractures syndrome are male; however carrier females have been reported to have mild symptoms. There is no known cure for intellectual disability-developmental delay-contractures syndrome. Treatment is symptomatic and supportive.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003225-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Intellectual disability-developmental delay-contractures syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Intellectual disability-developmental delay-contractures syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Intellectual disability-developmental delay-contractures syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of movement 90% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Neurological speech impairment 90% Ophthalmoparesis 90% Skeletal muscle atrophy 90% Kyphosis 7.5% Ptosis 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Oculomotor apraxia 5% Apnea - Apraxia - Areflexia - Broad alveolar ridges - Camptodactyly - Cerebral atrophy - Congenital foot contractures - Congenital onset - Decreased fetal movement - Delayed myelination - Delayed speech and language development - Distal amyotrophy - Drooling - Dystonia - Facial palsy - Feeding difficulties - High anterior hairline - High palate - Hip dislocation - Hyperlordosis - Intellectual disability, mild - Long philtrum - Low-set ears - Muscular hypotonia - Narrow chest - Neonatal respiratory distress - Proximal placement of thumb - Retrognathia - Seizures - Short neck - Short stature - Smooth philtrum - Spasticity - Talipes equinovarus - Upslanted palpebral fissure - U-Shaped upper lip vermilion - X-linked recessive inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003225-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Intellectual disability-developmental delay-contractures syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is intellectual disability-developmental delay-contractures syndrome inherited? Intellectual disability-developmental delay-contractures syndrome syndrome is inherited in an X-linked recessive manner and is caused by mutations in the ZC4H2 gene. A condition is considered X-linked if the gene with the mutation that causes the disorder is located on the X chromosome, one of the two sex chromosomes. In males (who have only one X chromosome), one altered copy of the gene in each cell is sufficient to cause the condition. In females (who have two X chromosomes), a mutation must be present in both copies of the gene to cause the disorder. As such, males are affected by X-linked recessive disorders much more frequently than females. In X-linked recessive inheritance, a female with one mutated copy of the gene in each cell is called a carrier. She can pass on the altered gene, but usually does not experience signs and symptoms of the disorder. Rarely, female carriers of a ZC4H2 gene mutation have been reported to exhibit mild symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
