<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003240" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9804/intrahepatic-cholestasis-of-pregnancy">
<Focus>Intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0268318</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Familial intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>ICP</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Recurrent intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>RICP</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pregnancy related cholestasis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003240-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy (ICP) is a disorder of the liver that occurs in women during pregnancy. Cholestasis is a condition that impairs the release of bile (a digestive juice) from liver cells. The bile then builds up in the liver, impairing liver function. Symptoms typically become apparent in the third trimester of pregnancy and can include severe itching (pruritus). Occasionally, the skin and the whites of the eyes can have a yellow appearance (jaundice). ICP is additionally associated with risks to the developing baby such as premature delivery and stillbirth. The cause of ICP is largely unknown, although approximately 15% of cases are caused by mutations in either the ABCB11 or ABCB4 genes. Mutations within the ABCB11 and ABCB4 genes are inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Symptoms of ICP are typically limited to pregnancy. Bile flow returns to normal after delivery and the signs and symptoms of the condition disappear, however, they can return during later pregnancies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003240-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal liver function tests during pregnancy - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Increased serum bile acid concentration during pregnancy - Intrahepatic cholestasis - Premature birth - Pruritus - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003240-3" qtype="causes">What causes Intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy? Largely, the cause of intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy (ICP) is unknown. ICP is present in approximately 1% of pregnancies in the United States. It is thought to be caused by a mixture of genetic, hormonal, and environmental factors. Risk factors include: A personal or family history of cholestasis of pregnancy A history of liver disease A multiple gestation pregnancy (twins, triplets, etc) Approximately 15% of women with ICP have a mutation in either the ABCB11 orABCB4 gene. Mutations within these genes increase the likelihood that a woman will develop ICP. Mutations within the ABCB11 and ABCB4 gene(s) are inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. This means that in order to be affected, a person only needs a change in one copy of the responsible gene in each cell. In some cases, an affected person inherits the mutation from an affected parent. Other cases may result from new (de novo) mutations within the gene. A person with a mutation in either theABCB11 or ABCB4 gene has a 50% chance with each pregnancy of passing along the altered gene to his or her child.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003240-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy diagnosed? Intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy (ICP) is suspected during pregnancy when symptoms of itching (pruritis) present after 25 weeks of gestation with absence of a rash or underlying maternal liver disease. The diagnosis is typically confirmed with the finding of elevated serum bile acids. Is genetic testing available for intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy? In the presence of a family history of intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy (ICP) and/or known mutations in either the ABCB11 or ABCB4 genes, genetic testing is available. The Genetic Testing Registry (GTR), a resource from the National Center for Biotechnology, offers a listing of laboratories that perform genetic testing for intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy. For more information, click on the link.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003240-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy be treated?  Treatment for intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy aims to relieve itching and prevent complications. Medications utilized to relieve itching might include ursodiol (Actigall, Urso), which helps decrease the level of bile in the mother&apos;s bloodstream, relieves itchiness and may reduce complications for the baby. To prevent pregnancy complications, close monitoring of the baby might be recommended. Even if prenatal tests appear normal, induction of early labor might be recommended.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
