<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003376" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6829/keratosis-follicularis-spinulosa-decalvans">
<Focus>Keratosis follicularis spinulosa decalvans</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0343057</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>KFSD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Keratosis follicularis spinulosa decalvans cum ophiasi</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003376-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Keratosis follicularis spinulosa decalvans ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keratosis follicularis spinulosa decalvans (KFSD) is a rare, inherited, skin condition. KFSD is a form of ichthyoses, a group of inherited conditions of the skin in which the skin tends to be thick and rough, and to have a scaly appearance. The face, neck, and forearms are frequently involved. The thickening of the skin is accompanied by the loss of eyebrows, eyelashes, and hair on the face and head. Allergic reactions (atopy), reduced tolerance of bright light (photophobia), and inflammation of the eye&apos;s cornea (keratitis) may also occur. KFSD is thought to be caused by mutations in the SAT1 gene and inherited in an X-linked manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003376-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Keratosis follicularis spinulosa decalvans ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Keratosis follicularis spinulosa decalvans? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Keratosis follicularis spinulosa decalvans. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Alopecia 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the eyebrow 90% Hyperkeratosis 90% Ichthyosis 90% Abnormality of the fingernails 50% Blepharitis 50% Myopia 50% Opacification of the corneal stroma 50% Retinal detachment 50% Abnormality of dental color 7.5% Abnormality of dental enamel 7.5% Carious teeth 7.5% Eczema 7.5% Conjunctivitis - Corneal dystrophy - Dry skin - Dystrophic fingernails - Ectropion - Facial erythema - Follicular hyperkeratosis - Heterogeneous - Keratitis - Nail dysplasia - Palmoplantar keratoderma - Perifollicular fibrosis - Photophobia - Scarring alopecia of scalp - Sparse eyebrow - Sparse eyelashes - X-linked recessive inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
