<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003522" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6873/ledderhose-disease">
<Focus>Ledderhose disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0158360</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Lederhose disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003522-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ledderhose disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ledderhose disease is a type of plantar fibromatosis characterized by thickening of the foot&apos;s deep connective tissue. While many individuals with Ledderhose disease do not experience symptoms, over time the condition may progress, causing considerable pain when walking. Repeated trauma, long-term alcohol consumption, chronic liver disease, diabetes, and epilepsy have been reported in association with the development of this condition. Heredity is also a clear factor in many patients. Often, patients with Ledderhose disease also have other fibrosing conditions such as Dupuytren contracture, knuckle pads, or Peyronie disease.  The exact prevalence of Ledderhose disease is unknown, with some studies stating it is rare, and others stating it is a common condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003522-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ledderhose disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Ledderhose disease? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Ledderhose disease. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Arthralgia 90% Lack of skin elasticity 90% Paresthesia 90% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003522-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Ledderhose disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Ledderhose disease be treated? There is little evidence regarding the effectiveness of specific treatment approaches for Ledderhose disease. Initial treatment approach may invovle regular (monthly or less often) glucocorticoid injection and soft shoe inserts with cutouts for the nodules. Surgery, such as selective fasciectomy or dermofasciectomy, has been used as treatment of people who do not respond to initial therapy. Recurrence following surgery is common. Collagenase injection is an additional therapy which has been used with variable sucess. Our search identified one case report describing the use of &quot;upper lateral arm flaps&quot; on the feet of two brother&apos;s who had multiple recurrences following other procedures. The reference for this article is provided below. Kan HJ, Hovius SE. Long-term follow-up of flaps for extensive Dupuytren&apos;s and Ledderhose disease in one family. J Plast Reconstr Aesthet Surg. 2012 December;65(12):1741-5. The International Dupyytren Society provides futher information on treatment options for Ledderhose disease at the following link:  http://www.dupuytren-online.info/ledderhose_therapies.html We strongly recommend that you review this information with your healthcare providers. Only a healthcare provider can help you make decisions regarding which treatment approach may be best for you.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
