<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003573" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12652/leukoencephalopathy-with-brain-stem-and-spinal-cord-involvement-and-lactate-elevation">
<Focus>Leukoencephalopathy with brain stem and spinal cord involvement and lactate elevation</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0270612</CUI>
			<CUI>C0748903</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Leukoencephalopathy with brain stem and spinal cord involvement - high lactate</Synonym>
		<Synonym>LBSL</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Leukoencephalopathy with brain stem and spinal cord involvement - lactate elevation</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MITOCHONDRIAL ASPARTYL-tRNA SYNTHETASE DEFICIENCY</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Leukoencephalopathy with brain stem and spinal cord involvement-high lactate syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Leukodystrophy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003573-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Leukoencephalopathy with brain stem and spinal cord involvement and lactate elevation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Leukoencephalopathy with brain stem and spinal cord involvement and lactate elevation (LBSL) is a rare neurological disease characterized by slowly progressive cerebellar ataxia (lack of control of the movements) and spasticity with dorsal column dysfunction (decreased position and vibration sense) in most patients. The disease involves the legs more than the arms. It usually starts in childhood or adolescence, but in some cases not until adulthood. Difficulty speaking develops over time. Other symptoms may include: epilepsy; learning problems; cognitive decline; and reduced consciousness, neurologic deterioration, and fever following minor head trauma. Many affected individuals become wheelchair dependent in their teens or twenties. The earlier the onset the more severe the disease is. The diagnosis is made in persons who had the characteristic abnormalities observed on brain and spinal cord MRI scans and with the genetic test identifiying the DARS2 gene alteration (mutation). There is still no cure and treatment is supportive and includes physical therapy and rehabilitation to improve movement function, and the following as needed: antiepileptic drugs, special education and speech therapy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003573-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Leukoencephalopathy with brain stem and spinal cord involvement and lactate elevation ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Leukoencephalopathy with brain stem and spinal cord involvement and lactate elevation ? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Leukoencephalopathy with brain stem and spinal cord involvement and lactate elevation . If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Cognitive impairment 5% Dysarthria 5% Ataxia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Babinski sign - Hyperreflexia - Hyporeflexia - Leukoencephalopathy - Motor delay - Muscle weakness - Nystagmus - Peripheral axonal neuropathy - Skeletal muscle atrophy - Slow progression - Spasticity - Tremor - Variable expressivity - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
