<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003270" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1535/isolated-corpus-callosum-agenesis">
<Focus>Isolated corpus callosum agenesis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0175754</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Corpus callosum agenesis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003270-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Isolated corpus callosum agenesis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Agenesis of the corpus callosum (ACC) is a birth defect in which the structure that connects the two sides of the brain (the corpus callosum) is partially or completely absent. This birth defect can occur as an isolated condition or in combination with other abnormalities. The effects of agenesis of the corpus callosum range from subtle or mild to severe, depending on associated brain abnormalities. Treatment usually involves management of symptoms and seizures if they occur.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003270-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Isolated corpus callosum agenesis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Isolated corpus callosum agenesis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Isolated corpus callosum agenesis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Abnormality of the fontanelles or cranial sutures 50% EEG abnormality 50% Microcephaly 50% Abnormality of the pulmonary artery 7.5% Abnormality of the ureter 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the cerebellum 7.5% Chorioretinal coloboma 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Dandy-Walker malformation 7.5% Deeply set eye 7.5% Displacement of the external urethral meatus 7.5% Frontal bossing 7.5% Macrocephaly 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Agenesis of corpus callosum - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Camptodactyly - Growth delay - Intellectual disability - Joint contracture of the hand - Preauricular skin tag - Prominent forehead - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
