<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0003402" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10280/klippel-feil-syndrome">
<Focus>Klippel Feil syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0022738</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Cervical vertebral fusion</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003402-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Klippel Feil syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Klippel Feil syndrome (KFS) is a congenital, musculoskeletal condition characterized by the fusion of at least two vertebrae of the neck. Common symptoms include a short neck, low hairline at the back of the head, and restricted mobility of the upper spine. This condition can cause chronic headaches as well as pain in both the neck and the back. Other features may involve various other body parts or systems. Sometimes, KFS occurs as a feature of another disorder or syndrome, such as Wildervanck syndrome or hemifacial microsomia. In these cases, affected people have the features of both KFS and the additional disorder. KFS may be caused by mutations in the GDF6 or GDF3 gene and inherited in an autosomal dominant manner; or, it may be caused by mutations in the MEOX1 gene and inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Treatment is symptomatic and may include medications, surgery, and/or physical therapy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003402-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Klippel Feil syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Klippel Feil syndrome? Klippel Feil syndrome is characterized by the fusion of 2 or more spinal bones in the neck (cervical vertebrae). The condition is present from birth (congenital). The 3 most common features include a low posterior hairline (at the back of the head); a short neck; and limited neck range of motion. However, not all affected people have these features. This condition can cause chronic headaches as well as pain in both the neck and the back. KFS has been reported in people with a very wide variety of other conditions and abnormalities, including: scoliosis (curvature of the spine) cervical dystonia (painful, involuntary tensing of the neck muscles) genitourinary abnormalities (those of the reproductive organs and/or urinary system, including the kidneys) Sprengel deformity cardiac (heart) defects such as ventricular septal defect pulmonary abnormalities (relating to the lungs) and respiratory problems hearing deficits facial asymmetry, or other abnormalities of the head and face (such as cleft palate or hemifacial microsomia) torticollis central nervous system abnormalities (including Chiari malformation, spina bifida, or syringomyelia), and/or neurological symptoms other skeletal abnormalities (including those of the ribs, limbs and/or fingers) situs inversus short stature synkinesia (where movement in one hand involuntarily mimics the deliberate movement of the other hand) Wildervank syndrome Duane syndrome or other eye (ocular) abnormalities The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Klippel Feil syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal vertebral segmentation and fusion 90% Cervical vertebral fusion (C2/C3) 90% Facial asymmetry 90% Limited neck range of motion 90% Low posterior hairline 90% Short neck 90% Vertebral segmentation defect 90% Webbed neck 90% Abnormality of the ribs 50% Abnormality of the shoulder 50% Congenital muscular torticollis 50% Hearing impairment 50% Scoliosis 50% Sprengel anomaly 50% Abnormality of limb bone morphology 7.5% Abnormality of the cranial nerves 7.5% Abnormality of the sacrum 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Ectopic anus 7.5% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 7.5% Posterior fossa cyst 7.5% Renal hypoplasia/aplasia 7.5% Spina bifida 7.5% Urogenital fistula 7.5% Ventricular septal defect 7.5% Scoliosis 30/50 Sprengel anomaly 21/50 Mixed hearing impairment 5/24 Bimanual synkinesia 9/50 Unilateral renal agenesis 7/45 Abnormality of cardiovascular system morphology 21/505 Abnormality of the pinna - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Cervicomedullary schisis - Cleft upper lip - Conductive hearing impairment - Fused cervical vertebrae - Sensorineural hearing impairment - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003402-3" qtype="causes">What causes Klippel Feil syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Klippel Feil syndrome (KFS)?  The specific underlying causes and mechanisms of Klippel Feil syndrome (KFS)are not well understood.  In general medical researchers believe KFS happens when the tissue of the embroyo that normally develops into separate vertebrae does not divide correctly.  More specifically, when KFS occurs with other syndromes such as fetal alcohol syndrome, Goldenhar syndrome, Wildervanck syndrome or hemifacial microsomia, medical researchers believe KFS has the same cause as the associated syndrome.  Isolated KFS (meaning not associated with another syndrome) can be sporadic or inherited.  Although KFS may in some cases be caused by a combination of genetic and environmental factors, mutations in at least three genes have been linked to KFS: GDF6, GDF3 and MEOX1 gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003402-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Klippel Feil syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is Klippel Feil syndrome inherited? In some cases, Klippel Feil syndrome (KFS) appears to occur randomly for unknown reasons (sporadically). In other cases, the condition appears to be genetic and may occur in more than one person in a family. Both autosomal dominant and autosomal recessive inheritance patterns have been reported, with different responsible genes. When KFS is caused by changes (mutations) in the GDF6 or GDF3 genes, it is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. This means that having a mutation in only one copy of the responsible gene is enough to cause features of the condition. When a person with an autosomal dominant condition has children, each child has a 50% (1 in 2) chance to inherit the mutated copy of the gene. When KFS is caused by mutations in the MEOX1 gene, it is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. This means that a person must have mutations in both copies of the responsible gene to be affected. The parents of a person with an autosomal recessive condition usually each carry one mutated copy of the gene and are referred to as carriers. Carriers are typically unaffected. When two carriers of the same autosomal recessive condition have children, each child has a 25% (1 in 4) risk to be affected, a 50% (1 in 2) chance to be an unaffected carrier like each parent, and a 25% risk to be unaffected and not be a carrier. When KFS occurs as a feature of another condition, the inheritance pattern follows that of the other condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003402-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Klippel Feil syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Klippel Feil syndrome diagnosed? Klippel Feil syndrome (KFS) is typically diagnosed when X-rays or other imaging techniques show fusion of cervical vertebrae. X-rays of the entire spine should be performed to detect other spinal abnormalities, and additional imaging studies may be needed to assess the extent of the abnormality. KFS can be associated with a wide range of other abnormalities involving many parts of the body. Therefore, other initial exams are needed to detect additional physical abnormalities or underlying conditions. These include: examination of the chest to rule out involvement of the heart and lungs examination of the chest wall to detect possible rib anomalies MRI for spinal stenosis or neurological deficits ultrasound of the kidneys for renal abnormalities hearing evaluation due to high incidence of hearing loss Various lab tests to assess organ function Additional tests or consultations with specialists may be recommended depending on the features present in each person with KFS.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003402-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Klippel Feil syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Klippel-Feil syndrome be treated? There is no cure for Klippel Feil syndrome (KFS); treatment is generally symptomatic and supportive. Management depends on the features and severity in each person, and can be life-long. Careful evaluation, consistent follow-up, and coordination with various specialists are needed to improve outcome and make sure that no related diagnosis is missed. There are various conservative therapies available, including the use of cervical collars, braces, traction, physical therapy, non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), and various pain medications. However, for many people with KFS, symptoms are progressive due to degenerative changes that occur in the spine. Surgery may be indicated for a variety of reasons, including persistent pain; neurologic deficits; cervical or craniocervical instability; constriction of the spinal cord; or to correct severe scoliosis. Some people with KFS may need surgery to repair other skeletal abnormalities, or those related to the heart, kidneys, ears, eyes, or other parts of the body. Those at an increased risk for neurological complications should be regularly monitored by their health care providers and may be advised to avoid activities that could lead to trauma or injury to cervical vertebrae.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
