<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004126" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3786/morquio-syndrome-b">
<Focus>Morquio syndrome B</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0086652</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Mucopolysaccharidosis type IVB</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MPS IVB</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MPS 4B</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mucopolysaccharidosis type IV</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004126-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Morquio syndrome B ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Morquio syndrome B? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Morquio syndrome B. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aortic valve stenosis - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Carious teeth - Cervical myelopathy - Cervical subluxation - Coarse facial features - Constricted iliac wings - Coxa valga - Decreased beta-galactosidase activity - Disproportionate short-trunk short stature - Epiphyseal deformities of tubular bones - Flaring of rib cage - Genu valgum - Grayish enamel - Hearing impairment - Hepatomegaly - Hyperlordosis - Hypoplasia of the odontoid process - Inguinal hernia - Intimal thickening in the coronary arteries - Joint laxity - Juvenile onset - Keratan sulfate excretion in urine - Kyphosis - Mandibular prognathia - Metaphyseal widening - Opacification of the corneal stroma - Osteoporosis - Ovoid vertebral bodies - Platyspondyly - Pointed proximal second through fifth metacarpals - Prominent sternum - Recurrent upper respiratory tract infections - Restrictive lung disease - Scoliosis - Ulnar deviation of the wrist - Wide mouth - Widely spaced teeth - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
