<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004069" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3669/miller-dieker-syndrome">
<Focus>Miller-Dieker syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
			<CUI>C0265219</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Miller-Dieker lissencephaly syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MDLS</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004069-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Miller-Dieker syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Miller-Dieker syndrome is a genetic condition characterized by lissencephaly, typical facial features, and severe neurologic abnormalities. Symptoms may include severe intellectual disability, developmental delay, seizures, muscle stiffness, weak muscle tone and feeding difficulties. Miller-Dieker syndrome is caused by a deletion of genetic material near the end of the short (p) arm of chromosome 17. Treatment is symptomatic and supportive.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004069-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Miller-Dieker syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Miller-Dieker syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Miller-Dieker syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Intellectual disability 100% Motor delay 100% Anteverted nares 90% Cerebral cortical atrophy 90% EEG abnormality 90% Epicanthus 90% Frontal bossing 90% High forehead 90% Posteriorly rotated ears 90% Seizures 90% Short nose 90% Abnormality of the cardiovascular system 50% Polyhydramnios 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 7.5% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 7.5% Incoordination 7.5% Nephropathy 7.5% Omphalocele 7.5% Sacral dimple 7.5% Lissencephaly 27/27 Short nose 26/26 Thick upper lip vermilion 25/25 Wide nasal bridge 24/25 Cavum septum pellucidum 17/22 Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 17/23 Sacral dimple 14/19 Microcephaly 17/25 Deep palmar crease 14/21 Midline brain calcifications 13/24 Low-set ears 14/27 Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 10/24 Epicanthus 8/22 Intrauterine growth retardation 8/22 Polyhydramnios 6/20 Abnormality of cardiovascular system morphology 6/27 Joint contracture of the hand 6/27 Single transverse palmar crease 5/24 Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Camptodactyly - Cataract - Cleft palate - Contiguous gene syndrome - Cryptorchidism - Decreased fetal movement - Delayed eruption of teeth - Duodenal atresia - Failure to thrive - Heterotopia - Infantile muscular hypotonia - Infantile spasms - Inguinal hernia - Pachygyria - Pelvic kidney - Polydactyly - Progressive spastic paraplegia - Recurrent aspiration pneumonia - Upslanted palpebral fissure - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
