<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004422" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3904/nijmegen-breakage-syndrome">
<Focus>Nijmegen breakage syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0398791</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Berlin Breakage syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ataxia-Telangiectasia variant V1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Microcephaly with normal intelligence immunodeficiency and lymphoreticular malignancies</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Nonsyndromal microcephaly autosomal recessive with normal intelligence</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Seemanova syndrome 2</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004422-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Nijmegen breakage syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Nijmegen breakage syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Nijmegen breakage syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal hair quantity 90% Abnormal immunoglobulin level 90% Abnormal nasal morphology 90% Abnormality of chromosome stability 90% Abnormality of the upper urinary tract 90% Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Convex nasal ridge 90% Decreased body weight 90% Deep philtrum 90% Depressed nasal bridge 90% Hearing abnormality 90% Hemolytic anemia 90% Low anterior hairline 90% Malabsorption 90% Microcephaly 90% Recurrent respiratory infections 90% Short neck 90% Short stature 90% Sinusitis 90% Sloping forehead 90% Thrombocytopenia 90% Upslanted palpebral fissure 90% Urogenital fistula 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the thymus 50% Abnormality of neuronal migration 7.5% Acute leukemia 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Cutaneous photosensitivity 7.5% Freckling 7.5% Glioma 7.5% Lymphoma 7.5% Medulloblastoma 7.5% Muscle weakness 7.5% Non-midline cleft lip 7.5% Respiratory insufficiency 7.5% Skeletal muscle atrophy 7.5% Anal atresia - Anal stenosis - Autoimmune hemolytic anemia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - B lymphocytopenia - Bronchiectasis - Cafe-au-lait spot - Choanal atresia - Cleft upper lip - Diarrhea - Dysgammaglobulinemia - Hydronephrosis - Hyperactivity - Intellectual disability - Intrauterine growth retardation - Long nose - Macrotia - Malar prominence - Mastoiditis - Neurodegeneration - Otitis media - Primary ovarian failure - Progressive vitiligo - Recurrent bronchitis - Recurrent infection of the gastrointestinal tract - Recurrent pneumonia - Recurrent urinary tract infections - Rhabdomyosarcoma - T lymphocytopenia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
