<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004934" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7412/poland-syndrome">
<Focus>Poland syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0032357</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Poland anomaly</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Poland syndactyly</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Poland sequence</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Unilateral defect of pectoralis muscle and syndactyly of the hand</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Poland's syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004934-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Poland syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Poland syndrome is characterized by an underdeveloped or absent chest muscle on one side of the body, absence of the breastbone portion (sternal) of the chest muscle, and webbing of the fingers of the hand on the same side. The cause of Poland syndrome is not known. This syndrome is nearly always sporadic. It tends to occur on the right side and is more common in boys than girls. Treatment typically involves surgical correction of the chest wall deformities.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004934-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Poland syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Poland syndrome? Signs and symptoms of Poland syndrome may be slight to severe. Some people with Poland syndrome have only absence of the breast tissue, while others may be missing all or part of the chest muscle and underlying ribs. Symptoms tend to occur on one side of the body. Below we have listed symptoms that can be found in this condition:  Absence of some of the chest muscles.  The end of the main chest muscle, where it attaches to the breastbone, is usually missing.  The nipple, including the darkened area around it (areola) is underdeveloped or missing; in females, this may extend to the breast and underlying tissues. Abnormally short and slightly webbed fingers. Often, the armpit (axillary) hair is missing. The skin in the area is underdeveloped (hypoplastic) with a thinned subcutaneous fat layer.  The upper rib cage can be underdeveloped or missing, Sometimes the shoulder blade or bones of the arm are also involved, Rarely, spine or kidney problems are present.   The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Poland syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aplasia of the pectoralis major muscle 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the nipples 90% Asymmetry of the thorax 90% Breast aplasia 90% Brachydactyly syndrome 50% Finger syndactyly 50% Split hand 50% Abnormal dermatoglyphics 7.5% Abnormality of the humerus 7.5% Abnormality of the liver 7.5% Abnormality of the lower limb 7.5% Abnormality of the ribs 7.5% Abnormality of the sternum 7.5% Abnormality of the ulna 7.5% Absent hand 7.5% Acute leukemia 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the radius 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the thumb 7.5% Cone-shaped epiphysis 7.5% Congenital diaphragmatic hernia 7.5% Low posterior hairline 7.5% Microcephaly 7.5% Neoplasm of the breast 7.5% Reduced bone mineral density 7.5% Renal hypoplasia/aplasia 7.5% Retinal hamartoma 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Short neck 7.5% Situs inversus totalis 7.5% Abnormality of the breast - Absence of pectoralis minor muscle - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Dextrocardia - Hemivertebrae - Hypoplasia of deltoid muscle - Hypoplasia of latissimus dorsi muscle - Hypoplasia of serratus anterior muscle - Rib fusion - Short ribs - Sprengel anomaly - Syndactyly - Unilateral absence of pectoralis major muscle - Unilateral brachydactyly - Unilateral hypoplasia of pectoralis major muscle - Unilateral oligodactyly - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004934-3" qtype="causes">What causes Poland syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Poland syndrome? The cause of Poland syndrome is unknown. Most evidence supports the idea that something abnormal happens during the sixth week of fetal development. This event most likely involves the vascular (blood and lymph) system. Speculations include: An interruption of the embryonic blood supply of the arteries that lie under the collarbone (subclavian arteries). This could be caused by the forward growth of the ribs reducing the flow of blood. A malformation of the subclavian arteries causes a reduced amount of blood delivered to the developing tissues on one side of the body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004934-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Poland syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is Poland syndrome inherited? Poland syndrome is rarely inherited and generally sporadic. Sporadic refers to the chance occurrence of a non-genetic disorder or abnormality that is not likely to recur in a family. In the few reported familial cases, researchers suggest that the condition may have stemmed from an inherited susceptibility to events such as interruption of blood flow that may predispose a person to the anomaly (i.e., make a person more likely to develop the anomaly).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004934-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Poland syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>When is Poland syndrome typically first diagnosed? The severity of Poland syndrome differs from person to person. As a result it is not often diagnosed or reported. Sometimes, a person does not realize they have the condition until puberty, when lopsided (asymmetrical) growth makes it more obvious.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004934-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Poland syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Poland syndrome be treated? Management of Poland syndrome may include surgical correction of the chest wall deformities. Surgical options are available to improve appearance in both males and females. In females, breast reconstruction is typically performed at the time of normal full breast development and can be planned in conjunction with or following reconstruction of the chest wall. In males reconstruction of the chest may not be necessary if there is no underlying chest wall deformity. The optimal surgical approach will vary from patient to patient. Surgical options should be discussed with a surgeon familiar with reconstructive surgery in people with Poland syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
