<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004143" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9673/mowat-wilson-syndrome">
<Focus>Mowat-Wilson syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1856113</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Mental retardation, microcephaly, and distinct facial features with or without Hirschsprung disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hirschsprung disease mental retardation syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004143-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Mowat-Wilson syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Mowat-Wilson syndrome (MWS) is a rare genetic disorder that affects many systems of the body. The main features include moderate to severe intellectual disability, distinctive facial features, and epilepsy. Other features may include Hirschsprung disease; heart (cardiac) defects; kidney (renal) abnormalities; genital abnormalities; eye abnormalities; and short stature. It is caused by a mutation or deletion in the ZEB2 gene, which usually occurs for the first time (sporadically) in affected people. Treatment typically focuses on the specific symptoms in each person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004143-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Mowat-Wilson syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Mowat-Wilson syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Mowat-Wilson syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Intellectual disability 100% Abnormality of the eyebrow 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Deeply set eye 90% External ear malformation 90% Frontal bossing 90% High forehead 90% Large earlobe 90% Microcephaly 90% Seizures 90% Aganglionic megacolon 62% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 50% Broad columella 50% Constipation 50% Cryptorchidism 50% Cupped ear 50% Displacement of the external urethral meatus 50% Epicanthus 50% Esotropia 50% Fine hair 50% Hypertelorism 50% Iris coloboma 50% Low hanging columella 50% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 50% Muscular hypotonia 50% Open mouth 50% Pointed chin 50% Prominent nasal tip 50% Ptosis 50% Short stature 50% Tapered finger 50% Uplifted earlobe 50% Wide nasal bridge 50% Agenesis of corpus callosum 42% Bifid scrotum 33% Generalized muscle hypertrophy 33% Hypospadias 33% Abnormal localization of kidney 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia affecting the eye 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the cerebellum 7.5% Camptodactyly of finger 7.5% Cerebral cortical atrophy 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Cleft upper lip 7.5% Deep plantar creases 7.5% Finger syndactyly 7.5% Hallux valgus 7.5% Nystagmus 7.5% Patent ductus arteriosus 7.5% Preaxial foot polydactyly 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Submucous cleft hard palate 7.5% Supernumerary nipple 7.5% Tetralogy of Fallot 7.5% Ventricular septal defect 7.5% Ventriculomegaly 7.5% Vesicoureteral reflux 7.5% Abdominal distention - Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Abnormality of the abdominal wall - Abnormality of the rib cage - Absent speech - Atria septal defect - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Broad eyebrow - Delayed eruption of teeth - Drooling - Happy demeanor - Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum - Intellectual disability, moderate - Motor delay - Pectus carinatum - Pectus excavatum - Pulmonary artery sling - Pulmonary artery stenosis - Pulmonic stenosis - Vomiting - Widely spaced teeth - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004143-3" qtype="causes">What causes Mowat-Wilson syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Mowat-Wilson syndrome? Mowat-Wilson syndrome is caused by mutations in the ZEB2 (also known as ZFHX1B or SIP-1) gene. This gene provides instructions for making a protein that plays a critical role in the formation of many organs and tissues before birth. It is a transcription factor, which means that it attaches (binds) to specific regions of DNA and helps control the activity of particular genes. Researchers believe that ZEB2 protein is involved in the development of tissues that give rise to the nervous system, digestive tract, facial features, heart, and other organs. Mowat-Wilson syndrome almost always results from the loss of one working copy of the ZEB2 gene in each cell. In some cases, the entire gene is deleted. In other cases, mutations within the gene lead to the production of an abnormally short, nonfunctional version of the ZEB2 protein. A shortage of this protein disrupts the normal development of many organs and tissues, which causes the varied signs and symptoms of Mowat-Wilson syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004143-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Mowat-Wilson syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Mowat-Wilson inherited? Mowat-Wilson syndrome is inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern, which means one copy of the altered gene in each cell is sufficient to cause the disorder. Most cases of Mowat-Wilson syndrome result from new (de novo) mutations in the gene that occur during the formation of reproductive cells (eggs or sperm) or in early embryonic development. These cases occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
