<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004906" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7400/pityriasis-lichenoides-chronica">
<Focus>Pityriasis lichenoides chronica</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0162851</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pityriasis lichenoides</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004906-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pityriasis lichenoides chronica ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pityriasis lichenoides chronica is the mild, chronic form of pityriasis lichenoides, a skin disorder of unknown cause. This condition is characterized by the gradual development of symptomless, small, scaling papules that spontaneously flatten and regress over a period of weeks or months. Lesions at various stages may be present at any one time. Patients with this condition often have exacerbations and relapses of the condition, which can last for months or years.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004906-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pityriasis lichenoides chronica ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the symptoms of pityriasis lichenoides chronica? Pityriasis lichenoides chronica usually starts out as a small pink papule that turns a reddish-brown color. There is usually a fine, mica-like adherent scale attached to the center which can be peeled off to reveal a shiny, pinkish brown surface. Over several weeks, the spot flattens out spontaneously and leaves behind a brown mark, which fades over several months. Pityriasis lichenoides chronica most commonly occurs over the trunk, buttocks, arms and legs, but may also occur on the hands, feet, face and scalp. Unlike the acute type of pityriasis lichenoides, lesions associated with pityriasis lichenoides chronica are not painful, itchy or irritating. What symptoms are associated with pityriasis lichenoides chronica (PLC)? PLC is the milder form of pityriasis lichenoides, and the lesions associated with this form consist of small, firm, red-brown spots. Unlike PLEVA, the lesions are not irritating and have mica-like adherent scale, which can be scraped off to reveal a shiny brown surface. The spot flattens out over several weeks to leave a brown mark which fades over several months. PLC can look like psoriasis, lichen planus, or insect bites.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004906-3" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Pityriasis lichenoides chronica ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is pityriasis lichenoides chronica diagnosed? The clinical appearance of pityriasis lichenoides chronica suggests the diagnosis. However, since it can look like psoriasis, lichen planus, or the common bug bite, a skin biopsy is recommended to confirm the diagnosis. A dermatologist is the type of specialist who is most often involved in the diagnosis and care of patients with this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004906-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Pityriasis lichenoides chronica ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might pityriasis lichenoides chronica be treated? Pityriasis lichenoides chronica may not always respond to treatment and relapses often occur when treatment is discontinued. If the rash is not causing symptoms, treatment may not be necessary. In cases where treatment is necessary, there are several different therapies available. First-line therapies may include: Sun exposure   Topical steroids  Topical immunomodulators such as tacrolimus or pimecrolimus  Oral antibiotics such as erythromycin and tetracycline  Second-line therapies may include: Phototherapy  artificial ultraviolet radiation treatment with UVB or PUVA  Third-line therapies may include: Systemic steroids Methotrexate  Acitretin Dapsone Ciclosporin For more resistant and severe disease, a combination of the above may be used PubMed, a searchable database of medical literature, lists several journal articles that discuss treatment of pityriasis lichenoides chronica. Click on the link to view abstracts of articles related to this topic.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
