<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004291" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8310/myotonic-dystrophy-type-1">
<Focus>Myotonic dystrophy type 1</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0027126</CUI>
			<CUI>C0410226</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Dystrophia myotonica type 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>DM1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Steinert disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Steinert myotonic dystrophy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Steinert's disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Myotonic dystrophy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004291-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Myotonic dystrophy type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Myotonic dystrophy type 1, one of the two types of myotonic dystrophy, is an inherited type of muscular dystrophy that affects the muscles and other body systems (e.g., heart, eyes, pancreas).  Myotonic dystrophy type 1 has been categorized into three somewhat overlapping subtypes: mild, classic, and congenital (present at birth). Symptoms of the mild form are the least severe with a normal life span. The classic form is characterized by muscle weakness and wasting, prolonged muscle tensing (myotonia), cataract, and often abnormal heart function; adults may become physically disabled and may have a shortened life span. The congenital form is characterized by severe generalized weakeness at birth (hypotonia), often causing complications with breathing and early death. The condition is inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern and is caused by mutations in the DMPK gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004291-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Myotonic dystrophy type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Myotonic dystrophy type 1? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Myotonic dystrophy type 1. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Arrhythmia 90% EMG abnormality 90% Hypertonia 90% Mask-like facies 90% Myotonia 90% Skeletal muscle atrophy 90% Abnormality of the endocrine system 50% Cataract 50% Cognitive impairment 50% Facial palsy 50% Muscular hypotonia 50% Respiratory insufficiency 50% Abnormal hair quantity 7.5% Abnormality of the hip bone 7.5% Abnormality of the upper urinary tract 7.5% Cryptorchidism 7.5% Hernia of the abdominal wall 7.5% Hydrocephalus 7.5% Non-midline cleft lip 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Atrial flutter 4/11 Autosomal dominant inheritance - Cerebral atrophy - Cholelithiasis - Decreased fetal movement - Dysphagia - Excessive daytime sleepiness - Facial diplegia - Feeding difficulties in infancy - First degree atrioventricular block - Frontal balding - Hypogonadism - Intellectual disability, progressive - Intellectual disability, severe - Obsessive-compulsive trait - Polyhydramnios - Respiratory distress - Testicular atrophy - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004291-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Myotonic dystrophy type 1 inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is myotonic dystrophy type 1 inherited? Myotonic dystrophy type 1 is inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern, which means one copy of the altered gene in each cell is sufficient to cause the disorder. In most cases, an affected person has one affected parent. As myotonic dystrophy is passed from one generation to the next, the disorder generally begins earlier in life and signs and symptoms become more severe. This phenomenon is called anticipation.  Some individuals diagnosed with Myotonic dystrophy type 1 have an obviously affected parent; others do not. A parent may appear to be unaffected because symptoms may be mild or absent. Genetic testing is available to confirm the presence of the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004291-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Myotonic dystrophy type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might myotonic dystrophy type 1 associated vision problems be treated? Treatment of eye and vision problems must be individually tailored. Refractive error and astigmatism can be corrected with eyeglasses, contact lenses, or surgery. Special glasses with eye &quot;crutches&quot; can be used to improve vision in people with ptosis. Surgery can be done to treat ptosis and cataracts, however ptosis often recurs and special precautions must be taken with anesthesia. If severe, strabismus may also be treated with surgery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
