<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004205" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10255/multiple-sclerosis">
<Focus>Multiple sclerosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0026769</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>MS</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004205-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Multiple sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a degenerative disorder that affects the central nervous system, specifically the brain and the spinal cord. The disorder is characterized by destruction of the myelin, the fatty tissue that surrounds and protects the nerve fibers and promotes the transmission of nerve impulses, and damage to nerve cells. The symptoms vary widely from person to person, and may include sensory disturbances in the limbs, problems with muscle control, tremors, muscle stiffness (spasticity), exaggerated reflexes (hyperreflexia), weakness, difficulty walking, poor bladder control, and vision problems. Most patients have periods during which they have symptoms (clinical attacks). The clinical attacks are typically followed by periods without any symptoms (remission). After several years, the symptoms worsen continuously. Multiple sclerosis is considered an autoimmune disorder but the exact cause is unknown. Risk factors for developing multiple sclerosis include genetic factors like changes in the HLA-DRB1 gene and in the IL7R gene and environmental factors, such as exposure to the Epstein-Barr virus, low levels of vitamin D, and smoking. The goal of treatment of MS is to decrease attacks and the inflammation within the central nervous system.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004205-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Multiple sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Multiple sclerosis? The peak age of onset is between ages 20 and 40, although it may develop in children and has also been identified in individuals over 60 years of age. The most common signs and symptoms include sensory disturbance of the limbs; partial or complete visual loss; acute and subacute motor dysfunction of the limbs; diplopia (double vision); and gait dysfunction. These signs and symptoms may occur alone or in combination, and have to be present for a minimum of 24 hours to be considered a &quot;clinical attack.&quot; The signs and symptoms in individuals with MS are extremely variable, even among affected relatives within families. Symptoms vary because the location and severity of each attack can be different. Episodes can last for days, weeks, or months. These episodes alternate with periods of reduced or no symptoms (remissions). While it is common for the disease to return (relapse), the disease may continue to get worse without periods of remission. Because nerves in any part of the brain or spinal cord may be damaged, patients with multiple sclerosis can have symptoms in many parts of the body. Muscle symptoms may include loss of balance, muscle spasms, numbness or abnormal sensation in any area, problems moving arms or legs, problems walking, problems with coordination and making small movements, and tremor or weakness in one or more arms or legs. Bowel and bladder symptoms may include constipation and stool leakage, difficulty beginning to urinate, frequent need or strong urge to urinate, and incontinence. Eye symptoms may include double vision, eye discomfort, uncontrollable rapid eye movements, and vision loss. There may be numbness, tingling, or pain in the face, muscles, arms or legs. Other brain and nerve symptoms may include decreased attention span, poor judgment, and memory loss; difficulty reasoning and solving problems; depression or feelings of sadness; dizziness and balance problems; and hearing loss. Individuals may also have slurred or difficult-to-understand speech, trouble chewing and swallowing, and sexual symptoms such as problems with erections or vaginal lubrication. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Multiple sclerosis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) CNS demyelination - Depression - Diplopia - Emotional lability - Incoordination - Multifactorial inheritance - Muscle weakness - Paresthesia - Spasticity - Urinary hesitancy - Urinary incontinence - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004205-3" qtype="causes">What causes Multiple sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes multiple sclerosis? Studies suggest that there are many factors that influence whether a person will develop multiple sclerosis (MS). The factors that contribute to its onset are multiple and may vary from person to person. The signs and symptoms of MS occur as a result of inflammation, loss of the protective nerve covering (myelin), and the breakdown of nerve cells. The most widely accepted theory is that MS begins as an autoimmune disorder, where white blood cells (lymphocytes) attack healthy tissues. Later, signs and symptoms occur as a result of abnormal activity of specific cells in the brain and spinal cord (microglial cells) and progressive injury and loss of brain and spinal cord cells. Additional theories regarding the cause of MS include chronic viral infections and genetic disease. Although many viruses, and particularly the Epstein-Barr virus, have been associated with MS, there is no specific evidence linking viruses directly to the development of MS. Still, Epstein-Barr virus infection is considered a risk factor for the disease. Certain gene changes, including ones in HLA-DRB1 are associated with an increased risk for developing multiple sclerosis. However, it is unclear exactly what role these gene changes play in the development of MS. Having a first-degree relative with MS, like a parent or sibling, does increase a persons risk for the condition (to around 2%). Learn more about gene changes and MS. Vitamin D is another area of interest. Those who are exposed to more sunlight tend to have higher levels of naturally-produced vitamin D, which is thought to support the immune function and may help protect against immune-mediated diseases like MS. Further information on the cause of MS is available at the National Multiple Sclerosis Society Web site.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004205-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Multiple sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is multiple sclerosis diagnosed? Symptoms of multiple sclerosis (MS) may be similar to those of many other nervous system disorders. The disease is made based on the person&apos;s signs and symptoms and is typically diagnosed by ruling out other conditions. &quot;Dissemination in time and space&quot; are commonly-used criteria for diagnosing the relapsing-remitting form of MS (RR-MS). &quot;Dissemination in time means&quot; that there are at least two clinical attacks, each lasting at least 24 hours, separated by at least one month, or a slow, step-wise progressive course for at least six months. &quot;Dissemination in space&quot; means that there are lesions in more than one area of the brain or spinal cord. For primary progressive MS (PP-MS), there are currently no diagnostic criteria that are universally accepted. Physicians may do many tests to evaluate an individual suspected of having MS. Neurological Exam: May show reduced nerve function in one area of the body or over many parts of the body. This may include abnormal nerve reflexes, decreased ability to move a part of the body, decreased or abnormal sensation, and other loss of nervous system functions. Eye Exam: May show abnormal pupil responses, changes in the visual fields or eye movements, decreased visual acuity, problems with the inside parts of the eye, and rapid eye movements triggered when the eye moves. Other Tests: Lumbar puncture (spinal tap) for cerebrospinal fluid tests, MRI scan of the brain, MRI scan of the spine; nerve function study; and several of blood tests. The Revised McDonald Criteria, published In 2010 by the International Panel on the Diagnosis of Multiple Sclerosis, include specific guidelines for using MRI, visual evoked potentials (VEP) and cerebrospinal fluid analysis to speed the diagnostic process.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
