<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004447" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3672/nonspherocytic-hemolytic-anemia-due-to-hexokinase-deficiency">
<Focus>Nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia due to hexokinase deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0002871</CUI>
			<CUI>C0472792</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hexokinase deficiency hemolytic anemia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004447-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia due to hexokinase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia due to hexokinase deficiency (NSHA due to HK1 deficiency) is a very rare condition mainly characterized by severe, chronic hemolysis, beginning in infancy. Approximately 20 cases of this condition have been described to date. Signs and symptoms of hexokinase deficiency are very similar to those of pyruvate kinase deficiency but anemia is generally more severe. Some affected individuals reportedly have had various abnormalities in addition to NSHA including multiple malformations, panmyelopathy, and latent diabetes. It can be caused by mutations in the HK1 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Treatment may include red cell transfusions for those with severe anemia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004447-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia due to hexokinase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia due to hexokinase deficiency? Hexokinase deficiency manifests itself primarily as nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia (NSHA). The signs and symptoms of hexokinase deficiency are very similar to those of pyruvate kinase deficiency, a more common inherited cause of hemolytic anemia, and may include jaundice, fatigue, lethargy, and pale skin.. However, the anemia associated with hexokinase deficiency is generally more severe. There have been reports of some affected individuals having various other abnormalities including multiple malformations, panmyelopathy, and latent diabetes. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia due to hexokinase deficiency. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal recessive inheritance - Cholecystitis - Cholelithiasis - Congenital onset - Hyperbilirubinemia - Jaundice - Nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia - Normochromic anemia - Normocytic anemia - Reticulocytosis - Splenomegaly - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004447-3" qtype="causes">What causes Nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia due to hexokinase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia due to hexokinase deficiency? Nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia due to hexokinase deficiency has been shown to be caused by mutations in the HK1 gene, which cause at least a partial deficiency of the enzyme hexokinase. This enzyme plays an important role in the chemical processes involved in the breakdown of sugar molecules (glycolysis). Red blood cells depend on this process for energy; if an enzyme is defective in any one of the stages, the red blood cell cannot function properly and hemolysis takes place. When red blood cells cannot be replaced faster than they destroy themselves, anemia results.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004447-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia due to hexokinase deficiency inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia due to hexokinase deficiency inherited? Nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia due to hexokinase deficiency is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. This means that a mutation in both copies of the gene associated with the condition must be present in order to be affected. The parents of an individual with an autosomal recessive condition each have one mutated copy of the gene in each cell and are referred to as carriers. Carriers typically do not have any signs or symptoms of the condition. When two carriers of the same autosomal recessive condition have children, each child has a 25% (1 in 4) risk to be affected, a 50% (1 in 2) risk to be an unaffected carrier like each parent, and a 25% risk to be unaffected and have 2 normal copies of the gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004447-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia due to hexokinase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might nonspherocytic hemolytic anemia due to hexokinase deficiency be treated? When severe anemia is present, blood transfusions may be necessary. Affected individuals should avoid any drugs that can cause destruction of red blood cells, as well as any environmental triggers that may be identified.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
