<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004652" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5121/oto-palato-digital-syndrome-type-1">
<Focus>Oto-palato-digital syndrome type 1</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265251</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Otopalatodigital syndrome type 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Taybi syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>OPD syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>OPD syndrome 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>OPD1</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004652-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Oto-palato-digital syndrome type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Oto-palato-digital syndrome type 1? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Oto-palato-digital syndrome type 1. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the nose 90% Cleft palate 90% Hearing impairment 90% Hypertelorism 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Prominent supraorbital ridges 90% Reduced number of teeth 90% Sandal gap 90% Short hallux 90% Abnormality of frontal sinus 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the thumb 50% Bowing of the long bones 50% Brachydactyly syndrome 50% Craniofacial hyperostosis 50% Elbow dislocation 50% Increased bone mineral density 50% Proximal placement of thumb 50% Short distal phalanx of finger 50% Synostosis of carpal bones 7.5% Tarsal synostosis 7.5% Abnormality of the fifth metatarsal bone - Absent frontal sinuses - Accessory carpal bones - Bipartite calcaneus - Broad distal phalanx of the thumb - Broad hallux - Bulbous tips of toes - Capitate-hamate fusion - Conductive hearing impairment - Coxa valga - Delayed closure of the anterior fontanelle - Dislocated radial head - Flat face - Frontal bossing - Hip dislocation - Intellectual disability, mild - Lateral femoral bowing - Limited elbow extension - Limited knee flexion - Malar flattening - Multiple impacted teeth - Nail dysplasia - Nail dystrophy - Narrow mouth - Omphalocele - Pectus excavatum - Prominent occiput - Scoliosis - Selective tooth agenesis - Short 3rd metacarpal - Short 4th metacarpal - Short 5th metacarpal - Short nose - Short stature - Thick skull base - Toe syndactyly - Wide nasal bridge - X-linked dominant inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
