<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004451" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7223/noonan-syndrome-1">
<Focus>Noonan syndrome 1</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0028326</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Noonan syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004451-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Noonan syndrome 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Noonan syndrome is a genetic disorder that causes abnormal development of multiple parts of the body. Features of Noonan syndrome may include a distinctive facial appearance, short stature, a broad or webbed neck, congenital heart defects, bleeding problems, skeletal malformations, and developmental delay. Noonan syndrome may be caused by mutations in any one of several genes including the PTPN11, KRAS, RAF1, SOS1, NRAS and BRAF genes. It is sometimes referred to as a specific subtype based on the responsible gene in an affected person. Noonan syndrome is typically inherited in an autosomal dominant manner but many cases are due to a new mutation and are not inherited from an affected parent.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004451-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Noonan syndrome 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Noonan syndrome 1? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Noonan syndrome 1. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Intellectual disability 25% Hypogonadism 7.5% Abnormal bleeding - Amegakaryocytic thrombocytopenia - Atria septal defect - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Brachydactyly syndrome - Clinodactyly - Coarctation of aorta - Cryptorchidism - Cubitus valgus - Cystic hygroma - Dental malocclusion - Epicanthus - Failure to thrive in infancy - Heterogeneous - High palate - Hypertelorism - Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy - Kyphoscoliosis - Low posterior hairline - Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears - Lymphedema - Male infertility - Myopia - Neurofibrosarcoma - Patent ductus arteriosus - Pectus excavatum of inferior sternum - Postnatal growth retardation - Ptosis - Pulmonic stenosis - Radial deviation of finger - Reduced factor XII activity - Reduced factor XIII activity - Sensorineural hearing impairment - Shield chest - Short neck - Short stature - Superior pectus carinatum - Synovitis - Triangular face - Ventricular septal defect - Webbed neck - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004451-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Noonan syndrome 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Noonan syndrome be treated? Management generally focuses on the specific signs and symptoms present in each person. Treatments for the complications of Noonan syndrome (such as cardiovascular abnormalities) are generally standard and do not differ from treatment in the general population. Developmental disabilities are addressed by early intervention programs and individualized education strategies. Treatment for serious bleeding depends upon the specific factor deficiency or platelet abnormality. Growth hormone treatment increases growth velocity. More detailed information about treatment for Noonan syndrome can be viewed on the GeneReviews Web site.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
