<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004905" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10265/pityriasis-lichenoides">
<Focus>Pityriasis lichenoides</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0162853</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pityriasis lichenoides chronica</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pityriasis lichenoides et varioliformis acuta</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004905-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pityriasis lichenoides ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pityriasis lichenoides is a skin disorder of unknown cause.  There are two types of pityriasis lichenoides; a more severe form with a sudden onset that tends to be short-lived (acute) which is usually found in children, known as pityriasis lichenoides et varioliformis acuta and a more mild but long-lasting (chronic) form known as pityriasis lichenoides chronica. Pityriasis lichenoides chronica may clear up in a few weeks or persist for years.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004905-2" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Pityriasis lichenoides ?</Question>
			<Answer>What treatment is available for pityriasis lichenoides? The different forms of treatment for pityriasis lichenoides that have been used range from natural sunlight exposure to chemotherapeutic agents. Treatment may not be necessary if the rash is not causing symptoms. When itching is severe, topical corticosteroids, tar preparations, and antihistamines may provide relief without changing the course of the disease. In adult patients, administration of methotrexate and oral tetracycline has led to good results; however, these medications are inappropriate for first-line treatment in young children. In addition to tetracycline, erythromycin is another antibiotic that is commonly used to treat pityriasis lichenoides. Sunlight is helpful, and excellent therapeutic responses to UVB phototherapy are documented. UVB therapy is more difficult in young children, and there is little data regarding the long-term risks of phototherapy in the pediatric population. It is difficult to interpret the results of formal therapy evaluations because of the frequency of spontaneous remissions.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
