<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004615" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8695/osteogenesis-imperfecta-type-iii">
<Focus>Osteogenesis imperfecta type III</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0268362</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>OI type 3</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Osteogenesis imperfecta, progressively deforming with normal sclerae</Synonym>
		<Synonym>OI type III</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Progressive deforming osteogenesis imperfecta</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Severe osteogenesis imperfecta</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Osteogenesis imperfecta</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004615-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Osteogenesis imperfecta type III ?</Question>
			<Answer>Osteogenesis imperfecta type III (OI type III) is a form of osteogenesis imperfecta, a group of genetic conditions that primarily affect the bones. In OI type III, specifically, a diagnosis can often be made shortly after birth as fractures (broken bones) during the newborn period simply from handling the infant are common. Other signs and symptoms vary significantly from person to person but may include severe bone fragility, bone malformations, short stature, dental problems (dentinogenesis imperfect), macrocephaly (unusually large head), hearing loss, and blue sclerae (whites of the eyes). Most affected people are unable to walk without assistance. OI type III is caused by changes (mutations) in the COL1A1 or COL1A2 genes and is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Treatment is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004615-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Osteogenesis imperfecta type III ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Osteogenesis imperfecta type III? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Osteogenesis imperfecta type III. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the nervous system - Abnormality of the thorax - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Basilar impression - Biconcave vertebral bodies - Blue sclerae - Bowing of limbs due to multiple fractures - Decreased calvarial ossification - Dentinogenesis imperfecta - Frontal bossing - Hearing impairment - Kyphosis - Multiple prenatal fractures - Neonatal short-limb short stature - Platybasia - Protrusio acetabuli - Pulmonary hypertension - Recurrent fractures - Scoliosis - Severe generalized osteoporosis - Slender long bone - Tibial bowing - Triangular face - Wide anterior fontanel - Wormian bones - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
