<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004457" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10719/noonan-like-syndrome-with-loose-anagen-hair">
<Focus>Noonan-like syndrome with loose anagen hair</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0028326</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
			<CUI>C3554793</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004457-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Noonan-like syndrome with loose anagen hair ?</Question>
			<Answer>Noonan-like syndrome with loose anagen hair is characterized  by facial features suggestive of Noonan syndrome (macrocephaly, high forehead, wide-set eyes or hypertelorism, palpebral ptosis, and low-set and posteriorly rotated ears) along with hair that resembles loose anagen hair syndrome (pluckable, sparse, thin and slow-growing). Other features include frequent congenital heart defects, distinctive skin features (darkly pigmented skin with eczema or ichthyosis), short stature which may be associated with a growth hormone deficiency, and developmental delays. The condition is caused by mutations in the SHOC2 gene. It follows an autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004457-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Noonan-like syndrome with loose anagen hair ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Noonan-like syndrome with loose anagen hair? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Noonan-like syndrome with loose anagen hair. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal hair quantity 90% Delayed skeletal maturation 90% Low posterior hairline 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Short nose 90% Short stature 90% Webbed neck 90% Abnormality of the pulmonary artery 50% Anteverted nares 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the eyebrow 50% Deep philtrum 50% Epicanthus 50% Hydrocephalus 50% Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy 50% Macrotia 50% Pectus excavatum 50% Abnormality of the elbow 7.5% Abnormality of the fingernails 7.5% Abnormality of the intervertebral disk 7.5% Abnormality of the palate 7.5% Brachydactyly syndrome 7.5% Carious teeth 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Cryptorchidism 7.5% Hearing impairment 7.5% Hypertelorism 7.5% Hypoplastic toenails 7.5% Thick lower lip vermilion 7.5% Thin vermilion border 7.5% Eczema 5% Ichthyosis 5% Nasal speech 5% Atria septal defect - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Hyperactivity - Intellectual disability - Loose anagen hair - Low-set ears - Macrocephaly - Posteriorly rotated ears - Prominent forehead - Pulmonic stenosis - Short neck - Sparse scalp hair - Strabismus - Ventricular septal defect - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
