<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004102" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8549/moebius-syndrome">
<Focus>Moebius syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0221060</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Mobius syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital facial diplegia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital facial diplegia syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital oculofacial paralysis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Moebius sequence</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004102-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Moebius syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moebius syndrome is a rare neurological condition that primarily affects the muscles that control facial expression and eye movement. Signs and symptoms of the condition may include weakness or paralysis of the facial muscles; feeding, swallowing, and choking problems; excessive drooling; crossed eyes; lack of facial expression; eye sensitivity; high or cleft palate; hearing problems; dental abnormalities; bone abnormalities in the hands and feet; and/or speech difficulties. Affected children often experience delayed development of motor skills (such as crawling and walking), although most eventually acquire these skills. Moebius syndrome is caused by the absence or underdevelopment of the 6th and 7th cranial nerves, which control eye movement and facial expression. Other cranial nerves may also be affected. There is no cure for Moebius syndrome, but proper care and treatment give many individuals a normal life expectancy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004102-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Moebius syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Moebius syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Moebius syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the voice 90% Mask-like facies 90% Open mouth 90% Ophthalmoparesis 90% Ptosis 90% Strabismus 90% Delayed speech and language development 55% Aplasia of the pectoralis major muscle 50% Brachydactyly syndrome 50% Feeding difficulties in infancy 50% Muscular hypotonia 50% Opacification of the corneal stroma 50% Talipes 50% Hypertelorism 25% Bifid uvula 11% Abnormality of the sense of smell 7.5% Abnormality of the ulna 7.5% Absent hand 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the radius 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the thumb 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the tongue 7.5% Autism 7.5% Blepharitis 7.5% Breast aplasia 7.5% Cafe-au-lait spot 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 7.5% Epicanthus 7.5% Finger syndactyly 7.5% Hearing impairment 7.5% Microdontia 7.5% Reduced number of teeth 7.5% Skeletal muscle atrophy 7.5% Visual impairment 7.5% Abnormality of pelvic girdle bone morphology - Abnormality of the nail - Abnormality of the nasopharynx - Abnormality of the pinna - Abnormality of the posterior cranial fossa - Aplasia/Hypoplasia involving the metacarpal bones - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Camptodactyly - Clinodactyly - Clumsiness - Congenital fibrosis of extraocular muscles - Decreased testicular size - Depressed nasal bridge - Dysarthria - Dysdiadochokinesis - Dysphagia - Esotropia - Exotropia - Facial diplegia - Gait disturbance - High palate - Hypogonadotrophic hypogonadism - Hypoplasia of the brainstem - Infantile muscular hypotonia - Intellectual disability, mild - Lower limb undergrowth - Micropenis - Microphthalmia - Motor delay - Pes planus - Phenotypic variability - Poor coordination - Radial deviation of finger - Respiratory difficulties - Short neck - Short phalanx of finger - Split hand - Sporadic - Syndactyly - Talipes equinovarus - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004102-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Moebius syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is Moebius syndrome inherited? Most cases of Moebius syndrome are not inherited and occur as isolated cases in individuals with no history of the condition in their family (sporadically). A small percentage of cases of Moebius syndrome have been familial (occurring in more than one individual in a family), but there has not been a consistent pattern of inheritance among all affected families. In some families the pattern has been suggestive of autosomal dominant inheritance, while in other families it has been suggestive of autosomal recessive or X-linked recessive inheritance.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
