<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004199" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7108/multiple-myeloma">
<Focus>Multiple myeloma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0026764</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Plasma cell myeloma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Kahler disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Myelomatosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Plasma cell dyscrasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Myeloma - multiple</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004199-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Multiple myeloma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Multiple myeloma is a form of cancer that occurs due to abnormal and uncontrolled growth of plasma cells in the bone marrow. Some people with multiple myeloma, especially those with early stages of the condition, have no concerning signs or symptoms. When present, the most common symptom is anemia, which can be associated with fatigue and shortness of breath. Other features of the condition may include multiple infections; abnormal bleeding; bone pain; weak and/or easily broken bones; and numbness and/or weakness of the arms and legs. The exact underlying cause of multiple myeloma is currently unknown. Factors that are associated with an increased risk of developing multiple myeloma include increasing age, male sex, African American race, radiation exposure, a family history of the condition, obesity, and/or a personal history of monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance (MGUS). Treatment varies based on many factors, but may include one or more of the following interventions: chemotherapy, corticosteroid medications, targeted therapy, stem cell transplant, biological therapy, radiation therapy, surgery and/or watchful waiting.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004199-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Multiple myeloma ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Multiple myeloma? In some cases, multiple myeloma is not associated with any signs and symptoms. When present, the most common symptom is anemia (low red blood cell count), which can be associated with fatigue, shortness of breath, and dizziness. Other features of the condition may include: Bone pain Nausea Constipation Loss of appetite Frequent infections Weight loss Excessive thirst Weakness and/or numbness in the arms and legs Confusion Abnormal bleeding Weak bones that may break easily Difficulty breathing The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Multiple myeloma. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Multiple myeloma - Somatic mutation - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004199-3" qtype="causes">What causes Multiple myeloma ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes multiple myeloma? Although the exact underlying cause of multiple myeloma is poorly understood, the specific symptoms of the condition result from abnormal and excessive growth of plasma cells in the bone marrow. Plasma cells help the body fight infection by producing proteins called antibodies. In people with multiple myeloma, excess plasma cells form tumors in the bone, causing bones to become weak and easily broken. The abnormal growth of plasma cells also makes it more difficult for the bone marrow to make healthy blood cells and platelets. The plasma cells produced in multiple myeloma produce abnormal antibodies that the immune system is unable to use. These abnormal antibodies build up in the body and cause a variety of problems. Factors that are associated with an increased risk of developing multiple myeloma include increasing age, male sex, African American race, radiation exposure, a family history of the condition, obesity, and/or a personal history of monoclonal gammopathy of undetermined significance (MGUS).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004199-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Multiple myeloma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is multiple myeloma diagnosed? A diagnosis of multiple myeloma may be suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. Additional testing can then be ordered to confirm the diagnosis. This may include: Specialized blood tests including immunoglobulin studies, complete blood count with differential, and blood chemistry studies Urine tests such as immunoglobulin studies and a twenty-four-hour urine test Bone marrow aspiration and biopsy Imaging studies such as an X-ray of the bones (skeletal bone survey), MRI, CT scan, and/or PET scan The American Cancer Society offers more information regarding the diagnosis of multiple myeloma, including a summary of the many tests that may be recommended. Please click on the link to access this resource. Some affected people may have no suspicious signs or symptoms of multiple myeloma, especially in the early stages of the condition. In these cases, multiple myeloma is sometimes diagnosed by chance when a blood test or urine test is ordered to investigate another condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004199-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Multiple myeloma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might multiple myeloma be treated? The treatment of multiple myeloma varies based on many factors including the age and general health of the affected person; the associated signs and symptoms; and the severity of the condition. In general, one or more of the following interventions may be used to treat multiple myeloma: Chemotherapy Corticosteroid medications Targeted therapy Stem cell transplant Biological therapy Radiation therapy Surgery Watchful waiting The National Cancer Institute offers information regarding the management of multiple myeloma, including more specific information regarding the treatments outlined above. Please click on the link to access this resource.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
