<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004872" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9420/pierson-syndrome">
<Focus>Pierson syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1836876</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Microcoria - congenital nephrotic syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Microcoria - congenital nephrosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004872-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pierson syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pierson syndrome is a very rare condition that mainly affects the kidneys and eyes. Signs and symptoms include congenital nephrotic syndrome and distinct ocular (eye) abnormalities, including microcoria (small pupils that are not responsive to light). Most affected children have early-onset, chronic renal failure; neurodevelopmental problems; and blindness. Hypotonia (poor muscle tone) and movement disorders have also been reported. Pierson syndrome is caused by changes (mutations) in the LAMB2 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. The long-term outlook is poor; affected infants may not survive past the first weeks or months of life.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004872-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pierson syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Pierson syndrome? The features and severity of Pierson syndrome can vary among affected people. Affected infants are usually born with serious and progressive kidney disease due to congenital nephrotic syndrome, although some do not have kidney failure until adulthood. Most require a renal transplant for end-stage kidney disease within the first decade of life. Ocular (eye) abnormalities are another common feature of Pierson syndrome. Most affected infants are born with abnormally small pupils (microcoria). Other ocular abnormalities may include cataracts, glaucoma, retinal detachments, and blindness. Those that survive past infancy typically have neurological disabilities and developmental delays. Many children with Pierson syndrome don&apos;t achieve normal milestones such as sitting, standing, and talking. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Pierson syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of movement 90% Cataract 90% EEG abnormality 90% Hematuria 90% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 90% Hypertension 90% Muscular hypotonia 90% Nephrotic syndrome 90% Nystagmus 90% Proteinuria 90% Hypoplasia of penis 50% Areflexia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Blindness - Diffuse mesangial sclerosis - Edema - Hypoplasia of the ciliary body - Hypoplasia of the iris - Hypoproteinemia - Neonatal onset - Posterior lenticonus - Stage 5 chronic kidney disease - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004872-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Pierson syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Pierson syndrome inherited? Pierson syndrome is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. This means that to be affected, a person must have a mutation in both copies of the responsible gene in each cell. Affected people inherit one mutated copy of the gene from each parent, who is referred to as a carrier. Carriers of an autosomal recessive condition typically do not have any signs or symptoms (they are unaffected). When 2 carriers of an autosomal recessive condition have children, each child has a: 25% (1 in 4) chance to be affected 50% (1 in 2) chance to be an unaffected carrier like each parent 25% chance to be unaffected and not be a carrier</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004872-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Pierson syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is genetic testing available for Pierson syndrome? Yes. The Genetic Testing Registry (GTR) provides information about the genetic tests available for Pierson syndrome. The intended audience for the GTR is health care providers and researchers. Patients and consumers with specific questions about a genetic test should contact a health care provider or a genetics professional. According to the GTR, genetic testing for Pierson syndrome may be available for diagnosis in a person suspected of having the condition, carrier testing, and prenatal testing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
