<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004307" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7160/nail-patella-syndrome">
<Focus>Nail-patella syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0027341</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>NPS 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Onychoosteodysplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Turner-Kieser syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fong disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Osteo-Onychodysplasia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004307-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Nail-patella syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nail-patella syndrome is an inherited condition characterized by abnormalities of the nails, knees, elbows, and pelvis. Some affected people may also experience problems in other areas of the body such as the kidneys and eyes. The severity of the condition and the associated signs and symptoms can vary significantly from person to person, even among members of the same family. Nail-patella syndrome is caused by changes (mutations) in the LMX1B gene and is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Treatment is supportive and based on the signs and symptoms present in each person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004307-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Nail-patella syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Nail-patella syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Nail-patella syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of pelvic girdle bone morphology 90% Abnormality of the fingernails 90% Anonychia 90% Cubitus valgus 90% Exostoses 90% Hypoplastic toenails 90% Joint hypermobility 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Patellar aplasia 90% Skeletal dysplasia 90% Sprengel anomaly 90% Joint dislocation 50% Joint swelling 50% Nephrotic syndrome 50% Osteoarthritis 50% Proteinuria 50% Cataract 7.5% Glaucoma 7.5% Glomerulopathy 7.5% Hearing impairment 7.5% Hematuria 7.5% Hypertension 7.5% Nephropathy 7.5% Renal insufficiency 7.5% Vasculitis 7.5% Absence of pectoralis minor muscle - Absent distal interphalangeal creases - Antecubital pterygium - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Biceps aplasia - Cleft palate - Cleft upper lip - Clinodactyly of the 5th finger - Concave nail - Disproportionate prominence of the femoral medial condyle - Elongated radius - Glenoid fossa hypoplasia - Glomerulonephritis - Hypoplasia of first ribs - Hypoplastic radial head - Iliac horns - Keratoconus - Lester&apos;s sign - Limited elbow extension - Lumbar hyperlordosis - Microcornea - Microphakia - Patellar dislocation - Pectus excavatum - Pes planus - Ptosis - Quadriceps aplasia - Ridged nail - Scoliosis - Sensorineural hearing impairment - Short stature - Spina bifida - Talipes equinovarus - Thickening of the lateral border of the scapula - Triceps aplasia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
