<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004265" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7144/myoclonic-epilepsy-with-ragged-red-fibers">
<Focus>Myoclonic epilepsy with ragged red fibers</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0014544</CUI>
			<CUI>C0162672</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Merrf syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MERRF</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Myoclonic epilepsy associated with ragged red fibers</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fukuhara syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Myoencephalopathy ragged-red fiber disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004265-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Myoclonic epilepsy with ragged red fibers ?</Question>
			<Answer>Myoclonic epilepsy with ragged red fibers (MERRF) is a multisystem disorder characterized by myoclonus, which is often the first symptom, followed by generalized epilepsy, ataxia, weakness, and dementia. Symptoms usually first appear in childhood or adolescence after normal early development. The features of MERRF vary widely from individual to individual, even within families. Other common findings include hearing loss, short stature, optic atrophy, and cardiomyopathy with Wolff-Parkinson-White (WPW) syndrome. The diagnosis is based on clinical features and a muscle biopsy finding of ragged red fibers (RRF). In over 80% of cases, MERRF is caused by mutations in the mitochondrial gene called MT-TK. Several other mitochondrial genes have also been reported to cause MERRF, but many of the individuals with mutations in these other genes have additional signs and symptoms. Seizures associated with MERRF are generally treated with conventional anticonvulsant therapy.  Coenzyme Q10 and L-carnitine are often used with the hope of improving mitochondrial function.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004265-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Myoclonic epilepsy with ragged red fibers ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Myoclonic epilepsy with ragged red fibers? Because muscle cells and nerve cells have especially high energy needs, muscular and neurological problems are common features of diseases that affect the mitochondria.  MERRF is a progressive multi-system syndrome with symptoms that begin during childhood, but onset may occur in adulthood. The rate of progression varies widely. Onset and extent of symptoms can differ widely from individual to individual and among affected siblings. The classic features of MERRF include: Myoclonus (brief, sudden, twitching muscle spasms)  the most characteristic symptom Epileptic seizures Ataxia (impaired coordination) Ragged-red fibers (a characteristic microscopic abnormality observed in muscle biopsy of patients with MERRF and other mitochondrial disorders) Additional symptoms may include: hearing loss, lactic acidosis (elevated lactic acid level in the blood), short stature, exercise intolerance, dementia, cardiac defects, eye abnormalities, and speech impairment. However, the exact symptoms aren&apos;t the same for everyone, because a person with mitochondrial disease can have a unique mixture of healthy and non-working mitochondria, with a unique distribution in the body. Despite their many potential effects, mitochondrial diseases sometimes cause little disability. Sometimes, a person has enough healthy mitochondria to compensate for the defective ones. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Myoclonic epilepsy with ragged red fibers. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of movement 90% EMG abnormality 90% Incoordination 90% Multiple lipomas 90% Myopathy 90% Sensorineural hearing impairment 90% Cognitive impairment 50% Short stature 50% Optic atrophy 7.5% Ataxia - Generalized myoclonic seizures - Increased serum lactate - Increased serum pyruvate - Mitochondrial inheritance - Muscle weakness - Myoclonus - Ragged-red muscle fibers - Seizures - Spasticity - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004265-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Myoclonic epilepsy with ragged red fibers inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is myoclonic epilepsy associated with ragged red fibers genetic? If so, how is it inherited? MERRF is caused by mutations in the mitochondrial DNA and is transmitted by maternal inheritance. It is called maternal inheritance because a child inherits the great majority of their mitochondria from their mother through the egg.   The Centre for Genetics Education provides a detail description of maternal inheritance.  The mother of an individual with MERRF usually has a mitochondrial mutation and may or may not have symptoms.  Or, an individual with MERRF may have a mitochondrial mutation that just occurred in them, called a de novo mutation.  If the mother has the mitochondrial mutation, all of her children will inherit the mutation and may or may not have symptoms.  All of her daughters children will also inherit the mitochondrial mutation.  Her son&apos;s children are not at risk of inheriting the mutation.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
