<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004827" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10743/persistent-genital-arousal-disorder">
<Focus>Persistent genital arousal disorder</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0012634</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Persistent genital arousal</Synonym>
		<Synonym>PGAD</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004827-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Persistent genital arousal disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Persistent genital arousal disorder (PGAD) in men may be considered as the condition of priapism and unwanted ejaculatory fluids being released without any sexual interest. In women there is still no consensus about a formal definition, but some of the experts propose that in women it should be defined as a rare, unwanted, and intrusive sexual dysfunction associated with excessive and unremitting genital arousal and engorgement in the absence of sexual interest. The persistent genital arousal usually does not resolve with orgasm and causes personal distress. Features include excessive excitement or excessive genital (lubrication, swelling, and engorgement) or other somatic responses. Causes may be neurological (central or peripheral involving the pudendal nerve), related to medication, vascular, hormonal, psychological or others.  Diagnosis of the cause is essential for an adequate patient management. The treatment may include avoiding offending medications, using medications that stabilize nerve transmission and/or effect mood, local topical anesthetic agents, ice and hormonal replacement. More recently PGAD has being described as one component of a broader Restless Genital Syndrome if the PGAD was also associated with urinary frequency/urgency and restless leg syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
