<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004315" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/267/nasodigitoacoustic-syndrome">
<Focus>Nasodigitoacoustic syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1850627</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Keipert Syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004315-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Nasodigitoacoustic syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Nasodigitoacoustic syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Nasodigitoacoustic syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of thumb phalanx 90% Anonychia 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the distal phalanges of the toes 90% Broad forehead 90% Hypertelorism 90% Preaxial foot polydactyly 90% Prominent nasal bridge 90% Sensorineural hearing impairment 90% Short distal phalanx of finger 90% Short hallux 90% Abnormality of the voice 50% Aplastic/hypoplastic toenail 50% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 50% Epicanthus 50% Exaggerated cupid&apos;s bow 50% Macrocephaly 50% Ptosis 50% Tented upper lip vermilion 50% Behavioral abnormality 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Short stature 7.5% Abnormality of the nail - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Broad distal phalanx of finger - Broad hallux - Broad thumb - Depressed nasal bridge - Enlarged epiphyses - Frontal bossing - High palate - Hoarse voice - Narrow palate - Prominent forehead - Pulmonic stenosis - Rounded epiphyses - Short 3rd metacarpal - Short phalanx of finger - Short toe - Thick upper lip vermilion - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
