<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004195" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10867/multiple-familial-trichoepithelioma">
<Focus>Multiple familial trichoepithelioma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1275122</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Epithelioma adenoides cysticum</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary multiple benign cystic epithelioma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Brooke-Fordyce trichoepitheliomas</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Trichoepithelioma multiple familial</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Familial multiple trichoepithelioma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Brooke-Spiegler syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Multiple familial trichoepithelioma 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Multiple familial trichoepithelioma 2</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004195-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Multiple familial trichoepithelioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Multiple familial trichoepithelioma is a rare condition characterized by multiple smooth, round, firm, skin-colored tumors (trichoepitheliomas) that usually occur on the face, but may also occur on the scalp, neck, and trunk. The tumors are derived from immature hair follicles. They usually first develop during childhood or adolescence and may grow larger and increase in number over time. The condition can be caused by alterations (mutations) in the CYLD gene or by mutations in other genes which are still unknown. The condition may be divided in two subtypes, multiple familial trichoepithelioma type 1 and multiple familial trichoepithelioma type 2.  Susceptibility to multiple familial trichoepithelioma is inherited in an autosomal dominant fashion, which means one copy of the altered gene in each cell increases the risk of developing this condition. However, a second, non-inherited mutation is required for development of skin appendage tumors in this disorder.Treatment often involves surgery to remove a single lesion and cryosurgery or laser surgery for multiple ones.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004195-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Multiple familial trichoepithelioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Multiple familial trichoepithelioma? People with multiple familial trichoepithelioma typically develop large large numbers of smooth, round, firm skin-colored tumors called trichoepitheliomas, which arise from hair follicles. These benign (noncancerous) tumors may occasionally transform into a type of skin cancer called basal cell carcinoma. Occasionally, other types of tumors, including growths called spiradenomas (which originate in sweat glands) and cylindromas (which likely originate in hair follicles) also develop. Affected individuals are also at-risk to develop tumors in other tissues, particularly benign tumors of the salivary glands. The tumors in multiple familial trichoepithelioma typically first appear during childhood or adolescence, and appear most often around the nose, forehead, upper lip, and occasionally scalp, neck, and upper trunk. They may grow larger and increase in number over time. In rare cases, the tumors may get in the way of the eyes, ears, nose, or mouth and affect vision or hearing. The growths can be disfiguring and may contribute to depression or other psychological problems. For reasons that remain unknown, females are often more severely affected than males.  The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Multiple familial trichoepithelioma. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Neoplasm of the skin 90% Telangiectasia of the skin 50% Basal cell carcinoma 5% Adult onset - Autosomal dominant inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004195-3" qtype="causes">What causes Multiple familial trichoepithelioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes multiple familial trichoepithelioma? Multiple familial trichoepithelioma is thought to be inherited in an autosomal dominant fashion with reduced penetrance. Autosomal dominant means that a single mutation in one copy of a gene is sufficient to cause the condition. Reduced penetrance means that not everyone with the gene mutation will develop symptoms of the condition. Multiple familial trichoepithelioma can be caused by mutations in the CYLD gene which is found on chromosome 16 or by a mutation on a gene on chromsome 9 that has yet to be identified.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004195-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Multiple familial trichoepithelioma inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is multiple familial trichoepithelioma inherited? Susceptibility to multiple familial trichoepithelioma has an autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance. This means that one copy of the altered gene in each cell increases the risk that a person will develop the condition. However, a second, non-inherited mutation is needed for development of the skin tumors characteristic of this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004195-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Multiple familial trichoepithelioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is multiple familial trichoepithelioma diagnosed? Diagnosis of multiple familial trichoepithelioma is made based upon the clinical symptoms in the patient, the patients family history, and the appearance of the trichoepithelioma cells under a microscope (histology). Multiple familial trichoepithelioma must be distinguished from basal cell carcinoma (cancerous tumor) and other rare genetic syndromes such as Cowden syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004195-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Multiple familial trichoepithelioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might multiple familial trichoepithelioma be treated? Several therapies have been used to treat multiple trichoepitheliomas, with variable results.  A single trichoepithelioma may be treated with surgery.  Cryosurgery or laser surgery may be used to remove multiple trichoepitheliomas.  Imiquimod cream has also been used as a treatment for trichoepitheliomas, with some improvement in symptoms.  Other treatments have included dermabrasion, photodynamic therapy, and other medications.  However, in most cases, multiple trichoepitheliomas eventually regrow following treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
