<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004097" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7051/mixed-connective-tissue-disease">
<Focus>Mixed connective tissue disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0026272</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>MCTD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Sharp syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Secondary glomerular disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004097-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Mixed connective tissue disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Mixed connective tissue disease (MCTD) is a rare autoimmune disorder that is characterized by features commonly seen in three different connective tissue disorders: systemic lupus erythematosus, scleroderma, and polymyositis. Some affected people may also have symptoms of rheumatoid arthritis. Although MCTD can affect people of all ages, it appears to be most common in women under age 30. Signs and symptoms vary but may include Raynaud&apos;s phenomenon; arthritis; heart, lung and skin abnormalities; kidney disease; muscle weakness, and dysfunction of the esophagus. The cause of MCTD is currently unknown. There is no cure but certain medications such as nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), corticosteroids and immunosuppresive drugs may help manage the symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004097-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Mixed connective tissue disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Mixed connective tissue disease? People with mixed connective tissue disease (MCTD) have symptoms that overlap with several connective tissue disorders, including systemic lupus erythematosus, polymyositis, scleroderma, and rheumatoid arthritis. A condition called Raynaud&apos;s phenomenon sometimes occurs months or years before other symptoms of MCTD develop. Most people with MCTD have pain in multiple joints, and/or inflammation of joints (arthritis). Muscle weakness, fevers, and fatigue are also common. Other signs and symptoms may include: Accumulation of fluid in the tissue of the hands that causes puffiness and swelling (edema) Skin findings including lupus-like rashes (including reddish brown patches), reddish patches over the knuckles, violet coloring of the eyelids, loss of hair (alopecia), and dilation of small blood vessels around the fingernails (periungual telangiectasia) Dysfunction of the esophagus (hypomotility) Abnormalities in lung function which may lead to breathing difficulties, and/or pulmonary hypertension Heart involvement (less common in MCTD than lung problems) including pericarditis, myocarditis, and aortic insufficiency Kidney disease Neurologic abnormalities (in about 10 percent of people with MCTD) such as organic brain syndrome; blood vessel narrowing causing &quot;vascular&quot; headaches; a mild form of meningitis; seizures; blockage of a cerebral vessel (cerebral thrombosis) or bleeding; and/or various sensory disturbances in multiple areas of the body (multiple peripheral neuropathies) Anemia and leukopenia (in 30 to 40 percent of cases) Lymphadenopathy, enlargement of the spleen (splenomegaly), enlargement of the liver (hepatomegaly), and/or intestinal involvement in some cases The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Mixed connective tissue disease. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the gastric mucosa 90% Acrocyanosis 90% Arthritis 90% Atypical scarring of skin 90% Autoimmunity 90% Chest pain 90% Myalgia 90% Nausea and vomiting 90% Pulmonary fibrosis 90% Respiratory insufficiency 90% Skin rash 90% Abnormality of temperature regulation 50% Abnormality of the pleura 50% Arthralgia 50% Behavioral abnormality 50% Joint swelling 50% Keratoconjunctivitis sicca 50% Myositis 50% Xerostomia 50% Abnormal tendon morphology 7.5% Abnormality of coagulation 7.5% Abnormality of the myocardium 7.5% Abnormality of the pericardium 7.5% Alopecia 7.5% Aseptic necrosis 7.5% Gastrointestinal hemorrhage 7.5% Hemolytic anemia 7.5% Hepatomegaly 7.5% Leukopenia 7.5% Limitation of joint mobility 7.5% Mediastinal lymphadenopathy 7.5% Meningitis 7.5% Nephropathy 7.5% Osteolysis 7.5% Peripheral neuropathy 7.5% Pulmonary hypertension 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Splenomegaly 7.5% Subcutaneous hemorrhage 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004097-3" qtype="causes">What causes Mixed connective tissue disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes mixed connective tissue disease? The exact underlying cause of mixed connective tissue disease (MCTD) is currently unknown. It is an autoimmune disorder, which means the immune system mistakes normal, healthy cells for those that that body should &quot;fight off.&quot; There are ongoing studies exploring how immune system dysfunction may be involved in the development of this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004097-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Mixed connective tissue disease inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is mixed connective tissue disease inherited? The role of genetics in the onset of mixed connective tissue disease (MCTD) is still unclear. Some people with MCTD have family members who are also affected by the condition. This suggests that in some cases, an inherited predisposition may contribute to the development of MCTD. People with an inherited or genetic predisposition have an increased risk of developing a certain condition due to their genes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004097-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Mixed connective tissue disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is mixed connective tissue disease diagnosed? Mixed connective tissue disease (MCTD) is often suspected after a physical examination reveals signs and symptoms associated with the condition. The diagnosis is supported by a blood test that shows high levels of antibodies associated with MCTD.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004097-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Mixed connective tissue disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might mixed connective tissue disease be treated? There is currently no cure for mixed connective tissue disease (MCTD). However, treatments can help manage symptoms of the condition. For example, medications such as over-the-counter or prescription nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs may help with inflammation and pain of the muscles or joints. Glucocorticoids may be recommended in certain situations, such as during disease flares or when complications arise (e.g., aseptic meningitis, myositis, pleurisy, pericarditis, and myocarditis). Some people with MCTD require long term use of immunosuppressant medications. Additional medications may be prescribed based on the signs and symptoms present in each person. For example, if a person with MCTD has developed symptoms similar to those of lupus, medications typically prescribed for people with lupus may be recommended. For additional information about the treatment of MCTD, visit the Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research Web site.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
