<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004435" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9736/nonbullous-congenital-ichthyosiform-erythroderma">
<Focus>Nonbullous congenital ichthyosiform erythroderma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0079154</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Ichthyosiform erythroderma, congenital, nonbullous, 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>NCIE</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ichthyosiform erythroderma, Brocq congenital, nonbullous form</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital ichthyosiform erythroderma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>CIE</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004435-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Nonbullous congenital ichthyosiform erythroderma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nonbullous congenital ichthyosiform erythroderma (NBCIE) is a specific type of ichthyosis mainly affecting the skin. Most infants with NBCIE are born with a tight, shiny covering on their skin, called a collodion membrane, which is typically shed within a few weeks. Other signs and symptoms include redness of the skin (erythroderma); fine, white scales on the skin; and thickening of the skin on the palms and soles of feet (palmoplantar keratoderma). Some people with NBCIE also have outward turning eyelids (ectropion); outward turning lips (eclabium); and nails that do not grow normally (nail dystrophy). NBCIE may be caused by mutations in any one of at least three genes: ALOX12B, ALOXE3 or NIPAL4. In some people with NBCIE, the cause of the disorder is unknown.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004435-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Nonbullous congenital ichthyosiform erythroderma ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Nonbullous congenital ichthyosiform erythroderma? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Nonbullous congenital ichthyosiform erythroderma. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Hypohidrosis 90% Ectropion 5% Short finger 5% Short toe 5% Small nail 5% Thin nail 5% Abnormality of the hair - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Congenital ichthyosiform erythroderma - Congenital nonbullous ichthyosiform erythroderma - External genital hypoplasia - Growth delay - Intellectual disability - Palmoplantar keratoderma - Paralysis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004435-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Nonbullous congenital ichthyosiform erythroderma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might nonbullous congenital ichthyosiform erythroderma be treated? There is currently no cure for nonbullous congenital ichthyosiform erythroderma (NBCIE). Treatment generally focuses on managing the specific signs and symptoms each individual has. For newborns, the most important goals are to provide a moist environment in an isolette, and to prevent and treat infections. Petrolatum-based creams and ointments are typically used to keep the skin soft and hydrated. As children age, keratolytic agents (agents that help the skin loosen and shed) such as alpha-hydroxy acid or urea preparations can be used to promote the peeling and thinning of the outer layer of the skin. For individuals with severe skin involvement, oral retinoid therapy may be recommended. However, because this is known to cause abnormalities in a developing fetus, it should be used with caution in women of child-bearing age. In general, any agents that irritate the skin should be avoided. Ectropion (turning out of the eyelid) can cause dryness of the cornea (especially at night), so artificial tears or prescription ointments may be used to keep the cornea moist. ClinicalTrials.gov provides access to information on clinical studies (including therapies) for different types of ichthyosis. To view a list of the studies currently listed, click here.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
