<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004581" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8391/ornithine-transcarbamylase-deficiency">
<Focus>Ornithine transcarbamylase deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0268542</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Ornithine carbamoyltransferase deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>OTC deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>OTCD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Urea cycle disorders</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004581-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ornithine transcarbamylase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ornithine transcarbamylase (OTC) deficiency is an inherited disorder that causes ammonia to accumulate in the blood. Ammonia, which is formed when proteins are broken down in the body, is toxic if the levels become too high. The nervous system is especially sensitive to the effects of excess ammonia. The signs and symptoms of OTC deficiency may include development delay, intellectual disability and liver problems. It is caused by changes (mutations) in the OTC gene. OTC deficiency is inherited as an X-linked condition. Treatment consists of not eating protein, taking certain medications and having hemodialysis, if needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004581-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ornithine transcarbamylase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Ornithine transcarbamylase deficiency? Ornithine transcarbamylase (OTC) deficiency often becomes evident in the first few days of life. An infant with OTC deficiency may be lacking in energy (lethargic) or unwilling to eat, and have a poorly-controlled breathing rate or body temperature. Some babies with this disorder may experience seizures or unusual body movements, or go into a coma. Complications from OTC deficiency may include developmental delay and intellectual disability. Progressive liver damage, skin lesions, and brittle hair may also be seen. In some affected individuals, signs and symptoms of OTC deficiency may be less severe, and may not appear until later in life. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Ornithine transcarbamylase deficiency. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aminoaciduria 90% Hepatic failure 90% Hyperammonemia 90% Hypoglycemia 90% Pyloric stenosis 90% Splenomegaly 90% Stroke 5% Cerebral edema - Coma - Episodic ammonia intoxication - Episodic ataxia - Failure to thrive - Hyperglutaminemia - Intellectual disability - Irritability - Lethargy - Low plasma citrulline - Protein avoidance - Respiratory alkalosis - Seizures - Vomiting - X-linked recessive inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004581-3" qtype="causes">What causes Ornithine transcarbamylase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes ornithine transcarbamylase (OTC) deficiency? Ornithine transcarbamylase (OTC) deficiency is caused by mutations in the OTC gene. OTC deficiency belongs to a class of genetic diseases called urea cycle disorders. The urea cycle is a sequence of reactions that occurs in liver cells. It processes excess nitrogen, generated when protein is used by the body, to make a compound called urea that is excreted by the kidneys. In OTC deficiency, the enzyme that starts a specific reaction within the urea cycle is damaged or missing. The urea cycle cannot proceed normally, and nitrogen accumulates in the bloodstream in the form of ammonia. Ammonia is especially damaging to the nervous system, so OTC deficiency causes neurological problems as well as eventual damage to the liver.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004581-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Ornithine transcarbamylase deficiency inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is ornithine transcarbamylase (OTC) deficiency inherited? Ornithine transcarbamylase (OTC) deficiency is an X-linked disorder. A condition is considered X-linked if the mutated gene that causes the disorder is located on the X chromosome, one of the two sex chromosomes. A characteristic of X-linked inheritance is that fathers cannot pass X-linked traits to their sons. In males (who have only one X chromosome), one altered copy of the gene in each cell is sufficient to cause the condition. In females (who have two X chromosomes), mutations in both copies of the gene will cause the disorder. Some females with only one altered copy of the OTC gene also show signs and symptoms of OTC deficiency.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
