<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004467" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7225/notalgia-paresthetica">
<Focus>Notalgia paresthetica</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0457010</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004467-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Notalgia paresthetica ?</Question>
			<Answer>Notalgia paresthetica is a common chronic, localized itch, that usually affects patches of skin on the upper back. Occasionally be more widespread and involve other parts of the back, the shoulders and upper chest. People feel both the sensation of an itch and paresthesia (a sensation of tingling, pricking, or numbness of the skin).  There are no signs on the skin except for signs of chronic scratching and rubbing.  Amyloid deposits (a collection of a specific type of protein) may be found in skin biopsies, but this is thought to be a secondary event.  The cause of the itch in notalgia paresthetica may be due to the compression of spinal nerves by bones or muscles as the nerves emerge through the vertebrae to the back muscles.  Sometimes degenerative changes in the area of the vertebrae that innervate the affected back muscles can be seen, but not always.  Symptoms of notalgia paresthetica may respond to topical capsaicin treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004467-2" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Notalgia paresthetica ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might notalgia paresthetica be treated? While this condition may be difficult to treat, typical neuralgia therapies are often employed with moderate success. Effective measures may include:  Cooling lotions as required (camphor and menthol) Capsaicin cream - this depletes nerve endings of their chemical transmitters Local anaesthetic creams Amitriptyline tablets at night Transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (TENS) Gabapentin Oxcarbazepine Botulinum toxin Phototherapy Exercise Additional information about treatment of notalgia paresthetica can be accessed by clicking here. You can find relevant journal articles on treatment of notalgia paresthetica through a service called PubMed, a searchable database of medical literature. Information on finding an article and its title, authors, and publishing details is listed here. Some articles are available as a complete document, while information on other studies is available as a summary abstract. To obtain the full article, contact a medical/university library (or your local library for interlibrary loan), or order it online using the following link. Using &apos;notalgia paresthetica AND treatment&apos; as your search term should locate 10 articles. Click here to view a search. http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?db=PubMed</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
