<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004038" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3640/microgastria-limb-reduction-defect">
<Focus>Microgastria limb reduction defect</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1834929</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Microgastria-limb reduction defects association</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MLRD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital microgastria and limb reduction defects</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004038-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Microgastria limb reduction defect ?</Question>
			<Answer>Microgastria limb reduction defect is a rare disorder with less than 60 previously reported cases. Children born with this condition have a small stomach (microgastria) and limb abnormalities. Symptoms may include vomiting, aspiration pneumonia and growth problems. Abnormalities involving the heart, lungs, kidney and gastrointestinal system are also symptoms of this condition. This condition is caused by an error that occurs during the development of the embryo. Treatment may involve reconstructive surgery (Hunt-Lawrence pouch) to help improve the child&apos;s feeding abilities.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004038-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Microgastria limb reduction defect ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Microgastria limb reduction defect? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Microgastria limb reduction defect. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the spleen 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the radius 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the thumb 90% Microgastria 90% Abnormality of the humerus 50% Abnormality of the metacarpal bones 50% Abnormality of the ulna 50% Congenital muscular torticollis 50% Frontal bossing 50% Multicystic kidney dysplasia 50% Plagiocephaly 50% Abnormal localization of kidney 7.5% Abnormal lung lobation 7.5% Abnormality of neuronal migration 7.5% Abnormality of the clavicle 7.5% Absent hand 7.5% Amelia 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia affecting the eye 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 7.5% Atria septal defect 7.5% Elbow dislocation 7.5% Hepatomegaly 7.5% Holoprosencephaly 7.5% Intestinal malrotation 7.5% Phocomelia 7.5% Renal hypoplasia/aplasia 7.5% Split hand 7.5% Tracheoesophageal fistula 7.5% Truncus arteriosus 7.5% Urogenital fistula 7.5% Absent gallbladder - Absent thumb - Aganglionic megacolon - Agenesis of corpus callosum - Anophthalmia - Arrhinencephaly - Asplenia - Bicornuate uterus - Biliary tract abnormality - Cryptorchidism - Cystic renal dysplasia - Failure to thrive - Fusion of the left and right thalami - Gastroesophageal reflux - Horseshoe kidney - Hypoplasia of the radius - Hypoplasia of the ulna - Oligodactyly (hands) - Pelvic kidney - Polymicrogyria - Secundum atrial septal defect - Sporadic - Type I truncus arteriosus - Unilateral renal agenesis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
