<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004550" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4098/opsismodysplasia">
<Focus>Opsismodysplasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0432219</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004550-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Opsismodysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Opsismodysplasia is a rare skeletal dysplasia characterized by congenital short stature and characteristic craniofacial abnormalities. Clinical signs observed at birth include short limbs, small hands and feet, relative macrocephaly with a large anterior fontanel (the space between the front bones of the skull), and characteristic craniofacial abnormalities including a prominent brow, depressed nasal bridge, a small anteverted nose, and a relatively long philtrum. Children with opsismodysplasia are at an increased risk for respiratory infections and respiratory failure. This condition is caused by mutations in the INPPL1 the gene. It is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004550-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Opsismodysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Opsismodysplasia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Opsismodysplasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 90% Abnormal vertebral ossification 90% Abnormality of epiphysis morphology 90% Abnormality of pelvic girdle bone morphology 90% Abnormality of the fontanelles or cranial sutures 90% Abnormality of the metaphyses 90% Brachydactyly syndrome 90% Delayed skeletal maturation 90% Depressed nasal bridge 90% Frontal bossing 90% Limb undergrowth 90% Macrocephaly 90% Respiratory insufficiency 90% Short nose 90% Tapered finger 90% Muscular hypotonia 50% Recurrent respiratory infections 50% Abnormality of thumb phalanx 7.5% Blue sclerae 7.5% Hepatomegaly 7.5% Limitation of joint mobility 7.5% Narrow chest 7.5% Pectus excavatum 7.5% Splenomegaly 7.5% Hypophosphatemia 5% Renal phosphate wasting 5% Anterior rib cupping - Anteverted nares - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Bell-shaped thorax - Disproportionate short-limb short stature - Edema - Flat acetabular roof - Hypertelorism - Hypoplastic ischia - Hypoplastic pubic bone - Hypoplastic vertebral bodies - Large fontanelles - Long philtrum - Metaphyseal cupping - Polyhydramnios - Posterior rib cupping - Protuberant abdomen - Rhizomelia - Severe platyspondyly - Short foot - Short long bone - Short neck - Short palm - Squared iliac bones - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
