<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004750" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4228/parsonage-turner-syndrome">
<Focus>Parsonage Turner syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0041408</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Acute brachial neuritis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Acute brachial neuritis syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Acute brachial radiculitis syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Acute shoulder neuritis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Neuralgic amyotrophy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004750-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Parsonage Turner syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Parsonage Turner syndrome is characterized by the sudden onset of shoulder and upper arm pain followed by progressive (worsening over time) weakness and/or atrophy of the affected area. Although the exact cause is unknown, researchers believe that most cases are due to an autoimmune response following exposure to an illness or environmental factor. Suspected triggers include viral and bacterial infections; surgery; vaccinations; injury; childbirth; strenuous exercise; certain medical procedures; and various health conditions. Treatment is symptomatic and may include pain relievers and physical therapy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004750-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Parsonage Turner syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Parsonage Turner syndrome? Parsonage Turner syndrome is usually characterized by the sudden onset of severe pain in the shoulder and upper arm, which is often described as sharp or throbbing. In some cases, the pain may extend to the neck, lower arm and/or hand on the affected side. Rarely, both sides of the body are involved. Affected people typically experience constant pain that may become worse with movement. Intense pain can last from a few hours to several weeks at which point the pain usually begins to subside; however, mild pain may continue for a year or longer. As the pain subsides, it is typically replaced by progressive (worsening over time) weakness of the affected area, ranging from mild weakness to nearly complete paralysis. Affected people may also experience muscle wasting (atrophy); absent or reduced reflexes; and/or loss of sensation. In some cases, nerves and muscles outside of the shoulder and upper arm region may be affected, as well.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004750-3" qtype="causes">What causes Parsonage Turner syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Parsonage Turner syndrome? The exact cause of Parsonage Turner syndrome (PTS) is unknown. Researchers suspect that most cases are due to an autoimmune response following exposure to an illness or environmental factor. In many cases, no triggering event or underlying cause can be identified. Factors known to trigger PTS include: Infections (both viral and bacterial) Surgery Vaccinations Childbirth Certain medical procedures, such as a spinal tap or imaging studies that require administration of radiologic dye Strenuous exercise Certain medical conditions, including connective tissue disorders and autoimmune disorders Injury Some researchers believe that PTS is a multifactorial condition, which means that it is caused by both environmental and genetic factors. In this case, a person may have a genetic susceptibility to PTS due to one or more genes, but won&apos;t develop the condition unless they are exposed to certain environmental triggers (such as those listed above).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004750-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Parsonage Turner syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is Parsonage Turner syndrome inherited? Parsonage Turner syndrome, which is also known as idiopathic neuralgic amyotrophy, is not inherited. However, an inherited form of neuralgic amyotrophy does exist, which is passed down through families in an autosomal dominant manner. For more information on hereditary neuralgic amyotrophy, please click here.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004750-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parsonage Turner syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Parsonage Turner syndrome diagnosed? A diagnosis of Parsonage Turner syndrome (PTS) is often suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. Specialized tests may be recommended to further investigate the shoulder pain and/or muscle weakness and to rule out other conditions that can cause similar features. These tests may include nerve conduction studies (tests that determine the ability of a specific nerve to relay a message to the brain), electromyography, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI scan) and/or an X-ray.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004750-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parsonage Turner syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Parsonage Turner syndrome be treated? Treatment for Parsonage Turner syndrome (PTS) varies based on the signs and symptoms present in each person. For example, pain medications may be prescribed depending on the severity of the nerve pain. Other techniques for pain management include application of heat or cold and transcutaneous electrical nerve stimulation (a method of pain relief in which a special device transmits low-voltage electrical impulses through electrodes on the skin to an area of the body that is in pain). Many affected people undergo physical therapy and/or occupational therapy to maintain muscle strength and range of motion of affected joints once the pain begins to subside. Surgeries to restore movement and function to the shoulder muscles and joint may be considered if other treatment options are not effective.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
