<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004006" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9844/microcephalic-osteodysplastic-primordial-dwarfism-type-2">
<Focus>Microcephalic osteodysplastic primordial dwarfism type 2</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0432244</CUI>
			<CUI>C0025958</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>MOPD 2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MOPD II</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Osteodysplastic primordial dwarfism type 2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Microcephalic osteodysplastic primordial dwarfism with tooth abnormalities</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Majewski osteodysplastic primordial dwarfism type II</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004006-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Microcephalic osteodysplastic primordial dwarfism type 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Microcephalic osteodysplastic primordial dwarfism type 2 (MOPD2) is a condition characterized by short stature (dwarfism), skeletal abnormalities and an unusually small head size (microcephaly). Other signs and symptoms of MOPD2 may include hip dysplasia; thinning of the bones in the arms and legs; scoliosis; shortened wrist bones; a high-pitched voice; distinctive facial features (prominent nose, full cheeks, a long midface, and a small jaw); small teeth; abnormal skin pigmentation; and blood vessel abnormalities. Intellectual development is typically normal. It is caused by mutations in the PCNT gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004006-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Microcephalic osteodysplastic primordial dwarfism type 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Microcephalic osteodysplastic primordial dwarfism type 2? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Microcephalic osteodysplastic primordial dwarfism type 2. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the hip bone 90% Abnormality of the metaphyses 90% Abnormality of the voice 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the earlobes 90% Brachydactyly syndrome 90% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 90% Delayed skeletal maturation 90% Fine hair 90% Intrauterine growth retardation 90% Microcephaly 90% Micromelia 90% Reduced number of teeth 90% Abnormality of female external genitalia 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the eyebrow 50% Cafe-au-lait spot 50% Dry skin 50% Full cheeks 50% Hypopigmented skin patches 50% Joint hypermobility 50% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 50% Microdontia 50% Scoliosis 50% Sensorineural hearing impairment 50% Truncal obesity 50% Underdeveloped nasal alae 50% Wide nasal bridge 50% Anemia 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 7.5% Atria septal defect 7.5% Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder 7.5% Blepharophimosis 7.5% Cerebral ischemia 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Cone-shaped epiphysis 7.5% Ivory epiphyses 7.5% Laryngomalacia 7.5% Long clavicles 7.5% Patent ductus arteriosus 7.5% Precocious puberty 7.5% Recurrent respiratory infections 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Straight clavicles 7.5% Thin clavicles 7.5% Tracheal stenosis 7.5% Ventriculomegaly 7.5% Distal symphalangism 5% Hypoplastic scapulae 5% Large sella turcica 5% Limited elbow extension 5% Narrow chest 5% Short middle phalanx of finger 5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Cerebral aneurysm - Coxa vara - Disproportionate short stature - Flared metaphysis - High pitched voice - Hypermetropia - Hypoplasia of dental enamel - Hypoplastic iliac wing - Hypospadias - Intellectual disability - Microtia - Moyamoya phenomenon - Narrow pelvis bone - Postnatal growth retardation - Prominent nasal bridge - Prominent nose - Proximal femoral epiphysiolysis - Pseudoepiphyses of the metacarpals - Radial bowing - Retrognathia - Short 1st metacarpal - Short distal phalanx of finger - Slender long bone - Sloping forehead - Sparse scalp hair - Tibial bowing - Type II diabetes mellitus - Ulnar bowing - Upslanted palpebral fissure - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
