<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004480" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4017/occipital-horn-syndrome">
<Focus>Occipital horn syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0268353</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>OHS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cutis laxa X-linked</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, occipital horn type (formerly)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>EDS IX (formerly)</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004480-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Occipital horn syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Occipital horn syndrome (OHS) is characterized by sagging and non-stretchy skin (cutis laxa), wedge-shaped calcium deposits in a bone at the base of the skull (occipital bone), coarse hair, and loose joints.  Individuals with OHS are said to have normal or slightly reduced intelligence. This condition is considered to be a mild type of Menkes diseases, which affects copper levels in the body.  Occipital horn syndrome may be caused by mutations in the ATP7A gene, and it is inherited in an x-linked recessive pattern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004480-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Occipital horn syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Occipital horn syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Occipital horn syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the fontanelles or cranial sutures 90% Cerebral calcification 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Exostoses 90% Hyperextensible skin 90% Joint hypermobility 90% Abnormality of the liver 50% Abnormality of the nose 50% Abnormality of the palate 50% Abnormality of the wrist 50% Aneurysm 50% Atypical scarring of skin 50% Brachydactyly syndrome 50% Bruising susceptibility 50% Elbow dislocation 50% Feeding difficulties in infancy 50% Hypothermia 50% Long philtrum 50% Muscular hypotonia 50% Narrow chest 50% Pectus carinatum 50% Pectus excavatum 50% Platyspondyly 50% Reduced bone mineral density 50% Synostosis of joints 50% Venous insufficiency 50% Abnormality of the fibula 7.5% Abnormality of the hip bone 7.5% Abnormality of the humerus 7.5% Abnormality of the pinna 7.5% Abnormality of the shoulder 7.5% Abnormality of the tibia 7.5% Bladder diverticulum 7.5% Coarse hair 7.5% Genu valgum 7.5% Hernia of the abdominal wall 7.5% High forehead 7.5% Kyphosis 7.5% Osteolysis 7.5% Pes planus 7.5% Recurrent urinary tract infections 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Bladder carcinoma - Broad clavicles - Broad ribs - Capitate-hamate fusion - Carotid artery tortuosity - Chronic diarrhea - Convex nasal ridge - Coxa valga - Hiatus hernia - High palate - Hydronephrosis - Joint laxity - Limited elbow extension - Limited knee extension - Long face - Long neck - Narrow face - Orthostatic hypotension - Osteoporosis - Pelvic bone exostoses - Persistent open anterior fontanelle - Redundant skin - Short clavicles - Short humerus - Soft skin - Ureteral obstruction - X-linked recessive inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004480-3" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Occipital horn syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is genetic testing available for occipital horn syndrome?</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
