<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004241" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10549/mycobacterium-malmoense">
<Focus>Mycobacterium Malmoense</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0317767</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T007</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>M. Malmoense</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mycobacterium Malmoense infection</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004241-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Mycobacterium Malmoense ?</Question>
			<Answer>Mycobacterium malmoense (M. malmoense) is a bacterium naturally found in the environment, such as in wet soil, house dust, water, dairy products, domestic and wild animals, food, and human waste. M. malmoense infections most often occur in adults with lung disease, and manifests as a lung infection. Skin and tissue infections with M. malmoense have also been described. In young children, M. Malmoense may cause an infection of lymphnodes in the neck (i.e., cervical lymphadenitis).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004241-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Mycobacterium Malmoense ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of mycobacterium malmoense infection? Many cases of M. malmoense infection cause no symptoms, and as a result go unrecognized. M. malmoense infections in adults often present as lung infections with or without fever. In children, M. malmoense infections can present as a single sided, non-tender, enlarging, neck mass. The mass may be violet in color and often does not respond to conventional antibiotic therapy. M. malmoense infection can also cause skin lesions or abscesses.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004241-3" qtype="causes">What causes Mycobacterium Malmoense ?</Question>
			<Answer>How are mycobacterium malmoense infections contracted? M. Malmoense infection may be acquired by breathing in or ingesting the bacteria, or through trauma, such as an injury or surgical incision. People who have suppressed immune systems are at an increased risk for developing signs and symptoms from these infections.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
