<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004885" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9452/pilomatrixoma">
<Focus>Pilomatrixoma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0206711</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pilomatricoma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>PTR</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Calcifying epithelioma of Malherbe</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004885-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pilomatrixoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pilomatrixoma is a benign (non-cancerous) skin tumor of the hair follicle (structure in the skin that makes hair). They tend to develop in the head and neck area and are usually not associated with any other signs and symptoms (isolated). Rarely, pilomatrixomas can become cancerous (known as a pilomatrix carcinoma). Although they can occur in people of all ages, pilomatrixomas are most commonly diagnosed in people under age 20. The exact underlying cause is not well understood; however, somatic changes (mutations) in the CTNNB1 gene are found in most isolated pilomatrixomas. Rarely, pilomatrixomas occur in people with certain genetic syndromes such as Gardner syndrome, myotonic dystrophy, and Rubinstein-Taybi syndrome; in these cases, affected people usually have other characteristic signs and symptoms of the associated condition. They are usually treated with surgical excision.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004885-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pilomatrixoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Pilomatrixoma? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Pilomatrixoma. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal dominant inheritance - Pilomatrixoma - Somatic mutation - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004885-3" qtype="causes">What causes Pilomatrixoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes a pilomatrixoma? The exact underlying cause of pilomatrixoma is not well understood. Changes (mutations) in the CTNNB1 gene are found in at least 75% of isolated (without other signs and symptoms) pilomatrixomas. These mutations are somatic, which means they are not inherited and are only present in the tumor cells. The CTNNB1 gene encodes a protein that is needed to regulate cell growth and attachment. When the gene is not working properly, it can result in abnormal cell growth. Rarely, pilomatrixomas occur in people with certain genetic syndromes such as Gardner syndrome, myotonic dystrophy, and Rubinstein-Taybi syndrome. In these cases, affected people usually have other characteristic features of the associated condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004885-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Pilomatrixoma inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is a pilomatrixoma inherited? Most isolated (without other signs and symptoms) pilomatrixomas are not inherited. However, more than one family member can rarely be affected, which suggests there may be a hereditary component in some cases. Rarely, pilomatrixomas occur in people with certain genetic syndromes such as Gardner syndrome, myotonic dystrophy, and Rubinstein-Taybi syndrome. In these cases, affected people usually have other characteristic signs and symptoms of the associated condition. All three of these conditions are inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. In some cases, an affected person inherits the mutation from an affected parent. Other cases may result from new (de novo) mutations in the gene. These cases occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004885-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Pilomatrixoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is a pilomatrixoma diagnosed? A diagnosis of pilomatrixoma is usually suspected on physical examination. Specialized tests may be ordered to confirm the diagnosis and rule out other conditions that cause similar features. These tests may include an ultrasound, an X-ray, and/or a small biopsy of the tumor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004885-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Pilomatrixoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might a pilomatrixoma be treated? Pilomatrixomas are usually surgically removed (excised). In most cases, the tumors do not grow back (recur) after surgery, unless the removal was incomplete.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
