<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004622" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4142/osteoglophonic-dysplasia">
<Focus>Osteoglophonic dysplasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0432283</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Osteoglophonic dwarfism</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fairbank-Keats syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>OGD</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004622-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Osteoglophonic dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Osteoglophonic dysplasia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Osteoglophonic dysplasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 90% Craniosynostosis 90% Hypertelorism 90% Reduced number of teeth 90% Short stature 90% Abnormality of the clavicle 50% Abnormality of the pinna 50% Anteverted nares 50% Delayed skeletal maturation 50% Limb undergrowth 50% Abnormality of bone mineral density 7.5% Brachydactyly syndrome 7.5% Choanal atresia 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Cryptorchidism 7.5% Hernia of the abdominal wall 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Abnormality of the nasopharynx - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Bowing of the long bones - Broad foot - Broad metacarpals - Broad metatarsal - Broad palm - Broad phalanx - Chordee - Cloverleaf skull - Delayed speech and language development - Depressed nasal bridge - Failure to thrive - Frontal bossing - High palate - Hypoplasia of midface - Hypoplastic scapulae - Hypoplastic toenails - Hypospadias - Increased susceptibility to fractures - Inguinal hernia - Long philtrum - Low-set ears - Malar flattening - Mandibular prognathia - Nasal obstruction - Platyspondyly - Pseudoarthrosis - Respiratory distress - Rhizomelia - Shallow orbits - Short foot - Short metacarpal - Short metatarsal - Short neck - Short nose - Short palm - Short phalanx of finger - Unerupted tooth - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
