<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004189" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10756/multiple-epiphyseal-dysplasia">
<Focus>Multiple epiphyseal dysplasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0026760</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>MED</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Epiphyseal dysplasia, multiple</Synonym>
		<Synonym>EDM</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004189-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Multiple epiphyseal dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Multiple epiphyseal dysplasia (MED) is a group of disorders of cartilage and bone development, primarily affecting the ends of the long bones in the arms and legs (epiphyses). There are two types of MED, which are distinguished by their patterns of inheritance - autosomal dominant and autosomal recessive. Signs and symptoms may include joint pain in the hips and knees; early-onset arthritis; a waddling walk; and mild short stature as adults. Recessive MED may also cause malformations of the hands, feet, and knees; scoliosis; or other abnormalities. Most people are diagnosed during childhood, but mild cases may not be diagnosed until adulthood. Dominant MED is caused by mutations in the COMP, COL9A1, COL9A2, COL9A3, or MATN3 genes (or can be of unknown cause), and recessive MED is caused by mutations in the SLC26A2 gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004189-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Multiple epiphyseal dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Multiple epiphyseal dysplasia? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Multiple epiphyseal dysplasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal cortical bone morphology 90% Abnormality of epiphysis morphology 90% Abnormality of the metaphyses 90% Abnormality of the ulna 90% Abnormality of the wrist 90% Anteverted nares 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the sacrum 90% Brachydactyly syndrome 90% Delayed skeletal maturation 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Myopia 90% Osteoarthritis 90% Rough bone trabeculation 90% Round face 90% Sensorineural hearing impairment 90% Short palm 90% Tarsal synostosis 90% Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 50% Abnormality of the femur 50% Abnormality of the hip bone 50% Arthralgia 50% Cleft palate 50% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 50% Gait disturbance 50% Malar flattening 50% Micromelia 50% Patellar aplasia 50% Scoliosis 50% Short stature 50% Talipes 50% Anonychia 7.5% Genu valgum 7.5% Genu varum 7.5% Hearing abnormality 7.5% Abnormality of the hip joint - Arthralgia of the hip - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Avascular necrosis of the capital femoral epiphysis - Broad femoral neck - Coxa vara - Delayed epiphyseal ossification - Delayed ossification of carpal bones - Delayed tarsal ossification - Disproportionate short-limb short stature - Elevated serum creatine phosphokinase - Epiphyseal dysplasia - Flat capital femoral epiphysis - Flattened epiphysis - Generalized joint laxity - Hip dysplasia - Hip osteoarthritis - Hypoplasia of the capital femoral epiphysis - Hypoplasia of the femoral head - Irregular epiphyses - Irregular vertebral endplates - Joint stiffness - Knee osteoarthritis - Limited elbow flexion - Limited hip movement - Metaphyseal irregularity - Mild short stature - Multiple epiphyseal dysplasia - Ovoid vertebral bodies - Premature osteoarthritis - Proximal muscle weakness - Short femoral neck - Short metacarpal - Short phalanx of finger - Small epiphyses - Talipes equinovarus - Waddling gait - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004189-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Multiple epiphyseal dysplasia inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is multiple epiphyseal dysplasia inherited? Multiple epiphyseal dysplasia (MED) may be inherited in an autosomal dominant or autosomal recessive manner depending on the genetic cause. Most cases are autosomal dominant. In autosomal dominant inheritance, having a mutation in only one of the 2 copies of the responsible gene is enough to cause the condition. The mutation may be inherited from a parent or can occur for the first time in the affected person. Each child of a person with an autosomal dominant condition has a 50% (1 in 2) chance to inherit the mutation. More rarely, MED is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. In autosomal recessive inheritance, a person must have a mutation in both copies of the responsible gene to be affected. The parents of a person with an autosomal recessive condition usually each carry one mutated copy of the gene and are referred to as carriers. Carriers typically do not have signs or symptoms and are unaffected. When two carriers for the same condition have children, each child has a 25% (1 in 4) chance to be affected, a 50% (1 in 2) chance to be a carrier like each parent, and a 25% to be both unaffected and not a carrier.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
