<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004768" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4259/patterson-pseudoleprechaunism-syndrome">
<Focus>Patterson pseudoleprechaunism syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1868546</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Patterson's leprechaunoid syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004768-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Patterson pseudoleprechaunism syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Patterson pseudoleprechaunism syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Patterson pseudoleprechaunism syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal cortical bone morphology 90% Abnormality of the hypothalamus-pituitary axis 90% Abnormality of the metaphyses 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Delayed skeletal maturation 90% Generalized hyperpigmentation 90% Hypertrichosis 90% Kyphosis 90% Macrotia 90% Abnormality of the clavicle 50% Abnormality of the ribs 50% Craniofacial hyperostosis 50% Hypercortisolism 50% Hyperextensible skin 50% Precocious puberty 50% Seizures 50% Type II diabetes mellitus 50% Cervical platyspondyly - Diabetes mellitus - Flat acetabular roof - Generalized bronze hyperpigmentation - Genu valgum - Growth abnormality - Hirsutism - Hypoplasia of the odontoid process - Intellectual disability, progressive - Intellectual disability, severe - Irregular acetabular roof - Irregular sclerotic endplates - Joint swelling onset late infancy - Kyphoscoliosis - Large hands - Long foot - Marked delay in bone age - Ovoid thoracolumbar vertebrae - Palmoplantar cutis laxa - Premature adrenarche - Prominent nose - Short long bone - Small cervical vertebral bodies - Sporadic - Talipes valgus - Thickened calvaria - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
