<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004331" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7172/neonatal-hemochromatosis">
<Focus>Neonatal hemochromatosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0268059</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Idiopathic neonatal Hemochromatosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>NH</Synonym>
		<Synonym>NHC</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Neonatal hepatitis (formerly)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Giant Cell Hepatitis (formerly)</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004331-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Neonatal hemochromatosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Neonatal hemochromatosis is a disease in which too much iron builds up in the body. In this form of hemochromatosis the iron overload begins before birth. This disease tends to progress rapidly and is characterized by liver damage that is apparent at birth or in the first day of life. There are a number of other forms of hemochromatosis. To learn more about these other forms click on the disease names listed below: Hemochromatosis type 1 Hemochromatosis type 2 Hemochromatosis type 3 Hemochromatosis type 4</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004331-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Neonatal hemochromatosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Neonatal hemochromatosis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Neonatal hemochromatosis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal localization of kidney 90% Anteverted nares 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the nipples 90% Blepharophimosis 90% Congenital hepatic fibrosis 90% Hypoglycemia 90% Abnormal bleeding - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Cholestasis - Cirrhosis - Congenital onset - Hepatic failure - Hepatic fibrosis - Hepatocellular necrosis - Increased serum ferritin - Increased serum iron - Intrauterine growth retardation - Nonimmune hydrops fetalis - Oligohydramnios - Prolonged neonatal jaundice - Rapidly progressive - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
