<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004370" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10686/neuroferritinopathy">
<Focus>Neuroferritinopathy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1853578</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Ferritin-related neurodegeneration</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Basal ganglia disease adult-onset</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Neurodegeneration with brain iron accumulation</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004370-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Neuroferritinopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Neuroferritinopathy is a movement disorder caused by the gradual accumulation of iron in the basal ganglia of the brain. People with neuroferritinopathy have progressive problems with movement that begin at about age 40. These movement problems can include involuntary jerking motions (chorea), rhythmic shaking (tremor), difficulty coordinating movements (ataxia), or uncontrolled tensing of muscles (dystonia). Symptoms of the disorder may be more prominent on one side of the body. Affected individuals may also have difficulty swallowing (dysphagia) and speaking (dysarthria). Intelligence is generally unaffected, but some individuals develop a gradual decline in thinking and reasoning abilities (dementia). Personality changes such as reduced inhibitions and difficulty controlling emotions may also occur as the disorder progresses. Neuroferritinopathy is caused by mutations in the FTL gene. It is inherited in an autosomal dominant fashion.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004370-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Neuroferritinopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Neuroferritinopathy? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Neuroferritinopathy. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Chorea 90% Hypertonia 90% Incoordination 90% Abnormality of eye movement 50% Feeding difficulties in infancy 50% Gait disturbance 50% Constipation 7.5% Developmental regression 7.5% Hypotension 7.5% Neurological speech impairment 7.5% Reduced consciousness/confusion 7.5% Tremor 7.5% Anarthria - Ataxia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Babinski sign - Blepharospasm - Bradykinesia - Cavitation of the basal ganglia - Choreoathetosis - Decreased serum ferritin - Dementia - Disinhibition - Dysarthria - Dysphagia - Emotional lability - Hyperreflexia - Laryngeal dystonia - Mutism - Neurodegeneration - Parkinsonism - Phenotypic variability - Progressive - Rigidity - Spasticity - Writer&apos;s cramp - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
