<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004627" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4148/osteopathia-striata-cranial-sclerosis">
<Focus>Osteopathia striata cranial sclerosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0432268</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>OSCS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hyperostosis generalisata with striations</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Osteopathia striata - cranial sclerosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Robinow-Unger syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Osteopathia striata-cranial sclerosis syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004627-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Osteopathia striata cranial sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Osteopathia striata cranial sclerosis is a type of skeletal dysplasia, which refers to a group of genetic conditions that affect the bones and hinder growth and development. The severity of the condition and the associated symptoms vary significantly from person to person, even within a single family. Features of the condition are generally present at birth and may include skeletal abnormalities (particularly at the ends of long bones), sclerosis (hardening) of the craniofacial bones, macrocephaly (unusually large head size), and characteristic facial features. Some affected people may also have developmental delay, hearing loss, heart defects and/or ophthalmoplegia (paralysis of the muscles surrounding the eyes). Osteopathia striata cranial sclerosis is caused by changes (mutations) in the WTX gene and is inherited in an X-linked dominant manner. Treatment is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004627-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Osteopathia striata cranial sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Osteopathia striata cranial sclerosis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Osteopathia striata cranial sclerosis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of pelvic girdle bone morphology 90% Craniofacial hyperostosis 90% Rough bone trabeculation 90% Cleft palate 50% Conductive hearing impairment 50% Delayed eruption of teeth 50% Frontal bossing 50% Macrocephaly 50% Malar flattening 50% Scoliosis 50% Wide nasal bridge 50% Intellectual disability, mild 33% High palate 15% Abnormality of the aorta 7.5% Asymmetry of the thorax 7.5% Cataract 7.5% Cerebral calcification 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Delayed speech and language development 7.5% Epicanthus 7.5% Facial palsy 7.5% Headache 7.5% Hyperlordosis 7.5% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 7.5% Neurological speech impairment 7.5% Short stature 7.5% Spina bifida occulta 7.5% Anal atresia 5% Anal stenosis 5% Multicystic kidney dysplasia 5% Omphalocele 5% Apnea - Arachnodactyly - Atria septal defect - Bifid uvula - Broad ribs - Camptodactyly - Cleft upper lip - Clinodactyly of the 5th finger - Craniofacial osteosclerosis - Delayed closure of the anterior fontanelle - Dental crowding - Dental malocclusion - Failure to thrive - Fibular aplasia - Fibular hypoplasia - Flexion contracture of toe - Gastroesophageal reflux - Hydrocephalus - Hypertelorism - Intestinal malrotation - Joint contracture of the hand - Large fontanelles - Laryngeal web - Microtia - Muscular hypotonia - Narrow forehead - Nasal speech - Natal tooth - Oligohydramnios - Osteopathia striata - Overfolded helix - Paranasal sinus hypoplasia - Partial agenesis of the corpus callosum - Patent ductus arteriosus - Pectus excavatum - Pierre-Robin sequence - Polyhydramnios - Sclerosis of skull base - Seizures - Straight clavicles - Talipes equinovarus - Thick lower lip vermilion - Thickened calvaria - Thoracolumbar kyphosis - Tracheomalacia - Ventricular septal defect - Webbed neck - Wide intermamillary distance - X-linked dominant inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
