<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004590" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10518/orofaciodigital-syndrome-3">
<Focus>Orofaciodigital syndrome 3</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
			<CUI>C0406726</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>OFD3</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Oral-facial-digital syndrome type 3</Synonym>
		<Synonym>OFD syndrome 3</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Sugarman syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Orofaciodigital syndrome III</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Orofaciodigital syndromes</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004590-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Orofaciodigital syndrome 3 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Orofaciodigital syndrome 3? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Orofaciodigital syndrome 3. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the pupil 90% Cleft palate 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Increased number of teeth 90% Kyphosis 90% Pectus excavatum 90% Postaxial hand polydactyly 90% Abnormal nasal morphology 50% Abnormality of eye movement 50% Abnormality of the fingernails 50% Abnormality of the nipple 50% Abnormality of the tragus 50% EEG abnormality 50% Frontal bossing 50% Hypertelorism 50% Hypertonia 50% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 50% Muscular hypotonia 50% Prominent occiput 50% Round face 50% Abnormality of the macula 7.5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Bifid uvula - Bulbous nose - Hyperconvex nail - Intellectual disability - Low-set ears - Microdontia - Myoclonus - Postaxial foot polydactyly - Short sternum - Tongue nodules - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
