<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004272" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10529/myofibrillar-myopathy">
<Focus>Myofibrillar myopathy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2678065</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Desminopathy (type)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Alpha Beta crystallinopathy (type)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Myotilinopathy (type)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Zaspopathy (type)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Filaminopathy (type)</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004272-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Myofibrillar myopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Myofibrillar myopathies (MFM) are a group of neuromuscular disorders characterized by slowly progressive weakness that can involve both proximal muscles (such as hips and shoulders) and distal muscles (those farther away from the trunk). Some affected individuals also experience sensory symptoms, muscle stiffness, aching, or cramps. Peripheral neuropathy or cardiomyopathy may also be present. Most people with MFM begin to develop muscle weakness in mid-adulthood, but features of the condition can appear anytime between infancy and late adulthood. It may be caused by mutations in any of several genes, including DES, CRYAB, MYOT, LDB3, FLNC,  and BAG3; the signs and symptoms of MFM can vary widely depending on the condition&apos;s genetic cause. It is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Treatment may include a pacemaker and implantable cardioverter defibrillator (ICD) for arrhythmia or cardiac conduction defects; cardiac transplantation for progressive or life-threatening cardiomyopathy; respiratory support for respiratory failure; and physical therapy and assistive devices for those with advanced muscle weakness.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004272-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Myofibrillar myopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Myofibrillar myopathy? Myofibrillar myopathy (MFM) primarily affects skeletal muscles, which are muscles that the body uses for movement. In some cases, the heart (cardiac) muscle is also affected. The signs and symptoms of MFM vary widely among affected individuals, typically depending on the condition&apos;s genetic cause. Most people with this disorder begin to develop muscle weakness (myopathy) in mid-adulthood. However, features of this condition can appear anytime between infancy and late adulthood. Muscle weakness most often begins in the hands and feet (distal muscles), but some people first experience weakness in the muscles near the center of the body (proximal muscles). Other affected individuals develop muscle weakness throughout their body. Facial muscle weakness can cause swallowing and speech difficulties. Muscle weakness worsens over time. Other signs and symptoms of MFM can include a weakened heart muscle (cardiomyopathy), muscle pain (myalgia), loss of sensation and weakness in the limbs (peripheral neuropathy), and respiratory failure. Individuals with this condition may have skeletal problems including joint stiffness (contractures) and abnormal side-to-side curvature of the spine (scoliosis). Rarely, people with this condition develop clouding of the front surface of the eyes (cataracts). The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Myofibrillar myopathy. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Arrhythmia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Bulbar palsy - Constipation - Diarrhea - Dilated cardiomyopathy - Distal muscle weakness - EMG: myopathic abnormalities - Facial palsy - Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy - Hyporeflexia of lower limbs - Late-onset proximal muscle weakness - Neck muscle weakness - Phenotypic variability - Respiratory insufficiency due to muscle weakness - Restrictive heart failure - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
