<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004436" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9592/non-classic-congenital-adrenal-hyperplasia-due-to-21-hydroxylase-deficiency">
<Focus>Non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1291314</CUI>
			<CUI>C0001627</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>LOCAH</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Non classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>NCCAH</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Attenuated congenital adrenal hyperplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>21-hydroxylase deficiency</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004436-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency (NCAH) is a milder and later onset form of a genetic condition known as congenital adrenal hyperplasia. Some people affected by the condition have no associated signs and symptoms while others experience symptoms of androgen (male hormone) excess. Women with NCAH are generally born with normal female genitalia. Later in life, signs and symptoms of the condition can vary but may include hirsutism, frontal baldness, delayed menarche (first period), menstrual irregularities, and infertility. Little has been published about males with NCAH. They may have early beard growth and relatively small testes. Typically, they have normal sperm counts. NCAH is caused by changes (mutations) in the CYP21A2 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Treatment is only necessary in people who are symptomatic and may include a glucocorticoid called dexamethasone.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004436-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency? The signs and symptoms of non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency (NCAH) may develop any time after birth. Affected people generally experience symptoms of androgen (male hormone) excess such as acne, premature development of pubic hair, accelerated growth, advanced bone age, and reduced adult height. Women with NCAH are generally born with normal female genitalia. Later in life, signs and symptoms of the condition can vary but may include hirsutism, frontal baldness, delayed menarche (first period), menstrual irregularities, and infertility. Little has been published about males with NCAH. They may have early beard growth and relatively small testes. Typically, they have normal sperm counts. Some men and women affected by NCAH have no signs or symptoms of the condition. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the thorax - Adrenal hyperplasia - Adrenogenital syndrome - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Fever - Growth abnormality - Gynecomastia - Hypertension - Hypoglycemia - Hypospadias - Renal salt wasting - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004436-3" qtype="causes">What causes Non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency? Non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency (NCAH) is caused by changes (mutations) in the CYP21A2 gene. This gene provides instructions for making an enzyme called 21-hydroxylase, which is found in the adrenal glands. The adrenal glands are cone-shaped organs that sit on top of the kidneys and are responsible for releasing various types of hormones that the body needs to function. Mutations in CYP21A2 lead to deficient levels of 21-hydroxylase which cause low levels of hormones such as cortisol and/or aldosterone and an overproduction of androgens (male hormones such as testosterone). Cortisol is a hormone that affects energy levels, blood sugar levels, blood pressure, and the body&apos;s response to stress, illness, and injury. Aldosterone helps the body maintain the proper level of sodium (salt) and water and helps maintain blood pressure. Irregular levels of these hormones lead to the signs and symptoms of NCAH. The amount of functional 21-hydroxylase enzyme determines the severity of the disorder. People with NCAH have CYP21A2 mutations that result in the production of reduced amounts of the enzyme, but more enzyme than the classic form of congenital adrenal hyperplasia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004436-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency inherited? Non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency (NCAH) is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. This means that to be affected, a person must have a mutation in both copies of the responsible gene in each cell. The parents of an affected person usually each carry one mutated copy of the gene and are referred to as carriers. Carriers typically do not show signs or symptoms of the condition. When two carriers of an autosomal recessive condition have children, each child has a 25% (1 in 4) risk to have the condition, a 50% (1 in 2) risk to be a carrier like each of the parents, and a 25% chance to not have the condition and not be a carrier.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004436-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency diagnosed? A diagnosis of non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency (NCAH) is often suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. Additional testing can then be ordered to confirm the diagnosis. This may include a blood test to measure the concentration of 17-hydroxyprogesterone (17-OHP) and/or an adrenocorticotropic hormone (ACTH) stimulation test. An ACTH stimulation test involves measuring the concentration of 17-OHP in the blood before ACTH is administered and 60 min after ACTH is given.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004436-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency be treated? In some cases, people affected by non-classic congenital adrenal hyperplasia due to 21-hydroxylase deficiency (NCAH) may not require any treatment. Many are asymptomatic throughout their lives, although symptoms may develop during puberty, after puberty, or post partum. If symptoms are present, a glucocorticoid called dexamethasone is often recommended. Dexamethasone can treat irregular menstruation, acne, and excess body hair (hirsutism).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
