<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004172" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9644/multicentric-castleman-disease">
<Focus>Multicentric Castleman Disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1334815</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>MCD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Plasmablastic multicentric Castleman disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>PMCD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Multicentric plasma cell variant of Castleman's disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Idiopathic multicentric Castleman's disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Castleman disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004172-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Multicentric Castleman Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Multicentric Castleman disease (MCD) is a rare condition that affects the lymph nodes and related tissues. It is a form of Castleman disease that is &quot;systemic&quot; and affects multiple sets of lymph nodes and other tissues throughout the body (as opposed to unicentric Castleman disease which has more &quot;localized&quot; effects). The signs and symptoms of MCD are often nonspecific and blamed on other, more common conditions. They can vary but may include fever; weight loss; fatigue; night sweats; enlarged lymph nodes; nausea and vomiting; and an enlarged liver or spleen. The eact underlying cause is unknown. Treatment may involve immunotherapy, chemotherapy, corticosteroid medications and/or anti-viral drugs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004172-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Multicentric Castleman Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of multicentric Castleman disease? The signs and symptoms of multicentric Castleman disease (MCD) are often nonspecific and blamed on other, more common conditions. They can vary but may include: Fever Enlarged lymph nodes Night sweats Loss of appetite and weight loss Weakness and fatigue Shortness of breath Nausea and vomiting Enlarged liver or spleen Peripheral neuropathy Skin abnormalities such as rashes and/or pemphigus Less commonly (&lt;10% of cases), people affected by MCD will have no signs or symptoms of the condition. Other conditions associated with MCD include amyloidosis, POEMS syndrome, autoimmune disease, hemolytic anemia, and immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004172-3" qtype="causes">What causes Multicentric Castleman Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes multicentric Castleman disease? The exact underlying cause of multicentric Castleman disease (MCD) is poorly understood. However, some scientists suspect that an increased production of interleukin-6 (IL-6) by the immune system may contribute to the development of MCD. IL-6 is a substance normally produced by cells within the lymph nodes that helps coordinate the immune response to infection. Increased production of IL-6 may result in an overgrowth of lymphatic cells, leading to many of the signs and symptoms of MCD. It has also been found that a virus called human herpes virus type 8 (also known as HHV-8, Kaposi&apos;s sarcoma-associated herpesvirus, or KSHV) is present in many people with MCD. HHV-8 is found in nearly all people who are HIV-positive and develop MCD, and in up to 60% of affected people without HIV. The HHV-8 virus may possibly cause MCD by making its own IL-6.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004172-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Multicentric Castleman Disease inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is multicentric Castleman disease inherited? Although the exact underlying cause of multicentric Castleman disease is unknown, it is thought to occur sporadically in people with no family history of the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004172-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Multicentric Castleman Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is multicentric Castleman disease diagnosed? The signs and symptoms of multicentric Castleman disease (MCD) are often nonspecific and blamed on other, more common conditions. However, if MCD is suspected, the following tests may be recommended to help establish the diagnosis and rule out other conditions that cause similar features: Blood tests can be ordered to evaluate the levels of Interleukin-6 (IL-6) and other substances in the body, which can be elevated in people with MCD. They can also be helpful in ruling out other autoimmune conditions and infections that are associated with similar signs and symptoms Imaging studies (such as a CT scan, PET scan, MRI scan, and/or ultrasound) can help identify enlarged lymph node(s) and other health problems A biopsy of affected tissue, often a lymph node, is usually recommended to confirm the diagnosis</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004172-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Multicentric Castleman Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might multicentric Castleman disease be treated? The treatment of multicentric Castleman disease (MCD) varies based on the severity of the condition and whether or not the patient has an HIV and/or human herpes virus type 8 (HHV-8) infection. Possible treatment options include: Immunotherapy can be used to block the action of the interleukin-6 (IL-6), a protein that is produced in excess by the immune system of people with MCD Chemotherapy may be recommended to slow the growth of lymphatic cells Corticosteroid medications can reduce inflammation Anti-viral drugs can block the activity of HHV-8 or HIV (in people who are infected by these viruses)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
