<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004212" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12811/multisystemic-smooth-muscle-dysfunction-syndrome">
<Focus>Multisystemic smooth muscle dysfunction syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3151201</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Congenital mydriasis, patent ductus arteriosus, thoracic aortic aneurysm, and vasculopathy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004212-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Multisystemic smooth muscle dysfunction syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Multisystemic smooth muscle dysfunction syndrome is a disease in which the activity of smooth muscle throughout the body is impaired. This leads to widespread problems including blood vessel abnormalities, a decreased response of the pupils to light, a weak bladder, and weakened contractions of the muscles used for the digestion of food (hypoperistalsis). A certain  mutation in the ACTA2 gene has been shown to cause this condition in some individuals.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004212-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Multisystemic smooth muscle dysfunction syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Multisystemic smooth muscle dysfunction syndrome? Symptoms for people with multisystemic smooth muscle dysfunction syndrome can include the following : Congenital mydriasis (fixed dilated pupils) Patent Ductus Arteriosus Vascular problems including aneurysms Gastrintestinal problems Weak bladder Lung disease White matter abnormalities Changes consistent with MoyaMoya disease The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Multisystemic smooth muscle dysfunction syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal dominant inheritance - Cerebral aneurysm - Cryptorchidism - Hyperperistalsis - Intestinal malrotation - Mydriasis - Patent ductus arteriosus - Pulmonary hypertension - Retinal infarction - Tachypnea - Thoracic aortic aneurysm - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
