<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004329" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12033/nemaline-myopathy">
<Focus>Nemaline myopathy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0206157</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Nemaline body disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Nemaline rod disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Rod body disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Rod-body myopathy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Rod myopathy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Adult-onset nemaline myopathy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Amish Nemaline Myopathy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Childhood-onset nemaline myopathy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Intermediate congenital nemaline myopathy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Myopathy congenital</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004329-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Nemaline myopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nemaline myopathy is a disorder that primarily affects skeletal muscles, which are muscles that the body uses for movement. People with nemaline myopathy have muscle weakness (myopathy) throughout the body, but it is typically most severe in the muscles of the face, neck, and limbs. This weakness can worsen over time. Affected individuals may have feeding and swallowing difficulties, foot deformities, abnormal curvature of the spine (scoliosis), and joint deformities (contractures). Mutations in at least six genes can cause nemaline myopathy. Some individuals with nemaline myopathy do not have an identified mutation. The genetic cause of the disorder is unknown in these individuals. Nemaline myopathy is usually inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern. Less often, this condition is inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern. Nemaline myopathy is divided into six types. You can search for information about a particular type of nemaline myopathy from the GARD Home page. Enter the name of the condition in the GARD search box and then select the type from the drop down menu.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
