<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004201" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7111/multiple-pterygium-syndrome-escobar-type">
<Focus>Multiple pterygium syndrome Escobar type</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265261</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Escobar syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Multiple pterygium syndrome nonlethal type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pterygium syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Multiple pterygium syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pterygium colli syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004201-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Multiple pterygium syndrome Escobar type ?</Question>
			<Answer>Multiple pterygium syndrome, Escobar type is characterized by webbing of the neck, elbows, and/or knees, and joint contractures. Symptoms of Escobar syndrome are present from birth. It can be caused by mutations in the CHRNG gene. It tends to be inherited in an autosomal recessive fashion.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004201-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Multiple pterygium syndrome Escobar type ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Multiple pterygium syndrome Escobar type? Symptoms of multiple pterygium syndrome, Escobar type vary but may include short stature, vertebral (spine) defects, joint contractures, and webbing of the neck, armpit, elbow, knee, between the legs, and of the fingers and toes. The joint contractures may interfere with walking, making walking more difficult. Other symptoms may include down-slanting eyes, skin fold over the inner corner of the eye, a pointed, receding chin, droopy eye lids, and cleft palate. Males with Escobar syndrome may have undescended testicles at birth, and females may have absent labia majora. People with Escobar syndrome may have in-curving of the little finger, joined fingers, and rocker-bottom feet. They may also have kyphoscoliosis and other spine defects, such as fusion of the spine. Abnormal ossicles (the three small bones in the ear) may lead to conductive hearing loss. Other skeletal anomalies include rib fusions, radial head and hip dislocations, talipes calcaneovalgus (the foot points inwards and down) or club foot, and missing or underdeveloped kneecap. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Multiple pterygium syndrome Escobar type. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Amniotic constriction ring 90% Finger syndactyly 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Pectus excavatum 90% Scoliosis 90% Symphalangism affecting the phalanges of the hand 90% Webbed neck 90% Abnormality of the foot 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the abdominal wall musculature 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the skin 50% Camptodactyly of finger 50% Epicanthus 50% Facial asymmetry 50% Hypertelorism 50% Intrauterine growth retardation 50% Long face 50% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 50% Microcephaly 50% Pointed chin 50% Popliteal pterygium 50% Ptosis 50% Respiratory insufficiency 50% Short stature 50% Telecanthus 50% Umbilical hernia 50% Vertebral segmentation defect 50% Abnormality of female external genitalia 7.5% Abnormality of the abdominal organs 7.5% Abnormality of the aortic valve 7.5% Abnormality of the ribs 7.5% Aortic dilatation 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the lungs 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Conductive hearing impairment 7.5% Cryptorchidism 7.5% Dolichocephaly 7.5% Gait disturbance 7.5% Hypoplasia of penis 7.5% Long philtrum 7.5% Low posterior hairline 7.5% Scrotal hypoplasia 7.5% Skeletal muscle atrophy 7.5% Spina bifida occulta 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Abnormality of the neck - Absence of labia majora - Antecubital pterygium - Anterior clefting of vertebral bodies - Arachnodactyly - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Axillary pterygia - Bilateral camptodactyly - Camptodactyly of toe - Congenital diaphragmatic hernia - Decreased fetal movement - Diaphragmatic eventration - Dislocated radial head - Downturned corners of mouth - Dysplastic patella - Exostosis of the external auditory canal - Fused cervical vertebrae - High palate - Hip dislocation - Hypoplastic nipples - Hypospadias - Inguinal hernia - Intercrural pterygium - Kyphosis - Long clavicles - Low-set ears - Narrow mouth - Neck pterygia - Neonatal respiratory distress - Patellar aplasia - Pulmonary hypoplasia - Rib fusion - Rocker bottom foot - Syndactyly - Talipes calcaneovalgus - Talipes equinovarus - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004201-3" qtype="causes">What causes Multiple pterygium syndrome Escobar type ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes multiple pterygium syndrome, Escobar type? Some cases of multiple pterygium syndrome, Escobar type are caused by mutations in the CHRNG gene. There are likely other causes of this syndrome as well which have not yet been identified. As a result, in some cases the cause for the syndrome can not be determined.  Escobar syndrome is usually inherited in an autosomal-recessive fashion.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004201-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Multiple pterygium syndrome Escobar type ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is multiple pterygium syndrome, Escobar type diagnosed? Multiple pterygium syndrome, Escobar type is diagnosed based on signs and symptoms in the patient. This syndrome should be considered in patients with webs across different body joints, particularly if additional signs and symptoms are present (e.g., subtle facial feature differences). Because skeletal birth defects (especially spine defects), are relatively common in Escobar syndrome radiographs of the complete skeleton may be helpful in diagnosis. Genetic testing for multiple pterygium syndrome, Escobar type is available on a limited basis. This testing can be done using linkage analysis or by sequencing the coding region for the gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004201-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Multiple pterygium syndrome Escobar type ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is multiple pterygium syndrome, Escobar type treated? There is currently no cure for multiple pterygium syndrome, Escobar type. As a result treatment is aimed at managing the associated symptoms. Orthopedics should be involved for issues arising from scoliosis. Infections should be treated promptly. Contracture releases have been performed with variable outcome. Physical therapy is important to help minimize contractures. When ptosis (droopy eyelids) is present, the patient should be referred to ophthalmology. Patients should also be referred to audiology due to the risk of conductive hearing loss.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
