<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004818" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12724/periventricular-heterotopia">
<Focus>Periventricular heterotopia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3714789</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Periventricular nodular heterotopia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>X-linked periventricular heterotopia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004818-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Periventricular heterotopia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Periventricular heterotopia is a condition in which the nerve cells (neurons) do not migrate properly during the early development of the fetal brain from about the 6th week to the 24th week of pregnancy. Affected people typically develop recurrent seizures (epilepsy) beginning in mid-adolescence. Intelligence is generally normal; however, some affected people may have mild intellectual disability, including difficulty with reading and/or spelling. Less common signs and symptoms include microcephaly, developmental delay, recurrent infections, and blood vessel abnormalities. Some cases are caused by changes (mutations) in the FLNA gene and are inherited in an X-linked dominant manner. Others are caused by mutations in the ARFGEF2 gene and are inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Rarely, periventricular heterotopia is associated with duplication of genetic material on chromosome 5. Treatment is generally focused on managing recurrent seizures with medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004818-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Periventricular heterotopia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of periventricular nodular heterotopia? The condition is first noticed when seizures appear, often during the teenage years. The nodules around the ventricles are then typically discovered when magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) studies are done. Patients usually have normal intelligence, although some have mild intellectual disability. Difficulty with reading and spelling (dyslexia) has been reported in some girls with periventricular heterotopia. Less commonly, individuals with periventricular heterotopia may have more severe brain malformations, small head size (microcephaly), developmental delays, recurrent infections, blood vessel abnormalities, or other problems. In the X-linked form of periventricular nodular heterotopia, affected patients are mostly females because in males the symptoms are too serious and they die before birth. The following clinical features have been reported: seizure disorder, mental problems, heart anomalies, stomach immobility, strabismus, short fingers and dyslexia. Periventricular heterotopia may also occur in association with other conditions such as Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (Ehlers-Danlos with periventricular heterotopia) which results in extremely flexible joints, skin that stretches easily, and fragile blood vessels. In the autosomal recessive form of periventricular heterotopia the disorder is severe and may include microcephaly, severe developmental delay, and seizures beginning in infancy. Most often, the parents of an individual with an autosomal recessive condition each carry one copy of the mutated gene, but do not show any signs or symptoms of this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004818-3" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Periventricular heterotopia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the recommended evaluations for patients diagnosed with periventricular nodular heterotopia? The following evaluations are recommended:[1823]  Imaging exams of the brain to establish the diagnosis  Evaluation by a neurologist  Evaluation by a doctor specialized in epilepsy if seizures are present  Psychiatric evaluation if necessary  Magnetic resonance angiography (MRA) of the brain vessels, carotid arteries, and aorta because of the risk for stroke  Evaluation by a cardiologist and either echocardiogram or a heart magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) because of the risk for aortic aneurysm  Evaluation by a hematologist if findings suggest a bleeding diathesis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004818-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Periventricular heterotopia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might periventricular nodular heterotopia be treated? Treatment of epilepsy generally follows principles for a seizure disorder caused by a known structural brain abnormality; carbamezipine is most often used, because most patients have focal seizures. However, antiepileptic drugs may be selected based on side effects, tolerability, and efficacy. It is recommended that patients with the X-linked form of the disease have studies evaluating the carotid artery and an abdominal ultrasound because of the risk for aortic or carotid dissection or other vascular anomalies.[1823] Treatment also include surgery for removal of the lesion and more recently, laser ablation guided with magnetic resonance.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
