<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004085" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7009/mitochondrial-encephalomyopathy-lactic-acidosis-and-stroke-like-episodes">
<Focus>Mitochondrial encephalomyopathy lactic acidosis and stroke-like episodes</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0162666</CUI>
			<CUI>C1857287</CUI>
			<CUI>C0001125</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>MELAS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MELAS syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004085-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Mitochondrial encephalomyopathy lactic acidosis and stroke-like episodes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Mitochondrial encephalomyopathy, lactic acidosis, and stroke-like episodes (MELAS) affects many parts of the body, particularly the brain and nervous system (encephalo-) and muscles (myopathy). Symptoms typically begin in childhood and may include muscle weakness and pain, recurrent headaches, loss of appetite, vomiting, and seizures. Most affected individuals experience stroke-like episodes beginning before age 40. People with MELAS can also have a buildup of lactic acid in their bodies that can lead to vomiting, abdominal pain, fatigue, muscle weakness, and difficulty breathing. The genes associated with MELAS are located in mitochondrial DNA and therefore follow a maternal inheritance pattern (also called mitochondrial inheritance). MELAS can be inherited from the mother only, because only females pass mitochondrial DNA to their children. In some cases, MELAS results from a new mutation that was not inherited from a person&apos;s mother.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004085-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Mitochondrial encephalomyopathy lactic acidosis and stroke-like episodes ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Mitochondrial encephalomyopathy lactic acidosis and stroke-like episodes? The signs and symptoms of MELAS often appear in childhood following a period of normal development. Early symptoms may include muscle weakness and pain, recurrent headaches, loss of appetite, vomiting, and seizures. Most affected individuals experience stroke-like episodes beginning before age 40. These episodes may involve temporary muscle weakness on one side of the body, altered consciousness, vision abnormalities, seizures, and severe headaches resembling migraines. Repeated stroke-like episodes can progressively damage the brain, leading to vision loss, problems with movement, and a loss of intellectual function. Many people with MELAS have a buildup of lactic acid in their bodies (lactic acidosis). This can lead to vomiting, abdominal pain, extreme fatigue, muscle weakness, and difficulty breathing. Involuntary muscle spasms, impaired muscle coordination, hearing loss, heart and kidney problems, diabetes, and hormonal imbalances may also occur. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Mitochondrial encephalomyopathy lactic acidosis and stroke-like episodes. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of mitochondrial metabolism 90% Cerebral ischemia 90% Developmental regression 90% EMG abnormality 90% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 90% Migraine 90% Muscle weakness 90% Myopathy 90% Abdominal pain 50% Amaurosis fugax 50% Anorexia 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the cerebellum 50% Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder 50% Cerebral calcification 50% Cerebral cortical atrophy 50% Decreased body weight 50% Decreased nerve conduction velocity 50% Hallucinations 50% Incoordination 50% Involuntary movements 50% Memory impairment 50% Nausea and vomiting 50% Pancreatitis 50% Ptosis 50% Reduced consciousness/confusion 50% Respiratory insufficiency 50% Sensorineural hearing impairment 50% Short stature 50% Type II diabetes mellitus 50% Visual field defect 50% Abnormality of neuronal migration 7.5% Abnormality of retinal pigmentation 7.5% Abnormality of temperature regulation 7.5% Abnormality of the genital system 7.5% Abnormality of the liver 7.5% Abnormality of the macula 7.5% Abnormality of the pinna 7.5% Abnormality of the renal tubule 7.5% Abnormality of visual evoked potentials 7.5% Anterior hypopituitarism 7.5% Aortic dilatation 7.5% Aortic dissection 7.5% Apnea 7.5% Autism 7.5% Carious teeth 7.5% Cataract 7.5% Congestive heart failure 7.5% Constipation 7.5% Delayed skeletal maturation 7.5% EEG abnormality 7.5% Feeding difficulties in infancy 7.5% Gingival overgrowth 7.5% Glomerulopathy 7.5% Goiter 7.5% Hypercalciuria 7.5% Hypertelorism 7.5% Hypertension 7.5% Hyperthyroidism 7.5% Hypertrichosis 7.5% Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy 7.5% Hypoparathyroidism 7.5% Hypopigmented skin patches 7.5% Hypothyroidism 7.5% Ichthyosis 7.5% Intestinal obstruction 7.5% Malabsorption 7.5% Mask-like facies 7.5% Microcephaly 7.5% Multiple lipomas 7.5% Muscular hypotonia 7.5% Myalgia 7.5% Nephrotic syndrome 7.5% Neurological speech impairment 7.5% Nyctalopia 7.5% Ophthalmoparesis 7.5% Optic atrophy 7.5% Paresthesia 7.5% Premature loss of teeth 7.5% Primary adrenal insufficiency 7.5% Proteinuria 7.5% Pulmonary embolism 7.5% Pulmonary hypertension 7.5% Renal insufficiency 7.5% Skeletal muscle atrophy 7.5% Spontaneous hematomas 7.5% Sudden cardiac death 7.5% Thyroiditis 7.5% Tremor 7.5% Type I diabetes mellitus 7.5% Ventriculomegaly 7.5% Visual impairment 7.5% Bilateral sensorineural hearing impairment - Congenital cataract - Cortical visual impairment - Dementia - Diabetes mellitus - Encephalopathy - Episodic vomiting - Generalized tonic-clonic seizures - Growth abnormality - Hemianopia - Hemiparesis - Lactic acidosis - Left ventricular hypertrophy - Mitochondrial inheritance - Mitochondrial myopathy - Ophthalmoplegia - Progressive sensorineural hearing impairment - Ragged-red muscle fibers - Stroke-like episodes - Wolff-Parkinson-White syndrome - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004085-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Mitochondrial encephalomyopathy lactic acidosis and stroke-like episodes inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is mitochondrial encephalomyopathy, lactic acidosis, and stroke-like episodes (MELAS) inherited? MELAS is caused by mutations in mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) and is therefore transmitted by maternal inheritance (also called mitochondrial inheritance). This type of inheritance applies to all conditions caused by genes in mtDNA. Mitochondria are structures in each cell that turn molecules into energy, and each contain a small amount of DNA. Only egg cells (not sperm cells) contribute mitochondria to offspring, so only females can pass on mitochondrial mutations to their children. Conditions resulting from mutations in mtDNA can appear in every generation of a family and can affect both males and females. In most cases, people with MELAS inherit an altered mitochondrial gene from their mother. Less commonly, the condition results from a new mutation in a mitochondrial gene and occurs in an individual with no history of MELAS in the family.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004085-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Mitochondrial encephalomyopathy lactic acidosis and stroke-like episodes ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the genetic testing options for mitochondrial encephalomyopathy lactic acidosis and stroke-like episodes (MELAS)? Genetic testing for a particular condition is typically available from only a few clinical laboratories because these conditions are rare and the tests are ordered infrequently. It is not uncommon to send DNA samples to a laboratory in another state, or even to laboratories in Canada or Europe. Genetic tests are more complicated than standard blood tests and are usually much more expensive. Due to the high cost of these tests, insurance companies may or may not provide coverage. Doctors sometimes write a letter of medical necessity to the insurance company stating why a particular test is needed, which sometimes pursuades the insurance company to cover the test. These letters state the medical benefits that a person would receive from a test, and how the test would alter a person&apos;s medical care. GeneTests lists the names of laboratories that perform genetic testing. This resource lists the contact information for the clinical laboratories conducting genetic testing for MELAS. Another option is to participate in a research study that is performing genetic testing. While the cost of testing is often covered by the research funding, the tests may be more experimental and less accurate. In addition, results may not be reported to participants, or it may take a much longer time to receive any results. To access the contact information for the research laboratory performing genetic testing for mitochondrial disorders (including MELAS), click here.  Please note:  Most of the laboratories listed through GeneTests do not accept direct contact from patients and their families; therefore, if you are interested in learning more, you will need to work with a health care provider or a genetics professional.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
