<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004079" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5053/mitochondrial-complex-ii-deficiency">
<Focus>Mitochondrial complex II deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1855008</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Complex 2 mitochondrial respiratory chain deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Succinate CoQ reductase deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mitochondrial respiratory chain complex II deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Succinate dehydrogenase deficiency</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004079-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Mitochondrial complex II deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complex II deficiency is a mitochondrial disease. Mitochondria are specialized compartments in cells that create more than 90% of the energy needed by the body. In mitochondrial diseases, the mitochondria don&apos;t work correctly resulting in less energy in the cell, cell injury and cell death. The signs and symptoms of mitochondrial complex II deficiency can vary greatly from severe life-threatening symptoms in infancy to muscle disease beginning in adulthood. Complex II deficiency can be caused by mutations in the SDHA, SDHB, SDHD, or SDHAF1 genes. In many cases the underlying gene mutations cannot be identified. Complex II deficiency is inherited in an autosomal recessive fashion. Complex II deficiency gene mutation carriers may be at an increased risk for certain cancers.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004079-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Mitochondrial complex II deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Mitochondrial complex II deficiency? The signs and symptoms of mitochondrial complex II deficiency can vary greatly from severe life-threatening symptoms in infancy to muscle disease beginning in adulthood. Many factors affect symptom and symptom severity, including what gene mutation is involved. Many genes must work together to ensure that the enzyme, complex II (succinate dehydrogenase), can perform its job normally in the body. Changes in the SDHA, SDHB, SDHC, SDHD, SDHAF1, or SDHAF2 genes can all potentially cause complex II deficiency. Much of what we know today about the signs and symptoms of complex II deficiency are based on articles which describe individual patients. Due to the rarity of this condition and the complexity of its cause, it is very difficult to predict how a person will be affected. We strongly recommend that you work with your or your childs healthcare provider to learn more about how the deficiency is affecting your or your childs health. In the meantime, we have summarized symptoms of complex II deficiency which have been described in case reports: Inheriting two SDHA gene mutations has caused myoclonic seizures and Leighs syndrome. Leigh syndrome is a severe neurological disorder that typically arises in the first year of life. This condition is characterized by progressive loss of mental and movement abilities (psychomotor regression) and typically results in death within a couple of years, usually due to respiratory failure. A small number of people develop symptoms in adulthood or have symptoms that worsen more slowly. The first signs of Leigh syndrome seen in infancy are usually vomiting, diarrhea, and difficulty swallowing (dysphagia) that leads to eating problems. Click here to visit Genetics Home Reference and learn more about Leigh syndrome. Inheriting two SDHB gene mutations can cause leukodystrophy. Leukodystrophies affect the myelin sheath, the material that surrounds and protects nerve cells. Damage to this sheath slows down or blocks messages between the brain and the rest of the body. This leads to problems with movement, speaking, vision, hearing, and mental and physical development. Most of the leukodystrophies appear during infancy or childhood. They can be hard to detect early because children seem healthy at first. However, symptoms gradually get worse over time.  Click here to visit MedlinePlus.gov and learn more about leukodystprohy. Inheriting two SDHAF1 gene mutations can cause severe progressive leukoencephalopathy beginning in infancy. Leukoencephalopathy refers to the degeneration of the white matter of the brain.  It is usually diagnosed by MRI. It causes cognitive impairment, increased muscle tone, and hyperactive reflexes. Inheriting two SDHD gene mutations can cause progressive loss of mental and movement abilities (psychomotor retardation), and seizures. Signs and symptoms may begin in infancy and progress through childhood. Complex II deficiency has also been described in association with dilated cardiomyopathy (and heart failure in childhood), hemolytic uremic syndrome and rhabdomyolysis, congenital dislocation of the hip joint, progressive encephalomyopathy (a disorder affecting the brain and skeletal muscle, usually causing weakness) with dementia, and KearnsSayre syndrome. Case reports have also demonstrated that people who have only a single mutation in one of these genes may also be at risk for health problems: Having one SDHA gene mutation caused optic atrophy, ataxia, proximal myopathy in adulthood. Having one mutation in the SDHA, SDHB, SDHC, SDHAF2, or SDHD gene can cause an increased risk for paragangliomas and/or pheochromocytomas. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Mitochondrial complex II deficiency. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal mitochondria in muscle tissue - Ataxia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Babinski sign - Cognitive impairment - Decreased activity of mitochondrial complex II - Developmental regression - Dilated cardiomyopathy - Dystonia - Exercise intolerance - Flexion contracture - Hyperreflexia - Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy - Increased intramyocellular lipid droplets - Increased serum lactate - Infantile onset - Leukoencephalopathy - Muscle weakness - Myoclonus - Neonatal hypotonia - Nystagmus - Ophthalmoplegia - Optic atrophy - Phenotypic variability - Pigmentary retinopathy - Progressive leukoencephalopathy - Ptosis - Ragged-red muscle fibers - Seizures - Short stature - Spasticity - Stress/infection-induced lactic acidosis - Visual impairment - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004079-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Mitochondrial complex II deficiency inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes mitochondrial complex II deficiency? Many genes must work together to ensure that the enzyme, complex II (succinate dehydrogenase), can perform its job normally in the body. Changes in the SDHA, SDHB, SDHC, SDHD, SDHAF1, and SDHAF2 genes can all potentially cause complex II deficiency. Complex II deficiency is inherited in an autosomal recessive fashion. This means that a person must inherit a gene mutation from both their mother and father in order to develop complex II deficiency. People who have a single mutation are called carriers. Carriers of complex II deficiency may be at an increased risk for certain health problems, including for paragangliomas and/or pheochromocytomas.[8676]</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004079-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Mitochondrial complex II deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might mitochondrial complex II deficiency be treated? Treatment options for complex II deficiency may be similar to those for other mitochondrial disorders in general.[8677] The United Mitochondrial Disease Foundation (UMDF) provides detailed information on treatment through their Web site at: http://www.umdf.org/site/pp.aspx?c=8qKOJ0MvF7LUG&amp;b=7934635 We strongly recommend that you discuss this information with a healthcare provider.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
