<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004334" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10214/neonatal-intrahepatic-cholestasis-caused-by-citrin-deficiency">
<Focus>Neonatal intrahepatic cholestasis caused by citrin deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1863844</CUI>
			<CUI>C0008372</CUI>
			<CUI>C1997910</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>NICCD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Neonatal-onset citrullinemia type II</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Citrin deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Neonatal-onset citrullinemia type 2</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004334-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Neonatal intrahepatic cholestasis caused by citrin deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Neonatal intrahepatic cholestasis caused by citrin deficiency (NICCD) is a liver condition is also known as neonatal-onset type II citrullinemia. NICCD blocks the flow of bile (a digestive fluid produced by the liver) and prevents the body from processing certain nutrients properly. This leads to transient intrahepatic cholestasis and variable liver dysfunction in children younger than one year of age. NICCD is generally not severe, and symptoms disappear by age one year with appropriate treatment. Years or even decades later, however, some of these individuals develop the characteristic features of adult-onset type II citrullinemia. NICCD is caused by mutations in the SLC25A13 gene. This condition is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004334-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Neonatal intrahepatic cholestasis caused by citrin deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Neonatal intrahepatic cholestasis caused by citrin deficiency? Neonatal intrahepatic cholestasis caused by citrin deficiency (NICCD) is characterized by transient intrahepatic cholestasis, diffuse fatty liver, hepatic fibrosis, low birth weight, growth retardation, hypoproteinemia, decreased coagulation factors, hemolytic anemia, hepatomegaly, variable liver dysfunction, and/or hypoglycemia in children younger than one year of age. NICCD is generally not severe, and symptoms typically disappear by age one year with appropriate treatment. At around age two, children with NICCD begin to show a particular fondness for protein-rich and fatty foods and an aversion to sugary and carbohydrate-rich foods. One of more decades later, some of these individuals develop neuropsychiatric symptoms characteristic of adult-onset citrullinemia type II.   The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Neonatal intrahepatic cholestasis caused by citrin deficiency. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal recessive inheritance - Cirrhosis - Elevated plasma citrulline - Failure to thrive - Growth delay - Hyperbilirubinemia - Hypercholesterolemia - Hypermethioninemia - Hypertriglyceridemia - Hypoalphalipoproteinemia - Intrahepatic cholestasis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
