<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004350" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3943/nephrosis-deafness-urinary-tract-digital-malformation">
<Focus>Nephrosis deafness urinary tract digital malformation</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0011053</CUI>
			<CUI>C0018772</CUI>
			<CUI>C1850552</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Nephrosis with deafness and urinary tract and digital malformations</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004350-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Nephrosis deafness urinary tract digital malformation ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Nephrosis deafness urinary tract digital malformation? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Nephrosis deafness urinary tract digital malformation. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Conductive hearing impairment 90% Nephrotic syndrome 90% Abnormality of the ureter 50% Cleft palate 50% Hematuria 50% Hypertension 50% Proteinuria 50% Abnormal localization of kidney 7.5% Abnormality of lipid metabolism 7.5% Renal insufficiency 7.5% Bifid distal phalanx of the thumb - Bifid uvula - Hearing impairment - Partial duplication of the distal phalanx of the hallux - Short distal phalanx of hallux - Short distal phalanx of the thumb - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
