<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004887" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10723/pineal-cyst">
<Focus>Pineal cyst</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1335411</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004887-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pineal cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pineal cysts are cysts of the pineal gland which is a small organ in the brain that produces melatonin (a sleep-regulating hormone). Pineal cysts are relatively common and may be found by chance in up to 10% of people undergoing CT or MRI brain imaging. The exact cause of pineal cysts is unknown. Most people with pineal cysts do not have any signs or symptoms. Rarely, a pineal cyst may cause headaches, hydrocephalus, eye movement abnormalities, and Parinaud syndrome. Treatment is usually only considered when a cyst is causing symptoms, in which case surgery, stereotactic aspiration or endoscopic treatment may be recommended.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004887-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pineal cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of pineal cysts? People with pineal cysts generally do not have any signs or symptoms. Occasionally, pineal cysts may cause headaches, hydrocephalus, disturbances in vision (gaze palsy), Parinaud syndrome, and vertigo, in which case they are called symptomatic pineal cysts. Although rare, people with symptomatic pineal cysts may have other symptoms such as difficulty moving (ataxia); mental and emotional disturbances; seizures; sleep (circadian rhythm) troubles; hormonal imbalances that may cause precocious puberty; or secondary parkinsonism.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004887-3" qtype="causes">What causes Pineal cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes pineal cysts? The exact cause of pineal cysts is unknown. However, some studies suggest that bleeding in the pineal region or hormonal influences may play a role in the development and progression of pineal cysts.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004887-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Pineal cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might pineal cysts be treated? The best treatment options for pineal cysts depend on many factors, including the size of the cyst and whether or not it is associated with symptoms. For example, people with pineal cysts that do not cause symptoms may not require any form of treatment. However, they may need to have regular check-ups with a physician and follow up imaging if they have a large cyst (greater than 10-14 mm) or develop symptoms that could be related to the cyst. Treatment is often recommended for those individuals with pineal cysts that cause hydrocephalus; neurological symptoms such as headache or disturbance of vision; or enlargement of the cyst over time. Treatment may include surgery to remove the cyst, sometimes followed by the placement of a ventriculoperitoneal shunt. Aspiration of the contents of the cyst using ultrasound guidance has been explored as an alternative approach to surgery, and more recently, endoscopic procedures have been used. Radiation therapy may be recommended for cysts that recur after treatment. What is the appropriate follow-up for a pineal cyst found incidentally on MRI? There is limited information about what happens to a pineal cyst over time.  Several studies have shown that most pineal cysts remain stable and do not increase in size or cause symptoms later in life.  One study found that larger cysts were more likely to decrease in size over time, and there is currently no evidence that larger cysts are more likely to cause symptoms.   Because guidelines for management depend on an understanding of the typical course of a condition, and currently there is limited information about pineal cysts, there is some debate about the most appropriate way to manage these cysts.  Some studies do not recommend repeated magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the cyst.  Other studies state that repeated imaging of a pineal cyst is not required.  Another approach is for individuals with a pineal cyst to have regular check-ups with their personal doctor; if at any point new symptoms arise that may be related to the pineal cyst, repeat imaging should be done.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
