<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004878" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4361/pili-torti">
<Focus>Pili torti</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0263491</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Twisted hair</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Coarse, dry, lusterless hair which breaks off easily</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004878-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pili torti ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pili torti is a rare hair condition characterized by fragile hair. In pili torti hair has a flattened shaft with clusters of narrow twists at irregular intervals. Some cases may be inherited in autosomal dominant or autosomal recessive patterns, while others are acquired. In the inherited form, symptoms tend to be present from early childhood. It can occur alone or as part of other diseases like ectodermal dysplasias, Menke disease, Bjornstand syndrome, or Bazex syndrome. Acquired cases of pili torti may be associated with anorexia nervosa, malnutrition, oral retinoid treatment, or inflammatory scalp conditions (e.g., cutaneous lupus erythematousus). If pili torti is detected, it is necessary to investigate possible neurological disorders, hearing loss, and defects in the hair, nails, sweat glands and teeth. There is no specific treatment for this condition, but it may improve spontaneously after puberty. Click here to visit Medscape and view an image of a child with pili torti.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004878-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pili torti ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Pili torti? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Pili torti. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Coarse hair 90% Pili torti 90% Abnormality of dental enamel 50% Abnormality of the eyebrow 50% Abnormality of the nail 50% Alopecia 50% Hearing impairment 7.5% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Brittle hair - Dry hair - Hair shafts flattened at irregular intervals and twisted through 180 degrees about their axes - Hypoplasia of dental enamel - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004878-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Pili torti ?</Question>
			<Answer>Are there new therapies for treatment of pili torti? In acquired pili torti, treatment involves stopping the exposure to the causative agent (e.g., to oral retinoids) or condition (e.g., improving diet). There is no specific treatment for the inherited form of pili torti. It may improve spontaneously after puberty. If pili torti is detected, further evaluation to investigate possible neurological disorders, problems with hair, teeth or nails (ectodermal disturbances) and hearing loss is mandatory. It is generally recommended that people with pili torti try to avoid trauma to the hair. Suggestions include, sleeping on a satin pillowcase, avoiding excessive grooming, braiding, heat treatments, dying and coloring, reducing exposure to sunlight (wear a hat), using gentle shampoos diluted in warm water, adding conditioner to freshly washed hair, avoiding use of a hair dryer (or using it on cool setting), and avoiding oral retinoids (e.g., isotretinoin, acitretin) if possible. Some individuals with pili torti choose to wear a wig.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
