<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004954" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/108/polyglucosan-body-disease-adult">
<Focus>Polyglucosan body disease, adult</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3687361</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>APBD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Polyglucosan body disease, adult form</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004954-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Polyglucosan body disease, adult ?</Question>
			<Answer>Polyglucosan body disease affects the nervous system. Individuals with this condition usually begin to show signs of the disorder after the age of 40. Signs and symptoms include trouble walking due to decreased sensation in the legs (peripheral neuropathy) and muscle weakness and stiffness (spasticity). Individuals may also have trouble controlling bladder function as a result of damage to the nerves of the bladder (neurogenic bladder). Approximately half of the individuals with adult polyglucosan body disease also experience some degree of intellectual impairment. Mutations in the GBE1 gene can cause adult polyglucosan body disease. In some cases, no mutation can be found and the cause of the disease is not known. Adult polyglucosan body disease is thought to be inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Treatment usually involves a team of specialists who can address the specific symptoms such as walking difficulties, incontinence, and intellectual impairment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004954-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Polyglucosan body disease, adult ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Polyglucosan body disease, adult? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Polyglucosan body disease, adult. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal pyramidal signs 90% Abnormal renal physiology 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Erectile abnormalities 90% Gait disturbance 90% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 90% Hypertonia 90% Muscle weakness 90% Peripheral neuropathy 90% Behavioral abnormality 50% Skin ulcer 50% Abnormality of extrapyramidal motor function 7.5% Developmental regression 7.5% EMG abnormality 7.5% Incoordination 7.5% Limitation of joint mobility 7.5% Abnormal upper motor neuron morphology - Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Adult onset - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Distal sensory impairment - Paresthesia - Slow progression - Tetraparesis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
