<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004452" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10698/noonan-syndrome-2">
<Focus>Noonan syndrome 2</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
			<CUI>C1854469</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>NS2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Noonan syndrome autosomal recessive</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Autosomal recessive Noonan syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Noonan syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004452-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Noonan syndrome 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Noonan syndrome is a genetic disorder that causes abnormal development of multiple parts of the body. Features of Noonan syndrome may include a distinctive facial appearance, short stature, a broad or webbed neck, congenital heart defects, bleeding problems, skeletal malformations, and developmental delay. Noonan syndrome may be caused by mutations in any one of several genes including the PTPN11, KRAS, RAF1, SOS1, NRAS and BRAF genes. It is sometimes referred to as a specific subtype based on the responsible gene in an affected person. Noonan syndrome is typically inherited in an autosomal dominant manner but many cases are due to a new mutation and are not inherited from an affected parent.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004452-2" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Noonan syndrome 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Noonan syndrome be treated? Management generally focuses on the specific signs and symptoms present in each person. Treatments for the complications of Noonan syndrome (such as cardiovascular abnormalities) are generally standard and do not differ from treatment in the general population. Developmental disabilities are addressed by early intervention programs and individualized education strategies. Treatment for serious bleeding depends upon the specific factor deficiency or platelet abnormality. Growth hormone treatment increases growth velocity. More detailed information about treatment for Noonan syndrome can be viewed on the GeneReviews Web site.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
