<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004008" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/895/microcephalic-primordial-dwarfism-montreal-type">
<Focus>Microcephalic primordial dwarfism, Montreal type</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0342573</CUI>
			<CUI>C1859468</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Bird-headed dwarfism with features of premature senility</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Premature senility, premature graying and loss of scalp hair and wrinkled skin of the palms</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dwarfism</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004008-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Microcephalic primordial dwarfism, Montreal type ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Microcephalic primordial dwarfism, Montreal type? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Microcephalic primordial dwarfism, Montreal type. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal dermatoglyphics 90% Abnormal hair quantity 90% Abnormality of the nipple 90% Abnormality of the palate 90% Carious teeth 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Convex nasal ridge 90% Cryptorchidism 90% Dental malocclusion 90% Dry skin 90% EEG abnormality 90% Hernia of the abdominal wall 90% Hyperhidrosis 90% Hyperreflexia 90% Hypertonia 90% Kyphosis 90% Lipoatrophy 90% Low posterior hairline 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Microcephaly 90% Premature graying of hair 90% Ptosis 90% Reduced bone mineral density 90% Scoliosis 90% Shagreen patch 90% Short stature 90% Vertebral segmentation defect 90% Alopecia of scalp - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Brain very small - Excessive wrinkling of palmar skin - Intellectual disability - Large eyes - Narrow face - Retrognathia - Severe short stature - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
