<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004504" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4038/oculocutaneous-albinism-type-2">
<Focus>Oculocutaneous albinism type 2</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0268495</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>OCA2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Oculocutaneous albinism tyrosinase positive</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Albinism 2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Albinism, oculocutaneous, type 2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Albinoidism</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004504-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Oculocutaneous albinism type 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Oculocutaneous albinism type 2 is a genetic condition that affects the coloring (pigmentation) of the skin, hair, and eyes. Affected individuals typically have very fair skin and white or light-colored hair. Long-term sun exposure greatly increases the risk of skin damage and skin cancers, including an aggressive form of skin cancer called melanoma, in people with this condition. This condition also reduces pigmentation of the colored part of the eye (the iris) and the light-sensitive tissue at the back of the eye (the retina). People with this condition usually have vision problems such as reduced sharpness; nystagmus and strabismus; and increased sensitivity to light (photophobia). This condition is caused by mutations in the OCA2 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive fashion.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004504-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Oculocutaneous albinism type 2 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Oculocutaneous albinism type 2? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Oculocutaneous albinism type 2. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Ocular albinism 90% Freckling 50% Nystagmus 50% Optic atrophy 50% Photophobia 50% Visual impairment 50% Melanoma 7.5% Neoplasm of the skin 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Albinism - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Blue irides - Freckles in sun-exposed areas - Hypopigmentation of the fundus - Hypoplasia of the fovea - Red hair - Reduced visual acuity - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
