<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004532" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7251/ollier-disease">
<Focus>Ollier disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0014084</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Dyschondroplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Enchondromatosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Multiple cartilaginous enchondroses</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Multiple enchondromatosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004532-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ollier disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ollier disease is a skeletal disorder characterized by an asymmetric distribution of cartilagenous tumors (endochondromas) which may lead to skeletal deformities and limb-length discrepancy.[3] This condition primarily affects the long bones and cartilage of the joints of the arms and legs, specifically the area where the shaft and head of a long bone meet (metaphyses). Clinical manifestations often appear in the first decade of life. The cause is unknown. There is no medical treatment, although surgery may be indicated in cases where complications (pathological fractures, growth defect, malignant transformation) arise.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004532-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ollier disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Ollier disease? Clinical manifestations in Ollier disease often appear in the first decade of life and usually start with the appearance of palpable bony masses on a finger or a toe, an asymetric shortening of an extremity with limping, and skeletal deformities which may be associated with pathologic fractures. Enchondromas frequently affect the long tubular bones, particularly the tibia, the femur, and/or the fibula; flat bones, especially the pelvis, can also be affected. The lesions may affect multiple bones and are usually asymetrically distributed, exclusively or predominantly affecting one side of the body. Affected bones are often shortened and deformed. Indeed, bone shortening may be the only clinical sign of the disease. These bone shortenings are often associated with bone bending and curving, and may lead to limitations in articular movement. Forearm deformities are frequently encountered. In childhood, the lesions are subjected to pathologic fractures. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Ollier disease. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the metaphyses 90% Cavernous hemangioma 90% Micromelia 90% Osteolysis 90% Visceral angiomatosis 90% Bone pain 50% Limitation of joint mobility 50% Abnormality of coagulation 7.5% Anemia 7.5% Lymphangioma 7.5% Ovarian neoplasm 7.5% Platyspondyly 7.5% Precocious puberty 7.5% Skin ulcer 7.5% Thrombophlebitis 7.5% Chondrosarcoma - Multiple enchondromatosis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004532-3" qtype="causes">What causes Ollier disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Ollier disease? The exact cause of Ollier disease is not known. It is usually a sporadic, non-familial disorder, however, in some cases, it may be inherited as an autosomal dominant genetic trait.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004532-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Ollier disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Ollier disease be treated? There is no specific medical treatment for Ollier disease. Surgery is indicated in cases where complications (pathological fractures, growth defect, malignant transformation) arise.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
