<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004337" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/330/neonatal-progeroid-syndrome">
<Focus>Neonatal progeroid syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0406586</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Wiedemann-Rautenstrauch syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Progeroid syndrome neonatal</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Wiedemann Rautenstrauch syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004337-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Neonatal progeroid syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Neonatal progeroid syndrome is a rare genetic syndrome characterized by an aged appearance at birth. Other signs and symptoms include intrauterine growth restriction, feeding difficulties, distinctive craniofacial features, hypotonia, developmental delay and mild to severe intellectual disability. In most cases, affected infants pass away before age 7 months, but rare reports exist of survival into the teens or early 20s. Although the exact underlying cause of neonatal progeroid syndrome is unknown, it is likely a genetic condition that is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Treatment is symptomatic and supportive.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004337-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Neonatal progeroid syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Neonatal progeroid syndrome? The signs and symptoms of neonatal progeroid syndrome vary but may include: Subcutaneous lipoatrophy (deficiency or absence of the fat layer beneath the skin) which gives infants an aged appearance at birth Intrauterine growth restriction Failure to thrive Feeding difficulties Distinctive craniofacial features such as a triangular face; large skull with wide anterior (front) fontanelle; small, underdeveloped facial bones; natal teeth; low-set, posteriorly (towards the back) rotated ears, ectropion; and/or unusually sparse scalp hair, eyebrows, and eyelashes Thin arms and legs with disproportionately large hands and feet Small fingers and toes with underdeveloped nails Osteopenia (low bone density) Horizontal nystagmus Developmental delay Mild to severe intellectual disability The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Neonatal progeroid syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal hair quantity 90% Abnormality of the eyelashes 90% Abnormality of the fontanelles or cranial sutures 90% Abnormality of the hip bone 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the eyebrow 90% Arachnodactyly 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Delayed skeletal maturation 90% Frontal bossing 90% Hearing impairment 90% High forehead 90% Intrauterine growth retardation 90% Laryngomalacia 90% Lipoatrophy 90% Macrocephaly 90% Narrow mouth 90% Short stature 90% Thin skin 90% Triangular face 90% Advanced eruption of teeth 50% Cerebral cortical atrophy 50% Convex nasal ridge 50% Cryptorchidism 50% Ventriculomegaly 50% Abnormality of chromosome stability 7.5% Limitation of joint mobility 7.5% Long penis 7.5% Flexion contracture 5% Hypertriglyceridemia 5% Hypospadias 5% Abnormality of cardiovascular system morphology - Absence of subcutaneous fat - Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the earlobes - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Blue sclerae - Congenital onset - Decreased subcutaneous fat - Delayed closure of the anterior fontanelle - Dysphagia - Ectropion - Entropion - Failure to thrive - Feeding difficulties - Gynecomastia - Hypertelorism - Hypoplastic ilia - Hypotrichosis - Increased serum testosterone level - Intellectual disability - Intention tremor - Large hands - Long fingers - Long foot - Long toe - Low-set ears - Malar flattening - Muscular hypotonia - Narrow nasal ridge - Natal tooth - Nystagmus - Parietal bossing - Prominent scalp veins - Recurrent respiratory infections - Short femur - Short humerus - Small nail - Sparse eyebrow - Sparse eyelashes - Sparse scalp hair - Sudanophilic leukodystrophy - Thin ribs - Truncal ataxia - Upslanted palpebral fissure - Widely patent fontanelles and sutures - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004337-3" qtype="causes">What causes Neonatal progeroid syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes neonatal progeroid syndrome? The exact underlying cause of neonatal progeroid syndrome is unknown. Scientists suspect that it is a genetic condition; however, a disease-causing gene has not been identified.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004337-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Neonatal progeroid syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is neonatal progeroid syndrome inherited? Although the underlying genetic cause of neonatal progeroid syndrome is unknown, studies suggest that it is likely inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. This means that to be affected, a person must have a mutation in both copies of the responsible gene in each cell. The parents of an affected person usually each carry one mutated copy of the gene and are referred to as carriers. Carriers typically do not show signs or symptoms of the condition. When two carriers of an autosomal recessive condition have children, each child has a 25% (1 in 4) risk to have the condition, a 50% (1 in 2) risk to be a carrier like each of the parents, and a 25% chance to not have the condition and not be a carrier.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004337-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Neonatal progeroid syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is neonatal progeroid syndrome diagnosed? A diagnosis of neonatal progeroid syndrome is made based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. Rarely, a diagnosis may be suspected before birth if concerning features are viewed on ultrasound; however, most cases are diagnosed shortly after birth.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004337-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Neonatal progeroid syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might neonatal progeroid syndrome be treated? Because neonatal progeroid syndrome affects many different systems of the body, medical management is often provided by a team of doctors and other healthcare professionals. Treatment varies based on the signs and symptoms present in each person. For example, a feeding tube may be recommended in infants with feeding difficulties who have trouble putting on weight.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
