<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004202" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3834/multiple-pterygium-syndrome-lethal-type">
<Focus>Multiple pterygium syndrome lethal type</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265261</CUI>
			<CUI>C3151529</CUI>
			<CUI>C1854678</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pterygium syndrome multiple lethal type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lethal multiple pterygium syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>LMPS</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004202-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Multiple pterygium syndrome lethal type ?</Question>
			<Answer>Multiple pterygium syndrome lethal type is a very rare genetic condition affecting the skin, muscles and skeleton. It is characterized by minor facial abnormalities, prenatal growth deficiency, spine defects, joint contractures, and webbing (pterygia) of the neck, elbows, back of the knees, armpits, and fingers.  Fetuses with this condition are usually not born. Some of the prenatal complications include cystic hygroma, hydrops, diaphragmatic hernia, polyhydramnios, underdevelopment of the heart and lungs, microcephaly, bone fusions, joint dislocations, spinal fusion, and bone fractures. Both X-linked and autosomal recessive inheritance have been proposed. Mutations in the CHRNG, CHRNA1, and CHRND genes have been found to cause this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004202-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Multiple pterygium syndrome lethal type ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Multiple pterygium syndrome lethal type? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Multiple pterygium syndrome lethal type. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the nose 90% Amniotic constriction ring 90% Camptodactyly of finger 90% Cystic hygroma 90% Epicanthus 90% Hydrops fetalis 90% Intrauterine growth retardation 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Polyhydramnios 90% Popliteal pterygium 90% Upslanted palpebral fissure 90% Webbed neck 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the lungs 50% Cleft palate 50% Hypertelorism 50% Long philtrum 50% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 50% Narrow mouth 50% Short thorax 50% Abnormal dermatoglyphics 7.5% Abnormality of the upper urinary tract 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the cerebellum 7.5% Congenital diaphragmatic hernia 7.5% Cryptorchidism 7.5% Intestinal malrotation 7.5% Malignant hyperthermia 7.5% Microcephaly 7.5% Skeletal muscle atrophy 7.5% Synostosis of joints 7.5% Abnormal cervical curvature - Abnormal facial shape - Akinesia - Amyoplasia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Depressed nasal ridge - Edema - Fetal akinesia sequence - Flexion contracture - Hypoplastic heart - Increased susceptibility to fractures - Joint dislocation - Low-set ears - Multiple pterygia - Pulmonary hypoplasia - Short finger - Thin ribs - Vertebral fusion - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
