<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004506" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7239/oculodentodigital-dysplasia">
<Focus>Oculodentodigital dysplasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0812437</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Oculo-dento-digital dysplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Oculo-dento-digital syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Oculodentodigital syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>ODDD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>ODD syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004506-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Oculodentodigital dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Oculodentodigital dysplasia is a condition that affects many parts of the body, particularly the eyes (oculo-), teeth (dento-), and fingers (digital). The condition is caused by mutations in the GJA1 gene. Most cases are inherited in an autosomal dominant pattern. Some cases are caused by a new mutation in the gene. A small number of cases follow an autosomal recessive pattern of inheritance. Management is multidisciplinary and based on specific symptoms. Early diagnosis is critical for prevention and treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004506-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Oculodentodigital dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Oculodentodigital dysplasia? Individuals with oculodentodigital dysplasia commonly have small eyes (microphthalmia) and other eye abnormalities that can lead to vision loss. They also frequently have tooth abnormalities, such as small or missing teeth, weak enamel, multiple cavities, and early tooth loss. Other common features of this condition include a thin nose and webbing of the skin (syndactyly) between the fourth and fifth fingers. Less common features of oculodentodigital dysplasia include sparse hair growth (hypotrichosis), brittle nails, an unusual curvature of the fingers (camptodactyly), syndactyly of the toes, small head size (microcephaly), and an opening in the roof of the mouth (cleft palate). Some affected individuals experience neurological problems such as a lack of bladder or bowel control, difficulty coordinating movements (ataxia), abnormal muscle stiffness (spasticity), hearing loss, and impaired speech (dysarthria). A few people with oculodentodigital dysplasia also have a skin condition called palmoplantar keratoderma. Palmoplantar keratoderma causes the skin on the palms and the soles of the feet to become thick, scaly, and calloused. Some features of oculodentodigital dysplasia are evident at birth, while others become apparent with age. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Oculodentodigital dysplasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of dental enamel 90% Anteverted nares 90% Broad columella 90% Camptodactyly of finger 90% Carious teeth 90% Cleft palate 90% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 90% Finger syndactyly 90% Microcornea 90% Narrow nasal bridge 90% Premature loss of primary teeth 90% Reduced number of teeth 90% Toe syndactyly 90% Underdeveloped nasal alae 90% Abnormal cortical bone morphology 50% Abnormal hair quantity 50% Abnormality of the fingernails 50% Abnormality of the metaphyses 50% Abnormality of the urinary system 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the cerebellum 50% Broad alveolar ridges 50% Cataract 50% Cerebral calcification 50% Cognitive impairment 50% Conductive hearing impairment 50% Craniofacial hyperostosis 50% External ear malformation 50% Gait disturbance 50% Glaucoma 50% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 50% High forehead 50% Hypermetropia 50% Hyperreflexia 50% Hypertelorism 50% Hypertonia 50% Hypotelorism 50% Incoordination 50% Mandibular prognathia 50% Median cleft lip 50% Muscle weakness 50% Myopia 50% Neurological speech impairment 50% Optic atrophy 50% Seizures 50% Short nose 50% Slow-growing hair 50% Visual impairment 50% Abnormal diaphysis morphology 7.5% Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 7.5% Abnormality of the clavicle 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the iris 7.5% Arrhythmia 7.5% Blepharophimosis 7.5% Brachydactyly syndrome 7.5% Deeply set eye 7.5% Epicanthus 7.5% Fine hair 7.5% Hypoglycemia 7.5% Madelung deformity 7.5% Non-midline cleft lip 7.5% Nystagmus 7.5% Palmoplantar keratoderma 7.5% Preaxial hand polydactyly 7.5% Short hallux 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Taurodontia 7.5% Umbilical hernia 7.5% Upslanted palpebral fissure 7.5% Ventricular septal defect 7.5% Abnormality of the pinna 5% Atria septal defect 5% Neurogenic bladder 5% 3-4 toe syndactyly - 4-5 finger syndactyly - Ataxia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Basal ganglia calcification - Cleft upper lip - Clinodactyly - Cubitus valgus - Dry hair - Dysarthria - Fragile nails - Hip dislocation - Hyperactive deep tendon reflexes - Hypoplasia of dental enamel - Intellectual disability - Joint contracture of the 5th finger - Microcephaly - Microdontia - Microphthalmia - Paraparesis - Premature loss of teeth - Selective tooth agenesis - Short middle phalanx of the 5th finger - Short palpebral fissure - Sparse hair - Spasticity - Tetraparesis - Thin anteverted nares - Vertebral hyperostosis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
