<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004068" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8410/miller-syndrome">
<Focus>Miller syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0812435</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
			<CUI>C0265257</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Genee-Wiedemann acrofacial dysostosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>GWAFD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Genee-Wiedemann syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Wildervanck-Smith syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Postaxial acrofacial dysostosis (POADS) syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004068-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Miller syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Miller syndrome is a rare condition that mainly affects the development of the face and limbs. Characteristic features include underdeveloped cheek bones, a very small lower jaw, cleft lip and/or palate, abnormalities of the eyes, absent fifth (pinky) fingers and toes, and abnormally formed bones in the forearms and lower legs. The severity of the disorder varies among affected individuals. Miller syndrome is caused by mutations in the DHODH gene. It is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004068-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Miller syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Miller syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Miller syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal dermatoglyphics 90% Abnormality of the ulna 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the radius 90% Cleft eyelid 90% Hypoplasia of the zygomatic bone 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Supernumerary nipple 90% Camptodactyly of finger 50% Conductive hearing impairment 50% Finger syndactyly 50% Non-midline cleft lip 50% Strabismus 7.5% Abnormality of the foot - Abnormality of the kidney - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Choanal atresia - Cleft palate - Cleft upper lip - Congenital hip dislocation - Conical tooth - Cryptorchidism - Cupped ear - Ectropion - Hypoplasia of the radius - Hypoplasia of the ulna - Low-set ears - Malar flattening - Micropenis - Midgut malrotation - Pectus excavatum - Postnatal growth retardation - Pyloric stenosis - Radioulnar synostosis - Short thumb - Supernumerary vertebrae - Syndactyly - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
