<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0004909" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7401/pityriasis-rubra-pilaris">
<Focus>Pityriasis rubra pilaris</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0032027</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>PRP</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Familial pityriasis rubra pilaris</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pityriasis rubra pilaris--familial type</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004909-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pityriasis rubra pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pityriasis rubra pilaris (PRP) refers to a group of skin conditions that cause constant inflammation and scaling of the skin. Affected people have reddish-orange colored patches; they may occur everywhere on the body or only on certain areas. There are several types of PRP, which are classified based on age of onset, body areas affected, and whether other associated conditions are present. PRP is usually sporadic (occurring randomly) but some forms may be inherited.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004909-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pityriasis rubra pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Pityriasis rubra pilaris? Features of this condition vary greatly between affected individuals. The onset is gradual in the familial type and can be more rapid in the acquired type. Redness and scaling of the face and scalp are often seen first, followed by redness and thickening of the palms and soles. Overall, the elbows, knees, backs of the hands and feet, and ankles are most commonly affected. A more widespread eruption consisting of scaling orange-red plaques can be observed on the trunk and extremities. The lesions may expand and coalesce and eventually cover the entire body. When the disease becomes widespread, the nails, mucous membranes and eyes may be affected. The familial type often persists throughout life, but the acquired form may have periods of remission (periods of time where symptoms improve or completely resolve). The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Pityriasis rubra pilaris. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Irregular hyperpigmentation 90% Palmoplantar keratoderma 90% Abnormality of the fingernails 50% Pruritus 50% Abnormality of the oral cavity 7.5% Eczema 7.5% Ichthyosis 7.5% Lichenification 7.5% Neoplasm 7.5% Pustule 7.5% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Subungual hyperkeratosis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004909-3" qtype="causes">What causes Pityriasis rubra pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes pityriasis rubra pilaris? In most cases, pityriasis rubra pilaris (PRP) occurs sporadically for unknown reasons. In a few families with the inherited form, familial PRP, the condition is caused by mutations in the CARD14 gene. This gene gives instructions for making a protein that turns on other proteins that regulate genes that control the body&apos;s immune responses and inflammatory reactions. It also protects cells from certain signals that would otherwise cause them to self-destruct. The CARD14 protein is particularly abundant in the skin. Mutations in the gene can cause a person to have an abnormal inflammatory response. Researchers are trying to find out how these mutations cause the specific features of familial PRP.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004909-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Pityriasis rubra pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might pityriasis rubra pilaris be treated? Treatment of pityriasis rubra pilaris (PRP) is mainly based on reports of patients&apos; experiences. No controlled trials have been done, so the effectiveness and safety of treatments is unclear. Currently there are no treatments approved by the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) or the European Medicines Agency (EMA) for use in PRP. Management of PRP often involves systemic and topical therapies combined. Topical therapies can help with the symptoms and may be enough for people with mild PRP. Topical treatments are usually combined with systemic therapy for PRP that affects a large part of the body. Most people need systemic therapy to control the condition. Oral retinoids (synthetic vitamin A derivatives) are usually preferred as a first-line systemic treatment for PRP. Methotrexate may be an alternative option for people who should not use systemic retinoids, or who don&apos;t respond to systemic retinoid therapy. For people who don&apos;t respond well to retinoid or methotrexate therapy, options may include biologic TNF-alpha inhibitors, azathioprine, cyclosporine, and/or phototherapy. Topical treatments used for PRP may include topical corticosteroids, keratolytics, tar, calcipotriol, topical tretinoin, and tazarotene. Some of the medications used to treat PRP can harm a developing fetus and are not recommended for use right before or during pregnancy. People seeking information about specific treatment options for themselves or family members should speak with their health care provider.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
