<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005548" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7627/septo-optic-dysplasia">
<Focus>Septo-optic dysplasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0338503</CUI>
			<CUI>C1855042</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Septooptic dysplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>De morsier syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Septo-optic dysplasia with growth hormone deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hypopituitarism and septooptic 'dysplasia'</Synonym>
		<Synonym>SOD</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005548-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Septo-optic dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Septo-optic dysplasia is a disorder of early brain development. The signs and symptoms vary from person to person; however, underdevelopment (hypoplasia) of the optic nerve, abnormal formation of structures along the midline of the brain, and pituitary hypoplasia are the characteristic findings. Recurring seizures, delayed development, and abnormal movements may be present in some people with septo-optic dysplasia. Although the exact cause of septo-optic dysplasia is unknown, it is believed that both genetic and environmental factors play a role. Viruses, medications, and blood flow disruption have all been suggested as possible environmental causes. Thus far, three genes (HESX1, OTX2, and SOX2) have been associated with septo-optic dysplasia. Typically, people do not have a family history of septo-optic dysplasia. However, there have been a few cases in which multiple family members have been diagnosed. Familial cases may follow an autosomal recessive or autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005548-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Septo-optic dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Septo-optic dysplasia? Symptoms may include blindness in one or both eyes, pupil dilation in response to light, nystagmus (a rapid, involuntary to-and-fro movement of the eyes), inward and outward deviation of the eyes, hypotonia (low muscle tone), and hormonal problems leading to slow growth, unusually short stature, low blood sugar, genital abnormalities and problems with sexual development. Seizures may also occur. In a few cases, jaundice (prolonged yellow skin discoloration) may occur at birth. Intellectual problems vary in severity among individuals. While some children with septo-optic dysplasia have normal intelligence, others have learning disabilities and mental retardation. Most, however, are developmentally delayed due to vision impairment or neurological problems. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Septo-optic dysplasia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Optic atrophy 90% Septo-optic dysplasia 90% Visual impairment 90% Anterior hypopituitarism 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 50% Cleft palate 50% Cryptorchidism 50% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 50% Hypoplasia of penis 50% Nystagmus 50% Seizures 50% Short stature 50% Strabismus 50% Abnormal renal physiology 7.5% Abnormality of the sense of smell 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the cerebellum 7.5% Autism 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Constipation 7.5% Diabetes insipidus 7.5% Dry skin 7.5% Hypohidrosis 7.5% Maternal diabetes 7.5% Obesity 7.5% Sensorineural hearing impairment 7.5% Sleep disturbance 7.5% Tracheoesophageal fistula 7.5% Absent septum pellucidum - Agenesis of corpus callosum - Anterior pituitary hypoplasia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Growth hormone deficiency - Optic disc hypoplasia - Optic nerve hypoplasia - Phenotypic variability - Polydactyly - Short finger - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005548-3" qtype="causes">What causes Septo-optic dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes septo-optic dysplasia? In most cases of septo-optic dysplasia, the cause of the disorder is unknown. Researchers suspect that a combination of genetic and environmental factors may play a role in causing this disorder. Proposed environmental risk factors include viral infections, specific medications, and a disruption in blood flow to certain areas of the brain during critical periods of development. At least three genes have been associated with septo-optic dysplasia, although mutations in these genes appear to be rare causes of this disorder. The three genes, HESX1, OTX2, and SOX2, all play important roles in embryonic development. In particular, they are essential for the formation of the eyes, the pituitary gland, and structures at the front of the brain (the forebrain) such as the optic nerves. Mutations in any of these genes disrupt the early development of these structures, which leads to the major features of septo-optic dysplasia. Researchers are looking for additional genetic changes that contribute to septo-optic dysplasia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0005548-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Septo-optic dysplasia inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is septo-optic dysplasia inherited?</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0005548-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Septo-optic dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Can septo-optic dysplasia be cured? There is no cure for septo-optic dysplasia. Treatment is symptomatic. Hormone deficiencies may be treated with hormone replacement therapy. The optical problems are generally not treatable. Vision, physical, and occupational therapies may be required.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
