<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005809" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6319/split-hand-foot-malformation">
<Focus>Split hand foot malformation</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2931018</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>SHFM</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ectrodactyly</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005809-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Split hand foot malformation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Split hand foot malformation (SHFM) is a type of birth defect that consists of missing digits (fingers and/or toes), a deep cleft down the center of the hand or foot, and fusion of remaining digits. The severity of this condition varies widely among affected individuals. SHFM is sometimes called ectrodactyly; however, this is a nonspecific term used to describe missing digits. SHFM may occur by itself (isolated) or it may be part of a syndrome with abnormalities in other parts of the body. At least six different forms of isolated SHFM have been described. Each type is associated with a different underlying genetic cause. SHFM1 has been linked to chromosome 7, and SHFM2 is linked to the X chromosome. SHFM3 is caused by a duplication of chromosome 10 at position 10q24. Changes (mutations) in the TP63 gene cause SHFM4. SHFM5 is linked to chromosome 2, and SHFM6 is caused by mutations in the WNT10B gene. SHFM may be inherited in an autosomal dominant, autosomal recessive, or X-linked manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005809-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Split hand foot malformation ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Split hand foot malformation? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Split hand foot malformation. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of chromosome segregation 90% Abnormality of the ankles 90% Abnormality of the metacarpal bones 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Abnormality of the wrist 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the radius 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the thumb 50% Cognitive impairment 50% Conductive hearing impairment 50% Cryptorchidism 50% Myopia 50% Narrow mouth 50% Proteinuria 50% Renal hypoplasia/aplasia 50% Renal insufficiency 50% Abnormality of the pinna 35% Hearing impairment 35% Cleft palate 33% Intellectual disability 33% Oligodactyly (feet) 33% Oligodactyly (hands) 33% Syndactyly 33% Abnormality of cardiovascular system morphology 13% Abnormality of the ulna 7.5% Absent hand 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the iris 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the tongue 7.5% Macrocephaly 7.5% Microdontia 7.5% Nystagmus 7.5% Prominent nasal bridge 7.5% Sensorineural hearing impairment 7.5% Short stature 7.5% Tarsal synostosis 7.5% Hypoplasia of the maxilla 5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia involving the metacarpal bones - Aplasia/Hypoplasia of metatarsal bones - Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the phalanges of the hand - Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the phalanges of the toes - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Broad hallux - Camptodactyly - Clinodactyly - Ectrodactyly - Finger syndactyly - High palate - Incomplete penetrance - Microretrognathia - Nail dystrophy - Renal hypoplasia - Ridged nail - Short metacarpal - Short phalanx of finger - Split foot - Split hand - Toe syndactyly - Triphalangeal thumb - X-linked inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005809-3" qtype="causes">What causes Split hand foot malformation ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes split hand foot malformation? Split hand foot malformation may occur as an isolated feature or it may be associated with a genetic syndrome. Researchers believe that a large number of mutations can cause split hand foot malformation. A few of which have been identified: FBXW4 and TP63. Most commonly the conditions are passed through families in an autosomal dominant fashion with reduced penetrance. In autosomal dominant inheritance an affected parent would have a 1 in 2 or 50% chance with each pregnancy of passing the genetic defect to his/her offspring. In conditions with reduced penetrance a person who inherits the underlying genetic defect, may never develop the condition. More rarely other forms of inheritance have been reported (e.g., autosomal-recessive, X-linked, chromosome deletions, chromosome duplications).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
