<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005695" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9637/spastic-diplegia-cerebral-palsy">
<Focus>Spastic diplegia cerebral palsy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0270804</CUI>
			<CUI>C0221165</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Cerebral palsy spastic diplegic</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005695-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Spastic diplegia cerebral palsy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Spastic diplegia cerebral palsy is a form of cerebral palsy, a neurological condition that usually appears in infancy or early childhood and permanently affects muscle control and coordination. Affected people have increased muscle tone which leads to spasticity (stiff or tight muscles and exaggerated reflexes) in the legs. The arm muscles are generally less affected or not affected at all. Other signs and symptoms may include delayed motor or movement milestones (i.e. rolling over, sitting, standing); walking on toes; and a &quot;scissored&quot; gait (style of walking). It occurs when the portion of the brain that controls movement is damaged or develops abnormally. The exact underlying cause is often unknown; however, the condition has been associated with genetic abnormalities; congenital brain malformations; maternal infections or fevers; and/or injury before, during or shortly after birth. There is no cure, and treatment options vary depending on the signs and symptoms present in each person and the severity of the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005695-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Spastic diplegia cerebral palsy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of spastic diplegia cerebral palsy? The symptoms and severity of spastic diplegia cerebral palsy vary significantly from person to person. It is a form of cerebral palsy, a neurological condition that usually appears in infancy or early childhood and permanently affects muscle control and coordination. Affected people have increased muscle tone which leads to stiff or tight muscles and exaggerated reflexes (spasticity). Other signs and symptoms may include delayed motor or movement milestones (i.e. rolling over, sitting, standing); walking on toes; and a &quot;scissored&quot; gait (style of walking). Although symptoms may change as a person gets older, the condition does not get worse over time (progress). Cerebral palsy, including spastic diplegia cerebral palsy, can be associated with a variety of other health problems, including: Intellectual disability Learning disabilities Seizures Delayed growth Spinal abnormalities Osteoarthritis Impaired vision Hearing loss Speech and language disorders Poor bladder control Contractures</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005695-3" qtype="causes">What causes Spastic diplegia cerebral palsy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes spastic diplegia cerebral palsy? Spastic diplegia cerebral palsy occurs when the portion of the brain that controls movement is damaged or develops abnormally. This usually occurs before birth, but can happen at any time while the brain is still developing (usually before age 2). In many cases, the exact underlying cause is unknown; however, the condition has been associated with genetic abnormalities; congenital brain malformations; maternal infections or fevers; injury before, during or shortly after birth; problems with blood flow to the brain; and severe lack of oxygen to the brain. The following medical conditions or events may increase the risk for a child to be born with or develop cerebral palsy: Premature birth Low birth weight (less than 5 and a half pounds) Mothers with infections or high fevers during pregnancy Multiple births (twins, triplets and other multiples) Rh incompatibility (blood type incompatibility between mother and child) Mothers with thyroid abnormalities, intellectual disability, excess protein in the urine, or seizures Breech presentation Complicated labor and delivery Low Apgar score Newborn jaundice</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0005695-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Spastic diplegia cerebral palsy inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is spastic diplegia cerebral palsy inherited? Scientists have found that family members of people with cerebral palsy, including spastic diplegia cerebral palsy, have an increased risk of developing the condition. The exact risk depends on the how closely the family members are related: A child with a sibling (brother, sister) or parent with cerebral palsy would have a six- to nine-fold increased risk of developing the condition (actual risk: 1 to 1.5%) A child with a half sibling with cerebral palsy would have up to a three-fold risk of developing the condition (actual risk: less than 1%) A child with a first cousin with cerebral palsy would have a 1.5-fold increased risk of developing the condition (actual risk: less than 1%) This suggests that there may be a genetic component in some cases of cerebral palsy. However, the inheritance is likely multifactorial which means the condition is caused by multiple genes interacting with each other and with environmental factors.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0005695-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Spastic diplegia cerebral palsy ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is spastic diplegia cerebral palsy diagnosed? A diagnosis of spastic diplegia cerebral palsy is based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. However, the following tests may be recommended to rule out other conditions that cause similar features. Blood tests CT scan of the head MRI scan of the head Electroencephalogram (EEG) Electromyography For more information about the diagnosis of spastic diplegia cerebral palsy and other types of cerebral palsy, please click here.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0005695-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Spastic diplegia cerebral palsy ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might spastic diplegia cerebral palsy be treated? Treatment of spastic diplegia cerebral palsy varies based on the signs and symptoms present in each person and the severity of the condition. Affected people are often cared for by a team of healthcare providers who specialize in a variety of different medical fields (i.e. neurologists, rehabilitation physicians, social workers, physical therapists, etc). Orthotic devices (such as a walker, wheelchair or leg braces), physical therapy, and occupational therapy can help improve independent mobility. Certain medications may be prescribed to relax stiff, contracted, or overactive muscles. Orthopedic surgery is often recommended for severely affected people who have symptoms that make walking and moving difficult or painful. For more information on the treatment of spastic diplegia cerebral palsy and other forms of cerebral palsy, please click here.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
