<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005453" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/319/sacrococcygeal-teratoma">
<Focus>Sacrococcygeal Teratoma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0559459</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005453-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sacrococcygeal Teratoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>A sacrococcygeal teratoma is a tumor that grows at the base of the spine in a developing fetus.  It occurs in one in 40,000 newborns and girls are four times more likely to be affected than boys.  Though it is usually benign, there is a possibility that the teratoma could become malignant.  As such, the recommended treatment of a teratoma is complete removal of the tumor by surgery, performed soon after the birth.  If not all of the tumor is removed during the initial surgery, the teratoma may grow back (recur) and additional surgeries may be needed.  Studies have found that sacrococcygeal teratomas recur in up to 22% of cases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005453-2" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Sacrococcygeal Teratoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might a sacrococcygeal teratoma be treated? The treatment for sacrococcygeal teratoma (SCT) typically involves surgery to remove the tumor. Surgery occurs either in the prenatal period or shortly after delivery. The timing is dependent on the size of the tumor and the associated symptoms. To learn more about both prenatal and postnatal surgery for SCT, visit the following links from The Children&apos;s Hospital of Philadelphia (CHOP) http://www.chop.edu/treatments/fetal-surgery-sacrococcygeal-teratoma-sct/about#.VqGW_PkrJD8 http://www.chop.edu/treatments/postnatal-surgery-sacrococcygeal-teratoma-sct#.VqGX7vkrJD8</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
