<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005333" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4683/retinitis-pigmentosa-deafness-mental-retardation-and-hypogonadism">
<Focus>Retinitis pigmentosa, deafness, mental retardation, and hypogonadism</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0011053</CUI>
			<CUI>C0025362</CUI>
			<CUI>C0020619</CUI>
			<CUI>C0035334</CUI>
			<CUI>C0018772</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Insulin-resistant diabetes with acanthosis nigricans, hypogonadism, pigmentary retinopathy, deafness, and mental retardation</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005333-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Retinitis pigmentosa, deafness, mental retardation, and hypogonadism ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Retinitis pigmentosa, deafness, mental retardation, and hypogonadism? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Retinitis pigmentosa, deafness, mental retardation, and hypogonadism. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Acanthosis nigricans 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Gynecomastia 90% Hyperinsulinemia 90% Nystagmus 90% Sensorineural hearing impairment 90% Short stature 90% Type II diabetes mellitus 90% Atypical scarring of skin 50% Brachydactyly syndrome 50% Broad foot 50% Cataract 50% Coarse facial features 50% Cryptorchidism 50% Delayed skeletal maturation 50% Dry skin 50% Obesity 50% Secondary amenorrhea 50% Short toe 50% Visual impairment 50% Cerebral cortical atrophy 7.5% Hyperlordosis 7.5% Kyphosis 7.5% Polycystic ovaries 7.5% Abnormality of the ear - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Broad palm - Cerebellar atrophy - Cerebral atrophy - Elevated hepatic transaminases - Hypergonadotropic hypogonadism - Insulin-resistant diabetes mellitus - Intellectual disability - Pigmentary retinopathy - Rod-cone dystrophy - Sparse hair - Subcapsular cataract - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
