<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005078" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5170/progressive-deafness-with-stapes-fixation">
<Focus>Progressive deafness with stapes fixation</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1397523</CUI>
			<CUI>C1837645</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T020</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Thies Reis syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Thies-Reis syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Stapedo-vestibular ankylosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005078-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Progressive deafness with stapes fixation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Progressive deafness with stapes fixation, also known as Thies Reis syndrome, is a form of conductive or mixed hearing loss caused by fixation of the stapes. The stapes is one of the tiny bones in the middle ear. It rests in the entrance to the inner ear, allowing sounds to pass to the inner ear. If it becomes fixated, sound waves cannot pass through to the inner ear, resulting in loss of hearing. This condition may be associated with a number of conditions, including ostosclerosis, Paget&apos;s disease and osteogenesis imperfecta, or it may be found in isolation. It may also result from chronic ear infections (otitis media with tympanosclerosis). The progression of hearing loss is generally slow, rarely profound, and usually resolves following treatment. Conductive hearing loss can be restored through surgery or hearing aids. Sensorineural hearing loss can be managed with hearing aids or cochlear implants.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005078-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Progressive deafness with stapes fixation ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Progressive deafness with stapes fixation? Deafness, progressive with stapes fixation is characterized by bilateral hearing loss - either conductive or mixed - and stapes fixation. Hearing loss typically begins between ages 8 and 24. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Progressive deafness with stapes fixation. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal recessive inheritance - Bilateral conductive hearing impairment - Stapes ankylosis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005078-3" qtype="causes">What causes Progressive deafness with stapes fixation ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes deafness, progressive with stapes fixation? The exact cause of deafness, progressive with stapes fixation depends on whether it is associated with an underlying condition or infection. Isolated cases may be inherited.  Autosomal dominant, autosomal recessive, and X-linked cases have been reported. In some cases, no underlying cause can be identified.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0005078-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Progressive deafness with stapes fixation ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might deafness, progressive with stapes fixation be treated? Treatment for deafness, progressive with stapes fixation typically involves surgery. The conductive component of the hearing loss can be restored by surgery or hearing aids. The associated sensorineural component is managed by hearing aids or cochlear implants, depending on its severity. Stapedotomy (a procedure where a laser is used to make a hole in the stapes) or partial stapedectomy (removal of the stapes) with stapes replacement using a prostheses most commonly achieves satisfactory results with minimal complications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
