<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005981" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/6054/synovial-chondromatosis">
<Focus>Synovial Chondromatosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0029427</CUI>
			<CUI>C0008476</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Synovial osteochondromatosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005981-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Synovial Chondromatosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Synovial chondromatosis is a type of non-cancerous tumor that arises in the lining of a joint. The knee is most commonly affected, however it can affect any joint. The tumors begin as small nodules of cartilage. These nodules can separate and become loose within the joint. Some tumors may be no larger than a grain of rice. Synovial chondromatosis most commonly occurs in adults ages 20 to 50. Signs and symptoms may include pain, swelling, a decreased range of motion, and locking of the joint. The exact underlying cause of the condition is unknown. Treatment may involve surgery to remove the tumor. Recurrence of the condition is common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005981-2" qtype="causes">What causes Synovial Chondromatosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes synovial chondromatosis? The exact underlying cause of synovial chondromatosis is unknown. Some research suggests that trauma may play a role in its development because the condition primarily occurs in weight-bearing joints. Infection has also been considered as a contributing factor. The condition is not inherited. Synovial chondromatosis can reportedly occur as either a primary or secondary form. Primary synovial chondromatosis, which is more rare, occurs spontaneously and does not appear to relate to any pre-existing conditions. Secondary synovial chondromatosis is the more common form and often occurs when there is pre-existent osteoarthritis, rheumatoid arthritis, osteonecrosis, osteochondritis dissecans, neuropathic osteoarthropathy (which often occurs in diabetic individuals), tuberculosis, or osteochondral fractures (torn cartilage covering the end of a bone in a joint) in the affected individual.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
