<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005007" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10145/potocki-lupski-syndrome">
<Focus>Potocki-Lupski syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1970482</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>PTLS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Duplication 17p11.2 syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Potocki-Lupski syndrome (dup(17)(p11.2p11.2))</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005007-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Potocki-Lupski syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Potocki-Lupski syndrome (PTLS) is a genetic disorder characterized by the presence of an extra copy of a tiny portion of chromosome 17 (duplication of 17p11.2). People with this duplication often have low muscle tone, poor feeding, and failure to thrive during infancy. They may also present with delayed development of motor and verbal milestones. In addition, many individuals display some behaviors commonly associated with autism spectrum disorders. While most cases of Potocki-Lupski syndrome occur sporadically, in rare cases, it may be inherited. Treatment involves physical, occupational, and speech therapy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005007-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Potocki-Lupski syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Potocki-Lupski syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Potocki-Lupski syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of chromosome segregation 90% Abnormality of the pharynx 90% Apnea 90% Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder 90% Autism 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Muscular hypotonia 90% Neurological speech impairment 90% Broad forehead 50% EEG abnormality 50% Hypermetropia 50% Scoliosis 50% Triangular face 50% Abnormality of dental morphology 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 7.5% Dental malocclusion 7.5% Hearing impairment 7.5% Hypertelorism 7.5% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 7.5% Microcephaly 7.5% Short stature 7.5% Wide mouth 7.5% Hypothyroidism 5% Abnormal renal morphology - Abnormality of the cardiovascular system - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Delayed myelination - Dental crowding - Dysphasia - Echolalia - Expressive language delay - Failure to thrive - Feeding difficulties in infancy - Gastroesophageal reflux - Generalized hypotonia - High palate - Hyperactivity - Hypocholesterolemia - Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum - Intellectual disability, mild - Language impairment - Mandibular prognathia - Oral-pharyngeal dysphagia - Patent foramen ovale - Phenotypic variability - Poor eye contact - Prominent nasal tip - Receptive language delay - Seizures - Sleep apnea - Small for gestational age - Smooth philtrum - Sporadic - Stereotypic behavior - Trigonocephaly - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
