<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005690" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10091/sotos-syndrome">
<Focus>Sotos syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0175695</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Cerebral gigantism</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Distinctive facial appearance, overgrowth in childhood, and learning disabilities or delayed development</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005690-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sotos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sotos syndrome is a condition characterized mainly by distinctive facial features; overgrowth in childhood; and learning disabilities or delayed development. Facial features may include a long, narrow face; a high forehead; flushed (reddened) cheeks; a small, pointed chin; and down-slanting palpebral fissures. Affected infants and children tend to grow quickly; they are significantly taller than their siblings and peers and have a large head. Other signs and symptoms may include intellectual disability; behavioral problems; problems with speech and language; and/or weak muscle tone (hypotonia). Sotos syndrome is usually caused by a mutation in the NSD1 gene and is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. About 95% of cases are due to a new mutation in the affected person and occur sporadically (are not inherited).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005690-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sotos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Sotos syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Sotos syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Accelerated skeletal maturation 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Depressed nasal ridge 90% Frontal bossing 90% High forehead 90% Hypertelorism 90% Macrocephaly 90% Macrotia 90% Mandibular prognathia 90% Tall stature 90% Advanced eruption of teeth 50% Anteverted nares 50% Conductive hearing impairment 50% Dolichocephaly 50% Hypoglycemia 50% Obesity 50% Precocious puberty 50% Abnormality of the fingernails 7.5% Abnormality of the hip bone 7.5% Abnormality of the ureter 7.5% Behavioral abnormality 7.5% Coarse facial features 7.5% Craniosynostosis 7.5% Cryptorchidism 7.5% Displacement of the external urethral meatus 7.5% EEG abnormality 7.5% Genu valgum 7.5% Genu varum 7.5% Hyperreflexia 7.5% Neoplasm of the nervous system 7.5% Patent ductus arteriosus 7.5% Polycystic kidney dysplasia 7.5% Presacral teratoma 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Abnormal glucose tolerance - Atria septal defect - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Cavum septum pellucidum - Enlarged cisterna magna - Expressive language delay - High anterior hairline - High palate - Hypermetropia - Intellectual disability - Joint laxity - Large hands - Long foot - Narrow palate - Neonatal hypotonia - Nephroblastoma (Wilms tumor) - Nystagmus - Otitis media - Partial agenesis of the corpus callosum - Pes planus - Pointed chin - Poor coordination - Small nail - Sporadic - Ventricular septal defect - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005690-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Sotos syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Sotos syndrome inherited? Sotos syndrome is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. This means that having a mutation in only one of the 2 copies of the responsible gene (the NSD1 gene) is enough to cause signs and symptoms of the condition. 95% of people with Sotos syndrome do not inherit the condition from a parent. In these cases, the condition is the result of a new (de novo) mutation that occurred for the first time in the affected person. Only about 5% of people with Sotos syndrome have an affected parent and inherit the condition from that parent. If a parent of an affected person with an identified NSD1 mutation does not have any features of Sotos syndrome, that parent is very unlikely to have a mutation in the gene. This can be confirmed with genetic testing if the mutation has been identified in the child. If a person with Sotos syndrome has children, each child has a 50% (1 in 2) chance to inherit the mutation. However, the specific features and severity can vary from one generation to the next, so it is not possible to predict how a child will be affected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
