<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005819" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10726/spondylocostal-dysostosis-1">
<Focus>Spondylocostal dysostosis 1</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265343</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>SCDO1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Costovertebral dysplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Spondylocostal dysostosis 1 autosomal recessive</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005819-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Spondylocostal dysostosis 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Spondylocostal dysostosis is a group of conditions characterized by abnormal development of the bones in the spine and ribs. In the spine, the vertebrae are misshapen and fused. Many people with this condition have an abnormal side-to-side curvature of the spine (scoliosis). The ribs may be fused together or missing. These bone malformations lead to short, rigid necks and short midsections. Infants with spondylocostal dysostosis have small, narrow chests that cannot fully expand. This can lead to life-threatening breathing problems. Males with this condition are at an increased risk for inguinal hernia, where the diaphragm is pushed down, causing the abdomen to bulge out. There are several types of spondylocostal dysostosis. These types have similar features and are distinguished by their genetic cause and how they are inherited.  Spondylocostal dysostosis 1 is caused by mutations in the DLL3 gene. It is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Treatment is symptomatic and supportive and may include respiratory support and surgery to correct inguinal hernia and scoliosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005819-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Spondylocostal dysostosis 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Spondylocostal dysostosis 1? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Spondylocostal dysostosis 1. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 90% Abnormality of immune system physiology 90% Abnormality of the intervertebral disk 90% Abnormality of the ribs 90% Intrauterine growth retardation 90% Respiratory insufficiency 90% Scoliosis 90% Short neck 90% Short stature 90% Short thorax 90% Vertebral segmentation defect 90% Kyphosis 50% Abnormality of female internal genitalia 7.5% Abnormality of the ureter 7.5% Anomalous pulmonary venous return 7.5% Anteverted nares 7.5% Broad forehead 7.5% Camptodactyly of finger 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Congenital diaphragmatic hernia 7.5% Cryptorchidism 7.5% Depressed nasal bridge 7.5% Displacement of the external urethral meatus 7.5% Finger syndactyly 7.5% Long philtrum 7.5% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 7.5% Macrocephaly 7.5% Meningocele 7.5% Microcephaly 7.5% Prominent occiput 7.5% Spina bifida occulta 7.5% Umbilical hernia 7.5% Urogenital fistula 7.5% Abnormality of the odontoid process - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Block vertebrae - Death in infancy - Disproportionate short-trunk short stature - Hemivertebrae - Recurrent respiratory infections - Rib fusion - Severe short stature - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
