<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005086" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7338/progressive-hemifacial-atrophy">
<Focus>Progressive hemifacial atrophy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0015458</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Parry-Romberg syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hemifacial atrophy, progressive</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Romberg hemi-facial atrophy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005086-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Progressive hemifacial atrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Progressive hemifacial atrophy, or Parry-Romberg syndrome, is a condition that causes the breakdown of the skin and soft tissues of half of the face. Symptoms and severity vary from person to person. This condition tends to begin in childhood between the ages of 5 and 15 years, and worsen over the course of 2 to 10 years before stabilizing. In addition to the skin and soft tissues, the deterioration can involve the mouth and tongue, facial bones, eye socket, and eye. Other symptoms may include loss of facial hair, changes in skin color in affected areas, seizures, and episodes of severe facial pain. Treatment may involve reconstructive or microvascular surgery. Currently, the cause of the condition is unknown.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005086-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Progressive hemifacial atrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Progressive hemifacial atrophy? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Progressive hemifacial atrophy. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Irregular hyperpigmentation 90% Abnormality of the musculature 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the skin 50% Asymmetric growth 50% Seizures 50% Deeply set eye 7.5% Heterochromia iridis 7.5% Ptosis 7.5% Alopecia areata - Ataxia - Blepharophimosis - Delayed eruption of teeth - Dental malocclusion - Hemifacial atrophy - Horner syndrome - Kyphosis - Microtia - Migraine - Onset - Poliosis - Short mandibular rami - Sporadic - Trigeminal neuralgia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005086-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Progressive hemifacial atrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might progressive hemifacial atrophy  be treated?</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
