<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005216" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4614/pyomyositis">
<Focus>Pyomyositis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1704275</CUI>
			<CUI>C0041188</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005216-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pyomyositis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pyomyositis is rare bacterial infection of the skeletal muscle (the muscles used for movement). Signs and symptoms may include pain and tenderness of the affected muscle, fever, and abscess formation. If left untreated, the abscess may extend into the bone and joint or blood poisoning may occur. Approximately 90% of cases are caused by the bacterium, Staphylococcus aureus. Risk factors for the condition include strenuous activity, muscle trauma, skin infections, infected insect bites, illicit drug injections, connective tissue disorders, and diabetes. Treatment generally includes surgical drainage of the abscess and antibiotics.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005216-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pyomyositis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Pyomyositis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Pyomyositis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of temperature regulation 90% Myalgia 90% Myositis 90% Recurrent cutaneous abscess formation 90% Leukocytosis 50% Weight loss 50% Renal insufficiency 7.5% Sepsis 7.5% Sudden cardiac death 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
