<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005582" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4835/short-rib-polydactyly-syndrome-type-3">
<Focus>Short rib-polydactyly syndrome type 3</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0152427</CUI>
			<CUI>C2117329</CUI>
			<CUI>C0036996</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>SRPS type 3</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Short rib-polydactyly syndrome type III</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Polydactyly with neonatal chondrodystrophy type III</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Verma Naumoff syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Short rib polydactyly syndrome Verma Naumoff type</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005582-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Short rib-polydactyly syndrome type 3 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Short rib-polydactyly syndrome type 3? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Short rib-polydactyly syndrome type 3. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of pelvic girdle bone morphology 90% Abnormality of the metaphyses 90% Abnormality of the ribs 90% Brachydactyly syndrome 90% Limb undergrowth 90% Narrow chest 90% Respiratory insufficiency 90% Short thorax 90% Short toe 90% Skeletal dysplasia 90% Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 50% Congenital hepatic fibrosis 50% Depressed nasal bridge 50% Displacement of the external urethral meatus 50% Epicanthus 50% Frontal bossing 50% Hydrops fetalis 50% Long philtrum 50% Macrocephaly 50% Median cleft lip 50% Postaxial hand polydactyly 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 7.5% Cataract 7.5% Ectopic anus 7.5% Midline facial cleft 7.5% Omphalocele 7.5% Polycystic kidney dysplasia 7.5% Preaxial hand polydactyly 7.5% Ventriculomegaly 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
