<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005865" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7693/sprengel-deformity">
<Focus>Sprengel deformity</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0152438</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Congenital upward displacement of the scapula</Synonym>
		<Synonym>High scapula</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Sprengel's shoulder</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital elevation of the scapula</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Sprengel's deformity</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005865-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sprengel deformity ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sprengel deformity is a congenital condition characterized by abnormal development and elevation of the shoulder blade (scapula). Severity can range considerably from being almost invisible when covered with clothes, to the shoulder being elevated over 5 centimeters, with neck webbing. Signs and symptoms may include a lump in the back of the base of the neck and limited movement in the shoulder or arm. The condition may also be associated with other skeletal (bone or cartilage) or muscular abnormalities. Sprengel deformity typically occurs sporadically for no apparent reason but autosomal dominant inheritance has been reported. It is caused by an interruption of normal development and movement of the scapula during early fetal growth (probably between the 9th and 12th weeks of gestation). Treatment often includes physical therapy, but severe cases may require surgery to improve cosmetic appearance and scapular function.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005865-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sprengel deformity ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Sprengel deformity? Signs and symptoms of Sprengel deformity can vary depending on the severity and whether additional skeletal or muscular abnormalities are present. Some people may not have noticeable signs or symptoms. It more commonly occurs on the left side, but can occur on both sides (bilaterally). In addition to shoulder asymmetry, the elevated shoulder blade may cause a lump in the back of the base of the neck; underdeveloped or incomplete muscles in the surrounding area; and limited movement of the shoulder and arm on the affected side. Some people have bone, cartilage or fiber- like tissue between the shoulder blade and the spinal bones (vertebrae) next to it. Other features that have been found in association with Sprengel deformity include: scoliosis Klippel Feil syndrome limb length discrepancy an underdeveloped backbone (hemivertebrae) missing, fused, or extra ribs (cervical ribs) abnormalities of the collarbone abnormalities of the chest organs of the body displaced on the opposite side (ex: liver on the left and heart on the right) spina bifida occulta cleft palate The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Sprengel deformity. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the shoulder 90% Sprengel anomaly 90% Cleft palate 7.5% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Cervical segmentation defect - Hemivertebrae - Neck muscle hypoplasia - Rib segmentation abnormalities - Scoliosis - Shoulder muscle hypoplasia - Spina bifida occulta - Sporadic - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005865-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Sprengel deformity ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Sprengel deformity be treated? Treatment of Sprengel deformity depends on the degree of functional impairment and/or cosmetic disfigurement. Many people with Sprengel deformity do not need surgery and may have physical therapy to maintain range of motion and strengthen weak muscles. For those who do require surgery, the goals are to release the binding of the scapula and relocate the scapula. Surgery can improve the cosmetic appearance and contour of the neck, and improve the scapular function when it is severely impaired. However, the ability to increase shoulder abduction is limited. For surgical indication, many experts refer to the Cavendish classification - one method used for grading the severity of Sprengel deformity. This method classifies the condition into grades I through IV, with grade I being the most mild (almost invisible when covered with clothes) and grade IV being the most severe (with over 5 centimeters of elevation of the shoulder, and neck webbing). Although no improvement or worsening has been reported in untreated grade I and II cases, surgery is recommended in grade III and IV deformities. However, the Cavendish classification may be subjective and inaccurate since it is based on the structure of the deformity (rather than function) and aesthetic criteria. The optimal age for surgery is controversial, but most experts recommend that it be done before age 8 to obtain the best surgical result. There are several surgical options that may be considered depending on each person&apos;s situation. Many of the surgical procedures for Sprengel deformity leave unsightly scars, so the cosmetic improvement must be carefully considered.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
