<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005117" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10815/prothrombin-thrombophilia">
<Focus>Prothrombin thrombophilia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1867596</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Prothrombin 20210G>A thrombophilia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Prothrombin-related thrombophilia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hyperprothrombinemia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Prothrombin G20210A thrombophilia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Factor II-related thrombophilia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005117-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Prothrombin thrombophilia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Prothrombin thrombophilia is an inherited disorder of blood clotting. Thrombophilia is an increased tendency to form abnormal blood clots in blood vessels. People who have prothrombin thrombophilia are at somewhat higher than average risk for a type of clot called a deep venous thrombosis, which typically occur in the deep veins of the legs. Affected people also have an increased risk of developing a pulmonary embolism. However, most people with prothrombin thrombophilia never develop abnormal blood clots. Prothrombin thrombophilia is the second most common inherited form of thrombophilia after factor V Leiden thrombophilia. It is more common in Caucasian populations. This condition is caused by a particular mutation (written G20210A or 20210G&gt;A) in the F2 gene. People can inherit one or two copies of the gene mutation from their parents.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005117-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Prothrombin thrombophilia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Prothrombin thrombophilia? The signs and symptoms of this condition depend on whether a person has inherited one or two copies of the F2 gene mutation from his or her parents. A person who inherits one gene mutation is called a heterozygote. Whereas a person that inherits two gene mutations (one from each parent) is considered a homozygote for this condition; although it is very rare to find individuals who are homozygous. An affected heterozygous person usually experiences mild to moderate increase in their thrombin production, which is associated with 2.5 to 3 fold greater risk of developing a venous thromboembolism. There is not enough information about risk in those who are homozygous. Some research suggests that in women, prothrombin thrombophilia is associated with a somewhat increased risk of pregnancy loss (miscarriage) and may also increase the risk of other complications during pregnancy. These complications may include pregnancy-induced high blood pressure (preeclampsia), slow fetal growth, and early separation of the placenta from the uterine wall (placental abruption). It is important to note, however, that most women with prothrombin thrombophilia have normal pregnancies. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Prothrombin thrombophilia. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal dominant inheritance - Cerebral venous thrombosis - Childhood onset - Deep venous thrombosis - Pulmonary embolism - Recurrent thrombophlebitis - Thromboembolism - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005117-3" qtype="inheritance">Is Prothrombin thrombophilia inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is prothrombin thrombophilia inherited? Prothrombin thrombophilia is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. For this condition, this means that having one mutated copy of the disease-causing gene (F2) in each cell may be sufficient to cause signs or symptoms of the condition. The mutation in the F2 gene that causes prothrombin thrombophilia is called 20210G&gt;A (also called the 20210G&gt;A allele). An individual can be heterozygous (having the mutation in only one copy of the F2 gene) or homozygous (having a mutation in both copies of the F2 gene). Heterozygosity results in an increased risk for thrombosis; homozygosity results in more severe thrombophilia and/or increased risk for thrombosis. All individuals reported to date with prothrombin thrombophilia who are heterozygous for the 20210G&gt;A allele have had an affected parent. Because of the relatively high prevalence of this allele in the general population, occasionally one parent is homozygous or both parents are heterozygous for this allele. When an individual who is heterozygous for the 20210G&gt;A allele has children, each child has a 50% (1 in 2) risk to inherit that allele and also be heterozygous. An individual who is homozygous will always pass one of the 20210G&gt;A alleles to each of his/her children. If two heterozygotes have children together, each child has a 25% (1 in 4) risk to be homozygous (having 2 mutated copies), a 50% risk to be heterozygous like each parent, and a 25% risk to inherit 2 normal copies of the F2 gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0005117-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Prothrombin thrombophilia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What kind of tests can determine if an individual has, or is a carrier of, prothrombin thrombophilia? No clinical signs or symptoms are specific for prothrombin thrombophilia. A confirmed diagnosis of this condition requires specific genetic testing via DNA analysis of the F2 gene, which provides instructions for making the protein prothrombin. The test identifies the presence of a common change (mutation) called 20210G&gt;A. An individual can be a heterozygote (having one mutated copy of the F2 gene) or a homozygote (having two mutated copies). Most heterozygotes have a mildly elevated plasma concentration of prothrombin (which can be measured in a blood test) that is approximately 30% higher than normal. However, these values can vary greatly, and the range of prothrombin concentrations in heterozygotes overlaps significantly with the normal range. Therefore, plasma concentration of prothrombin is not reliable for diagnosis of this condition. Individuals interested in learning more about testing for prothrombin thrombophilia should speak with a genetics professional or other healthcare provider.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
