<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005651" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10252/sjogren-syndrome">
<Focus>Sjogren syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1527336</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Sicca syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Sjogren-Gougerot syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005651-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sjogren syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sjgren syndrome is an autoimmune disorder in which immune cells attack and destroy the glands that produce tears and saliva. Sjgren syndrome is also associated with rheumatic disorders such as rheumatoid arthritis or systemic lupus erythematosus. The hallmark symptoms of the disorder are dry mouth and dry eyes. In addition, Sjogren syndrome may cause skin, nose, and vaginal dryness, and may affect other organs of the body including the kidneys, blood vessels, lungs, liver, pancreas, and brain. Treatment is symptomatic and supportive and may include moisture replacement therapies, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs and, in severe cases, corticosteroids or immunosuppressive drugs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005651-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sjogren syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Sjogren syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Sjogren syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Arthralgia 90% Arthritis 90% Autoimmunity 90% Dry skin 90% Increased antibody level in blood 90% Keratoconjunctivitis sicca 90% Xerostomia 90% Abnormality of temperature regulation 50% Abnormality of the gastric mucosa 50% Abnormality of the pharynx 50% Acrocyanosis 50% Carious teeth 50% Corneal erosion 50% Diplopia 50% Feeding difficulties in infancy 50% Furrowed tongue 50% Myalgia 50% Opacification of the corneal stroma 50% Paresthesia 50% Pulmonary fibrosis 50% Pulmonary infiltrates 50% Recurrent respiratory infections 50% Sinusitis 50% Sleep disturbance 50% Visual impairment 50% Abnormal tendon morphology 7.5% Abnormality of the pleura 7.5% Abnormality of the renal tubule 7.5% Abnormality of the sense of smell 7.5% Alopecia 7.5% Arrhythmia 7.5% Asthma 7.5% Atelectasis 7.5% Cerebral ischemia 7.5% Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease 7.5% Conductive hearing impairment 7.5% Cryoglobulinemia 7.5% Cutis marmorata 7.5% Diabetes insipidus 7.5% Epistaxis 7.5% Facial palsy 7.5% Glomerulopathy 7.5% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 7.5% Hepatomegaly 7.5% Hypercalciuria 7.5% Hypokalemia 7.5% Leukopenia 7.5% Lymphoma 7.5% Malabsorption 7.5% Meningitis 7.5% Microcytic anemia 7.5% Myositis 7.5% Nephrolithiasis 7.5% Nephrotic syndrome 7.5% Neurological speech impairment 7.5% Ophthalmoparesis 7.5% Otitis media 7.5% Pancreatitis 7.5% Photophobia 7.5% Proteinuria 7.5% Ptosis 7.5% Pulmonary hypertension 7.5% Reduced bone mineral density 7.5% Renal insufficiency 7.5% Respiratory insufficiency 7.5% Salivary gland neoplasm 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Splenomegaly 7.5% Subcutaneous hemorrhage 7.5% Thrombocytopenia 7.5% Thyroiditis 7.5% Urticaria 7.5% Vasculitis 7.5% Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Rheumatoid arthritis - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005651-3" qtype="causes">What causes Sjogren syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Sjogren syndrome? Sjogren syndrome likely results from a combination of genetic and environmental factors (multifactorial). Several different genes appear to affect the risk of developing the condition, however, specific genes have yet to be confirmed. Simply having one of these genes does not cause a person to develop the disease; some sort of trigger is also needed. That trigger may be a viral or bacterial infection. The genetic variations that increase susceptibility may reduce the body&apos;s ability to turn off the immune response when it is no longer needed. The possibility that the endocrine and nervous systems may play a role in the disease is also under investigation.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0005651-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Sjogren syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is Sjogren syndrome inherited? A genetic predisposition to Sjogren syndrome has been suggested. Familial clustering of different autoimmune diseases as well as co-association of multiple autoimmune diseases in individuals have frequently been reported. Some studies have shown up to 30% of people with Sjogren syndrome have relatives with autoimmune diseases. While the relatives of people with Sjogren syndrome are at an increased risk of developing autoimmune diseases in general, they are not necessarily more likely to develop Sjogren syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
