<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005034" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4482/prieto-x-linked-mental-retardation-syndrome">
<Focus>Prieto X-linked mental retardation syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0025362</CUI>
			<CUI>C1839730</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>X-linked dysmorphic syndrome with mental retardation</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mental retardation, X-linked with dysmorphism and cerebral atrophy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>PRS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MRXS2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mental retardation, X-linked, syndromic 2</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005034-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Prieto X-linked mental retardation syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Prieto X-linked mental retardation syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Prieto X-linked mental retardation syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the nose 90% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Gait disturbance 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Ventriculomegaly 90% Abnormal dermatoglyphics 50% Abnormality of the hip bone 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the earlobes 50% Cryptorchidism 50% High forehead 50% Hypertelorism 50% Increased number of teeth 50% Muscular hypotonia 50% Neurological speech impairment 50% Optic atrophy 50% Patellar dislocation 50% Sacral dimple 50% Seizures 50% Abnormality of the pupil 7.5% Abnormality of the ribs 7.5% Delayed skeletal maturation 7.5% Epicanthus 7.5% Hernia of the abdominal wall 7.5% Nystagmus 7.5% Ptosis 7.5% Reduced bone mineral density 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% 11 pairs of ribs - Abnormality of the skin - Abnormality of the teeth - Cerebral atrophy - Clinodactyly - Coxa valga - Inguinal hernia - Intellectual disability - Low-set ears - Osteoporosis - Patellar subluxation - Prominent nose - Radial deviation of finger - Retrognathia - Talipes equinovarus - X-linked recessive inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
