<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005004" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9597/postural-orthostatic-tachycardia-syndrome">
<Focus>Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1299624</CUI>
			<CUI>C3827868</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039231</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>POTS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Postural tachycardia syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chronic othostatic intolerance</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005004-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (POTS) is a rare condition that is primarily characterized by orthostatic intolerance (an excessively reduced volume of blood returns to the heart when moving from a lying down to a standing position). Orthostatic Intolerance is generally associated with lightheadedness and/or fainting that is typically relieved by lying down again. In people with POTS, these symptoms are also accompanied by a rapid increase in heartbeat. Although POTS can affect men and women of all ages, most cases are diagnosed in women between the ages of 15 and 50. The exact underlying cause of POTS is currently unknown. However, episodes often begin after a pregnancy, major surgery, trauma, or a viral illness and may increase right before a menstrual period. Treatment aims to relieve low blood volume and/or regulate circulatory problems that could be causing the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005004-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome? Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (POTS) is primarily characterized by orthostatic intolerance (an excessively reduced volume of blood returns to the heart when moving from a lying down to a standing position). Orthostatic Intolerance is generally associated with lightheadedness and/or fainting that is typically relieved by lying down again. In people with POTS, these symptoms are also accompanied by a rapid increase in heartbeat. Other symptoms reported in POTS include: Visual changes (i.e. blurry vision) Throbbing of the head Poor concentration Tiredness Gastrointestinal symptoms (i.e. nausea, cramps, bloating, constipation, diarrhea) Shortness of breath Head, neck and/or chest discomfort Weakness Sleep disorders Exercise intolerance Sweating Anxiety</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005004-3" qtype="causes">What causes Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome? The underlying cause of postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (POTS) is poorly understood. However, episodes often begin after a pregnancy, major surgery, trauma, or a viral illness and may increase right before a menstrual period. Many researchers suspect that there may be more than one cause for the condition. The following abnormalities can be associated with POTS and may play a role in the development of the condition: Peripheral denervation - reduced nerve stimulation to certain muscles. The lower extremities are generally most affected in people with POTS. Hypovolemia - an abnormal decrease or redistribution of blood in the body Changes in venous function - more specifically, a reduction in the volume of blood that returns to the heart (venous return) when moving from a lying down to a standing position Cardiovascular deconditioning - changes in cardiovascular function Baroreflex abnormalities - the baroreflexes play an important role in blood pressure regulation. When they sense a change in blood pressure, the heart rate is adjusted and the sympathetic nerve system fibers are activated to cause the blood vessels to narrow. Increased activity of the sympathetic nervous system Although most cases of POTS appear to occur sporadically in people with no family history of the condition, some affected people report a family history of orthostatic intolerance (an excessively reduced volume of blood returns to the heart when moving from a lying down to a standing position). This suggests that genetic factors may play a role in the development of POTS in some cases. Some studies also suggest that polymorphisms in certain genes (NOS3, ADRB2) may be associated with an increased risk of developing the condition and a change (mutation) in the norepinephrine transporter gene (SLC6A2) has been identified in one family with POTS.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0005004-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome inherited? Most cases of postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (POTS) are not thought to be inherited. Although the condition generally occurs sporadically, some people with POTS do report a family history of orthostatic intolerance (an excessively reduced volume of blood returns to the heart when moving from a lying down to a standing position). This suggests that inherited factors may play a role in the development of POTS in some families.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0005004-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome diagnosed? A diagnosis of postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (POTS) is often suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. Additional testing can then be ordered to confirm the diagnosis. Many physicians will conduct a physical examination, including measuring blood pressure and heart rate while lying, sitting, and standing. A tilt table test may also be recommended to help confirm the diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0005004-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome treated? Because postural orthostatic tachycardia syndrome (POTS) is thought to have a variety of causes, there is no single treatment that is effective for all people with the condition. In general, management of POTS aims to relieve low blood volume and/or regulate circulatory problems that could be causing the condition. In some affected people, simple life style interventions such as adding extra salt to the diet, ensuring adequate fluid intake, participating in a specialized exercise program, and avoiding factors that exacerbate the condition appear to improve symptoms. Certain medications have also been used to treat POTS with some success.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
