<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005201" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3103/punctate-palmoplantar-keratoderma-type-i">
<Focus>Punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type I</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1274216</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Buschke fischer brauer syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Keratodermia palmoplantaris papulosa, Buschke-Fischer-Brauer type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Type I punctate palmoplantar keratoderma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Keratoderma, palmoplantar punctate type 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Keratosis palmoplantaris papulosa</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Palmoplantar keratoderma</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005201-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type I ?</Question>
			<Answer>Punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type I, also known as keratosis palmoplantaris papulosa (KPPP) or Brauer-Buschke-Fisher Syndrome is is a rare condition that affects the skin. It is a type of punctate palmoplantar keratoderma. Signs and symptoms begin in early adolescence or later and include hard, round bumps of thickened skin on the palms of the hands and soles of the feet. It is is usually inherited in an autosomal dominant manner and can be caused by mutations in the AAGAB gene. Treatment options may include chemical or mechanical keratolysis as well as systemic acitretin. Some affected individuals have used surgical approaches consisting of excision and skin grafting.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005201-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type I ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type I? Signs and symptoms of punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type 1 tend to become evident between the ages of 10 to 30 years. Symptoms include multiple, tiny, hard rounded bumps of thickened skin on the palms of the hands and soles of the feet. The bumps may join to form calluses on pressure points. The legions may cause pain, making walking difficult and impairing hand/finger movement. Symptoms tend to worsen with time and may be aggravated by manual work or injury. In some families, punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type 1 appears to be associated with an increased risk for several types of cancer. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type I. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Palmoplantar keratoderma 90% Lymphoma 50% Neoplasm of the breast 50% Neoplasm of the colon 50% Neoplasm of the pancreas 50% Renal neoplasm 50% Abnormality of the nail 7.5% Abnormality of the skin - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Heterogeneous - Late onset - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005201-3" qtype="causes">What causes Punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type I ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes palmoplantar keratoderma type 1? Punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type 1 is a condition that is usually inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. It has recently been shown to be caused by mutations in the AAGAB gene in several families. Although the exact function of the AAGAB gene is currently unknown, the gene is thought to play an important role in skin integrity.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0005201-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type I inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type I inherited? Punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type I is usually inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Autosomal dominant inheritance is when only one mutated copy of a disease-causing gene in each cell is sufficient for a person to be affected. An autosomal dominant condition may occur for the first time in an affected individual due to a new mutation, or may be inherited from an affected parent. When a person with an autosomal dominant disorder has a child, there is a 50% chance that his/her child will inherit the condition. Keratosis palmoplantaris papulosa shows age dependent penetrance and possibly variable penetrance as well. Age dependant penetrance means that the older the person is, the more likely they are to develop symptoms if they have inherited the disease causing gene mutation. Variable penetrance means that not everyone who inherits the gene mutation that causes keratosis palmoplantaris papulosa develops the signs and symptoms of the condition. However this person would still be at risk of passing the disease-causing mutation to their offspring.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0005201-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type I ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type I diagnosed? Features that support the diagnosis of punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type I include a positive family history (i.e., other affected family members), the presence of multiple tiny hard rounded bumps of thickened skin on the hands and feet, and certain cell histology (i.e., appearance of skin samples when viewed under a microscope).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0005201-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type I ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might punctate palmoplantar keratoderma type 1 be treated? Treatment options for this condition generally include topical salicylic acid, mechanical debridement, excision, and systemic retinoids. These therapies can lead to a temporary decrease in skin thickness and softening of the skin. Unfortunately, in many cases, medical and surgical treatment for punctate keratodermas do not provide consistent or long-lasting results. In general, there has been some reported success using keratolytics such as corticosteroids, urea, salicylic acid, lactic acid, or Vitamin A. Systemic therapy using vitamin D analogues, aromatic retinoids, and 5-fluorouracil has also been used. However, individuals with successful resolution of lesions often relapse unless they are maintained on chronic low-dose therapy. These topical and systemic treatments carry a variety of side effects. Surgery (including excision and skin grafting) for punctate keratodermas has been used on lesions resistant to medical treatment, but healing after surgical treatment can be difficult. CO2 laser ablation has also been attempted and reportedly produces good results for limited areas of hyperkeratosis of the palms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
