<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005507" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/250/schwartz-jampel-syndrome-type-1">
<Focus>Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
			<CUI>C0036391</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>SJS1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Schwartz Jampel syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Schwartz Jampel Aberfeld syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Myotonic myopathy dwarfism chondrodystrophy and ocular and facial abnormalities</Synonym>
		<Synonym>SJA syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Progressive muscular dystrophy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005507-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1 (SJS1) is a genetic disorder that affects bone and muscle development. Signs and symptoms may include muscle weakness and stiffness, abnormal bone development, joint contractures,  short stature, small, fixed facial features, and eye abnormalities (some of which may impair vision). SJS1 can be divided into two subtypes differentiated by severity and age of onset. Type 1A, considered classic SJS, is the most commonly recognized type. Individuals with type 1A typically develop more mild symptoms later in childhood, while individuals with type 1B have symptoms that are more severe and are apparent immediately after birth. SJS1 is caused by mutations in the HSPG2 gene which makes a protein called perlecan. SJS1 is thought to be inherited in an autosomal recessive manner; however, some cases reported in the medical literature suggest an autosomal dominant inheritance pattern. Treatment for both type 1A and 1B aims to normalize muscle activity through various methods including massage and stretching, medications such as Botulinum toxin, and surgery.  There is a more severe, distinct condition called Stuve-Wiedemann syndrome which is caused by mutations in the LIFR gene. At one time cases of Stuve-Wiedemann syndrome were referred to as Neonatal Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 2. Click on the link above to learn more about this syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005507-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1? Individuals with Schwartz-Jampel syndrome type 1 (SJS1) have characteristic facial features, muscle weakness (hypotonia), and muscle stiffness (myotonia). Facial features of individuals with SJS1 can seem &quot;fixed&quot; in the same expression with puckered lips due to weakening and stiffening of the facial muscles. Additional facial features may include:   Blepharophimosis (narrowing of the eye opening) Epicanthal folds (skin fold of the upper eyelid covering the inner corner of the eye) Blepharospasm (involuntary blinking or spasm of the eyelids) Hypertrichosis (excessive hair) of the eye lashes         Micrognathia (small lower jaw) Individuals with SJS1 usually have short stature. Other skeletal and joint findings may include: Shortened neck Pectus carinatum (outward bowing of the chest) Kyphosis (curving of the spine that causes a bowing or rounding of the back) Coxa valga (hip deformity involving an increased neck-shaft angle of the femur) Joint contractures  Osteoporosis Widening of the metaphysis (portion of the bone containing the growth plate) Delayed bone age Other less common symptoms include: a high pitched voice, bilateral carpel tunnel syndrome, and malignant hyperthermia. One study suggested that as many as 20% of individuals with SJS1 have an intellectual disability; however, most individuals with SJS1 have normal intelligence. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of epiphysis morphology 90% Abnormality of the metaphyses 90% Cognitive impairment 90% EMG abnormality 90% Full cheeks 90% Gait disturbance 90% Genu valgum 90% Hypertonia 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 90% Micromelia 90% Myotonia 90% Narrow mouth 90% Pes planus 90% Short stature 90% Skeletal dysplasia 90% Talipes 90% Trismus 90% Visual impairment 90% Abnormal vertebral ossification 50% Abnormality of the eyebrow 50% Abnormality of the pharynx 50% Blepharophimosis 50% Cataract 50% Hyperlordosis 50% Kyphosis 50% Malar flattening 50% Mask-like facies 50% Myopathy 50% Myopia 50% Overfolded helix 50% Pectus carinatum 50% Platyspondyly 50% Prominent nasal bridge 50% Ptosis 50% Reduced bone mineral density 50% Scoliosis 50% Short neck 50% Skeletal muscle hypertrophy 50% Spinal rigidity 50% Strabismus 50% Abnormality of immune system physiology 7.5% Abnormality of the ribs 7.5% Abnormality of the ureter 7.5% Abnormally straight spine 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia affecting the eye 7.5% Apnea 7.5% Arrhythmia 7.5% Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Decreased body weight 7.5% Delayed skeletal maturation 7.5% Distichiasis 7.5% Ectopia lentis 7.5% Elbow dislocation 7.5% Feeding difficulties in infancy 7.5% Hypertelorism 7.5% Hypertrichosis 7.5% Increased bone mineral density 7.5% Laryngomalacia 7.5% Long philtrum 7.5% Low anterior hairline 7.5% Malignant hyperthermia 7.5% Microcephaly 7.5% Microcornea 7.5% Muscle weakness 7.5% Myalgia 7.5% Nephrolithiasis 7.5% Neurological speech impairment 7.5% Odontogenic neoplasm 7.5% Pectus excavatum 7.5% Polyhydramnios 7.5% Prenatal movement abnormality 7.5% Protrusio acetabuli 7.5% Pulmonary hypertension 7.5% Respiratory insufficiency 7.5% Skeletal muscle atrophy 7.5% Sprengel anomaly 7.5% Testicular torsion 7.5% Umbilical hernia 7.5% Wormian bones 7.5% Abnormality of femoral epiphysis - Anterior bowing of long bones - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Congenital hip dislocation - Coronal cleft vertebrae - Coxa valga - Coxa vara - Decreased testicular size - Flat face - Flexion contracture of toe - Generalized hirsutism - High pitched voice - Hip contracture - Hyporeflexia - Inguinal hernia - Intellectual disability - Joint contracture of the hand - Kyphoscoliosis - Long eyelashes in irregular rows - Low-set ears - Lumbar hyperlordosis - Metaphyseal widening - Osteoporosis - Pursed lips - Shoulder flexion contracture - Talipes equinovarus - Weak voice - Wrist flexion contracture - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005507-3" qtype="causes">What causes Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1? Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1 (SJS1) is caused by mutations in the HSPG2 gene. The HSPG2 gene codes for the protein perlecan, which is found in muscle and cartilage. Although the role of the perlecan protein is not fully understood, it is thought to play an essential role in many biological activities such as cell signaling and cellular structure. In SJS1, it is suspected that a disturbance in perlecan function leads to a deficiency of acetylcholinesterase, an enzyme involved in breaking down acetylcholine, a neurotransmitter that sends messages between nerves, leading to muscle contraction. If acetylcholine is not broken down, it may lead to an prolonged muscle contraction or stiffening of the muscles (myotonia).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0005507-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1 inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1 inherited? The majority of cases of Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1 (SJS1) are inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern. This means that to have the disorder, a person must have a mutation in both copies of the responsible gene in each cell. Individuals with SJS1 inherit one mutated copy of the gene from each parent, who is referred to as a carrier. Carriers of an autosomal recessive condition typically do not have any signs or symptoms (they are unaffected). Rarely, cases of SJS1 with autosomal dominant inheritance have been reported. This means that having a change (mutation) in only one copy of the responsible gene in each cell is enough to cause features of the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0005507-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1 diagnosed? The diagnosis of Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1 (SJS1) is suspected based on clinical findings including characteristic facial features, skeletal features, and muscle stiffness (myotonia). Studies that may be useful in diagnosing  SJS1 include: blood tests (which may show elevated serum creatine kinase or adolase); imaging studies; muscle biopsy; and electromyography (EMG)/nerve conduction studies. Genetic testing of the HSPG2 gene may additionally be helpful to confirm the diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0005507-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1 be treated? Treatment of Schwartz Jampel syndrome type 1 (SJS1) aims to reduce stiffness and cramping of muscles. This might include nonpharmacologic modalities such as massage, warming of muscles, and gradual strengthening exercises. Medications that might be utilized include muscle relaxants and anti seizure medications, particularly Carbamazepine. Botox might additionally be used to relieve eye symptoms such as blepharospasm (involuntary blinking of spasm of eyes).  If Botox is not successful in managing eye symptoms, a variety of surgical techniques have been found to be effective. When considering surgery as an option, an important consideration is the risk for malignant hyperthermia, which could lead to adverse outcomes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
