<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005234" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/226/rabson-mendenhall-syndrome">
<Focus>Rabson-Mendenhall syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0271695</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pineal hyperplasia, insulin-resistant diabetes mellitus, and somatic abnormalities</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mendenhall Syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005234-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Rabson-Mendenhall syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Rabson-Mendenhall syndrome is a genetic disorder characterized by severe insulin resistance. Insulin, a hormone produced by the pancreas, regulates blood sugar levels by promoting the movement of glucose into cells for energy production or into the liver and fat cells for storage. Symptoms of Rabson-Mendenhall syndrome may include intrauterine and postnatal growth retardation, hypertrophy of muscle and fat tissues, abnormalities of the head and face, abnormalities of the teeth and nails, and skin abnormalities such as acanthosis nigricans. Additional symptoms may also be present. Rabson-Mendenhall syndrome is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Treatment is difficult and may include high doses of insulin and/or recombinant insulin-like growth factor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005234-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Rabson-Mendenhall syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Rabson-Mendenhall syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Rabson-Mendenhall syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the abdominal wall 90% Abnormality of the fingernails 90% Acanthosis nigricans 90% Advanced eruption of teeth 90% Coarse facial features 90% Congenital, generalized hypertrichosis 90% Diabetes mellitus 90% Female pseudohermaphroditism 90% Growth hormone excess 90% Intrauterine growth retardation 90% Long penis 90% Mandibular prognathia 90% Abnormality of the thyroid gland 50% Brachydactyly syndrome 50% Coarse hair 50% Dry skin 50% Peripheral neuropathy 50% Precocious puberty 50% Prematurely aged appearance 50% Proteinuria 50% Short stature 50% Abnormality of the upper urinary tract 7.5% Polycystic ovaries 7.5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Clitoromegaly - Diabetic ketoacidosis - Fasting hypoglycemia - High palate - Hyperglycemia - Hyperinsulinemia - Hypertrichosis - Hypoglycemia - Insulin-resistant diabetes mellitus - Onychauxis - Small for gestational age - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
