<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005502" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12390/schnitzler-syndrome">
<Focus>Schnitzler syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0524988</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Chronic urticaria with gammapathy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chronic urticaria with macroglobulinemia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chronic urticaria with gammopathy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005502-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Schnitzler syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Schnitzler syndrome is a rare autoinflammatory condition. Signs and symptoms of the condition vary but may include urticaria; recurrent fevers; joint pain and inflammation; organomegaly (abnormally enlarged organs); and/or blood abnormalities. The exact underlying cause of the condition is unknown; however, most cases occur sporadically in people with no family history of the condition. Treatment is focused on alleviating the signs and symptoms associated with the condition and may include various medications and/or phototherapy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005502-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Schnitzler syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Schnitzler syndrome? The signs and symptoms of Schnitzler syndrome vary but may include: Red raised patches of skin (urticaria) that may become itchy Recurrent fevers Join pain and inflammation Organomegaly (enlarged internal organs) often involving the lymph nodes, liver and/or spleen Bone pain Blood abnormalities Muscle aches Fatigue Weight loss People affected by Schnitzler syndrome also have an increased risk of developing certain lymphoproliferative disorders. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Schnitzler syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal immunoglobulin level 90% Abnormality of temperature regulation 90% Arthralgia 90% Arthritis 90% Bone pain 90% Hepatomegaly 90% Increased bone mineral density 90% Lymphadenopathy 90% Myalgia 90% Splenomegaly 90% Urticaria 90% Anemia 50% Leukocytosis 50% Lymphoma 7.5% Peripheral neuropathy 7.5% Pruritus 7.5% Vasculitis 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005502-3" qtype="causes">What causes Schnitzler syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Schnitzler syndrome? The exact underlying cause of Schnitzler syndrome is currently unknown. People affected by this condition often have a blood abnormality called monoclonal gammopathy, a condition in which the body over-produces certain immunoglobulins (typically immunoglobulin M). Immunoglobulins are proteins that are made by certain white blood cells. They play a role in the immune response by helping destroy bacteria, viruses, and other substances that appear foreign and harmful. Some researchers believe that the abnormal accumulation of immunoglobulins in the skin and other parts of the body may play a role in the development of the signs and symptoms of Schnitzler syndrome. Other scientists speculate that alterations in cytokines may play a role in the development of Schnitzler syndrome. Cytokines are specialized proteins that play an important role in the immune response. They are secreted by certain immune system cells and play a vital role in controlling the growth and activity of other immune system cells. Abnormal findings involving a specific cytokine called interleukin-1 have been found in some people with Schnitzler syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0005502-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Schnitzler syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Schnitzler syndrome diagnosed? A diagnosis of Schnitzler syndrome is often suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms identified through physical exam, laboratory studies (i.e. immunoelectrophoresis) and/or imaging studies. Additional testing should also be ordered to rule out other conditions that cause similar features. Medscape Reference&apos;s Web site offers more specific information on the diagnosis of Schnitzler syndrome. Please click on the link to access this resource.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0005502-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Schnitzler syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Schnitzler syndrome be treated? The treatment of Schnitzler syndrome is aimed at alleviating the signs and symptoms associated with the condition. The following medications have been used with variable success: Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) Corticosteroids Immunosuppressive agents Interleukin-1 receptor antagonists (medications that inhibit the cytokine IL-1) Colchicine Dapsone Thalidomide Rituximab Some studies suggest that phototherapy may improve the rash in some affected people. Medscape Reference and the National Organization for Rare Disorders both offer additional information regarding the treatment and management of Schnitzler syndrome. Please click on the links to access these resources.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
