<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005792" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12232/spinocerebellar-ataxia-autosomal-recessive-7">
<Focus>Spinocerebellar ataxia autosomal recessive 7</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0087012</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>SCAR7</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Childhood onset autosomal recessive slowly progressive spinocerebellar ataxia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary ataxia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005792-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Spinocerebellar ataxia autosomal recessive 7 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Spinocerebellar ataxia autosomal recessive 7, also called SCAR7, is a slowly progressive hereditary form of spinocerebellar ataxia.  Symptoms of SCAR7 can include difficulty walking and writing, speech difficulties (dysarthria), limb ataxia, and a decrease in the size of a region of the brain called the cerebellum (cerebellar atrophy). Of the few reported cases in the literature, some patients also had eye involvement that included nystagmus (in voluntary eye movements) and saccadic pursuit eye movements.  Out of 5 affected siblings examined in a large Dutch family, 2 became wheelchair-dependent late in life. The severity of the symptoms varies from mild to severe.  SCAR7 is caused by mutations in the TPP1 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005792-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Spinocerebellar ataxia autosomal recessive 7 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Spinocerebellar ataxia autosomal recessive 7? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Spinocerebellar ataxia autosomal recessive 7. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Ataxia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Babinski sign - Cerebellar atrophy - Clumsiness - Diplopia - Dysarthria - Gait ataxia - Hypermetric saccades - Hyperreflexia - Juvenile onset - Limb ataxia - Nystagmus - Postural tremor - Saccadic smooth pursuit - Slow progression - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
