<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005998" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9748/systemic-scleroderma">
<Focus>Systemic scleroderma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0036421</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Systemic sclerosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Scleroderma, systemic</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Progressive systemic sclerosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Diffuse cutaneous systemic sclerosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Limited cutaneous systemic sclerosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Limited systemic sclerosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Scleroderma</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005998-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Systemic scleroderma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Systemic scleroderma is an autoimmune disorder that affects the skin and internal organs. It is characterized by the buildup of scar tissue (fibrosis) in the skin and other organs. The fibrosis is caused by the body&apos;s production of too much collagen, which normally strengthens and supports connective tissues. The signs and symptoms of systemic scleroderma usually begin with episodes of Raynaud&apos;s phenomenon, which can occur weeks to years before fibrosis. This may be followed by puffy or swollen hands before the skin becomes thickened and hard. Fibrosis can also affect internal organs and can lead to impairment or failure of the affected organs. The most commonly affected organs are the esophagus, heart, lungs, and kidneys. There are three types of systemic scleroderma, defined by the tissues affected in the disorder. Diffuse cutaneous systemic sclerosis Limited cutaneous systemic sclerosis (which includes CREST syndrome) Limited systemic sclerosis (systemic sclerosis sine scleroderma)</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005998-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Systemic scleroderma ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Systemic scleroderma? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Systemic scleroderma. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the gastric mucosa 90% Acrocyanosis 90% Arthralgia 90% Arthritis 90% Atypical scarring of skin 90% Autoimmunity 90% Chest pain 90% Chondrocalcinosis 90% Edema 90% Hyperkeratosis 90% Lack of skin elasticity 90% Myalgia 90% Nausea and vomiting 90% Skeletal muscle atrophy 90% Weight loss 90% Abnormality of the myocardium 50% Abnormality of the pericardium 50% Carious teeth 50% Feeding difficulties in infancy 50% Gangrene 50% Malabsorption 50% Mucosal telangiectasiae 50% Myositis 50% Pulmonary fibrosis 50% Pulmonary infiltrates 50% Respiratory insufficiency 50% Skin ulcer 50% Telangiectasia of the skin 50% Trismus 50% Xerostomia 50% Abnormal renal physiology 7.5% Abnormal tendon morphology 7.5% Arrhythmia 7.5% Bowel incontinence 7.5% Coronary artery disease 7.5% Erectile abnormalities 7.5% Hypertensive crisis 7.5% Irregular hyperpigmentation 7.5% Migraine 7.5% Narrow mouth 7.5% Osteolysis 7.5% Osteomyelitis 7.5% Peripheral neuropathy 7.5% Pulmonary hypertension 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Abnormality of chromosome stability - Abnormality of the abdomen - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Calcinosis - Sclerodactyly - Scleroderma - Telangiectasia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005998-3" qtype="causes">What causes Systemic scleroderma ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes systemic scleroderma? The exact, underlying cause of systemic sclerosis is unknown. The cause appears to involve some injury to the cells that line blood vessels, resulting in excessive activation of dermal connective tissue cells, called fibroblasts. Fibroblasts normally produce collagen and other proteins. Build-up of collagen in the skin and other organs causes the signs and symptoms of the condition. It is suspected that scleroderma may develop from a variety of factors, which may include: Abnormal immune or inflammatory activity Genetic susceptibility: while no specific genes are thought to cause scleroderma, certain genes (or combination of genes) may increase a person&apos;s risk to be affected. However, the condition is not passed directly from parents to children. Environmental triggers: suspected triggers may include infections; injury; drugs (e.g. vitamin K, cocaine, penicillamine, appetite suppressants and some chemotherapeutic agents); and chemicals (e.g. silica, organic solvents, pesticides, aliphatic hydrocarbons and epoxy resin). Hormones: because women develop scleroderma more often than men, researchers suspect that hormones may play a role. However, the role of female hormones has not been proven. Widespread scleroderma can also occur in association with other autoimmune diseases, including systemic lupus erythematosus and polymyositis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0005998-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Systemic scleroderma inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is systemic scleroderma inherited? Most cases of systemic scleroderma are sporadic and are not inherited. This means the condition typically occurs in people with no history of the condition in their family. Some people with systemic scleroderma have relatives with other autoimmune disorders, and a few cases of the condition have been reported to run in families. However, the condition is not caused by a single gene that is passed on to offspring. Multiple genetic and environmental factors likely interact to put someone at an increased risk to develop the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0005998-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Systemic scleroderma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is genetic testing available for systemic scleroderma? Because systemic scleroderma is not caused by a mutation in any one specific gene, clinical genetic testing to confirm a diagnosis or identify a &quot;carrier&quot; is not currently available.  Even if someone is known to carry a version of a gene that may make them susceptible to the condition, it does not mean they will definitely develop the condition. You can view a list of centers that may be involved in research projects on systemic scleroderma on Orphanet&apos;s Web site. You can also view a list of clinical trials involving people with systemic scleroderma on ClinicalTrials.gov. People interested in learning more about genes and genetic testing for systemic scleroderma should speak with a genetics professional.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
