<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005366" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4703/rhizomelic-dysplasia-patterson-lowry-type">
<Focus>Rhizomelic dysplasia Patterson Lowry type</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0334044</CUI>
			<CUI>C1832359</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Patterson-Lowry rhizomelic dysplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Patterson Lowry syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005366-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Rhizomelic dysplasia Patterson Lowry type ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Rhizomelic dysplasia Patterson Lowry type? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Rhizomelic dysplasia Patterson Lowry type. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 90% Abnormality of the hip bone 90% Abnormality of the humerus 90% Abnormality of the metacarpal bones 90% Brachydactyly syndrome 90% Depressed nasal ridge 90% Deviation of finger 90% Epicanthus 90% Genu valgum 90% Hyperlordosis 90% Large face 90% Limb undergrowth 90% Malar flattening 90% Mandibular prognathia 90% Short nose 90% Coxa vara - Deformed humeral heads - Platyspondyly - Rhizomelia - Short humerus - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
