<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005876" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10295/star-syndrome">
<Focus>STAR syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2678045</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Syndactyly, telecanthus, anogenital and renal malformations</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Toe syndactyly, telecanthus, anogenital and renal malformations</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005876-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of STAR syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of STAR syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for STAR syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 90% External ear malformation 90% Short stature 90% Toe syndactyly 90% Urogenital fistula 90% Abnormal localization of kidney 50% Abnormality of female internal genitalia 50% Abnormality of the cardiac septa 50% Female pseudohermaphroditism 50% Midline defect of the nose 50% Renal hypoplasia/aplasia 50% Renal insufficiency 50% Telecanthus 50% Thin vermilion border 50% Vesicoureteral reflux 50% Abnormality of the aortic valve 7.5% Abnormality of the macula 7.5% Abnormality of the pulmonary artery 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the radius 7.5% Chorioretinal abnormality 7.5% Cleft eyelid 7.5% Mitral stenosis 7.5% Myopia 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Syringomyelia 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
