<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005213" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7510/pyoderma-gangrenosum">
<Focus>Pyoderma gangrenosum</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0085652</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005213-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pyoderma gangrenosum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pyoderma gangrenosum is a rare, destructive inflammatory skin disease of which a painful nodule or pustule breaks down to form a progressively enlarging ulcer. Lesions may occur either in the absence of any apparent underlying disorder or in association with other diseases, such as ulcerative colitis, Crohn&apos;s disease, polyarthritis (an inflammation of several joints together), gammopathy, and other conditions . Pyoderma gangrenosum belongs to a group of skin diseases in which a common cellular denominator is the neutrophil. Neutrophils are a type of white blood cell or leukocyte which form an early line of defense against bacterial infections.  Each year in the United States, pyoderma gangrenosum occurs in about 1 person per 100.000 people.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005213-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pyoderma gangrenosum ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Pyoderma gangrenosum? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Pyoderma gangrenosum. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Myositis 90% Pulmonary infiltrates 90% Skin rash 90% Skin ulcer 90% Abnormal blistering of the skin 50% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005213-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Pyoderma gangrenosum ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might pyoderma gangrenosum be treated? Although antibiotics are often prescribed prior to having a correct diagnosis (and may be continued if there is a secondary infection or surrounding cellulitis), antibiotics are generally not helpful for treating uncomplicated cases of pyoderma gangrenosum (PG). The best documented treatments for PG are systemic corticosteroids and cyclosporin A. Smaller ulcers may be treated with strong topical steroid creams, steroid injections, special dressings, oral anti-inflammatory antibiotics, and/or other therapies. More severe PG typically requires immunosuppressive therapy (used to decrease the body&apos;s immune responses). Combinations of steroids with cytotoxic drugs may be used in resistant cases. There has reportedly been rapid improvement of PG with use of anti-tumor necrosis alpha therapy (such as infliximab), which is also used to treat Crohn&apos;s disease and other conditions. Skin transplants and/or the application of bioengineered skin is useful in selected cases as a complementary therapy to immunosuppressive treatment. The use of modern wound dressings is helpful to minimize pain and the risk of secondary infections. Treatment for PG generally does not involve surgery because it can result in enlargement of the ulcer; however, necrotic tissue (dying or dead tissue) should be gently removed. More detailed information about the treatment of pyoderma gangrenosum is available on eMedicine&apos;s Web site and can be viewed by clicking here.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
