<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005300" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8477/renal-oncocytoma">
<Focus>Renal oncocytoma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0346255</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Oncocytoma renal</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Oncocytoma kidney</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005300-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Renal oncocytoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Renal oncocytoma is a benign (noncancerous) growth of the kidney. They generally do not cause any signs or symptoms and are often discovered incidentally (by chance) while a person is undergoing diagnostic imaging for other conditions. Some people with renal oncocytoma will have abdominal or flank pain; blood in the urine; and/or an abdominal mass. Although these tumors can occur in people of all ages, they most commonly develop in men who are over age 50. The exact underlying cause of most isolated (single tumor affecting one kidney) renal oncocytomas is unknown; however, multiple and bilateral (affecting both kidneys) renal oncocytomas sometimes occur in people with certain genetic syndromes such as tuberous sclerosis complex and Birt-Hogg-Dube syndrome. Although many benign tumors do not require treatment unless they are causing unpleasant symptoms, it can be difficult to confidently differentiate a renal oncocytoma from renal cell carcinoma. Most affected people are, therefore, treated with surgery which allows for confirmation of the diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005300-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Renal oncocytoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Renal oncocytoma? Most people with a renal oncocytoma do not have any signs or symptoms. In fact, these tumors are often discovered incidentally (by chance) while a person is undergoing diagnostic imaging for other conditions. In about a third of cases, people with renal oncocytoma will present with abdominal or flank pain; blood in the urine; and/or an abdominal mass. Affected people usually have a single, unilateral (only affecting one kidney) renal oncocytoma. However, multiple, bilateral (affecting both kidneys) tumors have rarely been reported in people with tuberous sclerosis complex and Birt-Hogg-Dube syndrome. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Renal oncocytoma. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Mitochondrial inheritance - Neoplasm - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005300-3" qtype="causes">What causes Renal oncocytoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes a renal oncocytoma? The exact underlying cause of most renal oncocytomas is unknown. However, researchers suspect that acquired (not present at birth) changes in mitochondrial DNA may play a role in the development of some of these tumors. Renal oncocytomas sometimes occur in people with certain genetic syndromes such as tuberous sclerosis complex and Birt-Hogg-Dube syndrome. In these cases, affected people often have multiple and bilateral (affecting both kidneys) oncocytomas and may also have family members with these tumors. When renal oncocytomas are part of a genetic syndrome, they are caused by changes (mutations) in a specific gene. Tuberous sclerosis complex is caused by mutations in the TSC1 gene or TSC2 gene, while Birt-Hogg-Dube syndrome is caused by mutations in the FLCN gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0005300-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Renal oncocytoma inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is a renal oncocytoma inherited?  Most renal oncocytomas are not inherited. They usually occur sporadically in people with no family history of tumors. However, in rare cases, they can occur in people with certain genetic syndromes such as tuberous sclerosis complex and Birt-Hogg-Dube syndrome. Both of these conditions are inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0005300-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Renal oncocytoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is renal oncocytoma diagnosed? A diagnosis of renal oncocytoma is often suspected based on imaging studies such as computed tomography (CT scan) and/or magnetic resonance imaging (MRI scan). However, it can be difficult to differentiate a renal oncocytoma from renal cell carcinoma based on imaging studies alone. Although researchers are currently studying several new techniques for the diagnosis of renal oncocytoma, a biopsy and surgery are typically necessary to confirm the diagnosis. Is genetic testing available for renal oncocytoma? Genetic testing is not available for many people with renal oncocytoma since most of these tumors occur sporadically (by chance) and are not caused by a genetic mutation. However, genetic testing is an option for people with an inherited condition that predisposes to renal oncocytoma such as tuberous sclerosis complex and Birt-Hogg-Dube syndrome. Carrier testing for at-risk relatives and prenatal testing are possible if the disease-causing mutation in the family is known. The Genetic Testing Registry (GTR) is a centralized online resource for information about genetic tests. It provides a list of laboratories performing genetic testing for tuberous sclerosis complex and Birt-Hogg-Dube syndrome. The intended audience for the GTR is health care providers and researchers. Patients and consumers with specific questions about a genetic test should contact a health care provider or a genetics professional.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0005300-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Renal oncocytoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might renal oncocytoma be treated? Most renal oncocytomas are benign (non-cancerous) and metastasis is very rare. Although many benign tumors do not require treatment unless they are causing unpleasant symptoms, it can be difficult to confidently differentiate a renal oncocytoma from renal cell carcinoma based on diagnostic imaging tests alone. Most people are, therefore, treated with surgery which allows for confirmation of the diagnosis. If a renal oncocytoma is strongly suspected prior to surgery, a more conservative procedure such as a partial nephrectomy, may be performed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
