<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005025" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7446/precocious-puberty">
<Focus>Precocious puberty</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0034013</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Sexual precocity</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Idiopathic sexual precocity</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Familial precocious puberty</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Aromatase excess syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005025-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Precocious puberty ?</Question>
			<Answer>Precocious puberty is when a person&apos;s sexual and physical traits develop and mature earlier than normal. Normal puberty typically begins between ages 10 and 14 for girls, and ages 12 and 16 for boys. The start of puberty depends on various factors such as family history, nutrition and gender. The cause of precocious puberty is not always known. Some cases of precocious puberty are due to conditions that cause changes in the body&apos;s release of hormones. Treatment involves medications that can stop the release of sexual hormones.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005025-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Precocious puberty ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Precocious puberty? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Precocious puberty. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Hypothyroidism 7.5% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Elevated follicle stimulating hormone - Elevated luteinizing hormone - Isosexual precocious puberty - Short stature - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005025-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Precocious puberty ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the long term effects of treatment for precocious puberty? Several studies have looked at the long-term effects of treatment with hormone therapy on children with precocious puberty. Long-term hormone treatment has been found to be safe for the reproductive system and helpful in reaching target adult height levels. Additionally, there is little evidence suggesting that long term hormone treatment is associated with psychological or behavioral problems. More studies are needed to determine this association.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
