<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005505" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4768/schwannomatosis">
<Focus>Schwannomatosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1335929</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Neurilemmomatosis congenital cutaneous</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital cutaneous neurilemmomatosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Neurofibromatosis type 3</Synonym>
		<Synonym>NF3</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Neurofibromatosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005505-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Schwannomatosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Schwannomatosis is a rare form of neurofibromatosis that is primarily characterized by multiple schwannomas (benign tumors of the nervous system) in the absence of bilateral (affecting both sides) vestibular schwannomas. Signs and symptoms of the condition vary based on the size, location and number of schwannomas but may include pain; numbness; tingling; and/or weakness in the fingers and toes. Inherited forms of the disorder account for only 15 percent of all cases. In some of these families, schwannomatosis is caused by changes (mutations) in the SMARCB1 or LZTR1 genes; in other cases, the exact underlying cause is unknown. When inherited, the condition is passed down in an autosomal dominant manner with highly variable expressivity and reduced penetrance. Treatment is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person but may include medications and/or surgery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005505-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Schwannomatosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Schwannomatosis? Signs and symptoms of the schwannomatosis often develop during adulthood between ages 25 and 30. Affected people generally have multiple schwannomas, which are benign tumors of the nervous system. In schwannomatosis, these tumors can grow along any nerve in the body, although they are less common on the vestibular nerve (vestibular schwannomas, also known as acoustic neuromas). People with vestibular schwannomas, especially those with tumors affecting the vestibular nerve on both sides of the head (bilateral), may have neurofibromatosis type 2 instead. The signs and symptoms associated with schwannomatosis vary based on the size and location of the schwannomas. The most common symptom is chronic pain, which can develop as a growing schwannoma presses on nerves or surrounding tissues. Some people may develop a mass if the schwannomas is located just beneath the skin. Others can experience neurological symptoms such as numbness; tingling; and/or weakness in the fingers and toes. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Schwannomatosis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the skin - Abnormality of the vertebral column - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Incomplete penetrance - Meningioma - Schwannoma - Somatic mutation - Spinal cord tumor - Variable expressivity - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005505-3" qtype="causes">What causes Schwannomatosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes schwannomatosis? Some cases of schwannomatosis are caused by changes (mutations) in the SMARCB1 or LZTR1 genes. SMARCB1 and LZTR1 are tumor suppressor genes, which means that they encode a protein that stops cells from growing and dividing too rapidly or in an uncontrolled way. Mutations in these genes result in abnormal proteins that are unable to carry out their normal roles. This contributes to the development of the many different types of tumors found in schwannomatosis. When schwannomatosis is caused by a mutation in SMARCB1 or LZTR1, the affected person is typically born with one mutated copy of the gene in each cell and is, therefore, genetically predisposed to develop the tumors associated with the condition. For a tumor to form, two copies of the gene must be altered. The mutation in the second copy of the gene is considered a somatic mutation because it occurs during a person&apos;s lifetime and is not inherited. In affected people without a mutation in SMARCB1 or LZTR1, the underlying cause of the condition is unknown.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0005505-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Schwannomatosis inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is schwannomatosis inherited? Approximately 15% percent of all schwannomatosis cases are thought to be inherited. In these cases, the condition is thought to be inherited in an autosomal dominant manner with highly variable expressivity and reduced penetrance. This means that a person only needs a change (mutation) in one copy of the responsible gene in each cell to have a genetic predisposition to the tumors associated with schwannomatosis. In some cases, an affected person inherits the mutation from an affected parent. Other cases may result from new (de novo) mutations in the gene. These cases occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family. People with an inherited form of schwannomatosis have a 50% chance with each pregnancy of passing the condition on to the next generation.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0005505-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Schwannomatosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is schwannomatosis diagnosed? A diagnosis of schwannomatosis is often suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms, especially if there are other family members with the condition. Additional testing can then be ordered to further support the diagnosis and rule out other conditions with similar features (namely, neurofibromatosis type 2). This may include: Tumor pathology confirming that the growths are, in fact, schwannomas Imaging studies, such as an MRI examining the vestibular nerve. It is important to rule out the presence of bilateral (affecting both sides) vestibular schwannomas which would be suggestive of neurofibromatosis type 2 rather than schwannomatosis Genetic testing for a change (mutation) in the SMARCB1 or LZTR1 genes. Unfortunately, genetic testing is not informative in all people affected by schwannomatosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0005505-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Schwannomatosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might schwannomatosis be treated? Treatment for schwannomatosis is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person. For example, pain is one of the most common symptoms of the condition. Treatment with medications such as gabapentin or pregabalin and the use of short-acting opioids and/or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatories for pain can be successful for many patients. If pain cannot be managed with other means or if the schwannomas are causing other symptoms, they can be surgically removed. However this treatment is often used as a last resort because surgery may put patients at risk of further neurologic problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
