<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005916" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/405/subaortic-stenosis-short-stature-syndrome">
<Focus>Subaortic stenosis short stature syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0158621</CUI>
			<CUI>C0018133</CUI>
			<CUI>C0340375</CUI>
			<CUI>C1279471</CUI>
			<CUI>C0424639</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Onat syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005916-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Subaortic stenosis short stature syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Subaortic stenosis short stature syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Subaortic stenosis short stature syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the aorta 90% Abnormality of the voice 90% Anteverted nares 90% Arrhythmia 90% Short stature 90% Hernia of the abdominal wall 50% Kyphosis 50% Obesity 50% Respiratory insufficiency 50% Scoliosis 50% Abnormality of lipid metabolism 7.5% Acne 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia affecting the eye 7.5% Biliary tract abnormality 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Epicanthus 7.5% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 7.5% Microdontia 7.5% Nystagmus 7.5% Short neck 7.5% Single transverse palmar crease 7.5% Synostosis of carpal bones 7.5% Type II diabetes mellitus 7.5% Autosomal recessive inheritance - Barrel-shaped chest - Broad finger - Broad toe - Diastema - Flat face - Glaucoma - Growth delay - Hypoplasia of midface - Hypoplasia of the maxilla - Intellectual disability - Low-set ears - Malar flattening - Membranous subvalvular aortic stenosis - Microcornea - Microphthalmia - Narrow mouth - Opacification of the corneal stroma - Pectus excavatum - Round face - Shield chest - Short foot - Short nose - Short palm - Short phalanx of finger - Short toe - Short upper lip - Small hand - Strabismus - Subaortic stenosis - Wide intermamillary distance - Wide nasal bridge - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
