<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005514" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8169/sclerosing-mesenteritis">
<Focus>Sclerosing mesenteritis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0267770</CUI>
			<CUI>C2721733</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Retractile mesenteritis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Liposclerotic mesenteritis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mesenteric lipogranuloma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mesenteric fibromatosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mesenteric panniculitis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005514-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sclerosing mesenteritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sclerosing mesenteritis is one of many terms used to describe a spectrum of chronic inflammatory diseases affecting the small bowel mesentery, the membrane that anchors the small intestine to the back of the abdominal wall.  The cause of this condition is unknown. The most common symptom is abdominal pain or a palpable abdominal mass. Click on the highlighted text to view an illustration of the small intestine.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005514-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sclerosing mesenteritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of sclerosing mesenteritis? Common symptoms of sclerosing mesenteritis include abdominal pain or a palpable abdominal mass, weight loss, abdominal distention, vomiting, diarrhea, constipation, and fever of unknown cause.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005514-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Sclerosing mesenteritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might sclerosing mesenteritis be treated? Treatment for sclerosing mesenteritis is most often based on the stage of the disease. In the early stage when fat necrosis predominates, many physicians tend not to treat because the disease process may regress spontaneously. When chronic inflammation becomes a prominent feature but fibrosis is not yet fully developed, medical treatment with corticosteroids, colchicine, immunosuppressants, or orally administered progesterone may be beneficial in the prevention of disease progression. These medications are only given for a short period since they can cause serious side effects. Some studies have shown that patients with sclerosing mesenteritis may benefit from a drug combination of tamoxifen and prednisone. When fibrosis becomes extensive, especially when the disease presents as a large fibrotic mass with bowel obstruction, surgical interventions may be necessary.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
