<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005542" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/322/senior-loken-syndrome">
<Focus>Senior Loken Syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Senior-Loken Syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Renal dysplasia retinal aplasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Renal-retinal syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Juvenile nephronophthisis with Leber amaurosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Loken-Senior syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005542-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Senior Loken Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Senior Loken syndrome is a rare disorder characterized by the combination of two specific features: a kidney condition called nephronophthisis and an eye condition known as Leber congenital amaurosis. It can be caused by mutations in one of at least six genes. The proteins produced from these genes are known or suspected to play roles in cell structures called cilia. These microscopic, finger-like projections stick out on the surface of cells and are involved in signaling pathways that transmit information between cells. Cilia are important for the structure and function of many types of cells, including certain cells in the kidneys. They are also necessary for the perception of sensory input (such as vision, hearing, and smell). Senior Loken syndrome is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005542-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Senior Loken Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Senior Loken Syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Senior Loken Syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of retinal pigmentation 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Hypertension 90% Multicystic kidney dysplasia 90% Polycystic kidney dysplasia 90% Short stature 90% Visual impairment 90% Abnormality of the renal tubule 50% Abnormality of bone mineral density 7.5% Cataract 7.5% Cone-shaped epiphysis 7.5% Congenital hepatic fibrosis 7.5% Incoordination 7.5% Anemia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Heterogeneous - Nephronophthisis - Polydipsia - Polyuria - Stage 5 chronic kidney disease - Tapetoretinal degeneration - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
