<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005974" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/1443/syndromic-microphthalmia-type-3">
<Focus>Syndromic microphthalmia, type 3</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0026010</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>MCOPS3</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Microphthalmia and esophageal atresia syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Anophthalmia clinical with associated anomalies</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Anophthalmia esophageal genital syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>AEG syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Microphthalmia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005974-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Syndromic microphthalmia, type 3 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Syndromic microphthalmia, type 3 is a rare condition that affects the eyes and other parts of the body. Babies with this condition are generally born without eyeballs (anophthalmia) or with eyes that are unusually small (microphthalmia). Both of these abnormalities can be associated with severe vision loss. Other signs and symptoms of syndromic microphthalmia, type 3 may include seizures, brain malformations, esophageal atresia, delayed motor development, learning disabilities, and sensorineural hearing loss. The condition is caused by changes (mutations) in the SOX2 gene and is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Treatment is based on the signs and symptoms present in each person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005974-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Syndromic microphthalmia, type 3 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Syndromic microphthalmia, type 3? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Syndromic microphthalmia, type 3. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aplasia/Hypoplasia affecting the eye 90% Tracheoesophageal fistula 90% Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 50% Cryptorchidism 50% External ear malformation 50% Visual impairment 50% Abnormality of the ribs 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Displacement of the external urethral meatus 7.5% Holoprosencephaly 7.5% Hydrocephalus 7.5% Hypoplasia of penis 7.5% Iris coloboma 7.5% Patent ductus arteriosus 7.5% Sclerocornea 7.5% Ventricular septal defect 7.5% Agenesis of corpus callosum - Anophthalmia - Anterior pituitary hypoplasia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Butterfly vertebrae - Coloboma - Esophageal atresia - Frontal bossing - Hemivertebrae - Hypogonadotrophic hypogonadism - Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum - Hypospadias - Hypothalamic hamartoma - Microcephaly - Micropenis - Microphthalmia - Missing ribs - Muscular hypotonia - Optic nerve hypoplasia - Postnatal growth retardation - Rib fusion - Sensorineural hearing impairment - Short stature - Spastic diplegia - Spastic tetraplegia - Specific learning disability - Supernumerary ribs - Vertebral fusion - Vertebral hypoplasia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
