<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005175" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/11894/pulmonary-alveolar-microlithiasis">
<Focus>Pulmonary alveolar microlithiasis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0155912</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005175-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pulmonary alveolar microlithiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pulmonary alveolar microlithiasis is a disorder in which tiny fragments (microliths) of calcium phosphate gradually accumulate in the small air sacs (alveoli) of the lungs. These deposits eventually cause widespread damage to the alveoli and surrounding lung tissue (interstitial lung disease). People with this disorder may also develop a persistent cough and difficulty breathing (dyspnea), especially during physical exertion. Chest pain that worsens when coughing, sneezing, or taking deep breaths is another common feature. People with pulmonary alveolar microlithiasis may also develop calcium phosphate deposits in other organs and tissue of the body. Though the  course of the disease can be variable, many cases slowly progress to lung fibrosis, respiratory failure, or cor pulmonale. The only effective therapy is lung transplantation. In some cases, pulmonary alveolar microlithiasis is caused by mutations in the SLC34A2 gene and inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005175-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pulmonary alveolar microlithiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Pulmonary alveolar microlithiasis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Pulmonary alveolar microlithiasis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal recessive inheritance - Intraalveolar nodular calcifications - Onset - Progressive pulmonary function impairment - Restrictive respiratory insufficiency - Slow progression - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
