<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005067" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4488/primrose-syndrome">
<Focus>Primrose syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0796121</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Ossified ear cartilages with mental deficiency, muscle wasting, and bony changes</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005067-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Primrose syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Primrose syndrome is characterized by severe learning disabilities, bony ear cartilage, a hard bony growth in the roof of the mouth, cystic changes on the top of the upper arm and leg bones, cataracts, hearing loss, adult-onset progressive ataxia and nervous system disease, and brain calcification. The cause of the condition is currently unknown. Treatment is supportive.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005067-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Primrose syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Primrose syndrome? Signs and symptoms of primrose syndrome that have been reported in the literature include: Severe learning disabilities Boney ear cartilage Cystic changes in to top of the arm and leg bones Cataracts (clouding of the lens of the eyes) Recurrent ear infections Hearing loss  Pogressive ataxia (uncoordinated movement) often with onset in   Pyramidal signs (which shows there is a problem with the nervous system) Muscle wasting of the lower limbs Torus palatinus (a hard bony growth in the roof of the mouth) Brain calcification (mineral deposits in the brain) Sparse hair Unique facial features (e.g., deep-set eyes, protruding lower jaw, droopy eyelids) Schizophrenia and a germ cell tumor was also reported in isolated cases. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Primrose syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal form of the vertebral bodies 90% Abnormality of the hip bone 90% Abnormality of the palate 90% Anemia 90% Bone cyst 90% Calcification of the auricular cartilage 90% Cataract 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Conductive hearing impairment 90% Developmental regression 90% Gait disturbance 90% Hydrocephalus 90% Kyphosis 90% Macrotia 90% Myopathy 90% Osteolysis 90% Scoliosis 90% Abnormality of the testis 50% Anonychia 50% Gynecomastia 50% Malar flattening 50% Narrow chest 50% Pectus excavatum 50% Plagiocephaly 50% Seizures 50% Short stature 50% Synophrys 50% Aggressive behavior 5% Autism 5% Bilateral cryptorchidism 5% Cerebral calcification 5% Self-injurious behavior 5% Absent axillary hair - Absent facial hair - Basilar impression - Brachycephaly - Broad forehead - Deeply set eye - Distal amyotrophy - Generalized osteoporosis - Genu valgum - Hearing impairment - Hip contracture - Hypoplasia of midface - Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum - Hypoplasia of the maxilla - Intellectual disability - Irregular vertebral endplates - Knee flexion contracture - Macrocephaly - Muscular hypotonia - Narrow iliac wings - Neurodegeneration - Pes cavus - Posterior polar cataract - Posterior scalloping of vertebral bodies - Ptosis - Short distal phalanx of finger - Sporadic - Superiorly displaced ears - Thick lower lip vermilion - Truncal obesity - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005067-3" qtype="causes">What causes Primrose syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes primrose syndrome? The cause of primrose syndrome is currently unknown. Cases of affected males and a affected female have been reported in the literature. All cases seem to be sporadic. Sporadic refers to either a genetic disorder that occurs for the first time in a family due to a new mutation or the chance occurrence of a non-genetic disorder or abnormality that is not likely to recur in a family.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
