<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005345" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9568/retroperitoneal-fibrosis">
<Focus>Retroperitoneal fibrosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0035357</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Idiopathic retroperitoneal fibrosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ormond's disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>IgG4-related retroperitoneal fibrosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ormond disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005345-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Retroperitoneal fibrosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Retroperitoneal fibrosis is a slowly progressive disorder in which the tubes that carry urine from the kidneys to the bladder (ureters) and other abdominal organs are blocked by a fibrous mass and inflammation in the back of the abdomen. The disorder may cause chronic unilateral obstructive uropathy or chronic bilateral obstructive uropathy. Risk factors for retroperitoneal fibrosis include asbestos exposure, smoking, tumor, infection, trauma, radiotherapy, surgery, and use of certain drugs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005345-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Retroperitoneal fibrosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the symptoms of retroperitoneal fibrosis? Early symptoms of retroperitoneal fibrosis may include: Dull pain in the abdomen that increases with time Swelling of one leg Decreased circulation in the legs leading to pain and discoloration Late symptoms of retroperitoneal fibrosis may include: Decreased urine output Total lack of urine (anuria) Nausea, vomiting, changes in thinking caused by kidney failure and the resulting build-up of toxic chemicals in the blood. Severe abdominal pain with hemorrhage due to ischemic bowel</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005345-3" qtype="causes">What causes Retroperitoneal fibrosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes retroperitoneal fibrosis? The cause of retroperitoneal fibrosis is unknown in many cases (idiopathic). Some cases occur in association with other factors, including: Asbestos exposure Smoking Neoplasms (tumor) Infections Trauma Radiotherapy Surgery Use of certain drugs</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0005345-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Retroperitoneal fibrosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might retroperitoneal fibrosis be treated? Treatment of retroperitoneal fibrosis may include: Corticosteroid therapy Tamoxifen Surgery Stents Corticosteroids are tried first. Dosing will be prescribed on a case by case basis, but doses often vary between 30 and 60 mg per day. Corticosteroids are then tapered slowly. Some people with retroperitoneal fibrosis may continue on low dose maintenance therapy for up to 2 years. If corticosteroid treatment doesn&apos;t work, a biopsy should be done to confirm the diagnosis. Other medicines to suppress the immune system, such as mycophenolate mofetil, methotrexate, azathioprine, cyclophosphamide or tamoxifen can be prescribed alone or in combination with corticosteroids. When medicine does not work, surgery and stents (draining tubes) are considered. Stents (drainage tubes) placed in the ureter or in the renal pelvis may provide short-term relief of the symptoms until the condition is surgically treated. Surgery aims to remove the mass and/or free the ureters.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
