<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005008" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/9762/potocki-shaffer-syndrome">
<Focus>Potocki-Shaffer syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1832588</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>PSS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Deletion of chromosome 11p11.2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Proximal 11p deletion syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>11p11.2 deletion</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005008-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Potocki-Shaffer syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Potocki-Shaffer syndrome is a contiguous gene deletion syndrome associated with deletions in a specific region of chromosome 11 (11p11.2). The characteristic features of Potocki-Shaffer syndrome include openings in the two bones that form the top and sides of the skull (enlarged parietal foramina), multiple benign bone tumors called exostoses, intellectual disability, developmental delay, a distinctive facial appearance, autism and problems with vision and hearing. In some cases, individuals with the syndrome may have a defect in the heart, kidneys, or urinary tract. The features of Potocki-Shaffer syndrome result from the loss of several genes on the short (p) arm of chromosome 11. In particular, the deletion of a gene called ALX4 causes enlarged parietal foramina, while the loss of another gene, EXT2, causes the multiple exostoses. Another condition called WAGR syndrome is caused by a deletion of genetic material in the p arm of chromosome 11, specifically at position 11p13. Occasionally, a deletion is large enough to include the 11p11.2 and 11p13 regions. Individuals with such a deletion have signs and symptoms of both Potocki-Shaffer syndrome and WAGR syndrome. A referral to an early childhood intervention and developmental-behavioral specialist at the time of diagnosis and to have an evaluation for vision and hearing problems, as well as a full skeletal survey at the time of diagnosis or by age 3 years, whichever is later, is recommended.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005008-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Potocki-Shaffer syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Potocki-Shaffer syndrome? The signs and symptoms can vary depending on the area and amount deleted. Some individuals with the syndrome have few issues and lead a normal life while others are very severely affected. The following signs and symptoms may be present:  Enlarged parietal foramina  Multiple exostoses  Intellectual disability  Developmental delay  Failure to thrive  Autism  Behavioral problems  Deafness  Myopia (nearsightedness)  Nystagmus  Cataract  Strabismus  Aniridia  Distinct facial features (microcephaly, epicanthus, sparse eyebrows, prominent nose, small mandible)  Kidney problems MedlinePlus has information pages on some of these signs and symptoms or can direct to you other trusted websites that offer information. If you would like to read more, visit the link and enter the sign and symptom about which you would like to learn.  The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Potocki-Shaffer syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Cognitive impairment 90% Decreased skull ossification 90% Exostoses 90% Craniofacial dysostosis 33% Cutaneous syndactyly between fingers 2 and 5 5% Multiple exostoses 10/10 Downturned corners of mouth 8/9 Micropenis 5/6 Single transverse palmar crease 5/6 Parietal foramina 9/11 Intellectual disability 7/10 Brachycephaly 6/9 Short philtrum 6/9 Sparse lateral eyebrow 6/9 Brachydactyly syndrome 5/8 Muscular hypotonia 5/9 Wormian bones 3/6 Epicanthus 4/9 Telecanthus 4/9 Seizures 2/11 Broad forehead - Contiguous gene syndrome - High forehead - Short nose - Turricephaly - Underdeveloped nasal alae - Wide nasal bridge - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005008-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Potocki-Shaffer syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Potocki-Shaffer be treated? The treatment depends on the signs and symptoms present in the affected individual. The following treatment options or recommendations might be offered: Treatment of Wilms tumor, which may include surgery to remove the kidney, radiation therapy and chemotherapy. Treatment of aniridia is aimed at maintaining vision. Glaucoma or cataracts can be treated with medication or surgery. Contact lenses should be avoided because they can damage the cornea. In cases of abnormalities in the testes or ovaries, surgery may be needed to remove them or to prevent cancer (gonadoblastoma). After they testes or ovaries are removed hormone replacement is needed. Children with undescended testicles (cryptorchidism) may also need surgery. In a study with 6 patients and a review of 31 previously reported cases of Potocki-Shaffer syndrome, the researchers made several recommendations for the care of children with the syndrome. These include: Referral to early childhood intervention and a developmental-behavioral specialist at the time of diagnosis; A full skeletal survey at diagnosis or by age three; Screening for strabismus and nystagmus by the pediatrician (at every well-child examination), and referral to a pediatric ophthalmologist at diagnosis or by age six months; Hearing loss evaluations in infants with the syndrome and after that at three months of age; audiogram at age one year and annually thereafter; Fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) studies and genetic counseling should be offered to the parents of a child with Potocki-Shaffer syndrome; Referral to a specialist in development and behavior at the time of diagnosis for vision therapy, physical, occupational and speech therapy; Abdominal and kidney ultrasound due to the possible risk of developing a Wilms&apos; tumor, especially in those individuals who have a deletion in the 11p13 region;  Cardiac evaluation to detect any heart abnormalities; Thyroid hormone level measurements to detect the hypothyroidism; and MRI scans are recommended if the individual has seizures, microcephaly, or global developmental delay.  Some individuals with Potocki-Shaffer syndrome, WAGR syndrome, and renal insufficiency may be treated with dialysis or kidney transplant.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
