<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005065" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4997/primary-spontaneous-pneumothorax">
<Focus>Primary spontaneous pneumothorax</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1868193</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Familial spontaneous pneumothorax</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Spontaneous pneumothorax</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005065-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Primary spontaneous pneumothorax ?</Question>
			<Answer>Primary spontaneous pneumothorax is an abnormal accumulation of air in the pleural space (the space between the lungs and the chest cavity) that can result in the partial or complete collapse of a lung. It is called primary because it occurs in the absence of lung disease such as emphysema and spontaneous because the pneumothhorax was not caused by an injury such as a rib fracture. Primary spontaneous pneumothorax is likely caused by the formation of small sacs of air (blebs) in lung tissue that rupture, causing air to leak into the pleural space. This air creates pressure on the lung and can lead to its collapse. Symptoms may include chest pain on the side of the collapsed lung and shortness of breath. The blebs that lead to primary spontaneous pneumothorax may be present in an individual&apos;s lung (or lungs) for a long time before they rupture. A change in air pressure or a very sudden deep breath may cause a rupture to occur. In most cases, there are no prior signs of illness. Once a bleb ruptures and causes a pneumothorax, rates for recurrence may be as high as 13 to 60 percent. Many researchers believe that genetic factors may play a role in the development of primary spontaneous pneumothorax. In rare cases, the condition can be caused by mutations in the FLCN gene. In these cases, the condition follows an autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance. In addition, several genetic disorders have been linked to primary spontaneous pneumothorax, including Marfan syndrome, homocystinuria, and Birt-Hogg-Dube syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005065-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Primary spontaneous pneumothorax ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Primary spontaneous pneumothorax? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Primary spontaneous pneumothorax. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the pleura 90% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Incomplete penetrance - Spontaneous pneumothorax - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
