<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005640" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4877/single-upper-central-incisor">
<Focus>Single upper central incisor</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1840235</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Solitary median maxillary central incisor</Synonym>
		<Synonym>SMMCI</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fused incisors</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Single central maxillary incisor</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Solitary median maxillary central incisor syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005640-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Single upper central incisor ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Single upper central incisor? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Single upper central incisor. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Choanal atresia 90% Midnasal stenosis 90% Short stature 90% Cognitive impairment 50% Hypotelorism 50% Intrauterine growth retardation 50% Microcephaly 50% Narrow nasal bridge 50% Premature birth 50% Short philtrum 50% Tented upper lip vermilion 50% Holoprosencephaly 33% Abnormality of the skin 7.5% Anosmia 7.5% Anterior hypopituitarism 7.5% Anteverted nares 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 7.5% Asthma 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Coloboma 7.5% Cyclopia 7.5% Duodenal stenosis 7.5% Hypoplasia of penis 7.5% Hypothyroidism 7.5% Iris coloboma 7.5% Maternal diabetes 7.5% Renal hypoplasia/aplasia 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Short nose 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Tetralogy of Fallot 7.5% Vertebral segmentation defect 7.5% Anophthalmia 5% Microphthalmia 5% Prominent median palatal raphe 14/14 Growth hormone deficiency 5/7 Midnasal stenosis 9/14 Choanal atresia 8/14 Hypotelorism 8/14 Short stature 7/14 Microcephaly 6/14 Specific learning disability 5/14 Intellectual disability, mild 3/14 Abnormality of chromosome segregation 2/14 Abnormality of the nasopharynx 1/14 Cleft upper lip 1/14 Autosomal dominant inheritance - Torus palatinus - Variable expressivity - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
