<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005681" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7664/sneddon-syndrome">
<Focus>Sneddon syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0282492</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Sneddon's syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Livedo reticularis and cerebrovascular accidents</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cerebro-vascular lesions and livedo reticularis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ehrmann-Sneddon syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Livedo racemosa and cerebrovascular accidents</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005681-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sneddon syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sneddon syndrome is a progressive condition characterized by livedo reticularis (bluish net-like patterns of discoloration on the skin) and neurological abnormalities. Symptoms may include headache, dizziness, high blood pressure, heart disease, mini-strokes and/or stroke. Reduced blood flow to the brain may cause lesions to develop within the central nervous system. This can lead to reduced mental capacity, memory loss and other neurological symptoms. The exact cause of Sneddon syndrome is unknown. Some familial cases have been described. It has also been associated with obliterating vasculitis and antiphospholipid antibody syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005681-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sneddon syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Sneddon syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Sneddon syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Behavioral abnormality 90% Cerebral ischemia 90% Cutis marmorata 90% Memory impairment 90% Migraine 90% Vertigo 90% Acrocyanosis 50% Amaurosis fugax 50% Developmental regression 50% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 50% Hypertension 50% Muscle weakness 50% Neurological speech impairment 50% Visual impairment 50% Autoimmunity 7.5% Chorea 7.5% Intracranial hemorrhage 7.5% Nephropathy 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Tremor 7.5% Antiphospholipid antibody positivity - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Dysarthria - Facial palsy - Headache - Hemiplegia - Mental deterioration - Progressive - Sporadic - Stroke - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0005681-3" qtype="causes">What causes Sneddon syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Sneddon syndrome? The cause of Sneddon syndrome is not well understood. It is possible that the syndrome has more than one cause (or way in which it may develop in a person). Some people develop Sneddon syndrome in association with other medical conditions such as obliterating vasculitis and antiphospholipid antibody syndrome. Most cases of Sneddon syndrome occur in people with no other family history of the condition, however there have been a few families with more than one member affected. A recent study found that in one family, Sneddon syndrome developed as a result of inheriting two changes in the CECR1 gene. In this family, Sneddon syndrome was inherited in an autosomal recessive fashion. Other case reports of familial Sneddon syndrome suggest an autosomal dominant pattern of inheritance.  It is not currently known if all familial cases are due to changes in CECR1.  Currently there is a research study titled, Genetics, Pathophysiology, and Treatment of Recessive Autoinflammatory Diseases, which is studying the effects of CECR1 gene mutations. The study lead is Dr. Daniel Kastner of the National Human Genome Research Institute. Click on the study title to learn more.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
