<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0005700" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/4919/spastic-paraplegia-11">
<Focus>Spastic paraplegia 11</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0037772</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>SPG11</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary spastic paraplegia mental impairment and thin corpus callosum</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Autosomal recessive spastic paraplegia type 11</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary spastic paraplegia 11</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Nakamura Osame syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary spastic paraplegia - autosomal dominant inheritance</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary spastic paraplegia - autosomal recessive inheritance</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0005700-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Spastic paraplegia 11 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Spastic paraplegia 11 is a form of hereditary spastic paraplegia. People with spastic paraplegia 11 experience progressive muscle stiffness and eventual paralysis of the lower limbs, as well as a range of other neurologic symptoms. The tissue connecting the left and right halves of the brain (corpus callosum) is abnormally thin in individuals with this condition. Spastic paraplegia 11 is caused by mutations in the SPG11 gene and is passed through families in an autosomal recessive fashion.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0005700-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Spastic paraplegia 11 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Spastic paraplegia 11? Signs and symptoms of spastic paraplegia 11, include: Spasticity (progressive muscle stiffness) Paraplegia (eventual paralysis of the lower limbs)   Numbness, tingling, or pain in the arms and legs Disturbance in the nerves used for muscle movement Intellectual disability Exaggerated reflexes of the lower limbs  Speech difficulties  Reduced bladder control  Muscle wasting  Less common features, include: Difficulty swallowing  High-arched feet  Scoliosis  Involuntary movements of the eyes Age at time of symptom onset varies from infancy to early adulthood, with onset in infancy to adolescence being most common. Learning disability may begin in childhood. Most people experience a decline in intellectual ability and an increase in muscle weakness and nerve abnormalities over time. As the condition progresses, some people require wheelchair assistance (often 10 to 20 years after symptom onset). The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Spastic paraplegia 11. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 90% Cerebral cortical atrophy 90% Gait disturbance 90% Incoordination 90% Neurological speech impairment 90% Seizures 90% Ventriculomegaly 90% Abnormality of the periventricular white matter - Adult onset - Agenesis of corpus callosum - Ankle clonus - Ataxia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Babinski sign - Childhood onset - Decreased number of peripheral myelinated nerve fibers - Degeneration of the lateral corticospinal tracts - Distal peripheral sensory neuropathy - Dysarthria - Dysphagia - Gaze-evoked nystagmus - Hyperreflexia - Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum - Impaired vibration sensation in the lower limbs - Intellectual disability - Knee clonus - Lower limb muscle weakness - Lower limb spasticity - Macular degeneration - Mental deterioration - Motor polyneuropathy - Obesity - Pes cavus - Progressive - Retinal degeneration - Sensory neuropathy - Spastic gait - Spastic paraplegia - Specific learning disability - Thenar muscle atrophy - Tip-toe gait - Urinary bladder sphincter dysfunction - Urinary incontinence - Urinary urgency - Visual impairment - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
