<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006210" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/2621/trismus-pseudocamptodactyly-syndrome">
<Focus>Trismus-pseudocamptodactyly syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265226</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hecht syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dutch-Kentucky syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Distal arthrogryposis type 7</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Arthrogryposis distal type 7</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Myosinopathies</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006210-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Trismus-pseudocamptodactyly syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Trismus-pseudocamptodactyly syndrome is a disorder of muscle development and function. It is characterized by short muscles and tendons resulting in limited range of motion of the hands, legs, and mouth. Both sporadic occurrence and autosomal dominant inheritance have been reported in the medical literature. The most serious complications of the condition occur as a result of the limited mobility of the mouth. Treatment may involve surgical correction and physical therapy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006210-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Trismus-pseudocamptodactyly syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Trismus-pseudocamptodactyly syndrome? While the symptoms of trismus-pseudocamptodactyly syndrome vary from patient to patient, characteristic symptoms include the inability to open the mouth wide (e.g., less than 6 mm, just under 1/4 of an inch) and shortened muscles, including of the hamstrings and calf muscles. As a result of shortened muscles some infants with trismus-pseudocamptodactyly syndrome have closed or clinched fists, club foot, metatarsus adductus, and calcaneovalgus (where the foot bends sharply at the ankle) at birth. Children with this syndrome may crawl on their knuckles. In adulthood the syndrome may cause reduced hand dexterity, however hand limitation does not often interfere with normal function. The most serious complications of the condition occur as a result of the limited mobility of the mouth, including impairment of adequate calorie intake, speech development, dental care, and difficulty with intubation. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Trismus-pseudocamptodactyly syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the musculature 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Short stature 90% Symphalangism affecting the phalanges of the hand 90% Abnormality of the hip bone 7.5% Mandibular prognathia 7.5% Ptosis 7.5% Deep philtrum 5% Macrocephaly 5% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Cutaneous syndactyly of toes - Distal arthrogryposis - Dysphagia - Facial asymmetry - Feeding difficulties - Hammertoe - Hip dislocation - Talipes equinovarus - Trismus - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0006210-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Trismus-pseudocamptodactyly syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might trismus-pseudocamptodactyly syndrome be treated? While the best treatment options for trismus-pseudocamptodactyly syndrome have not been well established cases of improvement of mouth mobility following surgery and physical therapy have been reported in the medical literature. We recommend that you speak with your healthcare provider to learn more about specific treatment options.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
