<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006224" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5372/troyer-syndrome">
<Focus>Troyer syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0393559</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>SPG20</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Spastic paraparesis, childhood-onset, with distal muscle wasting</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Spastic paraplegia, autosomal recessive, Troyer type</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Autosomal recessive spastic paraplegia type 20</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Spastic paraplegia 20, autosomal recessive</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary spastic paraplegia - autosomal recessive inheritance</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006224-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Troyer syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Troyer syndrome is a neurological disorder and one of the many types of hereditary spastic paraplegia. Signs and symptoms typically begin in early childhood and may include progressive muscle weakness and stiffness (spasticity) in the legs; muscle wasting in the hands and feet; paraplegia; leg contractures; developmental delays; speech difficulty; mood swings; and short stature. Symptoms worsen over time, with most people needing a wheelchair by their 50s or 60s. Life expectancy is normal. Troyer syndrome is caused by mutations in the SPG20 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Treatment is symptomatic and supportive.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006224-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Troyer syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Troyer syndrome? The signs and symptoms of Troyer syndrome can vary, and some people are more severely affected than others. Symptoms typically begin in early childhood. Most affected children have delays in walking and talking, followed by slow deterioration in both manner of walking (gait) and speech. Affected people have progressive muscle weakness and stiffness (spasticity) in the legs; muscle wasting in the hands and feet; paraplegia; leg contractures; learning disorders; and short stature. Mood swings and mood disorders, causing inappropriate euphoria and/or crying, are common. Other features can include drooling; exaggerated reflexes (hyperreflexia) in the legs; uncontrollable movements of the arms and legs (choreoathetosis); skeletal abnormalities; and a bending outward (valgus) of the knees. There is generally a slow, progressive decline in muscle and nerve function, and symptoms worsen over time. Most people need a wheelchair by their 50s or 60s. Affected people typically have a normal life expectancy. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Troyer syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Ankle clonus - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Babinski sign - Brachydactyly syndrome - Camptodactyly - Cerebellar atrophy - Childhood onset - Clinodactyly - Difficulty walking - Distal amyotrophy - Drooling - Dysarthria - Dysmetria - Emotional lability - Hammertoe - Hyperextensible hand joints - Hyperplasia of midface - Hyperreflexia - Hypertelorism - Intellectual disability, mild - Knee clonus - Kyphoscoliosis - Lower limb muscle weakness - Motor delay - Pes cavus - Short foot - Short stature - Spastic gait - Spastic paraparesis - Spastic paraplegia - Upper limb spasticity - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0006224-3" qtype="causes">What causes Troyer syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Troyer syndrome? Troyer syndrome is caused by mutations in the SPG20 gene. This gene gives the body instructions to make a protein called spartin, which is present in many body tissues, including those of the nervous system. However, the function of this protein is not fully understood. It is thought to play various roles needed for the functions of cells. Troyer syndrome is assumed to be caused by a loss of function of the spartin protein. More research on the normal functions of the spartin protein is needed to better understand exactly how mutations in the SPG20 gene cause the features of Troyer syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0006224-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Troyer syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Troyer syndrome inherited? Troyer syndrome is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. This means that to be affected, a person must have a mutation in both copies of the responsible gene in each cell. Affected people inherit one mutated copy of the gene from each parent, who is referred to as a carrier. Carriers of an autosomal recessive condition typically do not have any signs or symptoms (they are unaffected). When 2 carriers of an autosomal recessive condition have children, each child has: a 25% (1 in 4) chance to be affected a 50% (1 in 2) chance to be an unaffected carrier like each parent a 25% chance to be unaffected and not be a carrier.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0006224-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Troyer syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Troyer syndrome be treated? There are currently no treatments known to prevent or slow the progression of Troyer syndrome. Treatment aims to relieve symptoms of the disease and improve quality of life. Treatment for spasticity involves both exercise and medication, especially baclofen (Lioresal), which is used either orally or by intrathecal pump. Tizanidine, dantrolene (with precautions), and Botox have also been useful in reducing muscle spasticity. Daily physical therapy is recommended. Treatment may also include: Occupational therapy, assistive walking devices, and ankle-foot orthotics as needed Oxybutynin to reduce urinary urgency Antidepressants or mood stabilizers to manage emotional or mood disorders Additional information about the management of Troyer syndrome can be viewed on the GeneReviews Web site.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
