<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006449" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7893/wilson-disease">
<Focus>Wilson disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0019202</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hepatolenticular degeneration</Synonym>
		<Synonym>WND</Synonym>
		<Synonym>WD</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006449-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Wilson disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Wilson disease is a rare inherited disorder that is characterized by the accumulation of copper in the body. Because high levels of copper are toxic to tissues and organs, this buildup can lead to damage of the liver, brain and eyes. Signs and symptoms of Wilson disease include chronic liver disease, central nervous system abnormalities, and psychiatric (mental health-related) disturbances. It is caused by a mutation of the ATP7B gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Although there is no cure for Wilson disease, therapies exist that aim to reduce or control the amount of copper that accumulates in the body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006449-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Wilson disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Wilson disease? Wilson disease can affect many different systems of the body. Affected people often develop signs and symptoms of chronic liver disease in their teenaged years or early twenties. These features may include jaundice; abnormal fluid retention which can lead to swelling of the legs and/or abdomen; weight loss; nausea and vomiting; and/or fatigue. Unfortunately, some people may not experience any signs until they suddenly develop acute liver failure. Affected people often experience a variety of neurologic (central nervous system-related) signs and symptoms, as well. Neurologic features often develop after the liver has retained a significant amount of copper; however, they have been seen in people with little to no liver damage. These symptoms may include tremors; muscle stiffness; and problems with speech, swallowing and/or physical coordination. Almost all people with neurologic symptoms have Kayser-Fleisher rings - a rusty brown ring around the cornea of the eye that can best be viewed using an ophthalmologist&apos;s slit lamp. About a third of those with Wilson disease will also experience psychiatric (mental health-related) symptoms such as abrupt personality changes, depression accompanied by suicidal thoughts, anxiety, and/or psychosis. Other signs and symptoms may include: Menstrual period irregularities, increased risk of miscarriage and infertility in women Anemia Easy bruising and prolonged bleeding Kidney stones Early-onset arthritis Osteoporosis The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Wilson disease. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Kayser-Fleischer ring 90% Polyneuropathy 5% Aminoaciduria - Atypical or prolonged hepatitis - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Chondrocalcinosis - Cirrhosis - Coma - Dementia - Drooling - Dysarthria - Dysphagia - Dystonia - Esophageal varix - Glycosuria - Hemolytic anemia - Hepatic failure - Hepatomegaly - High nonceruloplasmin-bound serum copper - Hypercalciuria - Hyperphosphaturia - Hypoparathyroidism - Joint hypermobility - Mixed demyelinating and axonal polyneuropathy - Nephrolithiasis - Osteoarthritis - Osteomalacia - Osteoporosis - Personality changes - Poor motor coordination - Proteinuria - Renal tubular dysfunction - Tremor - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0006449-3" qtype="causes">What causes Wilson disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Wilson disease? Wilson disease is caused by changes (mutations) in the ATP7B gene. This gene encodes a protein that plays an important role in the transport of copper from the liver to the rest of the body. It also helps remove excess copper from the body. Mutations in the ATP7B gene prevent this protein from working properly, which can lead to an accumulation of copper in the body. Because high levels of copper are toxic, this buildup can damage tissues and organs and cause the many signs and symptoms of Wilson disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0006449-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Wilson disease inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is Wilson disease inherited? Wilson disease is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. This means that to be affected, a person must have a mutation in both copies of the responsible gene in each cell. The parents of an affected person usually each carry one mutated copy of the gene and are referred to as carriers. Carriers typically do not show signs or symptoms of the condition. When two carriers of an autosomal recessive condition have children, each child has a 25% (1 in 4) risk to have the condition, a 50% (1 in 2) risk to be a carrier like each of the parents, and a 25% chance to not have the condition and not be a carrier.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0006449-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Wilson disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Wilson disease be treated? There is currently no cure for Wilson disease; however, therapies exist that aim to reduce or control the amount of copper that accumulates in the body. Affected people require lifelong treatment, which may include certain medications and/or dietary modifications. If treatment is not effective or if liver failure develops, a liver transplant may be necessary. For more specific information on the treatment and management of Wilson disease, please visit the National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Disease&apos;s (NIDDK) website and/or GeneReviews. Click the link to view these resources.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
