<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006066" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5177/thompson-baraitser-syndrome">
<Focus>Thompson Baraitser syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2931130</CUI>
			<CUI>C1261128</CUI>
			<CUI>C2931226</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006066-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Thompson Baraitser syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Thompson Baraitser syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Thompson Baraitser syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Amniotic constriction ring 90% Finger syndactyly 90% Limitation of joint mobility 90% Pectus excavatum 90% Scoliosis 90% Symphalangism affecting the phalanges of the hand 90% Webbed neck 90% Abnormality of the foot 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the abdominal wall musculature 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the skin 50% Camptodactyly of finger 50% Epicanthus 50% Facial asymmetry 50% Hypertelorism 50% Intrauterine growth retardation 50% Long face 50% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 50% Microcephaly 50% Pointed chin 50% Popliteal pterygium 50% Ptosis 50% Respiratory insufficiency 50% Short stature 50% Telecanthus 50% Umbilical hernia 50% Vertebral segmentation defect 50% Abnormality of female external genitalia 7.5% Abnormality of the abdominal organs 7.5% Abnormality of the aortic valve 7.5% Abnormality of the ribs 7.5% Aortic dilatation 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the lungs 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Conductive hearing impairment 7.5% Cryptorchidism 7.5% Dolichocephaly 7.5% Gait disturbance 7.5% Hypoplasia of penis 7.5% Long philtrum 7.5% Low posterior hairline 7.5% Scrotal hypoplasia 7.5% Skeletal muscle atrophy 7.5% Spina bifida occulta 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Abnormality of the neck - Absence of labia majora - Antecubital pterygium - Anterior clefting of vertebral bodies - Arachnodactyly - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Axillary pterygia - Bilateral camptodactyly - Camptodactyly of toe - Congenital diaphragmatic hernia - Decreased fetal movement - Diaphragmatic eventration - Dislocated radial head - Downturned corners of mouth - Dysplastic patella - Exostosis of the external auditory canal - Fused cervical vertebrae - High palate - Hip dislocation - Hypoplastic nipples - Hypospadias - Inguinal hernia - Intercrural pterygium - Kyphosis - Long clavicles - Low-set ears - Narrow mouth - Neck pterygia - Neonatal respiratory distress - Patellar aplasia - Pulmonary hypoplasia - Rib fusion - Rocker bottom foot - Syndactyly - Talipes calcaneovalgus - Talipes equinovarus - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
