<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006041" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5148/tetra-amelia-syndrome">
<Focus>Tetra-amelia syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3814160</CUI>
			<CUI>C0002447</CUI>
			<CUI>C2931216</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Tetra-amelia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Tetra-amelia, autosomal recessive</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Tetraamelia, autosomal recessive</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Total Amelia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006041-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Tetra-amelia syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tetra-amelia syndrome is a very rare disorder characterized by the absence of all four limbs. This syndrome can also cause severe malformations of other parts of the body, including the face and head, heart, nervous system, skeleton, and genitalia. The lungs are underdeveloped in many cases, which makes breathing difficult or impossible. Because children with tetra-amelia syndrome have such serious medical problems, most are stillborn or die shortly after birth. The condition has been associated with a mutation in the WNT3 gene in one family, and it appears to be inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006041-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Tetra-amelia syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Tetra-amelia syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Tetra-amelia syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the outer ear 90% Amelia 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia involving the nose 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the lungs 90% Hydrocephalus 90% Oral cleft 90% Polyhydramnios 90% Abnormal lung lobation 50% Abnormal vertebral ossification 50% Abnormality of the larynx 50% Abnormality of the ribs 50% Abnormality of the sense of smell 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the nipples 50% Cataract 50% Cryptorchidism 50% Iris coloboma 50% Microcornea 50% Multicystic kidney dysplasia 50% Narrow mouth 50% Optic atrophy 50% Septo-optic dysplasia 50% Tracheal stenosis 50% Urogenital fistula 50% Abnormality of the diaphragm - Absent external genitalia - Adrenal gland agenesis - Anal atresia - Asplenia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Choanal atresia - Cleft palate - Cleft upper lip - Gastroschisis - Heterogeneous - Hypoplasia of the fallopian tube - Hypoplastic pelvis - Low-set ears - Microphthalmia - Peripheral pulmonary vessel aplasia - Pulmonary hypoplasia - Renal agenesis - Single naris - Single umbilical artery - Tetraamelia - Urethral atresia - Vaginal atresia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0006041-3" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Tetra-amelia syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is tetra-amelia syndrome diagnosed? The diagnosis of tetra-amelia syndrome can be established clinically (based on observed features) and is usually made on a routine prenatal ultrasound. The WNT3 gene has been associated with tetra-amelia syndrome, but the mutation detection frequency (how often a mutation will be found in an affected individual) is unknown because only a limited number of families have been studied. Is genetic testing available for tetra-amelia syndrome? Genetic testing for tetra-amelia syndrome is currently available. GeneTests lists the names of laboratories that are performing genetic testing for tetra-amelia syndrome. To view the contact information for the clinical laboratories conducting testing, click here. Please note: Most of the laboratories listed through GeneTests do not accept direct contact from patients and their families; therefore, if you are interested in learning more, you will need to work with a health care provider or a genetics professional.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
