<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006138" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7791/tracheobronchomalacia">
<Focus>Tracheobronchomalacia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0340231</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>TBM</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006138-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Tracheobronchomalacia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tracheobronchomalacia (TBM) is a rare condition that occurs when the walls of the airway (specifically the trachea and bronchi) are weak. This can cause the airway to become narrow or collapse. There are two forms of TBM: a congenital form (called primary TBM) that typically develops during infancy or early childhood and an acquired form (called secondary TBM) that is usually seen in adults. Some affected people may initially have no signs or symptoms. However, the condition is typically progressive (becomes worse overtime) and most people will eventually develop characteristic features such as shortness of breath, cough, sputum retention (inability to clear mucus from the respiratory tract), and wheezing or stridor with breathing. Most cases of primary TBM are caused by genetic conditions that weaken the walls of the airway, while the secondary form often occurs incidentally due to trauma, chronic inflammation and/or prolonged compression of the airways. Treatment is generally only required in those who have signs and symptoms of the condition and may include stenting, surgical correction, continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP), and tracheostomy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006138-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Tracheobronchomalacia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of tracheobronchomalacia? Tracheobronchomalacia (TBM) is a condition that occurs when the walls of the airway (specifically the trachea and bronchi) are weak. This can cause the airway to become narrow or collapse. There are two forms of TBM. Primary TBM (also called congenital TBM) typically develops during infancy or early childhood, while secondary TBM (also called acquired TBM) is usually seen in adults. Some affected people may initially have no signs or symptoms. However, the condition is typically progressive (becomes worse overtime) and many people will eventually develop characteristic features such as shortness of breath, cough, sputum retention (inability to clear mucus from the respiratory tract), and wheezing or stridor with breathing. Symptoms may become worse during periods of stress (i.e. illness), when reclining, or when forcing a cough. Infants and young children with TBM tend to have more frequent respiratory infections and delayed recovery from these illnesses.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0006138-3" qtype="causes">What causes Tracheobronchomalacia ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes tracheobronchomalacia? The underlying cause of tracheobronchomalacia (TBM) varies by subtype. Most cases of primary TBM (also called congenital TBM) are caused by genetic conditions that weaken the walls of the airway (specifically the trachea and bronchi). For example, TBM has been reported in people with mucopolysaccharidoses (such as Hunter syndrome and Hurler syndrome), Ehlers-Danlos Syndrome, and a variety of chromosome abnormalities. Primary TBM can also be idiopathic (unknown cause) or associated with prematurity and certain birth defects (i.e. tracheoesophageal fistula). The secondary form (also called acquired TBM) is caused by the degeneration (break down) of cartilage that typically supports the airways. It is most commonly associated with: Certain medical procedures such as endotracheal intubation or tracheostomy Conditions that lead to chronic (persisting or progressing for a long period of time) inflammation such as relapsing polychondritis or chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) Cancers, tumors, or cysts that cause prolonged compression of the airway</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0006138-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Tracheobronchomalacia inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is tracheobronchomalacia inherited? Primary tracheobronchomalacia (TBM) is often associated with certain genetic conditions. In some cases, an affected person inherits the condition from an affected parent. Other cases may result from new (de novo) gene mutations. These cases occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family. When TBM is part of a genetic condition, it can be passed on to future generations. Secondary TBM (also called acquired TBM) is not inherited. It generally occurs incidentally due to trauma, chronic inflammation and/or prolonged compression of the airways.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0006138-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Tracheobronchomalacia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is tracheobronchomalacia diagnosed? A diagnosis of tracheobronchomalacia (TBM) may be suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms or abnormal pulmonary function tests. Additional testing such as CT scan and bronchoscopy can then be performed to confirm the diagnosis and evaluate the severity of the condition. TBM is considered mild if the trachea narrows to 50% of its initial size while the affected person is breathing out, moderate if it narrows to 25%, and severe if the walls of the trachea touch.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0006138-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Tracheobronchomalacia ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might tracheobronchomalacia be treated? Treatment is only medically necessary in people who have signs and symptoms of tracheobronchomalacia (TBM). Management of symptomatic TBM first involves identifying underlying conditions contributing to symptoms, such as chronic inflammation, compression, or injury. Initial treatment will target these underlying medical concerns. If symptoms persist, people with TBM may undergo pulmonary function tests or other assessments to help guide therapy choice and allow monitoring of the response to treatment. Treatment options may include: Silicone and/or long-term stenting Surgical correction Continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) Tracheostomy (often used as a last resort as it can sometimes worsen TBM) We strongly recommend that you discuss your treatment options with a healthcare provider.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
