<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006296" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5433/uropathy-distal-obstructive-polydactyly">
<Focus>Uropathy distal obstructive polydactyly</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2931204</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006296-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Uropathy distal obstructive polydactyly ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Uropathy distal obstructive polydactyly? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Uropathy distal obstructive polydactyly. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the cardiac septa - Abnormality of the larynx - Abnormality of the ureter - Abnormality of the uterus - Accessory spleen - Adrenal hypoplasia - Agenesis of corpus callosum - Ambiguous genitalia, female - Ambiguous genitalia, male - Anal atresia - Anencephaly - Arnold-Chiari malformation - Asplenia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Bile duct proliferation - Bowing of the long bones - Breech presentation - Cerebellar hypoplasia - Cerebral hypoplasia - Cleft palate - Cleft upper lip - Clinodactyly - Coarctation of aorta - Cryptorchidism - Dandy-Walker malformation - Elevated amniotic fluid alpha-fetoprotein - External genital hypoplasia - Foot polydactyly - Hydrocephalus - Hypertelorism - Hypoplasia of the bladder - Hypotelorism - Intestinal malrotation - Intrauterine growth retardation - Iris coloboma - Large placenta - Lobulated tongue - Low-set ears - Microcephaly - Microphthalmia - Natal tooth - Occipital encephalocele - Olfactory lobe agenesis - Oligohydramnios - Omphalocele - Patent ductus arteriosus - Polycystic kidney dysplasia - Postaxial hand polydactyly - Pulmonary hypoplasia - Radial deviation of finger - Renal agenesis - Short neck - Single umbilical artery - Sloping forehead - Splenomegaly - Syndactyly - Talipes - Webbed neck - Wide mouth - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
