<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006562" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10936/17q231q232-microdeletion-syndrome">
<Focus>17q23.1q23.2 microdeletion syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1954751</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>17q23.1-q23.2 microdeletion syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Del(17)(q23.1q23.2)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Monosomy 17q23.1-q23.2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Monosomy 17q23.1q23.2</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chromosome 17q23.1-q23.2 deletion syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006562-1" qtype="information">What is (are) 17q23.1q23.2 microdeletion syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>17q23.1q23.2 microdeletion syndrome is a condition caused by a small deletion of genetic material from chromosome 17. The deletion occurs at a location encompassing bands 23.1 to 23.2 on the long (q) arm of the chromosome. People with 17q23.1q23.2 microdeletion syndrome may have developmental delay, microcephaly, short stature, heart defects and limb abnormalities. Most cases are approximately 2.2 Mb in size and include the transcription factor genes TBX2 and TBX4 which have been implicated in a number of developmental pathways, including those of the heart and limbs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006562-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of 17q23.1q23.2 microdeletion syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of 17q23.1q23.2 microdeletion syndrome? 17q23.1q23.2 microdeletion syndrome is characterized by developmental delay, microcephaly, short stature, heart defects and hand, foot and limb abnormalities. All individuals reported to date have had mild to moderate developmental delay, in particular delays in speech. Most have had heart defects, including patent ductus arteriosus or atrial septal defects. Limb abnormalities include long, thin fingers and toes, and hypoplasia (underdevelopment) of the patellae (knee caps). Scoliosis may also be present. Many patients have also had mild and unspecific unusual facial features. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for 17q23.1q23.2 microdeletion syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Arachnodactyly 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Long toe 90% Frontal bossing 50% Intrauterine growth retardation 50% Microcephaly 50% Neurological speech impairment 50% Patent ductus arteriosus 50% Pulmonary hypertension 50% Short stature 50% Abnormality of epiphysis morphology 7.5% Abnormality of the eyelashes 7.5% Abnormality of the hip bone 7.5% Abnormality of the teeth 7.5% Atria septal defect 7.5% Behavioral abnormality 7.5% Blepharitis 7.5% Camptodactyly of toe 7.5% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 7.5% Depressed nasal bridge 7.5% Epicanthus 7.5% Hearing impairment 7.5% Highly arched eyebrow 7.5% Hyperreflexia 7.5% Hypertelorism 7.5% Limitation of joint mobility 7.5% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 7.5% Malar flattening 7.5% Midline defect of the nose 7.5% Muscular hypotonia 7.5% Narrow mouth 7.5% Otitis media 7.5% Patellar aplasia 7.5% Pes planus 7.5% Respiratory insufficiency 7.5% Sacral dimple 7.5% Sandal gap 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Shawl scrotum 7.5% Single transverse palmar crease 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Abnormal facial shape - Aggressive behavior - Bicuspid aortic valve - Intellectual disability, mild - Long fingers - Postnatal growth retardation - Slender finger - Small for gestational age - Sporadic - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0006562-3" qtype="causes">What causes 17q23.1q23.2 microdeletion syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes 17q23.2q23.2 microdeletion syndrome? The syndrome is caused by an interstitial deletion (a deletion that does not involve the ends of a chromosome) encompassing bands 23.1 to 23.2 on the long (q) arm of chromosome 17. Two transcription factors, TBX2 and TBX4, which belong to a family of genes implicated in a variety of developmental pathways including those of heart and limbs, are found within this 2.2Mb region. This suggests that they may play a part in the symptoms seen in this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0006562-4" qtype="inheritance">Is 17q23.1q23.2 microdeletion syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is 17q23.2q23.2 microdeletion syndrome inherited? Parental FISH testing in most of the reported cases confirmed a de novo origin, meaning that the deletion was new to the family.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0006562-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose 17q23.1q23.2 microdeletion syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is 17q23.1q23.2 microdeletion syndrome diagnosed? The deletion can be identified by comparative genomic hybridization (CGH) microarray and fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
