<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006355" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/448/vici-syndrome">
<Focus>Vici syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1855772</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Immunodeficiency with cleft lip/palate, cataract, hypopigmentation and absent corpus callosum</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Absent corpus callosum cataract immunodeficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dionisi Vici Sabetta Gambarara syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006355-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Vici syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Vici syndrome is a multisystem disorder characterized by agenesis (failure to develop) of the corpus callosum, cataracts , hypopigmentation of the eyes and hair, cardiomyopathy, and combined immunodeficiency. Hearing loss, seizures, and delayed motor development have also been reported. Swallowing and feeding difficulties early on may result in a failure to thrive. Recurrent infections of the respiratory, gastrointestinal, and urinary tracts are common. Vici syndrome is caused by mutations in the EPG5 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner. Treatment is mainly supportive.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006355-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Vici syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Vici syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Vici syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of retinal pigmentation 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 90% Cellular immunodeficiency 90% Cognitive impairment 90% EEG abnormality 90% Generalized hypopigmentation 90% Hypertrophic cardiomyopathy 90% Hypopigmentation of hair 90% Muscular hypotonia 90% Recurrent respiratory infections 90% Short stature 90% Abnormality of neuronal migration 50% Abnormality of the palate 50% Abnormality of the renal tubule 50% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the cerebellum 50% Cataract 50% Nystagmus 50% Optic atrophy 50% Seizures 50% Abnormality of the macula 7.5% Cerebral cortical atrophy 7.5% Hypertelorism 7.5% Hypotelorism 7.5% Limitation of joint mobility 7.5% Sensorineural hearing impairment 7.5% Sleep disturbance 7.5% Abnormal posturing - Abnormality of the thymus - Acidosis - Agenesis of corpus callosum - Albinism - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Cerebellar vermis hypoplasia - Chronic mucocutaneous candidiasis - Cleft palate - Cleft upper lip - Congenital cataract - Congenital onset - Congestive heart failure - Cutaneous anergy - Decreased number of CD4+ T cells - Decreased T cell activation - Dilated cardiomyopathy - Failure to thrive - Growth delay - Hypopigmentation of the fundus - IgG deficiency - Immunoglobulin IgG2 deficiency - Left ventricular hypertrophy - Low-set ears - Microcephaly - Motor delay - Myopathy - Ocular albinism - Penile hypospadias - Recurrent bacterial infections - Recurrent fungal infections - Recurrent viral infections - Schizencephaly - White matter neuronal heterotopia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
