<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006185" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7802/trichorhinophalangeal-syndrome-type-3">
<Focus>Trichorhinophalangeal syndrome type 3</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265255</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>TRPS 3</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Sugio-Kajii Syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006185-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Trichorhinophalangeal syndrome type 3 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Trichorhinophalangeal syndrome type 3 (TRPS3), also known as Sugio-Kajii syndrome, is an extremely rare inherited multisystem disorder. TRPS3 is characterized by short stature, sparse hair, a bulbous nasal tip and cone-shaped epiphyses (the growing ends of bones), as well as severe generalized shortening of all finger and toe bones (brachydactyly). The range and severity of symptoms may vary from case to case. TRPS3 is caused by mutations in the TRPS1 gene which is localized to 8q24.12. TRPS3 is inherited in an autosomal dominant manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006185-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Trichorhinophalangeal syndrome type 3 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Trichorhinophalangeal syndrome type 3? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Trichorhinophalangeal syndrome type 3. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal hair quantity 90% Abnormal nasal morphology 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the eyebrow 90% Brachydactyly syndrome 90% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 90% Cone-shaped epiphysis 90% Frontal bossing 90% Long philtrum 90% Macrotia 90% Short distal phalanx of finger 90% Short stature 90% Thin vermilion border 90% Triangular face 90% Abnormality of the hip bone 50% Abnormality of the nail 50% Abnormality of the palate 50% Camptodactyly of finger 50% Hyperlordosis 50% Increased number of teeth 50% Muscular hypotonia 50% Pectus carinatum 50% Scoliosis 50% Abnormality of the nervous system - Accelerated bone age after puberty - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Avascular necrosis of the capital femoral epiphysis - Cone-shaped epiphyses of the middle phalanges of the hand - Coxa magna - Delayed skeletal maturation - Dental crowding - Osteopenia - Pear-shaped nose - Protruding ear - Short finger - Short foot - Short metacarpal - Short metatarsal - Short palm - Short phalanx of finger - Smooth philtrum - Sparse hair - Sparse lateral eyebrow - Underdeveloped nasal alae - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
