<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006044" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7751/tetrahydrobiopterin-deficiency">
<Focus>Tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0751436</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>BH4 deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hyperphenylalaninemia caused by a defect in biopterin metabolism</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hyperphenylalaninemia, non-phenylketonuric</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Non-phenylketonuric hyperphenylalaninemia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006044-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tetrahydrobiopterin (BH4) deficiency is a neurological condition caused by an inborn error of metabolism. BH4 is a substance in the body that enhances the action of other enzymes. Deficiency of BH4 leads to abnormally high blood levels of the amino acid phenylalanine, and low levels of certain neurotransmitters. Signs and symptoms can range from very mild to severe. Affected newborns appear normal at birth, but may begin to experience neurological symptoms such as abnormal muscle tone; poor sucking and coordination; seizures; and delayed motor development. Without early, appropriate treatment, the condition can cause permanent intellectual disability and even death. BH4 deficiency is caused by mutations in any one of several genes including the GCH1, PCBD1, PTS, and QDPR genes. It is inherited in an autosomal recessive manner.Treatment depends on the genetic cause and severity, and may include a low phenylalanine diet; oral BH4 supplementation; and neurotransmitter replacement.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006044-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency? Infants with tetrahydrobiopterin (BH4) deficiency typically appear normal and healthy at birth. Neurological signs and symptoms usually become apparent over time, and can range from mild to severe. These may include abnormal muscle tone; poor sucking and coordination; seizures; and delayed motor development. Other manifestations may include decreased spontaneous movements and difficulty swallowing. Without early and appropriate treatment, signs and symptoms progress and affected individuals may experience irreversible intellectual disability, behavioral problems, an inability to control body temperature, and even death in severe cases. The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Tetrahydrobiopterin deficiency. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Cognitive impairment 90% Microcephaly 90% Abnormality of eye movement - Ataxia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Bradykinesia - Cerebral calcification - Choreoathetosis - Dysphagia - Dystonia - Episodic fever - Excessive salivation - Hyperkinesis - Hyperphenylalaninemia - Hyperreflexia - Hypertonia - Infantile onset - Intellectual disability - Intellectual disability, progressive - Irritability - Lethargy - Limb hypertonia - Motor delay - Muscular hypotonia - Muscular hypotonia of the trunk - Myoclonus - Parkinsonism - Poor suck - Progressive neurologic deterioration - Rigidity - Seizures - Severe muscular hypotonia - Small for gestational age - Somnolence - Transient hyperphenylalaninemia - Tremor - Variable expressivity - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
