<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006111" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10100/tietze-syndrome">
<Focus>Tietze syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0040213</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Tietze's syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chondropathia tuberosa</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Costochondral junction syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006111-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Tietze syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tietze syndrome is an inflammatory condition characterized by chest pain and swelling of the cartilage that joins the upper ribs to the breastbone (costochondral junction). Signs and symptoms of this condition usually develop in young adults (before age 40) and include mild to severe chest pain that may extend into the arms and/or shoulders. The cause of this condition is unknown. In some cases, Tietze syndrome may resolve on its own without treatment. Management for others may include minimizing physical activity; applying local heat; and taking pain medications and/or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs. Of note, this syndrome is different from Tietz syndrome, which is characterized by profound hearing loss from birth, fair skin, and light-colored hair.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006111-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Tietze syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Tietze syndrome? The signs and symptoms of Tietze syndrome usually develop in young adulthood (before age 40). The most common symptom is mild to severe chest pain that may extend into the arms and/or shoulders. The onset of pain can be gradual or sudden and may worsen with coughing, sneezing, or deep breathing. More than 70% of cases occur on only one side (unilateral) and affect one joint. The affected joint is typically tender and swollen. While the pain associated with Tietze syndrome usually subsides after several weeks or months, the swelling may persist.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0006111-3" qtype="causes">What causes Tietze syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Tietze syndrome? The exact underlying cause of Tietze syndrome is currently unknown. Some researchers have speculated that small injuries to the anterior chest wall may contribute to the development of the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0006111-4" qtype="inheritance">Is Tietze syndrome inherited ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is Tietze syndrome inherited? Tietze syndrome is not thought to be inherited. Most cases occur sporadically in people with no family history of the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0006111-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Tietze syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Tietze syndrome diagnosed? Tietze syndrome is a diagnosis of exclusion. This means that a diagnosis is made in people with chest pain and swelling of the cartilage that joins the upper ribs to the breastbone (costochondral junction) after other conditions with similar signs and symptoms have been ruled out. A thorough physical exam and various tests (i.e. electrocardiogram, x-ray, CT scan) may be necessary to exclude other conditions.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0006111-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Tietze syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Tietze syndrome be treated? In some individuals, the pain associated with Tietze syndrome resolves on its own without any treatment. Management options for others may include avoidance of strenuous activity; applying local heat; taking pain medications and/or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs; and receiving local corticosteroid injections. Although the pain usually subsides after several weeks or months, swelling may persist.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
