<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006564" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10991/19p1312-microdeletion-syndrome">
<Focus>19p13.12 microdeletion syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1954751</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Chromosome19p13.12 microdeletion</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Del(19)(p13.12)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Monosomy 19p13.12</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006564-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of 19p13.12 microdeletion syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of 19p13.12 microdeletion syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for 19p13.12 microdeletion syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Cognitive impairment 90% Neurological speech impairment 90% Anteverted nares 50% Arrhythmia 50% Atria septal defect 50% Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder 50% Brachydactyly syndrome 50% Broad forehead 50% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 50% Epicanthus 50% Intrauterine growth retardation 50% Long philtrum 50% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 50% Microcephaly 50% Muscular hypotonia 50% Narrow nasal bridge 50% Reduced number of teeth 50% Scoliosis 50% Seizures 50% Sensorineural hearing impairment 50% Short neck 50% Synophrys 50% Thin vermilion border 50% Ventriculomegaly 50% Abnormality of lipid metabolism 7.5% Abnormality of the aortic valve 7.5% Abnormality of the mitral valve 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the cerebellum 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Conductive hearing impairment 7.5% Craniosynostosis 7.5% Cryptorchidism 7.5% Deep palmar crease 7.5% Deep plantar creases 7.5% Displacement of the external urethral meatus 7.5% Finger syndactyly 7.5% Hepatic steatosis 7.5% Hypertelorism 7.5% Hypothyroidism 7.5% Kyphosis 7.5% Myopia 7.5% Nystagmus 7.5% Obesity 7.5% Precocious puberty 7.5% Proptosis 7.5% Sandal gap 7.5% Self-injurious behavior 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Tibial deviation of toes 7.5% Ventricular septal defect 7.5% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
