<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006451" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5579/wilson-turner-syndrome">
<Focus>Wilson-Turner syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0796255</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Mental retardation, X-linked, with gynecomastia and obesity (formerly)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>WTS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Wilson Turner mental retardation syndrome (formerly)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mental retardation, X-linked, syndromic 6 (formerly)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MRXS6</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006451-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Wilson-Turner syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Wilson-Turner syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Wilson-Turner syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Obesity 90% Gynecomastia 50% Neurological speech impairment 50% Abnormality of calvarial morphology 7.5% Abnormality of the voice 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the earlobes 7.5% Arthritis 7.5% Coarse facial features 7.5% Cognitive impairment 7.5% Cryptorchidism 7.5% Gait disturbance 7.5% Hypoplasia of penis 7.5% Incoordination 7.5% Large earlobe 7.5% Lymphedema 7.5% Macrotia 7.5% Mandibular prognathia 7.5% Narrow mouth 7.5% Pointed chin 7.5% Preauricular skin tag 7.5% Reduced number of teeth 7.5% Round ear 7.5% Scoliosis 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Short palm 7.5% Striae distensae 7.5% Synophrys 7.5% Tapered finger 7.5% Thick eyebrow 7.5% Toxemia of pregnancy 7.5% Umbilical hernia 7.5% Brachycephaly - Broad nasal tip - Decreased muscle mass - Decreased testicular size - Deeply set eye - Delayed puberty - Delayed speech and language development - Emotional lability - Hypogonadism - Intellectual disability - Kyphosis - Microcephaly - Micropenis - Misalignment of teeth - Muscular hypotonia - Prominent supraorbital ridges - Retrognathia - Short ear - Short foot - Short stature - Small hand - Truncal obesity - X-linked dominant inheritance - X-linked recessive inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
