<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006094" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5204/thyroglossal-tract-cyst">
<Focus>Thyroglossal tract cyst</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1861114</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Thyroglossal duct cysts</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Thyroglossal duct cysts familial</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary thyroglossal duct cysts</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Familial thyroglossal duct cyst</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006094-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Thyroglossal tract cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>A thyroglossal duct cyst is a neck mass or lump that develops from cells and tissues remaining after the formation of the thyroid gland during embryonic development.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006094-2" qtype="causes">What causes Thyroglossal tract cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>Can thyroglossal duct cysts cause weight loss? Weight loss is not commonly cited as a specific symptom of thyroglossal duct cysts, however large cysts can cause difficulty swallowing and breathing. Infected cysts may be tender with associated difficulty in swallowing, loss of voice, fever, and increasing mass size. Some patients with an infected cyst experience drainage which can result in a foul taste in the mouth. These symptoms may make feedings difficult and unpleasant. We recommend you speak with your childs healthcare provider regarding his symptom.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0006094-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Thyroglossal tract cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might a thyroglossal duct cyst be treated? Surgical excision is the treatment of choice for uncomplicated thyroglossal duct cysts to prevent infection of the cyst. The Sistrunk procedure can be preformed to reduce the risk of recurrence. Infection of the cyst prior to surgery can make the removal more difficult and increase the chance for regrowth.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
