<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006561" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5659/17-beta-hydroxysteroid-dehydrogenase-3-deficiency">
<Focus>17-beta hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase 3 deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0268296</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>17 alpha ketosteroid reductase deficiency of testis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>17 alpha KSR deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Neutral 17 beta hydroxysteroid oxidoreductase deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Male pseudoherma-phroditism with gynecomastia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>17 beta hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase III deficiency</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006561-1" qtype="information">What is (are) 17-beta hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase 3 deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>17-beta hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase 3 deficiencyis an inherited condition that affects male sexual development. People with this condition are genetically male and have testes, but do not produce enough testosterone. Most people with this condition are born with external genitalia that appear female. In some cases, the external genitalia are ambiguous or appear male but are abnormal in size and/or appearance. During puberty, people with this condition typically go on to develop male secondary sex characteristics, such as increased muscle mass, deepening of the voice, and development of male pattern body hair. 17-beta hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase 3 deficiency is caused by mutations in the HSD17B3 gene and is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006561-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of 17-beta hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase 3 deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of 17-beta hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase 3 deficiency? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for 17-beta hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase 3 deficiency. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the urethra 90% Cryptorchidism 90% Decreased fertility 90% Gynecomastia 90% Male pseudohermaphroditism 90% Hypothyroidism 7.5% Abnormality of metabolism/homeostasis - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Infertility - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
