<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006426" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7887/west-syndrome">
<Focus>West syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0037769</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Infantile spasm</Synonym>
		<Synonym>IS</Synonym>
		<Synonym>X-linked infantile spasm syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>X-linked infantile spasms</Synonym>
		<Synonym>West's syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006426-1" qtype="information">What is (are) West syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>West syndrome is characterized by a specific type of seizure (infantile spasms) seen in infancy and childhood. This syndrome leads to developmental regression and causes a specific pattern, known as hypsarrhythmia (chaotic brain waves), on electroencephalography (EEG) testing. The infantile spasms usually begin in the first year of life, typically between 4-8 months. The seizures primarily consist of a sudden bending forward of the body with stiffening of the arms and legs; some children arch their backs as they extend their arms and legs. Spasms tend to occur upon awakening or after feeding, and often occur in clusters of up to 100 spasms at a time. Infants may have dozens of clusters and several hundred spasms per day. Infantile spasms usually stop by age five, but may be replaced by other types of seizures. Many underlying disorders, such as birth injury, metabolic disorders, and genetic disorders can lead to these spasms, making it important to identify the underlying cause. In some children, no cause can be found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006426-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of West syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of West syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for West syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Cognitive impairment 90% Hemiplegia/hemiparesis 90% Hypertonia 90% Seizures 90% Choreoathetosis - Dysphagia - Dyspnea - Dystonia - Epileptic encephalopathy - Generalized myoclonic seizures - Hyperreflexia - Hypsarrhythmia - Intellectual disability - Microcephaly - Muscular hypotonia of the trunk - Spasticity - Ventriculomegaly - X-linked recessive inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
