<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006527" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8591/x-linked-visceral-heterotaxy-1">
<Focus>X-linked visceral heterotaxy 1</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0266642</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>HTX1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Laterality, X-linked</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Situs inversus, complex cardiac defects, and splenic defects, X-linked</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Heterotaxy, visceral, 1, X-linked</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Heterotaxy, visceral, X-linked</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Heterotaxy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006527-1" qtype="information">What is (are) X-linked visceral heterotaxy 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>X-linked visceral heterotaxy type 1 is a very rare form of heterotaxy that has only been reported in a few families. Heterotaxy is the right/left transposition of thoracic and/or abdominal organs. This condition is caused by mutations in the ZIC3 gene, is inherited in an X-linked recessive fashion, and is usually seen in males. Physical features include heart abnormalities such as dextrocardia, transposition of great vessels, ventricular septal defect, patent ductus arteriosus, pulmonic stenosis; situs inversus, and missing (asplenia) and/or extra spleens (polysplenia). Affected individuals can also experience abnormalities in the development of the midline of the body, which can cause holoprosencephaly , myelomeningocele, urological anomalies, widely spaced eyes (hypertelorism), cleft palate, and abnormalities of the sacral spine and anus. Heterotaxia with recurrent respiratory infections are called primary ciliary dyskinesia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006527-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of X-linked visceral heterotaxy 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of X-linked visceral heterotaxy 1? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for X-linked visceral heterotaxy 1. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abdominal situs inversus - Asplenia - Dextrocardia - Patent ductus arteriosus - Polysplenia - Pulmonic stenosis - Ventricular septal defect - X-linked inheritance - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
