<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006440" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5566/wiedemann-oldigs-oppermann-syndrome">
<Focus>Wiedemann Oldigs Oppermann syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0795976</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hirsutism skeletal dysplasia mental retardation syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006440-1" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Wiedemann Oldigs Oppermann syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Wiedemann Oldigs Oppermann syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Wiedemann Oldigs Oppermann syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal nasal morphology 90% Abnormality of calvarial morphology 90% Abnormality of the clavicle 90% Abnormality of the elbow 90% Abnormality of the fingernails 90% Abnormality of the hip bone 90% Abnormality of the palate 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the earlobes 90% Astigmatism 90% Cognitive impairment 90% Epicanthus 90% Hearing abnormality 90% Hypertelorism 90% Hypertrichosis 90% Hyperuricemia 90% Long thorax 90% Narrow chest 90% Pectus carinatum 90% Proptosis 90% Proximal placement of thumb 90% Strabismus 90% Tracheal stenosis 90% Wide nasal bridge 90% Wormian bones 90% Autosomal dominant inheritance - Brachycephaly - Coxa valga - Down-sloping shoulders - Hirsutism - Intellectual disability - Long neck - Pes cavus - Skeletal dysplasia - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
