<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006183" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7800/trichorhinophalangeal-syndrome-type-1">
<Focus>Trichorhinophalangeal syndrome type 1</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0432233</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>TRPS1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Giedion syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006183-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Trichorhinophalangeal syndrome type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>Trichorhinophalangeal syndrome type 1 (TRPS1) is an extremely rare inherited multisystem disorder. TRPS1 is characterized by a distinctive facial appearance that includes sparse scalp hair; a rounded nose; a long, flat area between the nose and the upper lip (philtrum); and a thin upper lip. Individuals with this condition also have skeletal abnormalities such as cone-shaped epiphyses in their fingers and toes and short stature. The range and severity of symptoms may vary from case to case. Transmission of TRPS1 is autosomal dominant, linked to mutations in the TRPS1 gene localized to 8q24.12.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006183-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Trichorhinophalangeal syndrome type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Trichorhinophalangeal syndrome type 1? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Trichorhinophalangeal syndrome type 1. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal hair quantity 90% Abnormal nasal morphology 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the eyebrow 90% Brachydactyly syndrome 90% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 90% Cone-shaped epiphysis 90% Frontal bossing 90% Long philtrum 90% Macrotia 90% Short distal phalanx of finger 90% Short stature 90% Thin vermilion border 90% Triangular face 90% Abnormality of the hip bone 50% Abnormality of the nail 50% Abnormality of the palate 50% Camptodactyly of finger 50% Hyperlordosis 50% Increased number of teeth 50% Muscular hypotonia 50% Pectus carinatum 50% Scoliosis 50% Abnormally low-pitched voice - Accelerated bone age after puberty - Arthralgia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Avascular necrosis of the capital femoral epiphysis - Carious teeth - Chin with horizontal crease - Concave nail - Cone-shaped epiphyses of the middle phalanges of the hand - Cone-shaped epiphyses of the proximal phalanges of the hand - Coxa magna - Deep philtrum - Delayed eruption of teeth - Delayed skeletal maturation - Dental malocclusion - Fine hair - Flat capital femoral epiphysis - Infantile muscular hypotonia - Ivory epiphyses of the distal phalanges of the hand - Leukonychia - Microdontia - Narrow palate - Osteoarthritis - Osteopenia - Pear-shaped nose - Pes planus - Protruding ear - Recurrent respiratory infections - Scapular winging - Short metacarpal - Short metatarsal - Slow-growing hair - Sparse hair - Sparse lateral eyebrow - Swelling of proximal interphalangeal joints - Thin nail - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
