<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006192" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/7803/trichotillomania">
<Focus>Trichotillomania</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0040953</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hair-pulling syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006192-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Trichotillomania ?</Question>
			<Answer>Trichotillomania is an impulse control disorder characterized by an overwhelming urge to repeatedly pull out one&apos;s own hair (usually on the scalp), resulting in hair loss (alopecia). The eyelashes, eyebrows, and beard can also be affected. Many affected individuals feel extreme tension when they feel an impulse, followed by relief, gratification or pleasure afterwards. The condition may be mild and manageable, or severe and debilitating. Some individuals chew or swallow the hair they pull out (trichophagy), which can result in gastrointestinal problems. The exact cause of the condition is unknown. Treatment typically involves psychotherapy (including cognitive behavior therapy) and/or drug therapy, but these are not always effective.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006192-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Trichotillomania ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Trichotillomania? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Trichotillomania. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Alopecia - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Hair-pulling - Multifactorial inheritance - Obsessive-compulsive behavior - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0006192-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Trichotillomania ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might trichotillomania be treated? Behavioral treatment seems to be the most powerful treatment for trichotillomania. Parental involvement is important and should include enough support so that affected children grow well intellectually, physically, and socially. Shaving or clipping hair close to the scalp may be helpful to stop the behavior. Professional cognitive behavior therapy (CBT) is recommended if initial approaches are unsuccessful. CBT typically involves self monitoring (keeping records of the behavior); habit-reversal training; and stimulus control (organizing the environment). CBT is typically effective in highly motivated and compliant patients. The success of therapy may depend on firm understanding of the illness and the cooperation of the family members to help the affected individual comply with treatment. Several courses of CBT may be needed. No medication has been approved for the treatment of trichotillomania, and medications used have not been consistently effective. Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors have been utilized but responses to treatment have not been consistent. Fortunately, several recent studies regarding drug therapy for trichotillomania show promise. While drug therapy alone is currently generally not effective, combination therapy and other treatments may be helpful. More detailed information about current treatment options for trichotillomania is available on Medscape Reference&apos;s Web site and can be viewed by clicking here. You may need to register on the Web site, but registration is free.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
