<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006285" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5186/unna-thost-palmoplantar-keratoderma">
<Focus>Unna-Thost palmoplantar keratoderma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0022596</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Diffuse nonepidermolytic palmoplantar keratoderma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Diffuse NEPPK</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Thost-Unna disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>PPK diffusa circumscripta</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Thost-Unna palmoplantar keratoderma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Palmoplantar keratoderma</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006285-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Unna-Thost palmoplantar keratoderma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Unna-Thost palmoplantar keratoderma is a type of diffuse palmoplantar keratoderma that mostly affects the palms of the hands and soles of the feet. It usually begins in early childhood with redness of the palms and soles. The palms and soles gradually become thicker and develop a yellowish, waxy appearance. Increased sweating (hyperhidrosis) is quite common and there is a tendency to fungal and bacterial infections of the feet. This condition usually does not extend beyond the hands and feet. It may affect the knuckle pads and nails, but usually does not involve the thin skin on the top of the feet or hands. Unna-Thost palmoplantar keratoderma is inherited in an autosomal dominant fashion and caused by mutations in the KRT1 gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006285-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Unna-Thost palmoplantar keratoderma ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Unna-Thost palmoplantar keratoderma? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Unna-Thost palmoplantar keratoderma. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autosomal dominant inheritance - Nonepidermolytic palmoplantar keratoderma - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0006285-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Unna-Thost palmoplantar keratoderma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Unna-Thost palmoplantar keratoderma be treated? The following treatments can help to soften the thickened skin and make it less noticeable:  Emollients  Keratolytics (such as salicylic acid in propylene glycol) Topical retinoids Topical vitamin D ointment (calcipotriol) Systemic retinoids (acitretin) Antifungal medication may help if the condition occurs along with a fungal infection.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
