<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006137" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/5233/tracheal-agenesis">
<Focus>Tracheal agenesis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1261567</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Congenital tracheal agenesis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006137-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Tracheal agenesis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tracheal agenesis is a rare birth defect in which the trachea (windpipe) is completely absent (agenesis) or significantly underdeveloped (atresia). Signs and symptoms include polyhydramnios during pregnancy and respiratory distress, bluish skin color (cyanosis) and no audible cry shortly after birth. The underlying cause of tracheal agenesis is currently unknown. Approximately 90% of cases are associated with other anomalies, including those of the cardiovascular system, the gastrointestinal system and the genitourinary tract. Some cases may be part of a very rare condition known as VACTERL association. Surgery to repair the trachea may be attempted; however, the long-term outlook is generally poor in most cases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006137-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Tracheal agenesis ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Tracheal agenesis? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Tracheal agenesis. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormality of the cardiac septa 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the lungs 90% Polyhydramnios 90% Respiratory insufficiency 90% Tracheal stenosis 90% The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
