<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006607" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/12166/5q143-microdeletion-syndrome">
<Focus>5q14.3 microdeletion syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1954751</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Chromosome 5q14.3 deletion syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Monosomy 5q14.3</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Del(5)(q14.3)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mental retardation, autosomal dominant 20</Synonym>
		<Synonym>5q14.3 deletion syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chromosome 5q deletion</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006607-1" qtype="information">What is (are) 5q14.3 microdeletion syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>5q14.3 microdeletion syndrome is characterized by severe intellectual disability, absent speech, stereotypic movements and epilepsy. Unusual facial features include high broad forehead with variable small chin, short nose with anteverted nares (nostrils that open to the front rather than downward), large open mouth, upslanted palpebral fissures (outside corners of the eyes that point downward), and prominent eyebrows. The condition is caused by mutations affecting the MEF2C gene and deletions in the q14.3 region of chromosome 5.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006607-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of 5q14.3 microdeletion syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of 5q14.3 microdeletion syndrome ? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for 5q14.3 microdeletion syndrome . If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Autism 90% Broad forehead 90% Cognitive impairment 90% High forehead 90% Muscular hypotonia 90% Neurological speech impairment 90% Seizures 90% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the corpus callosum 50% Short nose 50% Short philtrum 50% Stereotypic behavior 50% Upslanted palpebral fissure 50% Ventriculomegaly 50% Anteverted nares 7.5% Aplasia/Hypoplasia of the cerebellum 7.5% Cerebral cortical atrophy 7.5% Deeply set eye 7.5% Open mouth 7.5% Optic atrophy 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Thick eyebrow 7.5% Toe syndactyly 7.5% Abnormality of the periventricular white matter 5% Epileptic encephalopathy 5% Depressed nasal bridge - Downturned corners of mouth - Hypertelorism - Inability to walk - Intellectual disability, severe - Low-set ears - Motor delay - Poor eye contact - Short chin - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
