<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006286" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3876/unverricht-lundborg-disease">
<Focus>Unverricht-Lundborg disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0751785</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Myoclonus progressive epilepsy of Unverricht and Lundborg</Synonym>
		<Synonym>EPM1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Epilepsy, progressive myoclonus 1</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Progressive myoclonus epilepsy baltic myoclonic epilepsy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Myoclonic epilepsy of Unverricht and Lundborg</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Progressive myoclonic epilepsy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006286-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Unverricht-Lundborg disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Unverricht-Lundborg disease is an inherited form of progressive myoclonus epilepsy that is characterized by episodes of involuntary muscle jerking or twitching (myoclonus) that increase in frequency and severity over time. Episodes of myoclonus may be brought on by physical exertion, stress, light, or other stimuli. Affected individuals usually begin showing signs and symptoms of the disorder between the ages of 6 and 15. Over time, the myoclonic episodes may become severe enough to interfere with walking and other everyday activities. Other features include seizures involving loss of consciousness, muscle rigidity, and convulsions (tonic-clonic or grand mal seizures). Like the myoclonic episodes, these may increase in frequency over several years but may be controlled with treatment. After several years of progression, the frequency of seizures may stabilize or decrease. Unverricht-Lundborg disease is caused by mutation in the CSTB gene. It is inherited in an autosomal recessive pattern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006286-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Unverricht-Lundborg disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Unverricht-Lundborg disease? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Unverricht-Lundborg disease. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Absence seizures - Ataxia - Autosomal recessive inheritance - Dysarthria - Generalized tonic-clonic seizures - Mental deterioration - Myoclonus - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
