<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006402" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/8569/warthin-tumor">
<Focus>Warthin tumor</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0001429</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Papillary cystadenoma lymphomatosum (formerly)</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006402-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Warthin tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Warthin tumor is a benign tumor of the salivary gland. The first symptom is usually a painless, slow-growing bump in front of the ear, on the bottom of the mouth, or under the chin. Warthin tumors may increase in size over time, but few become cancerous. Though the cause is currently unknown, smoking is believed to increase the chance of developing Warthin tumor. Treatment may consist of surgery to remove the tumor or careful observation to watch for changes in the tumor over time.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006402-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Warthin tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Warthin tumor? Warthin tumor is a benign (noncancerous) tumor of the salivary glands. They most commonly arise in the parotid glands, the largest salivary glands which are located in each cheek above the jaw in front of the ears. Approximately 5-14% of cases are bilateral and 12-20% of affected people experience multicentric (more than one tumor which formed separately from one another) disease. The first symptom is usually a firm, painless bump. Without treatment, the swelling may gradually increase overtime which can cause facial nerve palsy (difficulty moving one side of the face).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0006402-3" qtype="causes">What causes Warthin tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>What causes Warthin tumor? The exact underlying cause of Warthin tumor is currently unknown. However, smoking is thought to increase the risk of developing the tumor. Some studies suggest that radiation exposure and autoimmune disorders may also be associated with Warthin tumor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0006402-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Warthin tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>How is Warthin tumor diagnosed? A diagnosis of Warthin tumor is often suspected based on the presence of characteristic signs and symptoms. The following tests may then be ordered to confirm the diagnosis and rule out other conditions that cause similar features: X-rays of the salivary gland (called a ptyalogram or sialogram) CT scan, MRI and/or ultrasound Salivary gland biopsy</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0006402-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Warthin tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>How might Warthin tumor be treated? Treatment of Warthin tumor generally includes surgery to remove the tumor or careful observation to watch for changes in the tumor over time. Because Warthin tumor is almost always benign, additional treatment (i.e. radiation therapy and/or chemotherapy) is rarely needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
