<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006375" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/3092/vohwinkel-syndrome">
<Focus>Vohwinkel syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265964</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Deafness, congenital, with keratopachydermia and constrictions of fingers and toes</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mutilating keratoderma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Keratoderma hereditarium mutilans</Synonym>
		<Synonym>KHM</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006375-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Vohwinkel syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Vohwinkel syndrome is an inherited condition that affects the skin. People with the &quot;classic form&quot; generally have honeycomb-patterned calluses on the palms of the hands and the soles of the feet (palmoplantar keratoses); constricting bands of tissue on the fingers and toes which can cause amputation; starfish-shaped, thickened skin on the tops of the fingers and knees; and hearing loss. A &quot;variant form&quot; of Vohwinkel syndrome has also been identified which is characterized by ichthyosis in addition to the classic skin abnormalities and is not associated with hearing loss. Classic Vohwinkel syndrome is caused by changes (mutations) in the GJB2 gene and the variant form is caused by mutations in the LOR gene. Both are inherited in an autosomal dominant manner. Although there is currently no cure for the condition, treatments are available to alleviate symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006375-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Vohwinkel syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of Vohwinkel syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for Vohwinkel syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Sensorineural hearing impairment 90% Abnormality of the genital system 50% Cognitive impairment 50% Abnormality of the toenails 7.5% Alopecia 7.5% Cleft palate 7.5% Ichthyosis 7.5% Osteolysis 7.5% Self-injurious behavior 7.5% Amniotic constriction ring - Autoamputation of digits - Autosomal dominant inheritance - Honeycomb palmoplantar keratoderma - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
