<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0006555" source="GARD" url="https://rarediseases.info.nih.gov/gard/10296/15q133-microdeletion-syndrome">
<Focus>15q13.3 microdeletion syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2677613</CUI>
			<CUI>C1954751</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Chromosome 15q13.3 deletion syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Microdeletion 15q13.3 syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chromosome 15q13.3 microdeletion syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>15q13.3 microdeletion</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0006555-1" qtype="information">What is (are) 15q13.3 microdeletion syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>15q13.3 microdeletion syndrome is a type of contiguous gene deletion syndrome. Individuals with this microdeletion may have very different signs and symptoms from other affected individuals (even within the same family), or no symptoms at all. Features of the condition may include mild to moderate mental retardation, learning difficulties, or normal intelligence; autism; epilepsy (recurring seizures); and mental illness (such as schizophrenia or bipolar disorder). Various dysmorphic (abnormally formed) features have been reported, but there are no consistent physical features among individuals who have the condition. It is caused by a tiny deletion (microdeletion) on the long arm of chromosome 15 that spans at least 6 genes; the features of the syndrome are caused by the absence of these genes, which are usually necessary for normal growth and development. It can be inherited in an autosomal dominant manner with reduced penetrance, or can occur as a new (de novo) deletion. Treatment typically focuses on individual signs and symptoms (such as medication for seizures) when possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0006555-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of 15q13.3 microdeletion syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>What are the signs and symptoms of 15q13.3 microdeletion syndrome? The Human Phenotype Ontology provides the following list of signs and symptoms for 15q13.3 microdeletion syndrome. If the information is available, the table below includes how often the symptom is seen in people with this condition. You can use the MedlinePlus Medical Dictionary to look up the definitions for these medical terms. Signs and Symptoms Approximate number of patients (when available) Abnormal facial shape 50% Cognitive impairment 50% Incomplete penetrance 50% Abnormal nasal morphology 7.5% Abnormality of the pinna 7.5% Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder 7.5% Autism 7.5% Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 7.5% Epicanthus 7.5% Frontal bossing 7.5% Low-set, posteriorly rotated ears 7.5% Macrocephaly 7.5% Melanocytic nevus 7.5% Microcephaly 7.5% Muscular hypotonia 7.5% Seizures 7.5% Short stature 7.5% Strabismus 7.5% Behavioral abnormality 10/19 Muscular hypotonia 9/18 Abnormality of the palpebral fissures 7/19 Intellectual disability, moderate 6/17 Abnormality of the pinna 6/19 Intellectual disability, mild 5/17 Specific learning disability 7/25 Clinodactyly of the 5th finger 4/19 Intellectual disability, severe 3/18 Abnormality of cardiovascular system morphology 3/19 Brachydactyly syndrome 3/19 Hypertelorism 3/19 Strabismus 3/19 Synophrys 3/19 Seizures 2/18 Autosomal dominant inheritance - Phenotypic variability - The Human Phenotype Ontology (HPO) has collected information on how often a sign or symptom occurs in a condition. Much of this information comes from Orphanet, a European rare disease database. The frequency of a sign or symptom is usually listed as a rough estimate of the percentage of patients who have that feature. The frequency may also be listed as a fraction. The first number of the fraction is how many people had the symptom, and the second number is the total number of people who were examined in one study. For example, a frequency of 25/25 means that in a study of 25 people all patients were found to have that symptom. Because these frequencies are based on a specific study, the fractions may be different if another group of patients are examined. Sometimes, no information on frequency is available. In these cases, the sign or symptom may be rare or common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0006555-3" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose 15q13.3 microdeletion syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Is genetic testing available for 15q13.3 microdeletion syndrome? Genetic testing for 15q13.3 microdeletion testing is available. GeneTests lists the names of laboratories that are performing genetic testing for 15q13.3 microdeletion syndrome. To view the contact information for the clinical laboratories conducting testing click here. Please note: Most of the laboratories listed through GeneTests do not accept direct contact from patients and their families; therefore, individuals who are interested in learning more should work with a health care provider or a genetics professional. Click here for a list of online resources for locating a genetics professional near you.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
