<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000035" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/Diabetes/diagnosis-diabetes-prediabetes/Pages/index.aspx">
<Focus>Diagnosis of Diabetes and Prediabetes</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0362046</CUI>
			<CUI>C0011860</CUI>
			<CUI>C0011849</CUI>
			<CUI>C0271650</CUI>
			<CUI>C0011900</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000035-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Diagnosis of Diabetes and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Diabetes is a complex group of diseases with a variety of causes. People with diabetes have high blood glucose, also called high blood sugar or hyperglycemia.
                
Diabetes is a disorder of metabolismthe way the body uses digested food for energy. The digestive tract breaks down carbohydratessugars and starches found in many foodsinto glucose, a form of sugar that enters the bloodstream. With the help of the hormone insulin, cells throughout the body absorb glucose and use it for energy. Insulin is made in the pancreas, an organ located behind the stomach. As the blood glucose level rises after a meal, the pancreas is triggered to release insulin. Within the pancreas, clusters of cells called islets contain beta cells, which make the insulin and release it into the blood.
                
Diabetes develops when the body doesnt make enough insulin or is not able to use insulin effectively, or both. As a result, glucose builds up in the blood instead of being absorbed by cells in the body. The bodys cells are then starved of energy despite high blood glucose levels.
                
Over time, high blood glucose damages nerves and blood vessels, leading to complications such as heart disease, stroke, kidney disease, blindness, dental disease, and amputations. Other complications of diabetes may include increased susceptibility to other diseases, loss of mobility with aging, depression, and pregnancy problems.
                
Main Types of Diabetes
                
The three main types of diabetes are type 1, type 2, and gestational diabetes:
                
- Type 1 diabetes, formerly called juvenile diabetes, is usually first diagnosed in children, teenagers, and young adults. In this type of diabetes, the beta cells of the pancreas no longer make insulin because the bodys immune system has attacked and destroyed them.  - Type 2 diabetes, formerly called adult-onset diabetes, is the most common type of diabetes. About 90 to 95 percent of people with diabetes have type 2.1 People can develop type 2 diabetes at any age, even during childhood, but this type of diabetes is most often associated with older age. Type 2 diabetes is also associated with excess weight, physical inactivity, family history of diabetes, previous history of gestational diabetes, and certain ethnicities.   Type 2 diabetes usually begins with insulin resistance, a condition linked to excess weight in which muscle, liver, and fat cells do not use insulin properly. As a result, the body needs more insulin to help glucose enter cells to be used for energy. At first, the pancreas keeps up with the added demand by producing more insulin. But in time, the pancreas loses its ability to produce enough insulin in response to meals, and blood glucose levels rise.  - Gestational diabetes is a type of diabetes that develops only during pregnancy.  The hormones produced during pregnancy increase the amount of insulin needed to control blood glucose levels. If the body cant meet this increased need for insulin, women can develop gestational diabetes during the late stages of pregnancy.  Gestational diabetes usually goes away after the baby is born. Shortly after pregnancy, 5 to 10 percent of women with gestational diabetes continue to have high blood glucose levels and are diagnosed as having diabetes, usually type 2.1 Research has shown that lifestyle changes and the diabetes medication, metformin, can reduce or delay the risk of type 2 diabetes in these women. Babies born to mothers who had gestational diabetes are also more likely to develop obesity and type 2 diabetes as they grow up.  More information about gestational diabetes is provided in the NIDDK health topic, What I need to know about Gestational Diabetes,or by calling 18008608747.
                
Other Types of Diabetes
                
Many other types of diabetes exist, and a person can exhibit characteristics of more than one type. For example, in latent autoimmune diabetes in adults, people show signs of both type 1 and type 2 diabetes. Other types of diabetes include those caused by genetic defects, diseases of the pancreas, excess amounts of certain hormones resulting from some medical conditions, medications that reduce insulin action, chemicals that destroy beta cells, infections, rare autoimmune disorders, and genetic syndromes associated with diabetes.
                
More information about other types of diabetes is provided in the NIDDK health topic, Causes of Diabetes, or by calling 18008608747.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000035-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Diagnosis of Diabetes and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Prediabetes is when blood glucose levels are higher than normal but not high enough for a diagnosis of diabetes. Prediabetes means a person is at increased risk for developing type 2 diabetes, as well as for heart disease and stroke. Many people with prediabetes develop type 2 diabetes within 10 years.
                
However, modest weight loss and moderate physical activity can help people with prediabetes delay or prevent type 2 diabetes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000035-3" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Diagnosis of Diabetes and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Blood tests are used to diagnosis diabetes and prediabetes because early in the disease type 2 diabetes may have no symptoms. All diabetes blood tests involve drawing blood at a health care providers office or commercial facility and sending the sample to a lab for analysis. Lab analysis of blood is needed to ensure test results are accurate. Glucose measuring devices used in a health care providers office, such as finger-stick devices, are not accurate enough for diagnosis but may be used as a quick indicator of high blood glucose.
                
Testing enables health care providers to find and treat diabetes before complications occur and to find and treat prediabetes, which can delay or prevent type 2 diabetes from developing.
                
Any one of the following tests can be used for diagnosis:*
                
- an A1C test, also called the hemoglobin A1c, HbA1c, or glycohemoglobin test  - a fasting plasma glucose (FPG) test  - an oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT)
                
*Not all tests are recommended for diagnosing all types of diabetes. See the individual test descriptions for details.
                
Another blood test, the random plasma glucose (RPG) test, is sometimes used to diagnose diabetes during a regular health checkup. If the RPG measures 200 milligrams per deciliter or above, and the individual also shows symptoms of diabetes, then a health care provider may diagnose diabetes.
                
Symptoms of diabetes include
                
- increased urination  - increased thirst  - unexplained weight loss
                
Other symptoms can include fatigue, blurred vision, increased hunger, and sores that do not heal.
                
Any test used to diagnose diabetes requires confirmation with a second measurement unless clear symptoms of diabetes exist.
                
The following table provides the blood test levels for diagnosis of diabetes for nonpregnant adults and diagnosis of prediabetes.
                
A1C Test
                
The A1C test is used to detect type 2 diabetes and prediabetes but is not recommended for diagnosis of type 1 diabetes or gestational diabetes. The A1C test is a blood test that reflects the average of a persons blood glucose levels over the past 3 months and does not show daily fluctuations. The A1C test is more convenient for patients than the traditional glucose tests because it does not require fasting and can be performed at any time of the day.
                
The A1C test result is reported as a percentage. The higher the percentage, the higher a persons blood glucose levels have been. A normal A1C level is below 5.7 percent.
                
An A1C of 5.7 to 6.4 percent indicates prediabetes. People diagnosed with prediabetes may be retested in 1 year. People with an A1C below 5.7 percent maystill be at risk for diabetes, depending on the presence of other characteristics that put them at risk, also known as risk factors. People with an A1C above 6.0 percent should be considered at very high risk of developing diabetes. A level of 6.5 percent or above means a person has diabetes.
                
Laboratory analysis. When the A1C test is used for diagnosis, the blood sample must be sent to a laboratory using a method that is certified by the NGSP to ensure the results are standardized. Blood samples analyzed in a health care providers office, known as point-of-care tests, are not standardized for diagnosing diabetes.
                
Abnormal results. The A1C test can be unreliable for diagnosing or monitoring diabetes in people with certain conditions known to interfere with the results. Interference should be suspected when A1C results seem very different from the results of a blood glucose test. People of African, Mediterranean, or Southeast Asian descent or people with family members with sickle cell anemia or a thalassemia are particularly at risk of interference.
                
However, not all of the A1C tests are unreliable for people with these diseases. The NGSP provides information about which A1C tests are appropriate to use for specific types of interference and details on any problems with the A1C test at www.ngsp.org.
                
False A1C test results may also occur in people with other problems that affect their blood or hemoglobin such as chronic kidney disease, liver disease, or anemia.
                
More information about limitations of the A1C test and different forms of sickle cell anemia is provided in the NIDDK health topic, For People of African, Mediterranean, or Southeast Asian Heritage: Important Information about Diabetes Blood Tests, or by calling 18008608747.
                
Changes in Diagnostic Testing
                
In the past, the A1C test was used to monitor blood glucose levels but not for diagnosis. The A1C test has now been standardized, and in 2009, an international expert committee recommended it be used for diagnosis of type 2 diabetes and prediabetes.2
                
More information about the A1C test is provided in the NIDDK health topic, The A1C Test and Diabetes, or by calling 18008608747.
                
Fasting Plasma Glucose Test
                
The FPG test is used to detect diabetes and prediabetes. The FPG test has been the most common test used for diagnosing diabetes because it is more convenient than the OGTT and less expensive. The FPG test measures blood glucose in a person who has fasted for at least 8 hours and is most reliable when given in the morning.
                
People with a fasting glucose level of 100 to 125 mg/dL have impaired fasting glucose (IFG), or prediabetes. A level of 126 mg/dL or above, confirmed by repeating the test on another day, means a person has diabetes.
                
Oral Glucose Tolerance Test
                
The OGTT can be used to diagnose diabetes, prediabetes, and gestational diabetes. Research has shown that the OGTT is more sensitive than the FPG test, but it is less convenient to administer. When used to test for diabetes or prediabetes, the OGTT measures blood glucose after a person fasts for at least 8 hours and 2 hours after the person drinks a liquid containing 75 grams of glucose dissolved in water.
                
If the 2-hour blood glucose level is between 140 and 199 mg/dL, the person has a type of prediabetes called impaired glucose tolerance (IGT). If confirmed by a second test, a 2-hour glucose level of 200 mg/dL or above means a person has diabetes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000035-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Diagnosis of Diabetes and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Health care providers test for gestational diabetes using the OGTT. Women may be tested during their first visit to the health care provider after becoming pregnant or between 24 to 28 weeks of pregnancy depending on their risk factors and symptoms. Women found to have diabetes at the first visit to the health care provider after becoming pregnant may be diagnosed with type 2 diabetes.
                
Defining Safe Blood Glucose Levels for Pregnancy
                
Many studies have shown that gestational diabetes can cause complications for the mother and baby. An international, multicenter study, the Hyperglycemia and Adverse Pregnancy Outcome (HAPO) study, showed that the higher a pregnant womans blood glucose is, the higher her risk of pregnancy complications. The HAPO researchers found that pregnancy complications can occur at blood glucose levels that were once considered to be normal.
                
Based on the results of the HAPO study, new guidelines for diagnosis of gestational diabetes were recommended by the International Association of the Diabetes and Pregnancy Study Groups in 2011. So far, the new guidelines have been adopted by the American Diabetes Association (ADA)3 but not by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (ACOG)4 or other medical organizations. Researchers estimate these new guidelines, if widely adopted, will increase the proportion of pregnant women diagnosed with gestational diabetes to nearly 18 percent.5
                
Both ADA and ACOG guidelines for using the OGTT in diagnosing gestational diabetes are shown in the following tables.
                
Recommendations for Testing Pregnant Women for Diabetes
                
Time of testing    ACOG    ADA        At first visit during pregnancy    No recommendation    Test women with risk factors for diabetes using standard testing for diagnosis of type 2 diabetes.  Women found to have diabetes at this time should be diagnosed with type 2 diabetes, not gestational diabetes.        At 24 to 28 weeks of pregnancy    Test women for diabetes based on their history, risk factors, or a 50-gram, 1-hour, nonfasting, glucose challenge testa modified OGTT.  If score is 130140 mg/dL, test again with fasting, 100-gram, 3-hour OGTT.*    Test all women for diabetes who are not already diagnosed, using a fasting, 75-gram, 2-hour OGTT.*
                

                
OGTT Levels for Diagnosis of Gestational Diabetes
                
Time of Sample Collection    ACOG Levels**,4 (mg/dL)    ADA Levels3(mg/dL)        100-gram Glucose Drink    75-gram Glucose Drink        Fasting, before drinking glucose    95 or above    92 or above        1 hour after drinking glucose    180 or above    180 or above        2 hours after drinking glucose    155 or above    153 or above        3 hours after drinking glucose    140 or above    Not used        Requirements for Diagnosis    TWO or more of the above levels must be met    ONE or more of the above levels must be met
                

                

                

                
More information about treating gestational diabetes is provided in the NIDDK health topic, What I need to know about Gestational Diabetes, or by calling 18008608747.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000035-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Diagnosis of Diabetes and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>A major research study, the Diabetes Prevention Program (DPP), proved that people with prediabetes were able to sharply reduce their risk of developing diabetes during the study by losing 5 to 7 percent of their body weight through dietary changes and increased physical activity.
                
Study participants followed a low-fat, low-calorie diet and engaged in regular physical activity, such as walking briskly five times a week for 30 minutes. These strategies worked well for both men and women in all racial and ethnic groups, but were especially effective for participants age 60 and older. A follow-up study, the Diabetes Prevention Program Outcomes Study (DPPOS), showed losing weight and being physically active provide lasting results. Ten years after the DPP, modest weight loss delayed onset of type 2 diabetes by an average of 4 years.
                
The diabetes medication metformin also lowers the risk of type 2 diabetes in people with prediabetes, especially those who are younger and heavier and women who have had gestational diabetes. The DPPOS showed that metformin delayed type 2 diabetes by 2 years. People at high risk should ask their health care provider if they should take metformin to prevent type 2 diabetes. Metformin is a medication that makes insulin work better and can reduce the risk of type 2 diabetes.
                
More information about insulin resistance, the DPP, or how to lower risk for type 2 diabetes is provided in the NIDDK health topics:
                
- Am I at Risk for Type 2 Diabetes?  - Diabetes Prevention Program (DPP)  - Insulin Resistance and Prediabetes
                
Additional information about the DPP, funded under NIH clinical trial number NCT00004992, and the DPPOS, funded under NIH clinical trial number NCT00038727, can be found at www.bsc.gwu.edu/dpp.
                
As part of its Small Steps, Big Rewards campaign, the National Diabetes Education Program (NDEP) offers several booklets about preventing type 2 diabetes, including information about setting goals, tracking progress, implementing a walking program, and finding additional resources. These materials are available at www.ndep.nih.gov or by calling the NDEP at 1888693NDEP (18886936337).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000035-9" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Diagnosis of Diabetes and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>People can manage their diabetes with meal planning, physical activity, and if needed, medications. More information about taking care of type 1 or type 2 diabetes is provided in the NIDDK health topics:
                
- What I need to know about Diabetes Medicines  - What I need to know about Eating and Diabetes  - Your Guide to Diabetes: Type 1 and Type 2
                
These NDIC publications are available at http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/Diabetes/Pages/default.aspx or by calling 18008608747.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000035-10" qtype="considerations">What to do for Diagnosis of Diabetes and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Tests used for diagnosing diabetes and prediabetes include the A1C testfor type 2 diabetes and prediabetesthe fasting plasma glucose (FPG) test, and the oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT). Another blood test, the random plasma glucose (RPG) test, is sometimes used to diagnose diabetes when symptoms are present during a regular health checkup.  - Anyone age 45 or older should consider getting tested for diabetes or prediabetes. People younger than 45 should consider testing if they are overweight or obese and have one or more additional risk factors for diabetes.  - If results of testing are normal, testing should be repeated at least every 3 years. Health care providers may recommend more frequent testing depending on initial results and risk status.  - People whose test results indicate they have prediabetes may be tested again in 1 year and should take steps to prevent or delay type 2 diabetes.  - Many people with prediabetes develop type 2 diabetes within 10 years.  - Modest weight loss and moderate physical activity can help people with prediabetes delay or prevent type 2 diabetes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
