<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000174" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/kidney-disease/treatment-methods-for-kidney-failure-peritoneal-dialysis/Pages/facts.aspx">
<Focus>Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Peritoneal Dialysis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0035078</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000174-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Peritoneal Dialysis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Peritoneal dialysis is a treatment for kidney failure that uses the lining of your abdomen, or belly, to filter your blood inside your body. Doctors call this lining the peritoneum. A doctor will place a soft tube, called a catheter, in your belly a few weeks before you start treatment.
                
When you start peritoneal dialysis, dialysis solutionwater with salt and other additivesflows from a bag through the catheter into your belly. When the bag is empty, you can disconnect your catheter from the bag and cap it so you can move around and do your normal activities. While the dialysis solution is inside your belly, it soaks up wastes and extra fluid from your body. After a few hours, you drain the used dialysis solution into a drain bag. You can then dispose of the used dialysis solution, which is now full of wastes and extra fluid, in a toilet or down the drain of a sink or bathtub. Then you start over with a fresh bag of dialysis solution.
                
The process of first draining the used dialysis solution and then replacing it with fresh solution is called an exchange. Most people do four to six exchanges every day, or during the night using a machine that moves the fluid in and out. The process goes on continuously, so you always have dialysis solution in your belly soaking up wastes and extra fluid from your body. For the best results from peritoneal dialysis, it is important that you perform all of your exchanges as your doctor instructs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000174-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Peritoneal Dialysis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The two types of peritoneal dialysis are continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysisalso called CAPDand automated peritoneal dialysiswhich doctors sometimes call APD or continuous cycler-assisted peritoneal dialysis. After learning about the types of peritoneal dialysis, you can choose the type that best fits your schedule and lifestyle. If one schedule or type of peritoneal dialysis does not suit you, you can talk with your doctor about trying another type.
                
- Continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis does not require a machine. You can do it in any clean, well-lit place. The time period that the dialysis solution is in your belly is called the dwell time. With continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis, the dialysis solution stays in your belly for a dwell time of 4 to 6 hours, or more. Each exchange takes about 30 to 40 minutes. During an exchange, you can read, talk, watch television, or sleep. Usually, you change the dialysis solution at least four times a day and sleep with solution in your belly at night. You do not have to wake up and perform exchanges during the night.  - Automated peritoneal dialysis uses a machine called a cycler to fill and empty your belly three to five times during the night while you sleep. In the morning, you begin one exchange with a daylong dwell time. You may do an additional exchange around the middle of the afternoon without the cycler to increase the amount of waste removed and reduce the amount of fluid left behind in your body.
                
If you weigh more than 175 pounds or if your peritoneum filters wastes slowly, you may need a combination of continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis and automated peritoneal dialysis. For example, some people use a cycler at night and perform one exchange during the day. Your health care team will help you determine the best schedule for you.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000174-8" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Peritoneal Dialysis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care team will perform several tests to tell if your dialysis exchanges are removing enough wastes. These tests are especially important during the first weeks of treatment to determine whether your schedule is adequate.
                
Peritoneal Equilibration Test
                
For a peritoneal equilibration test, a dialysis nurse takes samples of your blood and dialysis solution during a 4-hour exchange. The peritoneal equilibration test measures how much dextrose your body absorbs from a bag of dialysis solution. The peritoneal equilibration test also measures how much urea and creatininewaste products of normal muscle and protein breakdownmove from your blood into the dialysis solution.
                
Clearance Test
                
For a clearance test, you will collect the used dialysis solution from a 24-hour period. A dialysis nurse takes a blood sample during the same 24-hour period. Your doctor or nurse compares the amount of urea in the used solution with the amount in your blood to see how much urea was removed. For the first months or even years of peritoneal dialysis treatment, you may still produce small amounts of urine. If you produce more than 100 milliliters (3 ounces) of urine per day, you will also collect your urine to measure its urea content.
                
From the measurements of used solution, blood, and, if available, urine, your health care team can determine your urea clearancea measurement doctors call your Kt/Vand your creatinine clearance rate. These measurements will show whether you are using the right peritoneal dialysis schedule and doses. If your dialysis schedule is not removing enough wastes, your doctor will make adjustments. More information is provided in the NIDDK health topic, Peritoneal Dialysis Dose and Adequacy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000174-11" qtype="considerations">What to do for Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Peritoneal Dialysis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Eating the right foods can help you feel better while on peritoneal dialysis. Talk with your dialysis centers dietitian to find a meal plan that works for you. Your dietary needs will depend on your treatment and other factors such as your weight and activity level. Staying healthy with CKD requires watching what is in your diet:
                
- Protein is in foods from animals and plants. Protein provides the building blocks that maintain and repair muscles, organs, and other parts of your body. Peritoneal dialysis can remove proteins from your body, so eat high-quality, protein-rich foods such as meat, fish, and eggs. However, many high-protein foods also contain phosphorous, which can weaken your bones. Talk with your dietitian about ways to get the protein you need without getting too much phosphorous.  - Phosphorus is a mineral that helps your bones stay healthy and your blood vessels and muscles work. Phosphorus is a natural part of foods rich in protein, and food producers often add it to many processed foods. Phosphorus can weaken your bones and make your skin itch if you consume too much. Peritoneal dialysis may not remove enough phosphorus from your body, so you will probably need to limit or avoid high-phosphorus foods such as milk and cheese, dried beans, peas, colas, nuts, and peanut butter. You may also need to take a pill called a phosphate binder that keeps phosphorus in your food from entering your bloodstream.  - Fluid includes water and drinks such as fruit juice and milk and water in foods such as fruits, vegetables, ice cream, gelatin, soup, and ice pops. You need water for your body to function properly; however, too much can cause swelling and make your heart work harder. Over time, having too much fluid in your body can cause high blood pressure and congestive heart failure. Peritoneal dialysis might cause you to have either too much or too little fluid, depending on the strength of the solution you use. Your diet can also influence whether you have too much or too little fluid. Your dietitian will help you determine how much liquid you need to consume each day.  - Sodium is a part of salt. Many canned, packaged, frozen, and fast foods contain sodium. Sodium is also a part of many condiments, seasonings, and meats. Too much sodium makes you thirsty, which makes you drink more liquid. Try to eat fresh foods that are naturally low in sodium, and look for products that say low sodium on the label, especially in canned and frozen foods.  - Potassium is a mineral that helps your nerves and muscles work the right way. Peritoneal dialysis can pull too much potassium from your blood, so you may need to eat more high-potassium foods such as bananas, oranges, potatoes, and tomatoes. However, be careful not to eat too much potassium. Your dietitian will help you choose the right amount.  - Calories are units for measuring the energy provided by foods and drinks. Eating foods with too many calories, such as oily and sugary foods, can make you gain weight. Your body can absorb the dextrose from your dialysis solution, which can increase your calorie intake. You may find you need to take in fewer calories to prevent weight gain. Your dietitian can help you create and follow a diet to stay at a healthy weight.  - Supplements help provide some of the vitamins and minerals that may be missing from your diet. Peritoneal dialysis also removes some vitamins from your body. Your doctor may prescribe a vitamin and mineral supplement that scientists have designed specifically for people with CKD and kidney failure. Never take vitamin and mineral supplements that you can buy over the counter. They may be harmful to you. Talk with your doctor before taking any medicine, including vitamin and mineral supplements, that he or she has not prescribed for you.
                
You may have a difficult time changing your diet at first. Eating the right foods will help you feel better. You will have more strength and energy. More information is provided in the NIDDK health topic, Make the Kidney Connection: Food Tips and Healthy Eating Ideas.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000174-12" qtype="considerations">What to do for Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Peritoneal Dialysis ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Peritoneal dialysis is a treatment for kidney failure that uses the lining of your abdomen, or belly, to filter your blood inside your body.  - The two types of peritoneal dialysis are continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis and automated peritoneal dialysis.  - The most common problem with peritoneal dialysis is peritonitis, a serious abdominal infection.  - When dialysis solution stays in the body too long, it becomes so full of wastes and extra fluid that it cannot absorb any more from the body. The process may even reverse, letting some wastes and extra fluid back into the body.  - Eating the right foods can help you feel better while on peritoneal dialysis. Talk with your dialysis centers dietitian to find a meal plan that works for you.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
