<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000121" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/digestive-diseases/smoking/Pages/facts.aspx">
<Focus>Smoking and the Digestive System</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1519384</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000121-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Smoking and the Digestive System ?</Question>
			<Answer>The digestive system is made up of the gastrointestinal (GI) tractalso called the digestive tractand the liver, pancreas, and gallbladder. The GI tract is a series of hollow organs joined in a long, twisting tube from the mouth to the anus. The hollow organs that make up the GI tract are the mouth, esophagus, stomach, small intestine, large intestinewhich includes the colon and rectumand anus. Food enters the mouth and passes to the anus through the hollow organs of the GI tract. The liver, pancreas, and gallbladder are the solid organs of the digestive system. The digestive system helps the body digest food, which includes breaking food down into nutrients the body needs. Nutrients are substances the body uses for energy, growth, and cell repair.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000121-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Smoking and the Digestive System? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Smoking has been found to increase the risk of cancers of the3
                
- mouth  - esophagus  - stomach  - pancreas
                
3
                
,
                
4
                
,
                
5
                
- liver  - colon  - rectum
                
More information about the link between smoking and cancers of the digestive system can be found on the National Cancer Institute website at www.cancer.gov/cancertopics/tobacco/smoking.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000121-3" qtype="information">What is (are) Smoking and the Digestive System ?</Question>
			<Answer>Smoking contributes to many common disorders of the digestive system, such as heartburn and gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD), peptic ulcers, and some liver diseases. Smoking increases the risk of Crohns disease, colon polyps, and pancreatitis, and it may increase the risk of gallstones.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000121-12" qtype="considerations">What to do for Smoking and the Digestive System ?</Question>
			<Answer>Eating, diet, and nutrition can play a role in causing, preventing, and treating some of the diseases and disorders of the digestive system that are affected by smoking, including heartburn and GERD, liver diseases, Crohns disease, colon polyps, pancreatitis, and gallstones. More information about eating, diet, and nutrition and these conditions can be found on the Digestive Diseases A-Z list.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="13">
			<Question qid="0000121-13" qtype="considerations">What to do for Smoking and the Digestive System ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Smoking has been found to increase the risk of cancers of the mouth, esophagus, stomach, and pancreas. Research suggests that smoking may also increase the risk of cancers of the liver, colon, and rectum.  - Smoking increases the risk of heartburn and gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD).  - Smoking increases the risk of peptic ulcers.  - Smoking may worsen some liver diseases, including primary biliary cirrhosis and nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD).  - Current and former smokers have a higher risk of developing Crohns disease than people who have never smoked.  - People who smoke are more likely to develop colon polyps.  - Smoking increases the risk of developing pancreatitis.  - Some studies have shown that smoking may increase the risk of developing gallstones. However, research results are not consistent and more study is needed.  - Quitting smoking can reverse some of the effects of smoking on the digestive system.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
