<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000173" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/kidney-disease/solitary-kidney/Pages/facts.aspx">
<Focus>Solitary Kidney</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0266294</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000173-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Solitary Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>When a person has only one kidney or one working kidney, this kidney is called a solitary kidney. The three main causes of a solitary kidney are
                
- birth defects. People with kidney agenesis are born with only one kidney. People born with kidney dysplasia have both kidneys; however, one kidney does not function. Many people with kidney agenesis or kidney dysplasia do not discover that they have a solitary kidney until they have an x ray, an ultrasound, or surgery for an unrelated condition.  - surgical removal of a kidney. Some people must have a kidney removed to treat cancer or another disease or injury. When a kidney is removed surgically due to disease or for donation, both the kidney and ureter are removed.  - kidney donation. A growing number of people are donating a kidney to be transplanted into a family member or friend whose kidneys have failed.
                
In general, people with a solitary kidney lead full, healthy lives. However, some people are more likely to develop kidney disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000173-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Solitary Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>The kidneys are two bean-shaped organs, each about the size of a fist. They are located just below the rib cage, one on each side of the spine. Every day, the kidneys filter about 120 to 150 quarts of blood to produce about 1 to 2 quarts of urine, composed of wastes and extra fluid. The urine flows from the kidneys to the bladder through tubes called ureters. The bladder stores urine until releasing it through urination.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000173-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Solitary Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with a solitary kidney do not need to eat a special diet. However, people with reduced kidney function may need to make changes to their diet to slow the progression of kidney disease. More information about recommended dietary changes is provided in the NIDDK health topics, Nutrition for Early Chronic Kidney Disease in Adults and Nutrition for Advanced Chronic Kidney Disease in Adults, and on the National Kidney Disease Education Program website. People should talk with their health care provider about what diet is right for them.
                
Controlling Blood Pressure
                
People can control their blood pressure by not smoking, eating a healthy diet, and taking certain medications. Medications that lower blood pressure can also significantly slow the progression of kidney disease. Two types of blood pressurelowering medications, angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors and angiotensin receptor blockers (ARBs), have proven effective in slowing the progression of kidney disease. Many people require two or more medications to control their blood pressure. In addition to an ACE inhibitor or ARB, a diuretica medication that helps the kidneys remove fluid from the bloodmay be prescribed. Beta-blockers, calcium channel blockers, and other blood pressure medications may also be needed.
                
Preventing Injury
                
For people with a solitary kidney, loss of the remaining working kidney results in the need for dialysis or kidney transplant. People should make sure their health care providers know they have a solitary kidney to prevent injury from medications or medical procedures. People who participate in certain sports may be more likely to injure the kidney; this risk is of particular concern with children, as they are more likely to play sports. The American Academy of Pediatrics recommends individual assessment for contact, collision, and limited-contact sports. Protective equipment may reduce the chance of injury to the remaining kidney enough to allow participation in most sports, provided that such equipment remains in place during activity. Health care providers, parents, and patients should consider the risks of any activity and decide whether the benefits outweigh those risks.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000173-6" qtype="considerations">What to do for Solitary Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>- When a person has only one kidney or one working kidney, this kidney is called a solitary kidney. The three main causes of a solitary kidney are birth defects, surgical removal of a kidney, and kidney donation.  - In general, people with a solitary kidney lead full, healthy lives. However, some people are more likely to develop kidney disease.  - People with a solitary kidney should be tested regularly for the following signs of kidney damage:      - albuminuria    - decreased glomerular filtration rate (GFR)    - high blood pressure    - People with a solitary kidney can protect their health by eating a nutritious diet, keeping their blood pressure at the appropriate level, and preventing injury to the working kidney.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
