<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000005" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/endocrine/hashimotos-disease/Pages/fact-sheet.aspx">
<Focus>Hashimoto's Disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0677607</CUI>
			<CUI>C0012634</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000005-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hashimoto's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hashimotos disease, also called chronic lymphocytic thyroiditis or autoimmune thyroiditis, is an autoimmune disease. An autoimmune disease is a disorder in which the bodys immune system attacks the bodys own cells and organs. Normally, the immune system protects the body from infection by identifying and destroying bacteria, viruses, and other potentially harmful foreign substances.
                
In Hashimotos disease, the immune system attacks the thyroid gland, causing inflammation and interfering with its ability to produce thyroid hormones. Large numbers of white blood cells called lymphocytes accumulate in the thyroid. Lymphocytes make the antibodies that start the autoimmune process.
                
Hashimotos disease often leads to reduced thyroid function, or hypothyroidism. Hypothyroidism is a disorder that occurs when the thyroid doesnt make enough thyroid hormone for the bodys needs. Thyroid hormones regulate metabolismthe way the body uses energyand affect nearly every organ in the body. Without enough thyroid hormone, many of the bodys functions slow down. Hashimotos disease is the most common cause of hypothyroidism in the United States.1
                
More information is provided in the NIDDK health topic, Hypothyroidism.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000005-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Hashimoto's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The thyroid is a 2-inch-long, butterfly-shaped gland weighing less than 1 ounce. Located in the front of the neck below the larynx, or voice box, it has two lobes, one on either side of the windpipe.
                
The thyroid is one of the glands that make up the endocrine system. The glands of the endocrine system produce and store hormones and release them into the bloodstream. The hormones then travel through the body and direct the activity of the bodys cells.
                
The thyroid makes two thyroid hormones, triiodothyronine (T3) and thyroxine (T4). T3 is the active hormone and is made from T4. Thyroid hormones affect metabolism, brain development, breathing, heart and nervous system functions, body temperature, muscle strength, skin dryness, menstrual cycles, weight, and cholesterol levels.
                
Thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH), which is made by the pituitary gland in the brain, regulates thyroid hormone production. When thyroid hormone levels in the blood are low, the pituitary releases more TSH. When thyroid hormone levels are high, the pituitary decreases TSH production.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000005-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hashimoto's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many people with Hashimotos disease have no symptoms at first. As the disease slowly progresses, the thyroid usually enlarges and may cause the front of the neck to look swollen. The enlarged thyroid, called a goiter, may create a feeling of fullness in the throat, though it is usually not painful. After many years, or even decades, damage to the thyroid causes it to shrink and the goiter to disappear.
                
Not everyone with Hashimotos disease develops hypothyroidism. For those who do, the hypothyroidism may be subclinicalmild and without symptoms, especially early in its course. With progression to hypothyroidism, people may have one or more of the following symptoms:
                
- fatigue  - weight gain  - cold intolerance  - joint and muscle pain  - constipation, or fewer than three bowel movements a week  - dry, thinning hair  - heavy or irregular menstrual periods and problems becoming pregnant  - depression  - memory problems  - a slowed heart rate</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000005-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hashimoto's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Diagnosis begins with a physical exam and medical history. A goiter, nodules, or growths may be found during a physical exam, and symptoms may suggest hypothyroidism. Health care providers will then perform blood tests to confirm the diagnosis. A blood test involves drawing blood at a health care providers office or a commercial facility and sending the sample to a lab for analysis. Diagnostic blood tests may include the
                
- TSH test. The ultrasensitive TSH test is usually the first test performed. This test detects even tiny amounts of TSH in the blood and is the most accurate measure of thyroid activity available. Generally, a TSH reading above normal means a person has hypothyroidism.  - T4 test. The T4 test measures the actual amount of thyroid hormone circulating in the blood. In hypothyroidism, the level of T4 in the blood is lower than normal.  - antithyroid antibody test. This test looks for the presence of thyroid autoantibodies, or molecules produced by a persons body that mistakenly attack the bodys own tissues. Two principal types of antithyroid antibodies are      - anti-TG antibodies, which attack a protein in the thyroid called thyroglobulin    - anti-thyroperoxidase (TPO) antibodies, which attack an enzyme called thyroperoxidase in thyroid cells that helps convert T4 to T3. Having TPO autoantibodies in the blood means the bodys immune system attacked the thyroid tissue in the past. Most people with Hashimotos disease have these antibodies, although people whose hypothyroidism is caused by other conditions do not.
                
A health care provider may also order imaging tests, including an ultrasound or a computerized tomography (CT) scan.
                
- Ultrasound. Ultrasound uses a device, called a transducer, that bounces safe, painless sound waves off organs to create an image of their structure. A specially trained technician performs the procedure in a health care providers office, an outpatient center, or a hospital, and a radiologista doctor who specializes in medical imaginginterprets the images; a patient does not need anesthesia.
                
- The images can show the size and texture of the thyroid, as well as a pattern of typical autoimmune inflammation, helping the health care provider confirm Hashimotos disease. The images can also show nodules or growths within the gland that suggest a malignant tumor.
                
- CT scan. CT scans use a combination of x rays and computer technology to create images. For a CT scan, a health care provider may give the patient a solution to drink and an injection of a special dye, called contrast medium. CT scans require the patient to lie on a table that slides into a tunnel-shaped device where the x rays are taken. An x-ray technician performs the procedure in an outpatient center or a hospital, and a radiologist interprets the images. The patient does not need anesthesia. In some cases of Hashimotos disease, a CT scan is used to examine the placement and extent of a large goiter, and to show a goiters effect on nearby structures.
                
More information is provided in the NIDDK health topic, Thyroid Tests.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000005-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hashimoto's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment generally depends on whether the thyroid is damaged enough to cause hypothyroidism. In the absence of hypothyroidism, some health care providers treat Hashimotos disease to reduce the size of the goiter. Others choose not to treat the disease and simply monitor their patients for disease progression.
                
Hashimotos disease, with or without hypothyroidism, is treated with synthetic thyroxine, which is man-made T4. Health care providers prefer to use synthetic T4, such as Synthroid, rather than synthetic T3, because T4 stays in the body longer, ensuring a steady supply of thyroid hormone throughout the day. The thyroid preparations made with animal thyroid are not considered as consistent as synthetic thyroid (Levothyroxine) and rarely prescribed today.
                
Health care providers routinely test the blood of patients taking synthetic thyroid hormone and adjust the dose as necessary, typically based on the result of the TSH test. Hypothyroidism can almost always be completely controlled with synthetic thyroxine, as long as the recommended dose is taken every day as instructed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000005-8" qtype="considerations">What to do for Hashimoto's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Iodine is an essential mineral for the thyroid. However, people with Hashimotos disease may be sensitive to harmful side effects from iodine. Taking iodine drops or eating foods containing large amounts of iodinesuch as seaweed, dulse, or kelpmay cause or worsen hypothyroidism. Read more in Iodine in diet at www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002421.htm.
                
Women need more iodine when they are pregnantabout 220 micrograms a daybecause the baby gets iodine from the mothers diet. Women who are breastfeeding need about 290 micrograms a day. In the United States, about 7 percent of pregnant women may not get enough iodine in their diet or through prenatal vitamins.3 Pregnant women should choose iodized saltsalt supplemented with iodineover plain salt and take prenatal vitamins containing iodine to ensure this need is met.
                
To help ensure coordinated and safe care, people should discuss their use of complementary and alternative medical practices, including their use of dietary supplements such as iodine, with their health care provider. Tips for talking with health care providers are available through the National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000005-9" qtype="considerations">What to do for Hashimoto's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Hashimotos disease, also called chronic lymphocytic thyroiditis or autoimmune thyroiditis, is an autoimmune disease.  - Hashimotos disease often leads to reduced thyroid function, or hypothyroidism. Hypothyroidism is a disorder that occurs when the thyroid doesnt make enough thyroid hormone for the bodys needs.  - Hashimotos disease is the most common cause of hypothyroidism in the United States. Many people with Hashimotos disease have no symptoms at first. As the disease slowly progresses, the thyroid usually enlarges and may cause the front of the neck to look swollen. The enlarged thyroid, called a goiter, may create a feeling of fullness in the throat, though it is usually not painful.  - Not everyone with Hashimotos disease develops hypothyroidism. For those who do, the hypothyroidism may be subclinicalmild and without symptoms, especially early in its course.  - Hashimotos disease is much more common in women than men. Although the disease often occurs in adolescent or young women, it more commonly appears between 30 and 50 years of age.  - Hashimotos disease, with or without hypothyroidism, is treated with synthetic thyroxine, which is man-made T4.  - Women with Hashimotos disease should discuss their condition with their health care provider before becoming pregnant.  - Pregnant women should choose iodized saltsalt supplemented with iodineover plain salt and take prenatal vitamins containing iodine.  - People should discuss their use of dietary supplements, such as iodine, with their health care provider.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
