<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000154" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/kidney-disease/kidney-dysplasia/Pages/facts.aspx">
<Focus>Kidney Dysplasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3536714</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000154-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Kidney Dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kidney dysplasia is a condition in which the internal structures of one or both of a fetus kidneys do not develop normally while in the womb. During normal development, two thin tubes of muscle called ureters grow into the kidneys and branch out to form a network of tiny structures called tubules. The tubules collect urine as the fetus grows in the womb. In kidney dysplasia, the tubules fail to branch out completely. Urine that would normally flow through the tubules has nowhere to go. Urine collects inside the affected kidney and forms fluid-filled sacs called cysts. The cysts replace normal kidney tissue and prevent the kidney from functioning.
                
Kidney dysplasia can affect one kidney or both kidneys. Babies with severe kidney dysplasia affecting both kidneys generally do not survive birth. Those who do survive may need the following early in life:
                
- blood-filtering treatments called dialysis  - a kidney transplant
                
Children with dysplasia in only one kidney have normal kidney function if the other kidney is unaffected. Those with mild dysplasia of both kidneys may not need dialysis or a kidney transplant for several years.
                
Kidney dysplasia is also called renal dysplasia or multicystic dysplastic kidney.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000154-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Kidney Dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The kidneys are two bean-shaped organs, each about the size of a fist. They are located just below the rib cage, one on each side of the spine. Every day, the two kidneys filter about 120 to 150 quarts of blood to produce about 1 to 2 quarts of urine, which is composed of wastes and extra fluid. Children produce less urine than adultsthe amount they produce depends on their age. The urine flows from the kidneys to the bladder through the two ureters, one on each side of the bladder. The bladder stores urine. The muscles of the bladder wall remain relaxed while the bladder fills with urine. As the bladder fills to capacity, signals sent to the brain tell a person to find a toilet soon. When the bladder empties, urine flows out of the body through a tube called the urethra, located at the bottom of the bladder.
                
The kidneys, ureters, bladder, and urethra are parts of the urinary tract. More information is provided in the NIDDK health topics, the kidneys and the urinary tract.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000154-3" qtype="causes">What causes Kidney Dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Genetic factors can cause kidney dysplasia. Genes pass information from both parents to the child and determine the childs traits. Sometimes, parents may pass a gene that has changed, or mutated, causing kidney dysplasia.
                
Genetic syndromes that affect multiple body systems can also cause kidney dysplasia. A syndrome is a group of symptoms or conditions that may seem unrelated yet are thought to have the same genetic cause. A baby with kidney dysplasia due to a genetic syndrome might also have problems of the digestive tract, nervous system, heart and blood vessels, muscles and skeleton, or other parts of the urinary tract.
                
A baby may also develop kidney dysplasia if his or her mother takes certain prescription medications during pregnancy, such as some used to treat seizures and high blood pressure. A mothers use of illegal drugs, such as cocaine, during pregnancy may also cause kidney dysplasia in her unborn child.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000154-4" qtype="frequency">How many people are affected by Kidney Dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kidney dysplasia is a common condition. Scientists estimate that kidney dysplasia affects about one in 4,000 babies.1 This estimate may be low because some people with kidney dysplasia are never diagnosed with the condition. About half of the babies diagnosed with this condition have other urinary tract defects.2</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000154-6" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Kidney Dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many babies with kidney dysplasia in only one kidney have no signs of the condition. In some cases, the affected kidney may be enlarged at birth and may cause pain.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000154-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Kidney Dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The complications of kidney dysplasia can include
                
- hydronephrosis of the working kidney. A baby with kidney dysplasia in only one kidney might have other urinary tract defects. When other defects in the urinary tract block the flow of urine, the urine backs up and causes the kidneys and ureters to swell, a condition called hydronephrosis. If left untreated, hydronephrosis can damage the working kidney and reduce its ability to filter blood. Kidney damage may lead to chronic kidney disease (CKD) and kidney failure.  - a urinary tract infection (UTI). A urine blockage may increase a babys chance of developing a UTI. Recurring UTIs can also lead to kidney damage.  - high blood pressure.  - a slightly increased chance of developing kidney cancer.
                
More information is provided in the NIDDK health topics, urine blockage in newbornsand UTIs in children.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000154-8" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Kidney Dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Health care providers may be able to diagnose kidney dysplasia during a womans pregnancy using a fetal ultrasound, also called a fetal sonogram. Ultrasound uses a device, called a transducer, that bounces safe, painless sound waves off organs to create an image of their structure. Fetal ultrasound is a test done during pregnancy to create images of the fetus in the womb. A specially trained technician performs the procedure in a health care providers office, an outpatient center, or a hospital, and an obstetrician or a radiologist interprets the images. An obstetrician is a doctor who specializes in pregnancy and childbirth. A radiologist is a doctor who specializes in medical imaging. The patientin this case, the fetus motherdoes not need anesthesia for this procedure. The images can show defects in the fetus kidneys and other parts of the urinary tract.
                
Health care providers do not always diagnose kidney dysplasia before a baby is born. After birth, health care providers often diagnose kidney dysplasia during an evaluation of the child for a UTI or another medical condition. A health care provider uses ultrasound to diagnose kidney dysplasia after the baby is born.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000154-9" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Kidney Dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>If the condition is limited to one kidney and the baby has no signs of kidney dysplasia, no treatment may be necessary. However, the baby should have regular checkups that include
                
- checking blood pressure.  - testing blood to measure kidney function.  - testing urine for albumin, a protein most often found in blood. Albumin in the urine may be a sign of kidney damage.  - performing periodic ultrasounds to monitor the damaged kidney and to make sure the functioning kidney continues to grow and remains healthy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000154-10" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Kidney Dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Researchers have not found a way to prevent kidney dysplasia caused by genetic factors or certain genetic syndromes. Pregnant women can prevent kidney dysplasia by avoiding the use of certain prescription medications or illegal drugs during pregnancy. Pregnant women should talk with their health care provider before taking any medications during pregnancy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000154-11" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Kidney Dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The long-term outlook for a child with kidney dysplasia in only one kidney is generally good. A person with one working kidney, a condition called solitary kidney, can grow normally and may have few, if any, health problems.
                
The affected kidney may shrink as the child grows. By age 10,3 the affected kidney may no longer be visible on x-ray or ultrasound. Children and adults with only one working kidney should have regular checkups to test for high blood pressure and kidney damage. A child with urinary tract problems that lead to failure of the working kidney may eventually need dialysis or a kidney transplant.
                
More information is provided in the NIDDK health topics, solitary kidney, dialysis, and kidney transplants.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000154-12" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Kidney Dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The long-term outlook for a child with kidney dysplasia in both kidneys is different from the long-term outlook for a child with one dysplastic kidney. A child with kidney dysplasia in both kidneys
                
- is more likely to develop CKD.  - needs close follow-up with a pediatric nephrologista doctor who specializes in caring for children with kidney disease. Children who live in areas that dont have a pediatric nephrologist available can see a nephrologist who cares for both children and adults.  - may eventually need dialysis or a kidney transplant.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="13">
			<Question qid="0000154-13" qtype="considerations">What to do for Kidney Dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Researchers have not found that eating, diet, and nutrition play a role in causing or preventing kidney dysplasia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="14">
			<Question qid="0000154-14" qtype="considerations">What to do for Kidney Dysplasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Kidney dysplasia is a condition in which the internal structures of one or both of a fetus kidneys do not develop normally while in the womb.  - Genetic factors can cause kidney dysplasia.  - Genetic syndromes that affect multiple body systems can also cause kidney dysplasia.  - A baby may also develop kidney dysplasia if his or her mother takes certain prescription medications during pregnancy, such as some used to treat seizures and high blood pressure.  - Many babies with kidney dysplasia in only one kidney have no signs of the condition.  - Health care providers may be able to diagnose kidney dysplasia during a womans pregnancy using a fetal ultrasound, also called a fetal sonogram.  - Health care providers do not always diagnose kidney dysplasia before a baby is born.  - If the condition is limited to one kidney and the baby has no signs of kidney dysplasia, no treatment may be necessary.  - Researchers have not found a way to prevent kidney dysplasia caused by genetic factors or certain genetic syndromes.  - Pregnant women can prevent kidney dysplasia by avoiding the use of certain prescription medications or illegal drugs during pregnancy.  - The long-term outlook for a child with kidney dysplasia in only one kidney is generally good.  - The long-term outlook for a child with kidney dysplasia in both kidneys is different from the long-term outlook for a child with one dysplastic kidney. A child with kidney dysplasia in both kidneys      - is more likely to develop chronic kidney disease (CKD)    - needs close follow-up with a pediatric nephrologist    - may eventually need dialysis or a kidney transplant</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
