<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000098" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/digestive-diseases/dumping-syndrome/Pages/facts.aspx">
<Focus>Dumping Syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0013288</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039082</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000098-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Dumping Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Dumping syndrome occurs when food, especially sugar, moves too fast from the stomach to the duodenumthe first part of the small intestinein the upper gastrointestinal (GI) tract. This condition is also called rapid gastric emptying. Dumping syndrome has two forms, based on when symptoms occur:
                
- early dumping syndromeoccurs 10 to 30 minutes after a meal  - late dumping syndromeoccurs 2 to 3 hours after a meal</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000098-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Dumping Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The GI tract is a series of hollow organs joined in a long, twisting tube from the mouth to the anusthe opening where stool leaves the body. The body digests food using the movement of muscles in the GI tract, along with the release of hormones and enzymes. The upper GI tract includes the mouth, esophagus, stomach, duodenum, and small intestine. The esophagus carries food and liquids from the mouth to the stomach. The stomach slowly pumps the food and liquids into the intestine, which then absorbs needed nutrients. Two digestive organs, the liver and the pancreas, produce digestive juices that reach the small intestine through small tubes called ducts.
                
The last part of the GI tractcalled the lower GI tractconsists of the large intestine and anus. The large intestine is about 5 feet long in adults and absorbs water and any remaining nutrients from partially digested food passed from the small intestine. The large intestine then changes waste from liquid to a solid matter called stool. Stool passes from the colon to the rectum. The rectum is located between the last part of the coloncalled the sigmoid colonand the anus. The rectum stores stool prior to a bowel movement. During a bowel movement, stool moves from the rectum to the anus.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000098-3" qtype="causes">What causes Dumping Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Dumping syndrome is caused by problems with the storage of food particles in the stomach and emptying of particles into the duodenum. Early dumping syndrome results from rapid movement of fluid into the intestine following a sudden addition of a large amount of food from the stomach. Late dumping syndrome results from rapid movement of sugar into the intestine, which raises the body&apos;s blood glucose level and causes the pancreas to increase its release of the hormone insulin. The increased release of insulin causes a rapid drop in blood glucose levels, a condition known as hypoglycemia, or low blood sugar.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000098-5" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Dumping Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The symptoms of early and late dumping syndrome are different and vary from person to person. Early dumping syndrome symptoms may include
                
- nausea  - vomiting  - abdominal pain and cramping  - diarrhea  - feeling uncomfortably full or bloated after a meal  - sweating  - weakness  - dizziness  - flushing, or blushing of the face or skin  - rapid or irregular heartbeat
                
- hypoglycemia  - sweating  - weakness  - rapid or irregular heartbeat  - flushing  - dizziness
                
About 75 percent of people with dumping syndrome report symptoms of early dumping syndrome and about 25 percent report symptoms of late dumping syndrome. Some people have symptoms of both types of dumping syndrome.1</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000098-6" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Dumping Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>A health care provider will diagnose dumping syndrome primarily on the basis of symptoms. A scoring system helps differentiate dumping syndrome from other GI problems. The scoring system assigns points to each symptom and the total points result in a score. A person with a score above 7 likely has dumping syndrome.
                
The following tests may confirm dumping syndrome and exclude other conditions with similar symptoms:
                
- A modified oral glucose tolerance test checks how well insulin works with tissues to absorb glucose. A health care provider performs the test during an office visit or in a commercial facility and sends the blood samples to a lab for analysis. The person should fasteat or drink nothing except waterfor at least 8 hours before the test. The health care provider will measure blood glucose concentration, hematocritthe amount of red blood cells in the bloodpulse rate, and blood pressure before the test begins. After the initial measurements, the person drinks a glucose solution. The health care provider repeats the initial measurements immediately and at 30-minute intervals for up to 180 minutes. A health care provider often confirms dumping syndrome in people with      - low blood sugar between 120 and 180 minutes after drinking the solution    - an increase in hematocrit of more than 3 percent at 30 minutes    - a rise in pulse rate of more than 10 beats per minute after 30 minutes     - A gastric emptying scintigraphy test involves eating a bland mealsuch as eggs or an egg substitutethat contains a small amount of radioactive material. A specially trained technician performs this test in a radiology center or hospital, and a radiologista doctor who specializes in medical imaginginterprets the results. Anesthesia is not needed. An external camera scans the abdomen to locate the radioactive material. The radiologist measures the rate of gastric emptying at 1, 2, 3, and 4 hours after the meal. The test can help confirm a diagnosis of dumping syndrome.
                
- An upper GI endoscopy involves using an endoscopea small, flexible tube with a lightto see the upper GI tract. A gastroenterologista doctor who specializes in digestive diseasesperforms the test at a hospital or an outpatient center. The gastroenterologist carefully feeds the endoscope down the esophagus and into the stomach and duodenum. A small camera mounted on the endoscope transmits a video image to a monitor, allowing close examination of the intestinal lining. A person may receive general anesthesia or a liquid anesthetic that is gargled or sprayed on the back of the throat. If the person receives general anesthesia, a health care provider will place an intravenous (IV) needle in a vein in the arm. The test may show ulcers, swelling of the stomach lining, or cancer.   - An upper GI series examines the small intestine. An x-ray technician performs the test at a hospital or an outpatient center and a radiologist interprets the images. Anesthesia is not needed. No eating or drinking is allowed before the procedure, as directed by the health care staff. During the procedure, the person will stand or sit in front of an x-ray machine and drink barium, a chalky liquid. Barium coats the small intestine, making signs of a blockage or other complications of gastric surgery show up more clearly on x rays.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000098-7" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Dumping Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment for dumping syndrome includes changes in eating, diet, and nutrition; medication; and, in some cases, surgery. Many people with dumping syndrome have mild symptoms that improve over time with simple dietary changes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000098-8" qtype="considerations">What to do for Dumping Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The first step to minimizing symptoms of dumping syndrome involves changes in eating, diet, and nutrition, and may include
                
- eating five or six small meals a day instead of three larger meals  - delaying liquid intake until at least 30 minutes after a meal  - increasing intake of protein, fiber, and complex carbohydratesfound in starchy foods such as oatmeal and rice  - avoiding simple sugars such as table sugar, which can be found in candy, syrup, sodas, and juice beverages  - increasing the thickness of food by adding pectin or guar gumplant extracts used as thickening agents
                
Some people find that lying down for 30 minutes after meals also helps reduce symptoms.
                
Medication
                
A health care provider may prescribe octreotide acetate (Sandostatin) to treat dumping syndrome symptoms. The medication works by slowing gastric emptying and inhibiting the release of insulin and other GI hormones. Octreotide comes in short- and long-acting formulas. The short-acting formula is injected subcutaneouslyunder the skinor intravenouslyinto a veintwo to four times a day. A health care provider may perform the injections or may train the patient or patient&apos;s friend or relative to perform the injections. A health care provider injects the long-acting formula into the buttocks muscles once every 4 weeks. Complications of octreotide treatment include increased or decreased blood glucose levels, pain at the injection site, gallstones, and fatty, foul-smelling stools.
                
Surgery
                
A person may need surgery if dumping syndrome is caused by previous gastric surgery or if the condition is not responsive to other treatments. For most people, the type of surgery depends on the type of gastric surgery performed previously. However, surgery to correct dumping syndrome often has unsuccessful results.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000098-9" qtype="considerations">What to do for Dumping Syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Dumping syndrome occurs when food, especially sugar, moves too fast from the stomach to the duodenumthe first part of the small intestinein the upper gastrointestinal (GI) tract.  - Dumping syndrome has two forms, based on when symptoms occur:      - early dumping syndromeoccurs 10 to 30 minutes after a meal    - late dumping syndromeoccurs 2 to 3 hours after a meal    - People who have had surgery to remove or bypass a significant part of the stomach are more likely to develop dumping syndrome. Other conditions that impair how the stomach stores and empties itself of food, such as nerve damage caused by esophageal surgery, can also cause dumping syndrome.  - Early dumping syndrome symptoms include      - nausea    - vomiting    - abdominal pain and cramping    - diarrhea    - feeling uncomfortably full or bloated after a meal    - sweating    - weakness    - dizziness    - flushing, or blushing of the face or skin    - rapid or irregular heartbeat    - The symptoms of late dumping syndrome include      - hypoglycemia    - sweating    - weakness    - rapid or irregular heartbeat    - flushing    - dizziness    - Treatment for dumping syndrome includes changes in eating, diet, and nutrition; medication; and, in some cases, surgery. Many people with dumping syndrome have mild symptoms that improve over time with simple dietary changes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
