<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000164" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/kidney-disease/nutrition-for-early-chronic-kidney-disease-in-adults/Pages/facts.aspx">
<Focus>Nutrition for Early Chronic Kidney Disease in Adults</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1561643</CUI>
			<CUI>C0403447</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000164-3" qtype="information">What is (are) Nutrition for Early Chronic Kidney Disease in Adults ?</Question>
			<Answer>CKD usually takes a long time to develop and does not go away. In CKD, the kidneys continue to workjust not as well as they should. Wastes may build up so gradually that the body becomes used to having those wastes in the blood. Salts containing phosphorus and potassium may rise to unsafe levels, causing heart and bone problems. Anemialow red blood cell countcan result from CKD because the kidneys stop making enough erythropoietin, a hormone that causes bone marrow to make red blood cells. After months or years, CKD may progress to permanent kidney failure, which requires a person to have a kidney transplant or regular blood filtering treatments called dialysis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000164-4" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Nutrition for Early Chronic Kidney Disease in Adults? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Millions of Americans are at risk for developing CKD because they have diabetes, high blood pressure, or both. High blood glucose levels put people with diabetes at risk for heart disease, stroke, amputation, and eye and kidney problems. People with high blood pressure are at risk for damaged blood vessels, including tiny vessels in the kidneys.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000164-5" qtype="information">What is (are) Nutrition for Early Chronic Kidney Disease in Adults ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with either type 1 or type 2 diabetes must choose foods carefully to control their blood glucose, the bodys main source of energy. Following a meal plan to keep blood glucose at a healthy level may prevent CKD from developing.
                
People with diabetes should talk with their health care provider about setting goals for maintaining healthy blood glucose levels and about how often to check their blood glucose level. The results from these blood glucose checks indicate whether a persons meal plan is helping to keep diabetes under control. People with diabetes should also ask their doctor for an A1C test at least twice a year. The A1C number reflects a persons average blood glucose level over the past 2 to 3 months.
                
- Eating about the same amount of food each day.  - Eating meals and snacks at about the same times each day.  - Not skipping meals or snacks.  - Taking medicines at the same times each day.  - Participating in physical activity every day.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000164-6" qtype="information">What is (are) Nutrition for Early Chronic Kidney Disease in Adults ?</Question>
			<Answer>As blood pressure rises, the risk of damage to the arteries, heart, brain, and kidneys increases. Controlling blood pressure through healthy food choices and regular physical activity can delay or prevent the development of CKD.
                
Blood pressure is expressed as two numbers. The top number represents the force of the blood pushing against the artery walls when the heart beats. The lower number represents the pressure between beats. Normal blood pressure is below 120/80 millimeters of mercury (mmHg). People with CKD should try to keep their blood pressure below 140/90 mmHg.
                
Following a meal plan can help control blood pressure and protect the kidneys. The National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute supported research that compared a typical American diet with the Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension (DASH) eating plan, which is lower in saturated fat, cholesterol, and total fat and emphasizes eating fruits, vegetables, and low-fat dairy foods. People who followed the DASH eating plan were able to reduce their blood pressure much more than those who ate a typical diet. The DASH eating plan also includes whole grain products, fish, poultry, and nuts. Limiting sodium, or salt, is another important feature of the plan. A dietitian can help find low-salt or salt-free alternatives to foods that are high in salt.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000164-7" qtype="information">What is (are) Nutrition for Early Chronic Kidney Disease in Adults ?</Question>
			<Answer>MNT is the use of nutrition counseling by a registered dietitian to help promote a medical or health goal. A doctor may refer a patient to a registered dietitian to help with the patients food plan. Many insurance policies cover MNT when recommended by a doctor. Anyone who qualifies for Medicare can receive a benefit for MNT from a registered dietitian or nutrition professional when a doctor provides a referral indicating the person has diabetes or kidney disease.
                
One way to locate a qualified dietitian is to contact the American Dietetic Association at www.eatright.organd click on Find a Registered Dietitian. Users can enter their address or ZIP code for a list of dietitians in their area. A person looking for dietary advice to prevent kidney damage should click on Renal (Kidney) Nutrition in the specialty field. Dietitians who specialize in helping people with CKD are called renal dietitians.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000164-9" qtype="considerations">What to do for Nutrition for Early Chronic Kidney Disease in Adults ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Controlling blood glucose and blood pressure through healthy food choices is an important step toward slowing or stopping the progression of chronic kidney disease (CKD).  - The kidneys remove wastes and extra water from the blood and make urine.  - Millions of Americans are at risk for developing CKD because they have diabetes, high blood pressure, or both.  - People with either type 1 or type 2 diabetes must choose foods carefully to control their blood glucose. Following a meal plan to keep blood glucose at a healthy level may prevent CKD from developing.  - Controlling blood pressure through healthy food choices and regular physical activity can delay or prevent the development of CKD. People with CKD should try to keep their blood pressure below 140/90 mmHg.  - Medical nutrition therapy (MNT) is the use of counseling by a registered dietitian to help promote a medical or health goal.   - Dietitians who specialize in helping people with CKD are called renal dietitians.   - Learning how to read and understand lab reports lets a person see how different foods can affect the kidneys. Patients can ask their doctor for copies of their lab reports and ask to have them explained, noting any results out of the normal range.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
