<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000142" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/kidney-disease/facing-the-challenges-of-chronic-kidney-disease-in-children/Pages/facts.aspx">
<Focus>Facing the Challenges of Chronic Kidney Disease in Children</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1561643</CUI>
			<CUI>C0403447</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000142-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Facing the Challenges of Chronic Kidney Disease in Children ?</Question>
			<Answer>For children with CKD, learning about nutrition is vital because their diet can affect how well their kidneys work. Parents or guardians should always consult with their childs health care team before making any dietary changes. Staying healthy with CKD requires paying close attention to the following elements of a diet:
                
- Protein. Children with CKD should eat enough protein for growth while limiting high protein intake. Too much protein can put an extra burden on the kidneys and cause kidney function to decline faster. Protein needs increase when a child is on dialysis because the dialysis process removes protein from the childs blood. The health care team recommends the amount of protein needed for the child. Foods with protein include      - eggs    - milk    - cheese    - chicken    - fish    - red meats    - beans    - yogurt    - cottage cheese    - Sodium. The amount of sodium children need depends on the stage of their kidney disease, their age, and sometimes other factors. The health care team may recommend limiting or adding sodium and salt to the diet. Foods high in sodium include      - canned foods    - some frozen foods    - most processed foods    - some snack foods, such as chips and crackers    - Potassium. Potassium levels need to stay in the normal range for children with CKD, because too little or too much potassium can cause heart and muscle problems. Children may need to stay away from some fruits and vegetables or reduce the number of servings and portion sizes to make sure they do not take in too much potassium. The health care team recommends the amount of potassium a child needs. Low-potassium fruits and vegetables include      - apples    - cranberries    - strawberries    - blueberries    - raspberries    - pineapple    - cabbage    - boiled cauliflower    - mustard greens    - uncooked broccoli   High-potassium fruits and vegetables include      - oranges    - melons    - apricots    - bananas    - potatoes    - tomatoes    - sweet potatoes    - cooked spinach    - cooked broccoli    - Phosphorus. Children with CKD need to control the level of phosphorus in their blood because too much phosphorus pulls calcium from the bones, making them weaker and more likely to break. Too much phosphorus also can cause itchy skin and red eyes. As CKD progresses, a child may need to take a phosphate binder with meals to lower the concentration of phosphorus in the blood. Phosphorus is found in high-protein foods. Foods with low levels of phosphorus include      - liquid nondairy creamer    - green beans    - popcorn    - unprocessed meats from a butcher    - lemon-lime soda    - root beer    - powdered iced tea and lemonade mixes    - rice and corn cereals    - egg whites    - sorbet    - Fluids. Early in CKD, a childs damaged kidneys may produce either too much or too little urine, which can lead to swelling or dehydration. As CKD progresses, children may need to limit fluid intake. The health care provider will tell the child and parents or guardians the goal for fluid intake.
                
More information is provided in the NIDDK health topics, Nutrition for Chronic Kidney Disease in Children and Kidney Failure: Eat Right to Feel Right on Hemodialysis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000142-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Facing the Challenges of Chronic Kidney Disease in Children ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Children with chronic kidney disease (CKD) may have a negative self-image and may have relationship problems with family members due to the stress of living with a chronic disease. The condition can lead to behavior problems and make participating in school and extracurricular activities more difficult.  - CKD can cause learning problems because the buildup of wastes in the body can slow down nerve and brain function. Children with CKD may have trouble concentrating and may develop language and motor skills more slowly than their peers.  - Parents and other adults can help children with CKD fit in at school, deal with low self-esteem, make friends, be physically active, and follow their treatment regimen. As children with CKD approach adulthood, they may need help with preparing to enter the workforce.  - School attendance is vital in helping children with CKD lead the best life possible.  - One way to help children feel empowered is to give them as much control and responsibility over their own care as possible:      - Children can learn more about their medications, including doses.    - Children on dialysis should be encouraged to take an active part in their treatments.    - Parents or guardians should allow children to participate in treatment decision making.    - Participating in regular classroom and extracurricular activities may help children improve their social skills. Summer camps and recreational programs for children with special needs can be a good place to make new friends.  - Parents or guardians may feel protective of children with CKD; however, they should not try to limit activities unless instructed to by a health care provider.   - Children with CKD may need to take multiple medications, eat a specific diet, and follow their health care providers orders to help control their disease. Many children have a hard time following the treatment regimen. Health care providers use the term nonadherence to describe the failure or refusal to take prescribed medications or follow a health care providers directions.  - Adherence can be improved with a combination of health education, motivational techniques, and behavioral skill methods.  - Many skilled professionals are available to ensure that children with CKD get the best possible care. The family may want to talk with a social worker, mental health professional, financial counselor, and dietitian. If a child reaches kidney failure, the medical staff at the dialysis center or transplantation clinic can provide help.  - For children with CKD, learning about nutrition is vital because their diet can affect how well their kidneys work. Parents or guardians should always consult with their childs health care team before making any dietary changes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
