<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000048" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/Diabetes/your-guide-diabetes/Pages/monitor.aspx">
<Focus>Monitor Your Diabetes</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0011860</CUI>
			<CUI>C0011849</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000048-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Monitor Your Diabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sometimes, no matter how hard you try to keep your blood glucose levels in your target range, they will be too high or too low. Blood glucose thats too high or too low can make you feel sick. If you try to control your high or low blood glucose and cant, you may become even sicker and need help. Talk with your doctor to learn how to handle these emergencies.
                
Learn about High Blood Glucose Levels
                
If your blood glucose levels stay above 180 for more than 1 to 2 hours, they may be too high. See the &quot;Daily Diabetes Record Page.&quot; High blood glucose, also called hyperglycemia, means you dont have enough insulin in your body. High blood glucose can happen if you
                
- miss taking your diabetes medicines  - eat too much  - dont get enough physical activity  - have an infection  - get sick  - are stressed  - take medicines that can cause high blood glucose
                
Be sure to tell your doctor about other medicines you take. When youre sick, be sure to check your blood glucose levels and keep taking your diabetes medicines. Read more about how to take care of yourself when youre sick in the section Take Care of Your Diabetes during Special Times or Events.
                
Signs that your blood glucose levels may be too high are the following:
                
- feeling thirsty  - feeling weak or tired  - headaches  - urinating often  - having trouble paying attention  - blurry vision  - yeast infections
                
Very high blood glucose may also make you feel sick to your stomach.
                
If your blood glucose levels are high much of the time, or if you have symptoms of high blood glucose, call your doctor. You may need a change in your healthy eating plan, physical activity plan, or medicines.
                
Learn about Low Blood Glucose Levels
                
If your blood glucose levels drop below 70, you have low blood glucose, also called hypoglycemia. Low blood glucose can come on fast and can be caused by
                
- taking too much diabetes medicine  - missing or delaying a meal  - being more physically active than usual  - drinking alcoholic beverages
                
Sometimes, medicines you take for other health problems can cause your blood glucose levels to drop.
                
Signs your blood glucose levels may be too low are the following:
                
- hunger  - dizziness or shakiness  - confusion  - being pale  - sweating more  - weakness  - anxiety or moodiness  - headaches  - a fast heartbeat
                
If your blood glucose levels drop lower, you could have severe hypoglycemia, where you pass out or have a seizure. A seizure occurs when cells in the brain release a rush of energy that can cause changes in behavior or muscle contractions. Some seizures are life threatening.
                
If you have any of these symptoms, check your blood glucose levels. If your blood glucose levels are less than 70, have one of the following right away:
                
- three or four glucose tablets  - one serving of glucose gelthe amount equal to 15 grams of carbohydrates  - 1/2 cup, or 4 ounces, of fruit juice  - 1/2 cup, or 4 ounces, of a regularnondietsoft drink  - 1 cup, or 8 ounces, of milk  - five or six pieces of hard candy  - 1 tablespoon of sugar, syrup, or honey
                
After 15 minutes, check your blood glucose levels again. Repeat these steps until your blood glucose levels are 70 or above. If it will be at least 1 hour before your next meal, eat a snack.
                
If you take diabetes medicines that can cause low blood glucose, always carry food for emergencies. You should also wear a medical identification bracelet or necklace that says you have diabetes.
                
If you take insulin, keep a prescription glucagon kit at home and at other places where you often go. A glucagon kit has a vial of glucagon, a syringe, and a needle to inject the glucagon. Given as a shot, the glucagon quickly raises blood glucose. If you have severe hypoglycemia, youll need someone to help bring your blood glucose levels back to normal by giving you a glucagon shot. Show your family, friends, and coworkers how to give you a glucagon shot when you have severe hypoglycemia. Someone should call 911 for help if a glucagon kit is not available.
                
Action Steps If You Take Insulin     - Tell your doctor if you have low blood glucose, especially at the same time of the day or night, several times in a row.   - Tell your doctor if youve passed out from low blood glucose.   - Ask your doctor about glucagon. Glucagon is a medicine that raises blood glucose.   - Show your family, friends, and coworkers how to give you a glucagon shot when you have severe hypoglycemia.   - When you have severe hypoglycemia, someone should call 911 for help if a glucagon shot is not available.
                

                
Action Steps If You Don&apos;t Take Insulin     - Tell your doctor if you have low blood glucose, especially at the same time of the day or night, several times in a row.   - Tell your doctor about other medicines you are taking.   - Ask your doctor whether your diabetes medicines might cause low blood glucose.
                
More information is provided in the NIDDK health topic, Hypoglycemia.
                

                
Go to Prevent Diabetes Problems
                
Return to Take Care of Your Diabetes Each Day
                

                
This content is provided as a service of the National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK), part of the National Institutes of Health. The NIDDK translates and disseminates research findings through its clearinghouses and education programs to increase knowledge and understanding about health and disease among patients, health professionals, and the public. Content produced by the NIDDK is carefully reviewed by NIDDK scientists and other experts.
                
The NIDDK would like to thank: Michael L. Parchman, M.D., M.P.H., F.A.A.F.P., MacColl Center for Health Care Innovation, Group Health Research Institute; Marion J. Franz, M.S., R.D., L.D., C.D.E., Minneapolis, Minnesota
                
This information is not copyrighted. The NIDDK encourages people to share this content freely.
                

                

                
February 2014</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
