<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000130" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/digestive-diseases/hirschsprung-disease/Pages/ez.aspx">
<Focus>What I need to know about Hirschsprung Disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0019569</CUI>
			<CUI>C2931876</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000130-1" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Hirschsprung Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hirschsprung* disease (HD) is a disease of the large intestine that causes severe constipation or intestinal obstruction. Constipation means stool moves through the intestines slower than usual. Bowel movements occur less often than normal and stools are difficult to pass. Some children with HD cant pass stool at all, which can result in the complete blockage of the intestines, a condition called intestinal obstruction. People with HD are born with it and are usually diagnosed when they are infants. Less severe cases are sometimes diagnosed when a child is older. An HD diagnosis in an adult is rare.
                
*See Pronunciation Guide for tips on how to say the words in bold type.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000130-2" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Hirschsprung Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The large intestine, which includes the colon and rectum, is the last part of the digestive tract. The large intestines main job is to absorb water and hold stool. The rectum connects the colon to the anus. Stool passes out of the body through the anus. At birth, the large intestine is about 2 feet long. An adults large intestine is about 5 feet long.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000130-3" qtype="causes">What causes What I need to know about Hirschsprung Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with HD have constipation because they lack nerve cells in a part or all of the large intestine. The nerve cells signal muscles in the large intestine to push stool toward the anus. Without a signal to push stool along, stool will remain in the large intestine.
                
How severe HD is depends on how much of the large intestine is affected. Short-segment HD means only the last part of the large intestine lacks nerve cells. Long-segment HD means most or all of the large intestine, and sometimes the last part of the small intestine, lacks nerve cells.
                
In a person with HD, stool moves through the large intestine until it reaches the part lacking nerve cells. At that point, the stool moves slowly or stops, causing an intestinal obstruction.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000130-4" qtype="causes">What causes What I need to know about Hirschsprung Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before birth, a childs nerve cells normally grow along the intestines in the direction of the anus. With HD, the nerve cells stop growing too soon. Why the nerve cells stop growing is unclear. Some HD is inherited, meaning it is passed from parent to child through genes. HD is not caused by anything a mother did while pregnant.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000130-5" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of What I need to know about Hirschsprung Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The main symptoms of HD are constipation or intestinal obstruction, usually appearing shortly after birth. Constipation in infants and children is common and usually comes and goes, but if your child has had ongoing constipation since birth, HD may be the problem.
                
Symptoms in Newborns
                
Newborns with HD almost always fail to have their first bowel movement within 48 hours after birth. Other symptoms include
                
- green or brown vomit  - explosive stools after a doctor inserts a finger into the rectum  - swelling of the belly, also known as the abdomen  - lots of gas  - bloody diarrhea
                

                
Symptoms in Toddlers and Older Children
                
Symptoms of HD in toddlers and older children include
                
- not being able to pass stools without laxatives or enemas. A laxative is medicine that loosens stool and increases bowel movements. An enema is performed by flushing water, or sometimes a mild soap solution, into the anus using a special wash bottle.  - swelling of the abdomen.  - lots of gas.  - bloody diarrhea.  - slow growth or development.  - lack of energy because of a shortage of red blood cells, called anemia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000130-6" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose What I need to know about Hirschsprung Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>HD is diagnosed based on symptoms and test results.
                
A doctor will perform a physical exam and ask questions about your childs bowel movements. HD is much less likely if parents can identify a time when their childs bowel habits were normal.
                
If HD is suspected, the doctor will do one or more tests.
                
X rays
                
An x ray is a black-and-white picture of the inside of the body. To make the large intestine show up better, the doctor may fill it with barium liquid. Barium liquid is inserted into the large intestine through the anus.
                
If HD is the problem, the last segment of the large intestine will look narrower than normal. Just before this narrow segment, the intestine will look bulged. The bulging is caused by blocked stool stretching the intestine.
                
Manometry
                
During manometry, the doctor inflates a small balloon inside the rectum. Normally, the rectal muscles will relax. If the muscles dont relax, HD may be the problem. This test is most often done in older children and adults.
                
Biopsy
                
Biopsy is the most accurate test for HD. The doctor removes a tiny piece of the large intestine and looks at it with a microscope. If nerve cells are missing, HD is the problem.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000130-7" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for What I need to know about Hirschsprung Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pull-through Procedure
                
HD is treated with surgery called a pull-through procedure. A surgeon removes the segment of the large intestine lacking nerve cells and connects the healthy segment to the anus. The pull-through procedure is usually done soon after diagnosis.
                
Ostomy surgery
                
An ostomy allows stool to leave the body through an opening in the abdomen. Although most children with HD do not need an ostomy, a child who has been very sick from HD may need an ostomy to get better before the pull-through procedure.
                
For ostomy surgery, the surgeon first takes out the diseased segment of the large intestine. The end of the healthy intestine is moved to an opening in the abdomen where a stoma is created. A stoma is created by rolling the intestines end back on itself, like a shirt cuff, and stitching it to the abdominal wall. An ostomy pouch is attached to the stoma and worn outside the body to collect stool. The pouch will need to be emptied several times each day.
                

                
If the surgeon removes the entire large intestine and connects the small intestine to the stoma, the surgery is called an ileostomy. If the surgeon leaves part of the large intestine and connects it to the stoma, the surgery is called a colostomy.
                
Later, during the pull-through procedure, the surgeon removes the stoma and closes the abdomen with stitches.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000130-10" qtype="considerations">What to do for What I need to know about Hirschsprung Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Hirschsprung disease (HD) is a disease of the large intestine that causes severe constipation or intestinal obstruction. People with HD are born with it.  - The large intestine, which includes the colon and rectum, is the last part of the digestive tract.  - The cause of HD is unclear. HD is not caused by anything a mother did while pregnant.  - The main symptoms of HD are constipation or intestinal obstruction, usually appearing shortly after birth.  - Newborns with HD almost always fail to have their first bowel movement within 48 hours after birth.  - HD is diagnosed based on symptoms and test results.  - HD is treated with surgery called a pull-through procedure.  - A child who has been very sick from HD may need an ostomy to get better before the pull-through procedure.  - Most children pass stool normally after the pull-through procedure.  - People with HD can suffer from an infection of the intestines, called enterocolitis, before or after surgery.  - If you have a child with HD, your chance of having more children with HD is greater.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
