<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000010" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/endocrine/multiple-endocrine-neoplasia-type-1/Pages/fact-sheet.aspx">
<Focus>Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia Type 1</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0025267</CUI>
			<CUI>C0014132</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000010-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia Type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>MEN1 is an inherited disorder that causes tumors in the endocrine glands and the duodenum, the first part of the small intestine. MEN1 is sometimes called multiple endocrine adenomatosis or Wermer&apos;s syndrome, after one of the first doctors to recognize it. MEN1 is rare, occurring in about one in 30,000 people.1 The disorder affects both sexes equally and shows no geographical, racial, or ethnic preferences.
                
Endocrine glands release hormones into the bloodstream. Hormones are powerful chemicals that travel through the blood, controlling and instructing the functions of various organs. Normally, the hormones released by endocrine glands are carefully balanced to meet the body&apos;s needs.
                
In people with MEN1, multiple endocrine glands form tumors and become hormonally overactive, often at the same time. The overactive glands may include the parathyroids, pancreas, or pituitary. Most people who develop overactivity of only one endocrine gland do not have MEN1.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000010-8" qtype="considerations">What to do for Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia Type 1 ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Multiple endocrine neoplasia type 1 (MEN1) is an inherited disorder that causes hormone-secreting tumors in the duodenum and the endocrine glands-most often the parathyroid, pancreas, and pituitary.  - Overactive parathyroid glands can lead to tiredness, weakness, muscle or bone pain, constipation, indigestion, kidney stones, or thinning of bones.  - Pancreatic and duodenal endocrine tumors called gastrinomas can cause dangerous stomach or intestinal ulcers.  - Pituitary tumors called prolactinomas can cause excessive production of breast milk or interfere with fertility in women or with sex drive and fertility in men.  - Although many tumors associated with MEN1 are benign, about half of people with MEN1 will eventually develop a cancerous tumor.  - MEN1 carriers can be detected through gene testing or other laboratory tests.  - MEN1 cannot be cured, but regular testing can detect the problems caused by MEN1 tumors many years before serious complications develop. Careful monitoring enables doctors to adjust an individual&apos;s treatment as needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
