<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000160" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/kidney-disease/medullary-sponge-kidney-msk/Pages/index.aspx">
<Focus>Medullary Sponge Kidney</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0022681</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000160-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Medullary Sponge Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>Medullary sponge kidney, also known as Cacchi-Ricci disease, is a birth defect where changes occur in the tubules, or tiny tubes, inside a fetus kidneys.
                
In a normal kidney, urine flows through these tubules as the kidney is being formed during a fetus growth. In medullary sponge kidney, tiny, fluid-filled sacs called cysts form in the tubules within the medullathe inner part of the kidneycreating a spongelike appearance. The cysts keep urine from flowing freely through the tubules.
                
Symptoms of medullary sponge kidney do not usually appear until the teenage years or the 20s. Medullary sponge kidney can affect one or both kidneys.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000160-2" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Medullary Sponge Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications of medullary sponge kidney include
                
- hematuria, or blood in the urine  - kidney stones  - urinary tract infections (UTIs)
                
Medullary sponge kidney rarely leads to more serious problems, such as chronic kidney disease or kidney failure.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000160-3" qtype="causes">What causes Medullary Sponge Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>Scientists do not fully understand the cause of medullary sponge kidney or why cysts form in the tubules during fetal development. Even though medullary sponge kidney is present at birth, most cases do not appear to be inherited.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000160-4" qtype="frequency">How many people are affected by Medullary Sponge Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>Medullary sponge kidney affects about one person per 5,000 people in the United States. Researchers have reported that 12 to 20 percent of people who develop calcium-based kidney stones have medullary sponge kidney1.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000160-6" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Medullary Sponge Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many people with medullary sponge kidney have no symptoms. The first sign that a person has medullary sponge kidney is usually a UTI or a kidney stone. UTIs and kidney stones share many of the same signs and symptoms:
                
- burning or painful urination  - pain in the back, lower abdomen, or groin  - cloudy, dark, or bloody urine  - foul-smelling urine  - fever and chills  - vomiting
                
People who experience these symptoms should see or call a health care provider as soon as possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000160-7" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Medullary Sponge Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>A health care provider diagnoses medullary sponge kidney based on
                
- a medical and family history  - a physical exam  - imaging studies
                
Medical and Family History
                
Taking a medical and family history can help diagnose medullary sponge kidney. A health care provider will suspect medullary sponge kidney when a person has repeated UTIs or kidney stones.
                
Physical Exam
                
No physical signs are usually present in a patient with medullary sponge kidney, except for blood in the urine. Health care providers usually confirm a diagnosis of medullary sponge kidney with imaging studies.
                
Imaging Studies
                
Imaging is the medical term for tests that use different methods to see bones, tissues, and organs inside the body. Health care providers commonly choose one or more of three imaging techniques to diagnose medullary sponge kidney:
                
- intravenous pyelogram  - computerized tomography (CT) scan  - ultrasound
                
A radiologista doctor who specializes in medical imaginginterprets the images from these studies, and patients do not need anesthesia.
                
Intravenous Pyelogram
                
In an intravenous pyelogram, a health care provider injects a special dye, called contrast medium, into a vein in the patients arm. The contrast medium travels through the body to the kidneys. The kidneys excrete the contrast medium into urine, which makes the urine visible on an x-ray. An x-ray technician performs this procedure at a health care providers office, an outpatient center, or a hospital. An intravenous pyelogram can show any blockage in the urinary tract, and the cysts show up as clusters of light.
                
Computerized Tomography Scans
                
Computerized tomography scans use a combination of x-rays and computer technology to create images. For a CT scan, a health care provider may give the patient a solution to drink and an injection of contrast medium. CT scans require the patient to lie on a table that slides into a tunnel-shaped device where the x-rays are taken. An x-ray technician performs the procedure in an outpatient center or a hospital. CT scans can show expanded or stretched tubules.
                
Ultrasound
                
Ultrasound uses a device, called a transducer, that bounces safe, painless sound waves off organs to create an image of their structure. A specially trained technician performs the procedure in a health care providers office, an outpatient center, or a hospital. Ultrasound can show kidney stones and calcium deposits within the kidney.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000160-8" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Medullary Sponge Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>Scientists have not discovered a way to reverse medullary sponge kidney. Once a health care provider is sure a person has medullary sponge kidney, treatment focuses on
                
- curing an existing UTI  - removing any kidney stones
                
Curing an Existing Urinary Tract Infection
                
To treat a UTI, the health care provider may prescribe a medication called an antibiotic that kills bacteria. The choice of medication and length of treatment depend on the persons medical history and the type of bacteria causing the infection. More information is provided in the NIDDK health topic, Urinary Tract Infections in Adults.
                
Removing Kidney Stones
                
Treatment for kidney stones usually depends on their size and what they are made of, as well as whether they are causing pain or obstructing the urinary tract. Kidney stones may be treated by a general practitioner or by a urologista doctor who specializes in the urinary tract.
                
Small stones usually pass through the urinary tract without treatment. Still, the person may need pain medication and should drink lots of liquids to help move the stone along. Pain control may consist of oral or intravenous (IV) medication, depending on the duration and severity of the pain. People may need IV fluids if they become dehydrated from vomiting or an inability to drink.
                
A person with a larger stone, or one that blocks urine flow and causes great pain, may need more urgent treatment, such as
                
- shock wave lithotripsy. A machine called a lithotripter is used to break up the kidney stone into smaller pieces to pass more easily through the urinary tract. The patient may need local or general anesthesia.  - ureteroscopy. A ureteroscopea long, tubelike instrument with an eyepieceis used to find and retrieve the stone with a small basket or to break the stone up with laser energy. Local or general anesthesia may be required.  - percutaneous nephrolithotomy. In this procedure, a wire-thin viewing instrument, called a nephroscope, is used to locate and remove the stones. During the procedure, which requires general anesthesia, a tube is inserted directly into the kidney through a small incision in the patients back.
                
More information is provided in the NIDDK health topic, Kidney Stones in Adults.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000160-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Medullary Sponge Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>Scientists have not yet found a way to prevent medullary sponge kidney. However, health care providers can recommend medications and dietary changes to prevent future UTIs and kidney stones.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000160-10" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Medullary Sponge Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>Health care providers may prescribe certain medications to prevent UTIs and kidney stones:
                
- A person with medullary sponge kidney may need to continue taking a low-dose antibiotic to prevent recurrent infections.  - Medications that reduce calcium in the urine may help prevent calcium kidney stones. These medications may include      - potassium citrate    - thiazide</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000160-11" qtype="considerations">What to do for Medullary Sponge Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>The following changes in diet may help prevent UTIs and kidney stone formation:
                
- Drinking plenty of water and other liquids can help flush bacteria from the urinary tract and dilute urine so kidney stones cannot form. A person should drink enough liquid to produce about 2 to 2.5 quarts of urine every day.3  - Reducing sodium intake, mostly from salt, may help prevent kidney stones. Diets high in sodium can increase the excretion of calcium into the urine and thus increase the chance of calciumcontaining kidney stones forming.  - Foods rich in animal proteins such as meat, eggs, and fish can increase the chance of uric acid stones and calcium stones forming. People who form stones should limit their meat consumption to 6 to 8 ounces a day.4  - People who are more likely to develop calcium oxalate stones should include 1,000 milligrams of calcium in their diet every day. Adults older than 50 years should consume 1,200 milligrams of calcium daily.3 Calcium in the digestive tract binds to oxalate from food and keeps it from entering the blood and the urinary tract, where it can form stones.
                
People with medullary sponge kidney should talk with their health care provider or a dietitian before making any dietary changes. A dietitian can help a person plan healthy meals.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000160-12" qtype="considerations">What to do for Medullary Sponge Kidney ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Medullary sponge kidney, also known as Cacchi-Ricci disease, is a birth defect where changes occur in the tubules, or tiny tubes, inside a fetus kidneys.  - Symptoms of medullary sponge kidney do not usually appear until the teenage years or the 20s. Medullary sponge kidney can affect one or both kidneys.  - Complications of medullary sponge kidney include      - hematuria, or blood in the urine    - kidney stones    - urinary tract infections (UTIs)    - Many people with medullary sponge kidney have no symptoms. The first sign that a person has medullary sponge kidney is usually a UTI or a kidney stone. UTIs and kidney stones share many of the same signs and symptoms:      - burning or painful urination    - pain in the back, lower abdomen, or groin    - cloudy, dark, or bloody urine    - foul-smelling urine    - fever and chills    - vomiting    - Health care providers commonly choose one or more of three imaging techniques to diagnose medullary sponge kidney:      - intravenous pyelogram    - computerized tomography (CT) scan    - ultrasound    - Scientists have not discovered a way to reverse medullary sponge kidney. Once a health care provider is sure a person has medullary sponge kidney, treatment focuses on      - curing an existing UTI    - removing any kidney stones    - Scientists have not yet found a way to prevent medullary sponge kidney. However, health care providers can recommend medications and dietary changes to prevent future UTIs and kidney stones.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
