<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000179" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/kidney-disease/kidney-failure-choosing-a-treatment-thats-right-for-you/Pages/ez.aspx">
<Focus>What I need to know about Kidney Failure and How Its Treated</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0035078</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000179-1" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Kidney Failure and How Its Treated ?</Question>
			<Answer>You have two kidneys. The kidneys are shaped like beans. Each kidney is about the size of a fist. They are located just below your ribcage, one on each side of your spine. Your kidneys filter your blood. Each kidney is made of 1 million little filters. During every minute of every day, these filters take out waste materials that can hurt you. They also take out extra fluid from your blood. The wastes and extra fluid make urine. The urine flows from your kidneys to your bladder through tubes called ureters.The bladder stores urine until you urinate. Then, urine leaves the body through a tube called the urethra.
                
*See the Pronunciation Guide for tips on how to say the the words in bold type.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000179-2" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Kidney Failure and How Its Treated ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kidney failure means your kidneys no longer filter your blood well enough to keep you healthy. Failing kidneys do a poor job of removing wastes and extra fluid from your blood. Wastes and extra fluid begin to build up. The buildup of wastes can make you sick. You may have the following symptoms:
                
- ankle, face, or belly swelling  - stomach sickness  - throwing up  - loss of appetite  - loss of sense of taste  - feeling tired  - weakness  - confusion  - headaches</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000179-3" qtype="causes">What causes What I need to know about Kidney Failure and How Its Treated ?</Question>
			<Answer>Diabetes and high blood pressure are the most common causes of kidney failure. Other factors include heart and blood vessel disease and a family history of kidney failure. African Americans, Hispanics/Latinos, and American Indians are more likely to have kidney failure.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000179-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for What I need to know about Kidney Failure and How Its Treated ?</Question>
			<Answer>The treatments for kidney failure are
                
- hemodialysis  - peritoneal dialysis  - a kidney transplant  - conservative management</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000179-5" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Kidney Failure and How Its Treated ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hemodialysis is a treatment for kidney failure that is done in a center several times per week. Some people learn to do hemodialysis in their homes. Hemodialysis uses a machine to filter your blood when your kidneys are too sick to filter any more. With hemodialysis, your blood is filtered outside of your body. Unfiltered blood is removed from the body and flows to the dialyzer to be cleaned. Filtered blood flows back to the body. First, a dialysis nurse places two needles into your arm. A pump on the hemodialysis machine draws your blood through one of the needles into a tube. The tube takes the blood to a filter, called a dialyzer. Inside the dialyzer, your blood flows through thin fibers that are like straws. The wastes and extra fluid leave the blood through tiny holes in the fibers. Then, a different tube carries the filtered blood back to your body through the second needle. The hemodialysis machine throws out the wastes and extra fluid, just like how your body makes urine. Hemodialysis does not make the kidneys better. However, it may help you feel better by filtering your blood when your kidneys fail.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000179-6" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Kidney Failure and How Its Treated ?</Question>
			<Answer>Peritoneal dialysis uses the lining of your belly to filter your blood inside your body. You can do peritoneal dialysis at home because it uses your body to filter. A doctor will place a soft tube called a catheter in your belly a few weeks before you start treatment. The catheter stays in your belly permanently.
                
The catheter lets you put a kind of salty water from a plastic bag into your belly. Then, you can move around and go about your day. While the salty water is inside your belly, it soaks up wastes and extra fluid from your body. After a few hours, you drain the salty water from your belly into a drain bag. The salty water removes wastes and extra fluid from your body. The salty water can be thrown away into a toilet or tub. Then you start over with a fresh bag of salty water. You will empty and fill your belly four to six times a day.
                
The salty water is always in your belly soaking up wastes and extra fluid. Peritoneal dialysis does not make the kidneys better. However, it may help you feel better by filtering your blood when your kidneys fail.
                

                
Is dialysis a cure for kidney failure?   No. Hemodialysis and peritoneal dialysis help you feel better and live longer; however, they do not cure kidney failure. Although people with kidney failure are now living longer than ever, over the years kidney disease can cause problems such as heart disease, bone disease, arthritis, nerve damage, infertility, and malnutrition. These problems wont go away with dialysis; however, doctors now have new and better ways to prevent or treat them. You should discuss these problems and their treatments with your doctor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000179-8" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Kidney Failure and How Its Treated ?</Question>
			<Answer>A kidney transplant places a healthy kidney from another person into your body. The kidney may come from someone who has just died. Your doctor will place your name on a waiting list for a kidney. A family member or friend might be able to give you a kidney. Then you dont have to wait.
                
Once it is placed inside your body, the new kidney takes over filtering your blood. The damaged kidneys usually stay where they are. The new kidney is placed in the front-lower abdomen, on one side of the bladder. Your body normally attacks anything that shouldnt be there, such as bacteria. The body will think the new kidney shouldnt be there. You will take medicines called immunosuppressants to keep your body from attacking the new kidney.
                
More information is provided in the NIDDK health topics:
                
- Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Hemodialysis  - Home Hemodialysis  - Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Peritoneal Dialysis  - Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Transplantation</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000179-9" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for What I need to know about Kidney Failure and How Its Treated ?</Question>
			<Answer>Conservative management means your doctors take care of you without dialysis or a transplant. The doctors may give you medicines that make you feel more comfortable. You can have conservative management in your home. You may want to go to a hospice, a special place where you receive nursing care. Some people choose conservative management when dialysis or a transplant would not help them live longer or would make them suffer longer. Without dialysis or a transplant, you may live for a few weeks or several months.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000179-10" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for What I need to know about Kidney Failure and How Its Treated ?</Question>
			<Answer>If you have kidney failure, learn about the treatments and think about which one best fits you. Talk with people who are on hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis. Ask what is good and bad about each treatment. If you make a choice and find you dont like it, talk with your doctor about trying something else. Ask your doctor about the transplant waiting list and the medicines needed after a transplant. Talk with people who have had kidney transplants and ask how it has changed their lives.
                
If you plan to keep working, think about which treatment choice would make working easier. If spending time with family and friends means a lot to you, ask which treatment gives you the most free time. Find out which treatment will give you the best chance to be healthy and live longer.
                
If you are thinking about conservative management, you may wish to speak with your family, friends, doctor, or mental health counselor as you decide.
                
You can take control of your care by talking with your doctor. You may need time to get used to your new treatment. Kidney failure can make your life harder. Treatments can help improve your life.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000179-12" qtype="considerations">What to do for What I need to know about Kidney Failure and How Its Treated ?</Question>
			<Answer>Eating healthy foods can help you keep up your energy and strength. All dialysis and transplant centers have a dietitian. The dietitian helps people with kidney failure learn about healthy food choices. You should talk with your centers dietitian to make a meal plan.
                
The best diet for you will depend on which kidney failure treatment you choose after talking with your doctor.
                
- Hemodialysis      - Limit how much liquid and water you drink. Fluid can build up in your body between hemodialysis sessions. Also, many foods contain water. The extra fluid in your body can cause swelling and high blood pressure. Extra fluid in your body makes your heart work harder.
                
-      - Limit sodium, or salt. Watch out for sodium in frozen foods and prepared meals. You can also find sodium in canned foods, hot dogs, and fast food. Sodium makes you thirsty, which makes you drink more water and other liquids than you should.    - Read more in the National Kidney Disease Education Program (NKDEP) fact sheet Sodium.    - Limit potassium. Potassium is found in many fruits and vegetables such as potatoes, tomatoes, oranges, and bananas. Too much potassium can make your heart beat unevenly. Hemodialysis does not remove potassium from your body well.    - Read more in the NKDEP fact sheet Potassium.    - Eat protein-rich foods such as meat, fish, and eggs. Hemodialysis removes protein from your body.    - Read more in the NKDEP fact sheet Protein.    - Limit phosphorus. Phosphorus helps your bones, blood vessels, and muscles work.    - However, too much phosphorus can make your bones weak. Limiting phosphorus can be hard. Foods that contain phosphorus, such as meat and milk, also contain protein that you need. You should be careful to eat enough protein, yet not so much that you get too much phosphorus. You can avoid other foods that contain phosphorus, such as cola, tea, beans, and nuts.    - Read more in the NKDEP fact sheet Phosphorus.    - Find healthy ways to add calories to your diet. Calories are found in all foods and give your body energy. Many people on hemodialysis do not have a good appetite and do not get enough calories. Vegetable oils are good sources of calories. Vegetable oils include olive oil, canola oil, and safflower oil. Use them on breads, rice, and noodles. Hard candy, sugar, honey, jam, and jelly provide calories and energy. However, if you have diabetes, speak with your doctor or dietitian before eating extra sweets.    - More information about nutrition for people who are on hemodialysis is provided in the NIDDK health topic, Eat Right to Feel Right on Hemodialysis.    - Peritoneal dialysis      - Drink as much water and other liquids as you need. If you are holding too much fluid or too little fluid, your doctor needs to know.    - Limit sodium to control your thirst and help prevent heart problems. You can use spices other than salt to flavor your food.
                
-      - You may need to eat more potassium-rich foods. Peritoneal dialysis removes potassium from your body. Talk with your doctor or dietitian about the right amount of potassium for you.    - Eat protein-rich foods. Peritoneal dialysis removes even more protein from your body than hemodialysis.    - Limit phosphorus to keep your bones strong.    - You may need to limit your calorie intake. The salty water also contains some sugar. Your body absorbs the sugar, which can cause you to gain weight.    - Kidney transplant      - Limit sodium to help prevent heart problems.    - You should be able to eat normal amounts of phosphorus and potassium. You may need to adjust the amounts if blood tests show a problem.
                
-      - Eat protein-rich foods to repair muscle breakdown and protect against infection.    - You may need to limit your calories. The medicines you take can make you gain weight.    - Conservative management      - Limit protein to prevent the buildup of wastes in your blood.
                
You may have other needs and limits, depending on how well your treatments work.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="13">
			<Question qid="0000179-13" qtype="considerations">What to do for What I need to know about Kidney Failure and How Its Treated ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Kidney failure means your kidneys no longer filter your blood well enough to keep you healthy.  - The treatments for kidney failure are      - hemodialysis    - peritoneal dialysis    - a kidney transplant    - conservative management    - Hemodialysis uses a machine to filter your blood when your kidneys are too sick to filter any more.  - Peritoneal dialysis uses the lining of your belly to filter your blood inside your body.  - A kidney transplant places a healthy kidney from another person into your body.  - Conservative management means your doctors take care of you without dialysis or a transplant. The doctors may give you medicines that make you feel more comfortable.  - All dialysis and transplant centers have a dietitian. The dietitian helps people with kidney failure learn about healthy food choices.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="14">
			<Question qid="0000179-14" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Kidney Failure and How Its Treated ?</Question>
			<Answer>You and your doctor will work together to choose a treatment that&apos;s best for you. The publications of the NIDDK Kidney Failure Series can help you learn about the specific issues you will face.
                
Booklets
                
- What I need to know about Kidney Failure and How its Treated  - Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Hemodialysis  - Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Peritoneal Dialysis  - Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Kidney Transplantation  - Kidney Failure: Eat Right to Feel Right on Hemodialysis
                
Fact Sheets
                
- Kidney Failure: What to Expect  - Vascular Access for Hemodialysis  - Hemodialysis Dose and Adequacy  - Peritoneal Dialysis Dose and Adequacy  - Amyloidosis and Kidney Disease  - Anemia in Chronic Kidney Disease  - Chronic Kidney Disease-Mineral and Bone Disorder  - Financial Help for Treatment of Kidney Failure
                
Learning as much as you can about your treatment will help make you an important member of your health care team.
                

                

                
This content is provided as a service of the National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases (NIDDK), part of the National Institutes of Health. The NIDDK translates and disseminates research findings through its clearinghouses and education programs to increase knowledge and understanding about health and disease among patients, health professionals, and the public. Content produced by the NIDDK is carefully reviewed by NIDDK scientists and other experts.
                
The NIDDK would like to thank: Neil R. Powe, M.D., M.P.H., M.B.A., University of California, San Francisco; Delphine Tuot, M.D.C.M., M.A.S., University of California, San Francisco; Vicki McClelland and Brian Testerman, both of the Free Medical Clinic of Northern Shenandoah Valley in Winchester, VA
                
This information is not copyrighted. The NIDDK encourages people to share this content freely.
                

                

                
September 2014</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
