<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000196" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/liver-disease/hepatitis-c/Pages/ez.aspx">
<Focus>What I need to know about Hepatitis C</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0019196</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000196-1" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Hepatitis C ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hepatitis* C is a virus, or infection, that causes liver disease and inflammation of the liver. Viruses can cause sickness. For example, the flu is caused by a virus. People can pass viruses to each other.
                
Inflammation is swelling that occurs when tissues of the body become injured or infected. Inflammation can cause organs to not work properly.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000196-2" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Hepatitis C ?</Question>
			<Answer>The liver is an organ that does many important things. You cannot live without a liver.
                
*See the Pronunciation Guide for tips on how to say the words in bold type.
                
The liver
                
- removes harmful chemicals from your blood  - fights infection  - helps digest food  - stores nutrients and vitamins  - stores energy</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000196-3" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for What I need to know about Hepatitis C? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anyone can get hepatitis C, but those more likely to are people who
                
- were born to a mother with hepatitis C  - are in contact with blood or infected needles at work  - have had more than one sex partner in the last 6 months or have a history of sexually transmitted disease  - are on kidney dialysisthe process of filtering wastes and extra water from the body by means other than the kidneys  - are infected with HIV  - have injected illegal drugs  - have had tattoos or body piercings  - work or live in a prison  - had a blood transfusion or organ transplant before July 1992  - have hemophilia and received clotting factor before 1987
                
Also, men who have sex with men are more likely to get hepatitis C.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000196-5" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of What I need to know about Hepatitis C ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most people do not have any symptoms until the hepatitis C virus causes liver damage, which can take 10 or more years to happen. Others may have one or more of the following symptoms:
                
- feeling tired  - muscle soreness  - upset stomach  - stomach pain  - fever  - loss of appetite  - diarrhea  - dark-yellow urine  - light-colored stools  - yellowish eyes and skin, called jaundice
                
When symptoms of hepatitis C occur, they can begin 1 to 3 months after coming into contact with the virus. See a doctor right away if you or a child in your care has symptoms of hepatitis C.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000196-6" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Hepatitis C ?</Question>
			<Answer>Acute hepatitis C is a short-term infection with the hepatitis C virus. Symptoms can last up to 6 months. The infection sometimes clears up because your body is able to fight off the infection and get rid of the virus.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000196-7" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Hepatitis C ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chronic hepatitis C is a long-lasting infection with the hepatitis C virus. Chronic hepatitis C occurs when the body cant get rid of the hepatitis C virus. Most hepatitis C infections become chronic.
                
Without treatment, chronic hepatitis C can cause liver cancer or severe liver damage that leads to liver failure. Liver failure occurs when the liver stops working properly.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000196-8" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose What I need to know about Hepatitis C ?</Question>
			<Answer>A blood test will show if you have hepatitis C. Blood tests are done at a doctors office or outpatient facility. A blood sample is taken using a needle inserted into a vein in your arm or hand. The blood sample is sent to a lab to test for hepatitis C.
                
If you are at higher risk of getting hepatitis C, get tested. Many people with hepatitis C do not know they are infected.
                
Your doctor may suggest getting a liver biopsy if chronic hepatitis C is suspected. A liver biopsy is a test to take a small piece of your liver to look for liver damage. The doctor may ask you to stop taking certain medicines before the test. You may be asked to fast for 8 hours before the test.
                
During the test, you lie on a table with your right hand resting above your head. Medicine is applied to numb the area where the biopsy needle will be inserted. If needed, sedatives and pain medicine are also given. The doctor uses a needle to take a small piece of liver tissue. After the test, you must lie on your right side for up to 2 hours. You will stay 2 to 4 hours after the test before being sent home.
                
A liver biopsy is performed at a hospital or outpatient center by a doctor. The liver sample is sent to a special lab where a doctor looks at the tissue with a microscope and sends a report to your doctor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000196-9" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for What I need to know about Hepatitis C ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hepatitis C is usually not treated unless it becomes chronic. Chronic hepatitis C is treated with medicines that slow or stop the virus from damaging the liver. Your doctor will closely watch your symptoms and schedule regular blood tests to make sure the treatment is working.
                
Medicines for Chronic Hepatitis C
                
Chronic hepatitis C is most often treated with a medicine combination that attacks the hepatitis C virus. Treatment may last from 24 to 48 weeks.
                
Today, newer treatments with medicine for chronic hepatitis C are appearing quickly. Talk with your doctor if you have questions about treatment.
                
Talk with your doctor before taking other prescription medicines and over-the-counter medicines.
                

                
Liver Transplant
                
A liver transplant may be necessary if chronic hepatitis C causes severe liver damage that leads to liver failure. Symptoms of severe liver damage include the symptoms of hepatitis C and
                
- generalized itching  - a longer than usual amount of time for bleeding to stop  - easy bruising  - swollen stomach or ankles  - spiderlike blood vessels, called spider angiomas, that develop on the skin
                
Liver transplant is surgery to remove a diseased or injured liver and replace it with a healthy one from another person, called a donor. If your doctors tell you that you need a transplant, you should talk with them about the long-term demands of living with a liver transplant.
                
A team of surgeonsdoctors who specialize in surgeryperforms a liver transplant in a hospital. You will learn how to take care of yourself after you go home and about the medicines youll need to take to protect your new liver. You will continue to take medicines because hepatitis C may come back after surgery.
                
Testing for Liver Cancer
                
Having hepatitis C increases your risk for liver cancer, so your doctor may suggest an ultrasound test of the liver every 6 to 12 months. Finding cancer early makes it more treatable. Ultrasound is a machine that uses sound waves to create a picture of your liver. Ultrasound is performed at a hospital or radiology center by a specially trained technician. The image, called a sonogram, can show the livers size and the presence of cancerous tumors.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000196-12" qtype="considerations">What to do for What I need to know about Hepatitis C ?</Question>
			<Answer>If you have chronic hepatitis C, you should do things to take care of yourself, including eating a healthy diet. Avoid drinking alcohol, which can harm the liver. Talk with your doctor before taking vitamins and other supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="13">
			<Question qid="0000196-13" qtype="considerations">What to do for What I need to know about Hepatitis C ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Hepatitis C is a virus, or infection, that causes inflammation of the liver.  - Anyone can get hepatitis C, but some people are more likely to than others.  - You could get hepatitis C through contact with an infected persons blood.  - Most people do not have any symptoms until the hepatitis C virus causes liver damage, which can take 10 or more years to happen.  - See a doctor right away if you or a child in your care has symptoms of hepatitis C.  - Acute hepatitis C is a short-term infection with the hepatitis C virus.  - Chronic hepatitis C is a long-lasting infection with the hepatitis C virus. Chronic hepatitis C occurs when the body cant get rid of the hepatitis C virus.  - A blood test will show if you have hepatitis C.  - If you are at higher risk of getting hepatitis C, get tested. Many people with hepatitis C do not know they are infected.  - Hepatitis C usually is not treated unless it becomes chronic. Chronic hepatitis C is treated with medicines that slow or stop the virus from damaging the liver.  - Tell your doctor and your dentist if you have hepatitis C.  - See your doctor right away if you think you have been in contact with the hepatitis C virus. Early diagnosis and treatment of chronic hepatitis C can help prevent liver damage.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
