<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000044" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/Diabetes/insulin-resistance-prediabetes/Pages/index.aspx">
<Focus>Insulin Resistance and Prediabetes</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0362046</CUI>
			<CUI>C0271650</CUI>
			<CUI>C0021655</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000044-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Insulin Resistance and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Insulin is a hormone made in the pancreas, an organ located behind the stomach. The pancreas contains clusters of cells called islets. Beta cells within the islets make insulin and release it into the blood.
                
Insulin plays a major role in metabolismthe way the body uses digested food for energy. The digestive tract breaks down carbohydratessugars and starches found in many foodsinto glucose. Glucose is a form of sugar that enters the bloodstream. With the help of insulin, cells throughout the body absorb glucose and use it for energy.
                
Insulin&apos;s Role in Blood Glucose Control
                
When blood glucose levels rise after a meal, the pancreas releases insulin into the blood. Insulin and glucose then travel in the blood to cells throughout the body.
                
- Insulin helps muscle, fat, and liver cells absorb glucose from the bloodstream, lowering blood glucose levels.  - Insulin stimulates the liver and muscle tissue to store excess glucose. The stored form of glucose is called glycogen.  - Insulin also lowers blood glucose levels by reducing glucose production in the liver.
                
In a healthy person, these functions allow blood glucose and insulin levels to remain in the normal range.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000044-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Insulin Resistance and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Insulin resistance is a condition in which the body produces insulin but does not use it effectively. When people have insulin resistance, glucose builds up in the blood instead of being absorbed by the cells, leading to type 2 diabetes or prediabetes.
                
Most people with insulin resistance don&apos;t know they have it for many yearsuntil they develop type 2 diabetes, a serious, lifelong disease. The good news is that if people learn they have insulin resistance early on, they can often prevent or delay diabetes by making changes to their lifestyle.
                
Insulin resistance can lead to a variety of serious health disorders. The section &quot;What is metabolic syndrome?&quot; provides more information about other health disorders linked to insulin resistance.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000044-4" qtype="causes">What causes Insulin Resistance and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Although the exact causes of insulin resistance are not completely understood, scientists think the major contributors to insulin resistance are excess weight and physical inactivity.
                
Excess Weight
                
Some experts believe obesity, especially excess fat around the waist, is a primary cause of insulin resistance. Scientists used to think that fat tissue functioned solely as energy storage. However, studies have shown that belly fat produces hormones and other substances that can cause serious health problems such as insulin resistance, high blood pressure, imbalanced cholesterol, and cardiovascular disease (CVD).
                
Belly fat plays a part in developing chronic, or long-lasting, inflammation in the body. Chronic inflammation can damage the body over time, without any signs or symptoms. Scientists have found that complex interactions in fat tissue draw immune cells to the area and trigger low-level chronic inflammation. This inflammation can contribute to the development of insulin resistance, type 2 diabetes, and CVD. Studies show that losing the weight can reduce insulin resistance and prevent or delay type 2 diabetes.
                
Physical Inactivity
                
Many studies have shown that physical inactivity is associated with insulin resistance, often leading to type 2 diabetes. In the body, more glucose is used by muscle than other tissues. Normally, active muscles burn their stored glucose for energy and refill their reserves with glucose taken from the bloodstream, keeping blood glucose levels in balance.
                
Studies show that after exercising, muscles become more sensitive to insulin, reversing insulin resistance and lowering blood glucose levels. Exercise also helps muscles absorb more glucose without the need for insulin. The more muscle a body has, the more glucose it can burn to control blood glucose levels.
                
Other Causes
                
Other causes of insulin resistance may include ethnicity; certain diseases; hormones; steroid use; some medications; older age; sleep problems, especially sleep apnea; and cigarette smoking.
                

                
Does sleep matter?   Yes. Studies show that untreated sleep problems, especially sleep apnea, can increase the risk of obesity, insulin resistance, and type 2 diabetes. Night shift workers may also be at increased risk for these problems. Sleep apnea is a common disorder in which a person&apos;s breathing is interrupted during sleep. People may often move out of deep sleep and into light sleep when their breathing pauses or becomes shallow. This results in poor sleep quality that causes problem sleepiness, or excessive tiredness, during the day.   Many people aren&apos;t aware of their symptoms and aren&apos;t diagnosed. People who think they might have sleep problems should talk with their health care provider.   More information about sleep problems is available from the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute at http://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/resources/sleep.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000044-6" qtype="information">What is (are) Insulin Resistance and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Prediabetes is a condition in which blood glucose or A1C levelswhich reflect average blood glucose levelsare higher than normal but not high enough for a diagnosis of diabetes. Prediabetes is becoming more common in the United States. The U.S. Department of Health and Human Services estimates that at least 86 million U.S. adults ages 20 or older had prediabetes in 2012.1 People with prediabetes are at increased risk of developing type 2 diabetes and CVD, which can lead to heart attack or stroke.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000044-8" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Insulin Resistance and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Insulin resistance and prediabetes usually have no symptoms. People may have one or both conditions for several years without knowing they have them. Even without symptoms, health care providers can identify people at high risk by their physical characteristics, also known as risk factors. The section &quot;Who should be tested for prediabetes?&quot; lists these risk factors.
                
People with a severe form of insulin resistance may have dark patches of skin, usually on the back of the neck. Sometimes people have a dark ring around their neck. Dark patches may also appear on elbows, knees, knuckles, and armpits. This condition is called acanthosis nigricans.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000044-11" qtype="information">What is (are) Insulin Resistance and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Metabolic syndrome, also called insulin resistance syndrome, is a group of traits and medical conditions linked to overweight and obesity that puts people at risk for both CVD and type 2 diabetes. Metabolic syndrome is defined* as the presence of any three of the following2:
                
- large waist sizewaist measurement of 40 inches or more for men and 35 inches or more for women  - high triglycerides in the bloodtriglyceride level of 150 milligrams per deciliter (mg/dL) or above, or taking medication for elevated triglyceride level  - abnormal levels of cholesterol in the bloodHDL, or good, cholesterol level below 40 mg/dL for men and below 50 mg/dL for women, or taking medication for low HDL  - high blood pressureblood pressure level of 130/85 or above, or taking medication for elevated blood pressure  - higher than normal blood glucose levelsfasting blood glucose level of 100 mg/dL or above, or taking medication for elevated blood glucose
                
In addition to type 2 diabetes, metabolic syndrome has been linked to the following health disorders:
                
- obesity  - CVD  - PCOS  - nonalcoholic fatty liver disease  - chronic kidney disease
                
However, not everyone with these disorders has insulin resistance, and some people may have insulin resistance without getting these disorders.
                
People who are obese or who have metabolic syndrome, insulin resistance, type 2 diabetes, or prediabetes often also have low-level inflammation throughout the body and blood clotting defects that increase the risk of developing blood clots in the arteries. These conditions contribute to increased risk for CVD.
                
*Similar definitions have been developed by the World Health Organization and the American Association of Clinical Endocrinologists.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000044-12" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Insulin Resistance and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Health care providers use blood tests to determine whether a person has prediabetes, but they do not usually test specifically for insulin resistance. Insulin resistance can be assessed by measuring the level of insulin in the blood.
                
However, the test that most accurately measures insulin resistance, called the euglycemic clamp, is too costly and complicated to be used in most health care providers&apos; offices. The clamp is a research tool used by scientists to learn more about glucose metabolism. Research has shown that if blood tests indicate prediabetes, insulin resistance most likely is present.
                
Blood Tests for Prediabetes
                
All blood tests involve drawing blood at a health care provider&apos;s office or commercial facility and sending the sample to a lab for analysis. Lab analysis of blood is needed to ensure test results are accurate. Glucose measuring devices used in a health care provider&apos;s office, such as finger-stick devices, are not accurate enough for diagnosis but may be used as a quick indicator of high blood glucose.
                
Prediabetes can be detected with one of the following blood tests:
                
- the A1C test  - the fasting plasma glucose (FPG) test  - the oral glucose tolerance test (OGTT)
                
A1C test. Sometimes called hemoglobin A1c, HbA1c, or glycohemoglobin test, this test reflects average blood glucose levels over the past 3 months. This test is the most reliable test for prediabetes, but it is not as sensitive as the other tests. In some individuals, it may miss prediabetes that could be caught by glucose tests.
                
Although some health care providers can quickly measure A1C in their office, that type of measurementcalled a point-of-care testis not considered reliable for diagnosis. For diagnosis of prediabetes, the A1C test should be analyzed in a laboratory using a method that is certified by the NGSP.
                
The A1C test can be unreliable for diagnosing prediabetes in people with certain conditions that are known to interfere with the results. Interference should be suspected when A1C results seem very different from the results of a blood glucose test. People of African, Mediterranean, or Southeast Asian descent, or people with family members with sickle cell anemia or a thalassemia, are particularly at risk of interference. People in these groups may have a less common type of hemoglobin, known as a hemoglobin variant, that can interfere with some A1C tests.
                
An A1C of 5.7 to 6.4 percent indicates prediabetes.
                
More information about the A1C test is provided in the NIDDK health topic, The A1C Test and Diabetes.
                
Fasting plasma glucose test. This test measures blood glucose in people who have not eaten anything for at least 8 hours. This test is most reliable when done in the morning. Prediabetes found with this test is called IFG.
                
Fasting glucose levels of 100 to 125 mg/dL indicate prediabetes.
                
OGTT. This test measures blood glucose after people have not eaten for at least 8 hours and 2 hours after they drink a sweet liquid provided by a health care provider or laboratory. Prediabetes found with this test is called IGT.
                
A blood glucose level between 140 and 199 mg/dL indicates prediabetes.
                
The following table lists the blood test levels for a diagnosis of prediabetes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="16">
			<Question qid="0000044-16" qtype="considerations">What to do for Insulin Resistance and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Adopting healthy eating habits can help people lose a modest amount of weight and reverse insulin resistance. Experts encourage people to slowly adopt healthy eating habits that they can maintain, rather than trying extreme weight-loss solutions. People may need to get help from a dietitian or join a weight-loss program for support.
                
In general, people should lose weight by choosing healthy foods, controlling portions, eating less fat, and increasing physical activity. People are better able to lose weight and keep it off when they learn how to adapt their favorite foods to a healthy eating plan.
                
The DASH (Dietary Approaches to Stop Hypertension) eating plan, developed by the NIH, has been shown to be effective in decreasing insulin resistance when combined with weight loss and physical activity. More information on DASH is available at www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/health-topics/topics/dash.
                
The U.S. Dietary Guidelines for Americans also offers healthy eating advice and tools for changing eating habits at www.choosemyplate.gov.
                
Dietary Supplements
                
Vitamin D studies show a link between people&apos;s ability to maintain healthy blood glucose levels and having enough vitamin D in their blood. However, studies to determine the proper vitamin D levels for preventing diabetes are ongoing; no special recommendations have been made about vitamin D levels or supplements for people with prediabetes.
                
Currently, the Institute of Medicine (IOM), the agency that recommends supplementation levels based on current science, provides the following guidelines for daily vitamin D intake:
                
- People ages 1 to 70 years may require 600 International Units (IUs).  - People ages 71 and older may require as much as 800 IUs.
                
The IOM also recommended that no more than 4,000 IUs of vitamin D be taken per day.
                
To help ensure coordinated and safe care, people should discuss use of complementary and alternative medicine practices, including the use of dietary supplements, with their health care provider.
                
More information about using dietary supplements to help with diabetes is provided in the NIDDK health topic, Complementary and Alternative Medical Therapies for Diabetes.
                

                
Physical Activity
                
Regular physical activity tackles several risk factors at once. Regular physical activity helps the body use insulin properly.
                
Regular physical activity also helps a person
                
- lose weight  - control blood glucose levels  - control blood pressure  - control cholesterol levels
                
People in the DPP who were physically active for 30 minutes a day, 5 days a week, reduced their risk of type 2 diabetes. Many chose brisk walking as their physical activity.
                
Most people should aim for at least 30 minutes of exercise most days of the week. For best results, people should do both aerobic activities, which use large muscle groups and make the heart beat faster, and muscle strengthening activities.
                
Aerobic activities include brisk walking, climbing stairs, swimming, dancing, and other activities that increase the heart rate.
                
Muscle strengthening activities include lifting weights and doing sit-ups or push-ups.
                
People who haven&apos;t been physically active recently should talk with their health care provider about which activities are best for them and have a checkup before starting an exercise program.
                
Not Smoking
                
Those who smoke should quit. A health care provider can help people find ways to quit smoking. Studies show that people who get help have a better chance of quitting.
                
For more information about how to reverse insulin resistance and prediabetes with diet and increased physical activity, see the following National Diabetes Education Program publications at www.yourdiabetesinfo.org:    - Get Real! You Don&apos;t Have to Knock Yourself Out to Prevent Diabetes!   - More Than 50 Ways to Prevent Diabetes   - Small Steps. Big Rewards. Your Game Plan to Prevent Type 2 Diabetes.
                
Medication
                
The medication metformin is recommended for treatment of some individuals at very high risk of developing type 2 diabetes. In the DPP, metformin was shown to be most effective in preventing or delaying the development of type 2 diabetes in younger, heavier people with prediabetes. In general, metformin is recommend for those who are younger than age 60 and have
                
- combined IGT and IFG  - A1C above 6 percent  - low HDL cholesterol  - elevated triglycerides  - a parent or sibling with diabetes  - a BMI of at least 35
                
Metformin also lowers the risk of diabetes in women who have had gestational diabetes. People at high risk should ask their health care provider if they should take metformin to prevent type 2 diabetes.
                
Several medications have been shown to reduce type 2 diabetes risk to varying degrees, but the only medication recommended by the ADA for type 2 diabetes prevention is metformin. Other medications that have delayed diabetes have side effects or haven&apos;t shown long-lasting benefits. No medication, including metformin, is approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration to treat insulin resistance or prediabetes or to prevent type 2 diabetes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="17">
			<Question qid="0000044-17" qtype="considerations">What to do for Insulin Resistance and Prediabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Insulin is a hormone that helps cells throughout the body absorb glucose and use it for energy. Insulin resistance is a condition in which the body produces insulin but does not use it effectively.  - Insulin resistance increases the risk of developing type 2 diabetes and prediabetes.  - The major contributors to insulin resistance are excess weight, especially around the waist, and physical inactivity.  - Prediabetes is a condition in which blood glucose or A1C levelswhich reflect average blood glucose levelsare higher than normal but not high enough for a diagnosis of diabetes.  - The Diabetes Prevention Program (DPP) study and its follow-up study, the Diabetes Prevention Program Outcomes Study (DPPOS), confirmed that people with prediabetes can often prevent or delay diabetes if they lose a modest amount of weight by cutting fat and calorie intake and increasing physical activity.  - By losing weight and being more physically active, people can reverse insulin resistance and prediabetes, thus preventing or delaying type 2 diabetes.  - People with insulin resistance and prediabetes can decrease their risk for diabetes by eating a healthy diet and reaching and maintaining a healthy weight, increasing physical activity, not smoking, and taking medication.  - The DPP showed the diabetes medication metformin to be most effective in preventing or delaying the development of type 2 diabetes in younger and heavier people with prediabetes and women who have had gestational diabetes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
