<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000013" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/endocrine/pregnancy-and-thyroid-disease/Pages/fact-sheet.aspx">
<Focus>Pregnancy and Thyroid Disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2186538</CUI>
			<CUI>C0040128</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000013-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pregnancy and Thyroid Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Thyroid disease is a disorder that affects the thyroid gland. Sometimes the body produces too much or too little thyroid hormone. Thyroid hormones regulate metabolismthe way the body uses energyand affect nearly every organ in the body. Too much thyroid hormone is called hyperthyroidism and can cause many of the bodys functions to speed up. Too little thyroid hormone is called hypothyroidism and can cause many of the bodys functions to slow down.
                
Thyroid hormone plays a critical role during pregnancy both in the development of a healthy baby and in maintaining the health of the mother.
                
Women with thyroid problems can have a healthy pregnancy and protect their fetuses health by learning about pregnancys effect on the thyroid, keeping current on their thyroid function testing, and taking the required medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000013-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Pregnancy and Thyroid Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The thyroid is a 2-inch-long, butterfly-shaped gland weighing less than 1 ounce. Located in the front of the neck below the larynx, or voice box, it has two lobes, one on either side of the windpipe. The thyroid is one of the glands that make up the endocrine system. The glands of the endocrine system produce, store, and release hormones into the bloodstream. The hormones then travel through the body and direct the activity of the bodys cells.
                
The thyroid gland makes two thyroid hormones, triiodothyronine (T3) and thyroxine (T4). T3 is the active hormone and is made from T4. Thyroid hormones affect metabolism, brain development, breathing, heart and nervous system functions, body temperature, muscle strength, skin dryness, menstrual cycles, weight, and cholesterol levels.
                
Thyroid hormone production is regulated by thyroid-stimulating hormone (TSH), which is made by the pituitary gland in the brain. When thyroid hormone levels in the blood are low, the pituitary releases more TSH. When thyroid hormone levels are high, the pituitary responds by decreasing TSH production.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000013-6" qtype="considerations">What to do for Pregnancy and Thyroid Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>During pregnancy, the body requires higher amounts of some nutrients to support the health of the mother and growing baby. Experts recommend pregnant women maintain a balanced diet and take a prenatal multivitamin and mineral supplement containing iodine to receive most nutrients necessary for thyroid health. More information about diet and nutrition during pregnancy is provided by the National Agricultural Library available at www.choosemyplate.gov/nutritional-needs-during-pregnancy.
                
Dietary Supplements
                
Because the thyroid uses iodine to make thyroid hormone, iodine is an important mineral for a mother during pregnancy. During pregnancy, the baby gets iodine from the mothers diet. Women need more iodine when they are pregnantabout 250 micrograms a day. In the United States, about 7 percent of pregnant women may not get enough iodine in their diet or through prenatal vitamins.3 Choosing iodized saltsalt supplemented with iodineover plain salt and prenatal vitamins containing iodine will ensure this need is met.
                
However, people with autoimmune thyroid disease may be sensitive to harmful side effects from iodine. Taking iodine drops or eating foods containing large amounts of iodinesuch as seaweed, dulse, or kelpmay cause or worsen hyperthyroidism and hypothyroidism. More information about iodine is provided by the National Library of Medicine in the fact sheet, Iodine in diet.
                
To help ensure coordinated and safe care, people should discuss their use of dietary supplements with their health care provider. Tips for talking with health care providers are available at the National Center for Complementary and Integrative Health&apos;s Time to Talk campaign.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000013-8" qtype="considerations">What to do for Pregnancy and Thyroid Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Thyroid disease is a disorder that results when the thyroid gland produces more or less thyroid hormone than the body needs.  - Pregnancy causes normal changes in thyroid function but can also lead to thyroid disease.  - Uncontrolled hyperthyroidism during pregnancy can lead to serious health problems in the mother and the unborn baby.  - During pregnancy, mild hyperthyroidism does not require treatment. More severe hyperthyroidism is treated with antithyroid medications, which act by interfering with thyroid hormone production.  - Uncontrolled hypothyroidism during pregnancy can lead to serious health problems in the mother and can affect the unborn babys growth and brain development.  - Hypothyroidism during pregnancy is treated with synthetic thyroid hormone, thyroxine (T4).  - Postpartum thyroiditisinflammation of the thyroid glandcauses a brief period of hyperthyroidism, often followed by hypothyroidism that usually goes away within a year. Sometimes the hypothyroidism is permanent.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
