<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000054" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/Diabetes/prevent-diabetes-problems/Pages/index.aspx">
<Focus>Prevent diabetes problems: Keep your diabetes under control</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0011860</CUI>
			<CUI>C0011849</CUI>
			<CUI>C2062378</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000054-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Prevent diabetes problems: Keep your diabetes under control ?</Question>
			<Answer>Diabetes problems are health problems that can happen when you have diabetes. If your diabetes is not under control, you will have too much glucose*, also called sugar, in your blood. Having too much glucose in your blood for a long time can affect many important parts of your body, such as your
                
- blood vessels and heart  - nerves  - kidneys  - mouth  - eyes  - feet
                
You can do a lot to prevent or slow down these health problems if you keep your diabetes under control.
                
This chart shows the body parts that can be affected by diabetes and the resulting health problems you may have.
                
Affected Body Part    Resulting Health Problems You May Have          Blood vessels and heart             - Heart disease      - Heart attack      - Stroke      - High blood pressure      - Poor blood circulation, or flow, throughout your body            Nerves             - Pain, tingling, weakness, or numbness in your hands, arms, feet, or legs      - Problems with your bladder, digestion, having sex, and keeping your heartbeats and blood pressure steady            Kidneys             - Protein loss through your urine      - Buildup of wastes and fluid in your blood            Mouth             - Gum disease and loss of teeth      - Dry mouth      - Thrush, or the growth of too much fungus in the mouth            Eyes             - Loss of vision and blindness            Feet             - Sores      - Infections      - Amputation
                
*See the Pronunciation Guide for tips on how to say the the words in bold type.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000054-6" qtype="information">What is (are) Prevent diabetes problems: Keep your diabetes under control ?</Question>
			<Answer>The A1C test, also called the hemoglobin A1C test, HbA1C, or glycohemoglobin test, is a blood test that reflects the average level of glucose in your blood during the past 3 months. Your A1C test result is given in percents. Your doctor might use the A1C test to help diagnose your diabetes. Your doctor will draw a sample of your blood in the office or send you to a lab to have a sample of your blood drawn for the test. After being diagnosed with diabetes, you should have the A1C test at least twice a year.
                
Your A1C result plus your record of blood glucose numbers show whether your blood glucose is under control.
                
- If your A1C result is too high, you may need to change your diabetes care plan. Your health care team can help you decide what part of your plan to change. For instance, you might need to change your meal plan, your diabetes medicines, or your physical activity plan.  - If your A1C result is on target, then your diabetes treatment plan is working. The lower your A1C is, the lower your chance of having diabetes problems.
                
This chart shows the A1C goals for different types of people with diabetes.
                
Types of People    A1C Goals          Most people with diabetes    below 7%        Women with diabetes who want to get pregnant or who are pregnant    below 6%
                
A1C goals can also depend on
                
- how long you have had diabetes  - whether or not you have other health problems
                
Ask your doctor what goal is right for you.
                

                
This chart shows how your A1C result may match up to your average blood glucose number.
                
What Your A1C Result Means          My A1C Result    My Average Blood Glucose Number        6%    135        7%    170        8%    205        9%    240        10%    275        11%    310        12%    345</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000054-9" qtype="considerations">What to do for Prevent diabetes problems: Keep your diabetes under control ?</Question>
			<Answer>Following a healthy eating plan is a key step in living with diabetes and preventing diabetes problems. Your health care team will help you make a healthy eating plan.
                
More information is provided in the NIDDK health topic, What I need to know about Eating and Diabetes or call 18008608747.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000054-12" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Prevent diabetes problems: Keep your diabetes under control ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can take steps each day to prevent diabetes problems.
                
Steps          Healthy Eating                     - Follow the healthy eating plan that you and your doctor or dietitian have made.      - Learn what to eat to keep your blood glucose levels under control.      - Make wise food choices to help you feel good every day and to lose weight if needed.            Blood Glucose                     - Check your blood glucose every day.      - Each time you check your blood glucose, write the number in a record book to share with your health care team.      - Treat low blood glucose quickly.            Physical Activity                     - Even small amounts of physical activity help manage diabetes. Aim for 30 to 60 minutes of physical activity most days of the week. Children and adolescents with type 2 diabetes who are 10 to 17 years old should aim for 60 minutes of activity every day.      - Not all physical activity has to take place at the same time.      - Do aerobic activities, such as brisk walking, which use your large muscles to make your heart beat faster. The large muscles are those of the upper and lower arms and legs and those that control head, shoulder, and hip movements.      - Do activities to strengthen muscles and bone, such as lifting weights or sit-ups. Aim for two times a week.      - Stretch to increase your flexibility, lower stress, and help prevent muscle soreness after physical activity.      - Increase daily activity by decreasing time spent watching TV or at the computer. Children and adolescents should limit screen time not related to school to less than 2 hours per day. Limiting screen time can help you meet your physical activity goal.      - Always talk with your doctor before you start a new physical activity program.            Medicines                     - Take your medicines as directed, including insulin if ordered by your doctor.            Feet                     - Check your feet every day for cuts, blisters, sores, swelling, redness, or sore toenails.            Mouth                     - Brush and floss your teeth every day.            Blood Pressure                     - Control your blood pressure and cholesterol.            Smoking                     - Dont smoke.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="14">
			<Question qid="0000054-14" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Prevent diabetes problems: Keep your diabetes under control ?</Question>
			<Answer>This chart lists important tests, exams, and vaccines to get at least once or twice a year.
                
Tests, Exams, and Vaccines to Get at Least Once or Twice a Year    Make Sure to          A1C test             - Have this blood test at least twice a year. Your result will tell you what your average blood glucose level was for the past 3 months.            Cholesterol test             - Get a blood test to check your              - total cholesterol        - LDL        - HDL        - triglycerides                  Kidney tests             - Once a year, get a urine test to check for protein.      - At least once a year, get a blood test to check for creatinine, a waste product healthy kidneys remove from the body.            Eye exam             - See an eye doctor once a year for a complete eye exam that includes using drops in your eyes to dilate your pupils.      - If you are pregnant, have a complete eye exam in your first 3 months of pregnancy. Have another complete eye exam 1 year after your baby is born.            Dental exam             - See your dentist twice a year for a cleaning and checkup.            Flu vaccine             - Get a flu vaccine each year.            Pneumonia vaccine             - Get this vaccine if you are younger than 64.      - If youre older than 64 and your vaccine was more than 5 years ago, get another one.            Hepatitis B vaccine             - Get this vaccine if youre younger than 60 and you have not already had the vaccine.      - Prevent exposure to Hepatitis B by not sharing blood glucose monitors or other diabetes equipment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
