<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000207" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/urologic-disease/peyronies-disease/Pages/facts.aspx">
<Focus>Peyronie's Disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0030848</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000207-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Peyronie's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Peyronies disease is a disorder in which scar tissue, called a plaque, forms in the penisthe male organ used for urination and sex. The plaque builds up inside the tissues of a thick, elastic membrane called the tunica albuginea. The most common area for the plaque is on the top or bottom of the penis. As the plaque builds up, the penis will curve or bend, which can cause painful erections. Curves in the penis can make sexual intercourse painful, difficult, or impossible. Peyronies disease begins with inflammation, or swelling, which can become a hard scar.
                
The plaque that develops in Peyronies disease is not the same plaque that can develop in a persons arteries. The plaque seen in Peyronies disease is benign, or noncancerous, and is not a tumor. Peyronies disease is not contagious or caused by any known transmittable disease.
                
Early researchers thought Peyronies disease was a form of impotence, now called erectile dysfunction (ED). ED happens when a man is unable to achieve or keep an erection firm enough for sexual intercourse. Some men with Peyronies disease may have ED. Usually men with Peyronies disease are referred to a urologista doctor who specializes in sexual and urinary problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000207-3" qtype="causes">What causes Peyronie's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Medical experts do not know the exact cause of Peyronies disease. Many believe that Peyronies disease may be the result of
                
- acute injury to the penis  - chronic, or repeated, injury to the penis  - autoimmune diseasea disorder in which the bodys immune system attacks the bodys own cells and organs
                
Injury to the Penis
                
Medical experts believe that hitting or bending the penis may injure the tissues inside. A man may injure the penis during sex, athletic activity, or an accident. Injury ruptures blood vessels, which leads to bleeding and swelling inside the layers of the tunica albuginea. Swelling inside the penis will block blood flow through the layers of tissue inside the penis. When the blood cant flow normally, clots can form and trap immune system cells. As the injury heals, the immune system cells may release substances that lead to the formation of too much scar tissue. The scar tissue builds up and forms a plaque inside the penis. The plaque reduces the elasticity of tissues and flexibility of the penis during erection, leading to curvature. The plaque may further harden because of calcificationthe process in which calcium builds up in body tissue.
                
Autoimmune Disease
                
Some medical experts believe that Peyronies disease may be part of an autoimmune disease. Normally, the immune system is the bodys way of protecting itself from infection by identifying and destroying bacteria, viruses, and other potentially harmful foreign substances. Men who have autoimmune diseases may develop Peyronies disease when the immune system attacks cells in the penis. This can lead to inflammation in the penis and can cause scarring. Medical experts do not know what causes autoimmune diseases. Some of the autoimmune diseases associated with Peyronies disease affect connective tissues. Connective tissue is specialized tissue that supports, joins, or separates different types of tissues and organs of the body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000207-4" qtype="frequency">How many people are affected by Peyronie's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Researchers estimate that Peyronies disease may affect 1 to 23 percent of men between 40 and 70 years of age.1 However, the actual occurrence of Peyronies disease may be higher due to mens embarrassment and health care providers limited reporting.1 The disease is rare in young men, although it has been reported in men in their 30s.1 The chance of developing Peyronies disease increases with age.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000207-6" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Peyronie's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The signs and symptoms of Peyronies disease may include
                
- hard lumps on one or more sides of the penis  - pain during sexual intercourse or during an erection  - a curve in the penis either with or without an erection  - narrowing or shortening of the penis  - ED
                
Symptoms of Peyronies disease range from mild to severe. Symptoms may develop slowly or appear quickly. In many cases, the pain decreases over time, although the curve in the penis may remain. In milder cases, symptoms may go away without causing a permanent curve.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000207-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Peyronie's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications of Peyronies disease may include
                
- the inability to have sexual intercourse  - ED  - anxiety, or stress, about sexual abilities or the appearance of the penis  - stress on a relationship with a sexual partner  - problems fathering a child because intercourse is difficult</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000207-8" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Peyronie's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>A urologist diagnoses Peyronies disease based on
                
- a medical and family history  - a physical exam  - imaging tests
                
Medical and Family History
                
Taking a medical and family history is one of the first things a urologist may do to help diagnose Peyronies disease. He or she will ask the man to provide a medical and family history, which may include the following questions:
                
- What is the mans ability to have an erection?  - What are the problems with sexual intercourse?  - When did the symptoms begin?  - What is the family medical history?  - What medications is the man taking?  - What other symptoms is the man experiencing?  - What other medical conditions does the man have?
                
Physical Exam
                
A physical exam may help diagnose Peyronies disease. During a physical exam, a urologist usually examines the mans body, including the penis.
                
A urologist can usually feel the plaque in the penis with or without an erection. Sometimes the urologist will need to examine the penis during an erection. The urologist will give the man an injectable medication to cause an erection.
                
Imaging Tests
                
To help pinpoint the location of the plaque buildup inside the penis, a urologist may perform
                
- ultrasound of the penis  - an x ray of the penis
                
For both tests, a specially trained technician performs the procedure in a health care providers office, an outpatient center, or a hospital, and a radiologista doctor who specializes in medical imaginginterprets the images. The patient does not need anesthesia.
                
Ultrasound. Ultrasound uses a device, called a transducer, that bounces safe, painless sound waves off organs to create an image of their structure.
                
X ray. An x ray is a picture created by using radiation and recorded on film or on a computer. The amount of radiation used is small. The man will lie on a table or stand during the x ray, and the technician may ask the man to change positions for additional pictures.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000207-9" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Peyronie's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>A urologist may treat Peyronies disease with nonsurgical treatments or surgery.
                
The goal of treatment is to reduce pain and restore and maintain the ability to have intercourse. Men with small plaques, minimal penile curvature, no pain, and satisfactory sexual function may not need treatment until symptoms get worse. Peyronies disease often resolves on its own without treatment.
                
A urologist may recommend changes in a mans lifestyle to reduce the risk of ED associated with Peyronies disease.
                
Nonsurgical Treatments
                
Nonsurgical treatments include medications and medical therapies.
                
Medications. A urologist may prescribe medications aimed at decreasing a mans penile curvature, plaque size, and inflammation. A man may take prescribed medications to treat Peyronies disease orallyby mouthor a urologist may inject medications directly into the plaque. Verapamil is one type of topical medication that a man may apply to the skin over the plaque.
                
- Oral medications. Oral medications may include      - vitamin E    - potassium para-aminobenzoate (Potaba)    - tamoxifen    - colchicine    - acetyl-L-carnitine    - pentoxifylline    - Injections. Medications injected directly into plaques may include      - verapamil    - interferon alpha 2b    - steroids    - collagenase (Xiaflex)
                
To date, collagenase is the first and only medication specifically approved for Peyronies disease.
                
Medical therapies. A urologist may use medical therapies to break up scar tissue and decrease plaque size and curvature. Therapies to break up scar tissue may include
                
- high-intensity, focused ultrasound directed at the plaque  - radiation therapyhigh-energy rays, such as x rays, aimed at the plaque  - shockwave therapyfocused, low-intensity electroshock waves directed at the plaque
                
A urologist may use iontophoresispainless, low-level electric current that delivers medications through the skin over the plaqueto decrease plaque size and curvature.
                
A urologist may use mechanical traction and vacuum devices aimed at stretching or bending the penis to reduce curvature.
                
Surgery
                
A urologist may recommend surgery to remove plaque or help straighten the penis during an erection. Medical experts recommend surgery for long-term cases when
                
- symptoms have not improved  - erections, intercourse, or both are painful  - the curve or bend in the penis does not allow the man to have sexual intercourse
                
Some men may develop complications after surgery, and sometimes surgery does not correct the effects of Peyronies diseasesuch as shortening of the penis. Some surgical methods can cause shortening of the penis. Medical experts suggest waiting 1 year or more from the onset of symptoms before having surgery because the course of Peyronies disease is different in each man.
                
A urologist may recommend the following surgeries:
                
- grafting. A urologist will cut or remove the plaque and attach a patch of skin, a vein, or material made from animal organs in its place. This procedure may straighten the penis and restore some lost length from Peyronies disease. However, some men may experience numbness of the penis and ED after the procedure.  - plication. A urologist will remove or pinch a piece of the tunica albuginea from the side of the penis opposite the plaque, which helps to straighten the penis. This procedure is less likely to cause numbness or ED. Plication cannot restore length or girth of the penis and may cause shortening of the penis.  - device implantation. A urologist implants a device into the penis that can cause an erection and help straighten it during an erection. Penile implants may be considered if a man has both Peyronies disease and ED. In some cases, an implant alone will straighten the penis adequately. If the implant alone does not straighten the penis, a urologist may combine implantation with one of the other two surgeries. Once a man has an implant, he must use the device to have an erection.
                
A urologist performs these surgeries in a hospital.
                
Lifestyle Changes
                
A man can make healthy lifestyle changes to reduce the chance of ED associated with Peyronies disease by
                
- quitting smoking  - reducing alcohol consumption  - exercising regularly  - avoiding illegal drugs
                
More information is provided in the NIDDK health topic, Erectile Dysfunction.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000207-10" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Peyronie's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Researchers do not know how to prevent Peyronies disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000207-11" qtype="considerations">What to do for Peyronie's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Researchers have not found that eating, diet, and nutrition play a role in causing or preventing Peyronies disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000207-12" qtype="considerations">What to do for Peyronie's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Peyronies disease is a disorder in which scar tissue, called a plaque, forms in the penisthe male organ used for urination and sex.  - Medical experts do not know the exact cause of Peyronies disease. Many believe that Peyronies disease may be the result of      - acute injury to the penis    - chronic, or repeated, injury to the penis    - autoimmune diseasea disorder in which the bodys immune system attacks the bodys own cells and organs    - The following factors may increase a mans chance of developing Peyronies disease:      - vigorous sexual or nonsexual activities that cause microscopic injury to the penis    - certain connective tissue and autoimmune disorders    - a family history of Peyronies disease    - aging    - The signs and symptoms of Peyronies disease may include      - hard lumps on one or more sides of the penis    - pain during sexual intercourse or during an erection    - a curve in the penis either with or without an erection    - narrowing or shortening of the penis    - erectile dysfunction (ED)    - Complications of Peyronies disease may include      - the inability to have sexual intercourse    - ED    - anxiety, or stress, about sexual abilities or the appearance of the penis    - stress on a relationship with a sexual partner    - problems fathering a child because intercourse is difficult    - A urologist diagnoses Peyronies disease based on      - a medical and family history    - a physical exam    - imaging tests    - A urologist may treat Peyronies disease with nonsurgical treatments or surgery.  - Researchers do not know how to prevent Peyronies disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
