<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000128" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/digestive-diseases/diverticular-disease/Pages/ez.aspx">
<Focus>What I need to know about Diverticular Disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1510475</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T190</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000128-1" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Diverticular Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Diverticular* disease affects the colon. The colon is part of the large intestine that removes waste from your body. Diverticular disease is made up of two conditions: diverticulosis and diverticulitis. Diverticulosis occurs when pouches, called diverticula, form in the colon. These pouches bulge out like weak spots in a tire. Diverticulitis occurs if the pouches become inflamed.
                
*See the Pronunciation Guide for tips on how to say the words in bold type.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000128-2" qtype="causes">What causes What I need to know about Diverticular Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Doctors are not sure what causes diverticular disease. Many think a diet low in fiber is the main cause. Fiber is a part of food that your body cannot digest. It is found in many fruits and vegetables. Fiber stays in the colon and absorbs water, which makes bowel movements easier to pass. Diets low in fiber may cause constipation, which occurs when stools are hard and difficult to pass. Constipation causes your muscles to strain when you pass stool. Straining may cause diverticula to form in the colon. If stool or bacteria get caught in the pouches, diverticulitis can occur.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000128-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of What I need to know about Diverticular Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The symptoms for diverticulosis and diverticulitis are different.
                
Diverticulosis. Many people don&apos;t have symptoms, but some people have cramping, bloating, and constipation. Some people also have bleeding, inflammation, and fistulas. If you are bleeding, bright red blood will pass through your rectum. The rectum is the end of the colon that connects to the anus. The rectum and anus are part of the gastrointestinal tract, which is the passage that food goes through. Rectal bleeding is usually painless, but it can be dangerous. You should see a doctor right away.
                
Diverticulitis. People with diverticulitis can have many symptoms. Often pain is felt in the lower part of the abdomen. If you have diverticulitis, you may have fevers, feel sick to your stomach, vomit, or have a change in your bowel habits.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000128-5" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for What I need to know about Diverticular Disease? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many people get diverticular disease. Starting at age 40, the chance of getting it increases about every 10 years. About half of people between the ages of 60 and 80 have diverticular disease. Almost everyone over 80 has it.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000128-7" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for What I need to know about Diverticular Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment for diverticular disease depends on how serious the problem is and whether you are suffering from diverticulosis or diverticulitis. Most people get better by changing their diet. If you have rectal bleeding, you need to go to the hospital so a doctor can find the part of your colon that is bleeding. The doctor may use a special drug that makes the bleeding stop. The doctor may also decide to operate and remove the part of the colon that is bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000128-8" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for What I need to know about Diverticular Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Eating high-fiber foods can help relieve symptoms. Sometimes mild pain medications also help.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000128-9" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for What I need to know about Diverticular Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>A doctor may prescribe antibiotics and recommend following a liquid diet. Most people get better with this treatment. Some people may need surgery and other treatments.
                
- Surgery. Serious problems from diverticulitis are treated with surgery. Surgeons can clean the abdomen after infections and remove bleeding pouches and fistulas.  - Colon resection. If you get diverticulitis many times, your doctor might suggest taking out the part of the colon with diverticula. The healthy sections can be joined together. With the diverticula gone, you may avoid other infections.  - Emergency surgery. If you have severe problems, you may need emergency surgery to clear the infection and remove part of the colon. Later, a second surgery rejoins the healthy sections of the colon. The colon is separated for a brief time between surgeries, because rejoining the colon during the first surgery is not always safe. A temporary colostomy is needed between the two surgeries. A colostomy is an opening made on the abdomen where a plastic bag is connected to collect stool after food is digested. The surgeon makes the opening, called a stoma, and connects it to the end of the colon.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000128-10" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Diverticular Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Eat a high-fiber diet to help prevent problems. Talk to your doctor about using fiber products like Benefiber, Citrucel, or Metamucil. Daily use can help you get the fiber you need if you do not get it through your diet.
                
Ask your doctor about which food choices are right for you.
                
Eating foods high in fiber is simple and can help reduce diverticular disease symptoms and problems.
                
Try eating more of the following:
                
- Fruit. Raw apples, peaches, pears, and tangerines.  - Vegetables. Fresh broccoli, squash, carrots, and brussels sprouts.  - Starchy vegetables. Potatoes, baked beans, kidney beans, and lima beans.  - Grains. Whole-wheat bread, brown rice, bran flake cereal, and oatmeal.
                
Talk with your doctor about making diet changes. Learn what to eat and how to put more of these high-fiber foods in your diet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000128-11" qtype="considerations">What to do for What I need to know about Diverticular Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Diverticular disease is more common in people as they grow older.  - A low-fiber diet is the most likely cause of the disease.  - Most people are treated with a high-fiber diet and pain medication.  - Add whole grain foods, high-fiber fruits, and vegetables to your diet.  - Contact a doctor if you notice symptoms such as fever, chills, nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, rectal bleeding, or change in bowel habits.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
