<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000131" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/digestive-diseases/lactose-intolerance/Pages/ez.aspx">
<Focus>What I need to know about Lactose Intolerance</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0022951</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000131-1" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Lactose Intolerance ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lactose
                
*
                
intestine
                
lactase
                
,
                
enzyme
                
*See the Pronunciation Guide for tips on how to say the words in bold type.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000131-2" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Lactose Intolerance ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lactose intolerance means you have symptoms such as bloating, diarrhea, and gas after you have milk or milk products.
                
If your small intestine does not produce much lactase, you cannot break down much lactose. Lactose that does not break down goes to your colon. The colon is an organ that absorbs water from stool and changes it from a liquid to a solid form. In your colon, bacteria that normally live in the colon break down the lactose and create fluid and gas, causing you to have symptoms.
                
The causes of low lactase in your small intestine can include the following:
                
- In some people, the small intestine makes less lactase starting at about age 2, which may lead to symptoms of lactose intolerance. Other people start to have symptoms later, when they are teenagers or adults.  - Infection, disease, or other problems that harm the small intestine can cause low lactase levels. Low lactase levels can cause you to become lactose intolerant until your small intestine heals.  - Being born early may cause babies to be lactose intolerant for a short time after they are born.  - In a rare form of lactose intolerance, the small intestine produces little or no lactase enzyme from birth.
                
Not all people with low lactase levels have symptoms. If you have symptoms, you are lactose intolerant.
                
Most people who are lactose intolerant can have some milk or milk products and not have symptoms. The amount of lactose that causes symptoms is different from person to person.
                

                
People sometimes confuse lactose intolerance with a milk allergy. While lactose intolerance is a digestive problem, a milk allergy is a reaction by the bodys immune system to one or more milk proteins. If you have a milk allergy, having even a small amount of milk or milk product can be life threatening. A milk allergy most commonly occurs in the first year of life. Lactose intolerance occurs more often during the teen years or adulthood.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000131-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of What I need to know about Lactose Intolerance ?</Question>
			<Answer>Common symptoms of lactose intolerance include
                
- bloating, a feeling of fullness or swelling, in your belly  - pain in your belly  - diarrhea  - gas  - nausea
                
You may feel symptoms 30 minutes to 2 hours after you have milk or milk products. You may have mild or severe symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000131-9" qtype="considerations">What to do for What I need to know about Lactose Intolerance ?</Question>
			<Answer>Talk with your doctor about your dietary plan. A dietary plan can help you manage the symptoms of lactose intolerance and get enough nutrients. If you have a child with lactose intolerance, follow the diet plan that your childs doctor recommends.
                
Milk and milk products. You may be able to have milk and milk products without symptoms if you
                
- drink small amounts of milkhalf a cup or lessat a time  - drink small amounts of milk with meals, such as having milk with cereal or having cheese with crackers  - add small amounts of milk and milk products to your diet a little at a time and see how you feel  - eat milk products that are easier for people with lactose intolerance to break down:      - yogurt    - hard cheeses such as cheddar and Swiss
                

                
Lactose-free and lactose-reduced milk and milk products. You can find lactose-free and lactose-reduced milk and milk products at the grocery store. These products are just as healthy for you as regular milk and milk products.
                
Lactase products. You can use lactase tablets and drops when you have milk and milk products. The lactase enzyme breaks down the lactose in food. Using lactase tablets or drops can help you prevent symptoms of lactose intolerance. Check with your doctor before using these products. Some people, such as young children and pregnant and breastfeeding women, may not be able to use these products.
                

                

                
Calcium and Vitamin D   If you are lactose intolerant, make sure you get enough calcium each day. Milk and milk products are the most common sources of calcium. Other foods that contain calcium include   - fish with soft bones, such as canned salmon or sardines   - broccoli and other leafy green vegetables   - oranges   - almonds, Brazil nuts, and dried beans   - tofu   - products with the label showing added calcium, such as cereals, fruit juices, and soy milk    Vitamin D helps the body absorb and use calcium. Be sure to eat foods that contain vitamin D, such as eggs, liver, and certain kinds of fish, such as salmon. Also, being outside in the sunlight helps your body make vitamin D. Some companies add vitamin D to milk and milk products. If you are able to drink small amounts of milk or eat yogurt, choose those that have vitamin D added.   Talk with your doctor about how to get enough nutrientsincluding calcium and vitamin Din your diet or your childs diet. Ask if you should also take a supplement to get enough calcium and vitamin D.   For safety reasons, talk with your doctor before using dietary supplements or any other nonmainstream medicine together with or in place of the treatment your doctor prescribes. Read more at www.ods.od.nih.gov and www.nccam.nih.gov.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000131-12" qtype="considerations">What to do for What I need to know about Lactose Intolerance ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Lactose is a sugar found in milk and milk products.  - Lactose intolerance means you have symptoms such as bloating, diarrhea, and gas after you have milk or milk products.  - Your doctor will try to find out if you have lactose intolerance with a medical, family, and diet history; a physical exam; and medical tests.  - Most people with lactose intolerance can eat or drink some lactose without symptoms.  - If you have lactose intolerance, you can make changes to what you eat and drink. Some people may only need to have less lactose. Others may need to avoid lactose altogether.  - Talk with your doctor about how to get enough nutrientsincluding calcium and vitamin Din your diet or your childs diet. Ask if you should also take a supplement to get enough calcium and vitamin D. For safety reasons, talk with your doctor before using dietary supplements or any other nonmainstream medicine together with or in place of the treatment your doctor prescribes.  - Lactose is in many food products and in some medicines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
