<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000002" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/endocrine/adrenal-insufficiency-addisons-disease/Pages/fact-sheet.aspx">
<Focus>Adrenal Insufficiency and Addison's Disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0405580</CUI>
			<CUI>C0266273</CUI>
			<CUI>C0001623</CUI>
			<CUI>C0001403</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000002-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Adrenal Insufficiency and Addison's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Adrenal insufficiency is an endocrine, or hormonal, disorder that occurs when the adrenal glands do not produce enough of certain hormones. The adrenal glands are located just above the kidneys.
                
Adrenal insufficiency can be primary or secondary. Addisons disease, the common term for primary adrenal insufficiency, occurs when the adrenal glands are damaged and cannot produce enough of the adrenal hormone cortisol. The adrenal hormone aldosterone may also be lacking. Addisons disease affects 110 to 144 of every 1 million people in developed countries.1
                
Secondary adrenal insufficiency occurs when the pituitary glanda pea-sized gland at the base of the brainfails to produce enough adrenocorticotropin (ACTH), a hormone that stimulates the adrenal glands to produce the hormone cortisol. If ACTH output is too low, cortisol production drops. Eventually, the adrenal glands can shrink due to lack of ACTH stimulation. Secondary adrenal insufficiency is much more common than Addisons disease.
                

                
1</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000002-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Adrenal Insufficiency and Addison's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Adrenal Insufficiency
                
The most common symptoms of adrenal insufficiency are
                
- chronic, or long lasting, fatigue   - muscle weakness   - loss of appetite   - weight loss   - abdominal pain
                
Other symptoms of adrenal insufficiency can include
                
- nausea   - vomiting   - diarrhea   - low blood pressure that drops further when a person stands up, causing dizziness or fainting   - irritability and depression   - craving salty foods   - hypoglycemia, or low blood sugar   - headache   - sweating   - irregular or absent menstrual periods   - in women, loss of interest in sex
                
Hyperpigmentation, or darkening of the skin, can occur in Addisons disease, although not in secondary adrenal insufficiency. This darkening is most visible on scars; skin folds; pressure points such as the elbows, knees, knuckles, and toes; lips; and mucous membranes such as the lining of the cheek.
                
The slowly progressing symptoms of adrenal insufficiency are often ignored until a stressful event, such as surgery, a severe injury, an illness, or pregnancy, causes them to worsen.
                
Adrenal Crisis
                
Sudden, severe worsening of adrenal insufficiency symptoms is called adrenal crisis. If the person has Addisons disease, this worsening can also be called an Addisonian crisis. In most cases, symptoms of adrenal insufficiency become serious enough that people seek medical treatment before an adrenal crisis occurs. However, sometimes symptoms appear for the first time during an adrenal crisis.
                
Symptoms of adrenal crisis include
                
- sudden, severe pain in the lower back, abdomen, or legs   - severe vomiting and diarrhea   - dehydration   - low blood pressure   - loss of consciousness
                
If not treated, an adrenal crisis can cause death.
                

                
Get Treatment for Adrenal Crisis Right Away   People with adrenal insufficiency who have weakness, nausea, or vomiting need immediate emergency treatment to prevent an adrenal crisis and possible death. An injection with a synthetic glucocorticoid hormone called a corticosteroid can save a persons life. People should make sure to have a corticosteroid injection with them at all times, and make sure their friends and family know how and when to give the injection.   Read more under How is adrenal insufficiency treated?</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000002-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Adrenal Insufficiency and Addison's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with adrenal insufficiency who have weakness, nausea, or vomiting need immediate emergency treatment to prevent an adrenal crisis and possible death. An injection with a synthetic glucocorticoid hormone called a corticosteroid can save a persons life. People should make sure to have a corticosteroid injection with them at all times, and make sure their friends and family know how and when to give the injection.
                
Read more under How is adrenal insufficiency treated?</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000002-5" qtype="causes">What causes Adrenal Insufficiency and Addison's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Autoimmune disorders cause most cases of Addisons disease. Infections and medications may also cause the disease.
                
Autoimmune Disorders
                
Up to 80 percent of Addisons disease cases are caused by an autoimmune disorder, which is when the bodys immune system attacks the bodys own cells and organs.2 In autoimmune Addisons, which mainly occurs in middle-aged females, the immune system gradually destroys the adrenal cortexthe outer layer of the adrenal glands.2
                
Primary adrenal insufficiency occurs when at least 90 percent of the adrenal cortex has been destroyed.1 As a result, both cortisol and aldosterone are often lacking. Sometimes only the adrenal glands are affected. Sometimes other endocrine glands are affected as well, as in polyendocrine deficiency syndrome.
                
Polyendocrine deficiency syndrome is classified into type 1 and type 2. Type 1 is inherited and occurs in children. In addition to adrenal insufficiency, these children may have
                
- underactive parathyroid glands, which are four pea-sized glands located on or near the thyroid gland in the neck; they produce a hormone that helps maintain the correct balance of calcium in the body.   - slow sexual development.   - pernicious anemia, a severe type of anemia; anemia is a condition in which red blood cells are fewer than normal, which means less oxygen is carried to the bodys cells. With most types of anemia, red blood cells are smaller than normal; however, in pernicious anemia, the cells are bigger than normal.   - chronic fungal infections.   - chronic hepatitis, a liver disease.
                
Researchers think type 2, which is sometimes called Schmidts syndrome, is also inherited. Type 2 usually affects young adults and may include
                
- an underactive thyroid gland, which produces hormones that regulate metabolism   - slow sexual development   - diabetes, in which a person has high blood glucose, also called high blood sugar or hyperglycemia   - vitiligo, a loss of pigment on areas of the skin
                
Infections
                
Tuberculosis (TB), an infection that can destroy the adrenal glands, accounts for 10 to 15 percent of Addisons disease cases in developed countries.1 When primary adrenal insufficiency was first identified by Dr. Thomas Addison in 1849, TB was the most common cause of the disease. As TB treatment improved, the incidence of Addisons disease due to TB of the adrenal glands greatly decreased. However, recent reports show an increase in Addisons disease from infections such as TB and cytomegalovirus. Cytomegalovirus is a common virus that does not cause symptoms in healthy people; however, it does affect babies in the womb and people who have a weakened immune systemmostly due to HIV/AIDS.2 Other bacterial infections, such as Neisseria meningitidis, which is a cause of meningitis, and fungal infections can also lead to Addisons disease.
                
Other Causes
                
Less common causes of Addisons disease are
                
- cancer cells in the adrenal glands   - amyloidosis, a serious, though rare, group of diseases that occurs when abnormal proteins, called amyloids, build up in the blood and are deposited in tissues and organs   - surgical removal of the adrenal glands   - bleeding into the adrenal glands   - genetic defects including abnormal adrenal gland development, an inability of the adrenal glands to respond to ACTH, or a defect in adrenal hormone production   - medication-related causes, such as from anti-fungal medications and the anesthetic etomidate, which may be used when a person undergoes an emergency intubationthe placement of a flexible, plastic tube through the mouth and into the trachea, or windpipe, to assist with breathing
                

                
2</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000002-6" qtype="causes">What causes Adrenal Insufficiency and Addison's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>A lack of CRH or ACTH causes secondary adrenal insufficiency. The lack of these hormones in the body can be traced to several possible sources.
                
Stoppage of Corticosteroid Medication
                
A temporary form of secondary adrenal insufficiency may occur when a person who has been taking a synthetic glucocorticoid hormone, called a corticosteroid, for a long time stops taking the medication. Corticosteroids are often prescribed to treat inflammatory illnesses such as rheumatoid arthritis, asthma, and ulcerative colitis. In this case, the prescription doses often cause higher levels than those normally achieved by the glucocorticoid hormones created by the body. When a person takes corticosteroids for prolonged periods, the adrenal glands produce less of their natural hormones. Once the prescription doses of corticosteroid are stopped, the adrenal glands may be slow to restart their production of the bodys glucocorticoids. To give the adrenal glands time to regain function and prevent adrenal insufficiency, prescription corticosteroid doses should be reduced gradually over a period of weeks or even months. Even with gradual reduction, the adrenal glands might not begin to function normally for some time, so a person who has recently stopped taking prescription corticosteroids should be watched carefully for symptoms of secondary adrenal insufficiency.
                
Surgical Removal of Pituitary Tumors
                
Another cause of secondary adrenal insufficiency is surgical removal of the usually noncancerous, ACTH-producing tumors of the pituitary gland that cause Cushings syndrome. Cushings syndrome is a hormonal disorder caused by prolonged exposure of the bodys tissues to high levels of the hormone cortisol. When the tumors are removed, the source of extra ACTH is suddenly gone and a replacement hormone must be taken until the bodys adrenal glands are able to resume their normal production of cortisol. The adrenal glands might not begin to function normally for some time, so a person who has had an ACTH-producing tumor removed and is going off of his or her prescription corticosteroid replacement hormone should be watched carefully for symptoms of adrenal insufficiency.
                
More information is provided in the NIDDK health topic, Cushings Syndrome.
                
Changes in the Pituitary Gland
                
Less commonly, secondary adrenal insufficiency occurs when the pituitary gland either decreases in size or stops producing ACTH. These events can result from
                
- tumors or an infection in the pituitary   - loss of blood flow to the pituitary   - radiation for the treatment of pituitary or nearby tumors   - surgical removal of parts of the hypothalamus   - surgical removal of the pituitary</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000002-7" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Adrenal Insufficiency and Addison's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>In its early stages, adrenal insufficiency can be difficult to diagnose. A health care provider may suspect it after reviewing a persons medical history and symptoms.
                
A diagnosis of adrenal insufficiency is confirmed through hormonal blood and urine tests. A health care provider uses these tests first to determine whether cortisol levels are too low and then to establish the cause. Imaging studies of the adrenal and pituitary glands can be useful in helping to establish the cause.
                
A lab technician performs the following tests in a health care providers office, a commercial facility, or a hospital.
                
Hormonal Blood and Urine Tests
                
- ACTH stimulation test. The ACTH stimulation test is the most commonly used test for diagnosing adrenal insufficiency. In this test, the patient is given an intravenous (IV) injection of synthetic ACTH, and samples of blood, urine, or both are taken before and after the injection. The cortisol levels in the blood and urine samples are measured in a lab. The normal response after an ACTH injection is a rise in blood and urine cortisol levels. People with Addisons disease or longstanding secondary adrenal insufficiency have little or no increase in cortisol levels.  Both low- and high-dose ACTH stimulation tests may be used depending on the suspected cause of adrenal insufficiency. For example, if secondary adrenal insufficiency is mild or has only recently occurred, the adrenal glands may still respond to ACTH because they have not yet shut down their own production of hormone. Some studies have suggested a low dose1 microgram (mcg)may be more effective in detecting secondary adrenal insufficiency because the low dose is still enough to raise cortisol levels in healthy people, yet not in people with mild or recent secondary adrenal insufficiency. However, recent research has shown that a significant proportion of healthy children and adults can fail the low-dose test, which may lead to unnecessary treatment. Therefore, some health care providers favor using a 250 mcg ACTH test for more accurate results.   - CRH stimulation test. When the response to the ACTH test is abnormal, a CRH stimulation test can help determine the cause of adrenal insufficiency. In this test, the patient is given an IV injection of synthetic CRH, and blood is taken before and 30, 60, 90, and 120 minutes after the injection. The cortisol levels in the blood samples are measured in a lab. People with Addisons disease respond by producing high levels of ACTH, yet no cortisol. People with secondary adrenal insufficiency do not produce ACTH or have a delayed response. CRH will not stimulate ACTH secretion if the pituitary is damaged, so no ACTH response points to the pituitary as the cause. A delayed ACTH response points to the hypothalamus as the cause.
                
Diagnosis during Adrenal Crisis
                
Although a reliable diagnosis is not possible during adrenal crisis, measurement of blood ACTH and cortisol during the crisisbefore treatment with corticosteroids is givenis often enough to make a preliminary diagnosis. Low blood sodium, low blood glucose, and high blood potassium are also sometimes present at the time of adrenal crisis. Once the crisis is controlled, an ACTH stimulation test can be performed to help make a specific diagnosis. More complex lab tests are sometimes used if the diagnosis remains unclear.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000002-8" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Adrenal Insufficiency and Addison's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>After Addisons disease is diagnosed, health care providers may use the following tests to look at the adrenal glands, find out whether the disease is related to TB, or identify antibodies associated with autoimmune Addisons disease.
                
- Ultrasound of the abdomen. Ultrasound uses a device, called a transducer, that bounces safe, painless sound waves off organs to create an image of their structure. A specially trained technician performs the procedure in a health care providers office, an outpatient center, or a hospital, and a radiologista doctor who specializes in medical imaginginterprets the images; a patient does not need anesthesia. The images can show abnormalities in the adrenal glands, such as enlargement or small size, nodules, or signs of calcium deposits, which may indicate bleeding.   - Tuberculin skin test. A tuberculin skin test measures how a patients immune system reacts to the bacteria that cause TB. A small needle is used to put some testing material, called tuberculin, under the skin. A nurse or lab technician performs the test in a health care providers office; a patient does not need anesthesia. In 2 to 3 days, the patient returns to the health care provider, who will check to see if the patient had a reaction to the test. The test can show if adrenal insufficiency could be related to TB.  To test whether a person has TB infection, which is when TB bacteria live in the body without making the person sick, a special TB blood test is used. To test whether a person has TB disease, which is when TB bacteria are actively attacking a persons lungs and making the person sick, other tests such as a chest x ray and a sample of sputumphlegm that is coughed up from deep in the lungsmay be needed.   - Antibody blood tests. A blood test involves drawing blood at a health care providers office or a commercial facility and sending the sample to a lab for analysis. The blood test can detect antibodiesproteins made by the immune system to protect the body from foreign substancesassociated with autoimmune Addisons disease.
                
After secondary adrenal insufficiency is diagnosed, health care providers may use the following tests to obtain a detailed view of the pituitary gland and assess how it is functioning:
                
- Computerized tomography (CT) scan. CT scans use a combination of x rays and computer technology to create images. For a CT scan, the patient may be given a solution to drink and an injection of a special dye, called contrast medium. CT scans require the patient to lie on a table that slides into a tunnel-shaped device where the x rays are taken. An x-ray technician performs the procedure in an outpatient center or a hospital, and a radiologist interprets the images. The patient does not need anesthesia. A CT scan can show size and shape of the pituitary gland to find out if an abnormality is present.   - Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). MRI machines use radio waves and magnets to produce detailed pictures of the bodys internal organs and soft tissues without using x rays. An MRI may include the injection of contrast medium. With most MRI machines, the patient lies on a table that slides into a tunnel-shaped device that may be open ended or closed at one end; some machines are designed to allow the patient to lie in a more open space. A specially trained technician performs the procedure in an outpatient center or a hospital, and a radiologist interprets the images. The patient does not need anesthesia, though people with a fear of confined spaces may receive light sedation, taken by mouth. MRIs can be used to produce a three-dimensional (3-D) image of the hypothalamus and the pituitary gland to find out if an abnormality is present.   - Hormonal blood tests. Hormonal blood tests can assess how the pituitary gland is functioning and its ability to produce other hormones.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000002-9" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Adrenal Insufficiency and Addison's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Adrenal insufficiency is treated by replacing, or substituting, the hormones that the adrenal glands are not making. The dose of each medication is adjusted to meet the needs of the patient.
                
Cortisol is replaced with a corticosteroid, such as hydrocortisone, prednisone, or dexamethasone, taken orally one to three times each day, depending on which medication is chosen.
                
If aldosterone is also deficient, it is replaced with oral doses of a mineralocorticoid hormone, called fludrocortisone acetate (Florinef), taken once or twice daily. People with secondary adrenal insufficiency normally maintain aldosterone production, so they do not require aldosterone replacement therapy.
                
During adrenal crisis, low blood pressure, low blood glucose, low blood sodium, and high blood levels of potassium can be life threatening. Standard therapy involves immediate IV injections of corticosteroids and large volumes of IV saline solution with dextrose, a type of sugar. This treatment usually brings rapid improvement. When the patient can take liquids and medications by mouth, the amount of corticosteroids is decreased until a dose that maintains normal hormone levels is reached. If aldosterone is deficient, the person will need to regularly take oral doses of fludrocortisone acetate.
                
Researchers have found that using replacement therapy for DHEA in adolescent girls who have secondary adrenal insufficiency and low levels of DHEA can improve pubic hair development and psychological stress. Further studies are needed before routine supplementation recommendations can be made.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000002-11" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Adrenal Insufficiency and Addison's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Adrenal crisis is treated with adrenal hormones. People with adrenal crisis need immediate treatment. Any delay can cause death. When people with adrenal crisis are vomiting or unconscious and cannot take their medication, the hormones can be given as an injection.
                
A person with adrenal insufficiency should carry a corticosteroid injection at all times and make sure that others know how and when to administer the injection, in case the person becomes unconscious.
                
The dose of corticosteroid needed may vary with a persons age or size. For example, a child younger than 2 years of age can receive 25 milligrams (mg), a child between 2 and 8 years of age can receive 50 mg, and a child older than 8 years should receive the adult dose of 100 mg.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000002-12" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Adrenal Insufficiency and Addison's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The following steps can help a person prevent adrenal crisis:
                
- Ask a health care provider about possibly having a shortage of adrenal hormones, if always feeling tired, weak, or losing weight.   - Learn how to increase the dose of corticosteroid for adrenal insufficiency when ill. Ask a health care provider for written instructions for sick days. First discuss the decision to increase the dose with the health care provider when ill.   - When very ill, especially if vomiting and not able to take pills, seek emergency medical care immediately.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="14">
			<Question qid="0000002-14" qtype="considerations">What to do for Adrenal Insufficiency and Addison's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Some people with Addisons disease who are aldosterone deficient can benefit from following a diet rich in sodium. A health care provider or a dietitian can give specific recommendations on appropriate sodium sources and daily sodium guidelines if necessary.
                
Corticosteroid treatment is linked to an increased risk of osteoporosisa condition in which the bones become less dense and more likely to fracture. People who take corticosteroids should protect their bone health by consuming enough dietary calcium and vitamin D. A health care provider or a dietitian can give specific recommendations on appropriate daily calcium intake based upon age and suggest the best types of calcium supplements, if necessary.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="15">
			<Question qid="0000002-15" qtype="considerations">What to do for Adrenal Insufficiency and Addison's Disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Adrenal insufficiency is an endocrine, or hormonal, disorder that occurs when the adrenal glands do not produce enough of certain hormones.   - Addisons disease, the common term for primary adrenal insufficiency, occurs when the adrenal glands are damaged and cannot produce enough of the adrenal hormone cortisol. The adrenal hormone aldosterone may also be lacking.   - Secondary adrenal insufficiency occurs when the pituitary gland fails to produce enough adrenocorticotropin (ACTH), a hormone that stimulates the adrenal glands to produce cortisol. If ACTH output is too low, cortisol production drops.   - The most common symptoms of adrenal insufficiency are chronic fatigue, muscle weakness, loss of appetite, weight loss, and abdominal pain. The slowly progressing symptoms are often ignored until a stressful event, such as surgery, a severe injury, an illness, or pregnancy, causes them to worsen.   - If not treated, an adrenal crisis can cause death.   - A diagnosis of adrenal insufficiency is confirmed through hormonal blood and urine tests. Imaging studies of the adrenal and pituitary glands can be useful in helping to establish the cause.   - Adrenal insufficiency is treated by replacing, or substituting, the hormones that the adrenal glands are not making.   - Problems can occur in people with adrenal insufficiency who are undergoing surgery, suffer a severe injury, have an illness, or are pregnant. These conditions place additional stress on the body, and people with adrenal insufficiency may need additional treatment to respond and recover.   - People with adrenal insufficiency should always carry identification stating their condition, adrenal insufficiency, in case of an emergency, as well as the supplies necessary to administer an emergency corticosteroid injection.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
