<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000078" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/Diabetes/gestational-diabetes/Pages/index.aspx">
<Focus>What I need to know about Gestational Diabetes</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0085207</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000078-1" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Gestational Diabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Gestational* diabetes is a type of diabetes that develops only during pregnancy. Diabetes means your blood glucose, also called blood sugar, is too high. Your body uses glucose for energy. Too much glucose in your blood is not good for you or your baby.
                
Gestational diabetes is usually diagnosed during late pregnancy. If you are diagnosed with diabetes earlier in your pregnancy, you may have had diabetes before you became pregnant.
                
Treating gestational diabetes can help both you and your baby stay healthy. You can protect your baby and yourself by taking action right away to control your blood glucose levels.
                
If you have gestational diabetes, a health care team will likely be part of your care. In addition to your obstetrician-gynecologist, or OB/GYNthe doctor who will deliver your babyyour team might include a doctor who treats diabetes, a diabetes educator, and a dietitian to help you plan meals.
                
For Women with Type 1 or Type 2 Diabetes   If you already have type 1 or type 2 diabetes and are thinking about having a baby, talk with your doctor before you get pregnant. Untreated or poorly controlled diabetes can cause serious problems for your baby. More information is provided in the NIDDK health topic, What I need to know about Preparing for Pregnancy if I Have Diabetes or call 18008608747 and request a copy.
                
*See the Pronunciation Guide for tips on how to say the words in bold type.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000078-2" qtype="causes">What causes What I need to know about Gestational Diabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Gestational diabetes happens when your body can&apos;t make enough insulin during pregnancy. Insulin is a hormone made in your pancreas, an organ located behind your stomach. Insulin helps your body use glucose for energy and helps control your blood glucose levels.
                
During pregnancy, your body makes more hormones and goes through other changes, such as weight gain. These changes cause your body&apos;s cells to use insulin less effectively, a condition called insulin resistance. Insulin resistance increases your body&apos;s need for insulin. If your pancreas can&apos;t make enough insulin, you will have gestational diabetes.
                
All pregnant women have some insulin resistance during late pregnancy. However, some women have insulin resistance even before they get pregnant, usually because they are overweight. These women start pregnancy with an increased need for insulin and are more likely to have gestational diabetes.
                

                
What are my chances of getting gestational diabetes?   Your chances of getting gestational diabetes are higher if you   - are overweight   - have had gestational diabetes before   - have given birth to a baby weighing more than 9 pounds   - have a parent, brother, or sister with type 2 diabetes   - have prediabetes, meaning your blood glucose levels are higher than normal yet not high enough for a diagnosis of diabetes   - are African American, American Indian, Asian American, Hispanic/Latina, or Pacific Islander American   - have a hormonal disorder called polycystic ovary syndrome, also known as PCOS</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000078-3" qtype="information">What is (are) What I need to know about Gestational Diabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your chances of getting gestational diabetes are higher if you
                
- are overweight  - have had gestational diabetes before  - have given birth to a baby weighing more than 9 pounds  - have a parent, brother, or sister with type 2 diabetes  - have prediabetes, meaning your blood glucose levels are higher than normal yet not high enough for a diagnosis of diabetes  - are African American, American Indian, Asian American, Hispanic/Latina, or Pacific Islander American  - have a hormonal disorder called polycystic ovary syndrome, also known as PCOS</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000078-6" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose What I need to know about Gestational Diabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Doctors use blood tests to diagnose gestational diabetes. All diabetes blood tests involve drawing blood at a doctor&apos;s office or a commercial facility. Blood samples are sent to a lab for analysis.
                

                
Screening Glucose Challenge Test
                
For this test, you will drink a sugary beverage and have your blood glucose level checked an hour later. This test can be done at any time of the day. If the results are above normal, you may need to have an oral glucose tolerance test.
                
Oral Glucose Tolerance Test
                
You will need to fast for at least 8 hours before the test. Fasting means having nothing to eat or drink except water. Your doctor will give you other instructions to follow before the test.
                
Your fasting blood glucose level will be checked before the test begins. Then you will drink a sugary beverage. Your blood glucose levels will be checked 1 hour, 2 hours, and possibly 3 hours later. Your doctor will use your test results to find out whether you have gestational diabetes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000078-8" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose What I need to know about Gestational Diabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>If you have gestational diabetes, your doctor may recommend that you have some extra tests to check your baby&apos;s health, such as
                
- ultrasound exams, which use sound waves to make images that show your baby&apos;s growth and whether your baby is larger than normal  - a nonstress test, which uses a monitor placed on your abdomen to check whether your baby&apos;s heart rate increases as it should when your baby is active  - kick counts to check the time between your baby&apos;s movements</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000078-10" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for What I need to know about Gestational Diabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treating gestational diabetes means taking steps to keep your blood glucose levels in a target range. Targets are numbers you aim for. Your doctor will help you set your targets. You will learn how to control your blood glucose using
                
- healthy eating  - physical activity  - insulin shots, if needed</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000078-11" qtype="considerations">What to do for What I need to know about Gestational Diabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care team will help you make a healthy eating plan with food choices that are good for both you and your baby. These choices are good for you to follow throughout pregnancy and after, as you raise your family.
                
Using a healthy eating plan will help your blood glucose stay in your target range. The plan will help you know which foods to eat, how much to eat, and when to eat. Food choices, amounts, and timing are all important in keeping your blood glucose levels in your target range.
                
More information is provided in the NIDDK health topic, What I need to know about Eating and Diabetes.
                

                
Physical Activity
                
Physical activity can help you reach your blood glucose targets. Talk with your doctor about the type of activity that is best for you. If you are already active, tell your doctor what you do. Being physically active will also help lower your chances of having type 2 diabetesand its problemsin the future. Now is the time to develop good habits for you and your baby.
                
For more information about physical activity and pregnancy, visit www.womenshealth.gov/pregnancy.
                
Insulin Shots
                
If you have trouble meeting your blood glucose targets, you may need to take a medicine called insulin, along with following a healthy meal plan and being physically active. Your health care team will show you how to give yourself insulin shots. Insulin will not harm your baby.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="13">
			<Question qid="0000078-13" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose What I need to know about Gestational Diabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care team may teach you how to test for chemicals called ketones in your morning urine or in your blood. High levels of ketones are a sign that your body is using your body fat for energy instead of the food you eat. Using fat for energy is not recommended during pregnancy. Ketones may be harmful for your baby.
                
If your ketone levels are high, your doctor may suggest that you change the type or amount of food you eat. Or you may need to change your meal or snack times.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="15">
			<Question qid="0000078-15" qtype="prevention">How to prevent What I need to know about Gestational Diabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can do a lot to prevent or delay type 2 diabetes by making these lifestyle changes:
                
- Reach and stay at a healthy weight. Try to reach your prepregnancy weight 6 to 12 months after your baby is born. Then, if you still weigh too much, work to lose at least 5 to 7 percent of your body weight and keep it off. For example, if you weigh 200 pounds, losing 10 to 14 pounds can greatly reduce your chance of getting diabetes.  - Be physically active for at least 30 minutes most days of the week.  - Follow a healthy eating plan. Eat more grains, fruits, and vegetables. Cut down on fat and calories. Your health care team can help you design a meal plan.  - Ask your doctor if you should take the diabetes medicine metformin. Metformin can lower your chances of having type 2 diabetes, especially if you are younger and heavier and have prediabetes or if you have had gestational diabetes.
                
These changes can help you enjoy a longer, healthier life. Your health care team can give you information and support to help you make these changes.
                
By delaying or preventing type 2 diabetes, you will also lower your chances of having heart and blood vessel disease and other problems as you get older.
                
Talk with your doctor if you are thinking about having another baby. For the safety of your baby, your blood glucose needs to be at healthy levels before you get pregnant again. Your doctor can help ensure you are ready for your next child.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="18">
			<Question qid="0000078-18" qtype="considerations">What to do for What I need to know about Gestational Diabetes ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Gestational diabetes is a type of diabetes that develops only during pregnancy. Diabetes means your blood glucose, also called blood sugar, is too high.  - Gestational diabetes happens when your body can&apos;t make enough insulin during pregnancy. Insulin is a hormone made in your pancreas, an organ located behind your stomach. Insulin helps your body use glucose for energy and helps control your blood glucose levels.  - You will probably be tested for gestational diabetes between weeks 24 and 28 of your pregnancy. If you have a higher chance of getting gestational diabetes, your doctor may test you for diabetes during your first visit after you become pregnant.  - If you have high blood glucose levels because your gestational diabetes is not under control, your baby will also have high blood glucose.  - Untreated or uncontrolled gestational diabetes can cause problems for your baby.  - Treating gestational diabetes means taking steps to keep your blood glucose levels in a target range.  - Even if your blood glucose levels return to normal after your pregnancy, your chances of getting diabetesusually type 2 diabeteslater in life are high. Therefore, you should be tested at least every 3 years for diabetes or prediabetes.  - You can give your baby a healthy start by breastfeeding.  - You can help your child be healthy by showing your child how to make healthy lifestyle choices, including being physically active, limiting screen time in front of the TV or video games, eating a healthy diet, and staying at a healthy weight.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
