<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000180" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/kidney-disease/kidney-failure-what-to-expect/Pages/ez.aspx">
<Focus>What I need to know about Living with Kidney Failure</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0035078</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000180-1" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for What I need to know about Living with Kidney Failure ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kidney failure means your kidneys no longer work well enough to do their job. You need treatment to replace the work your damaged kidneys have stopped doing. The treatments for kidney failure are
                
- hemodialysis  - peritoneal dialysis  - a kidney transplant
                
Your kidneys filter wastes and extra fluid from your blood to keep you healthy. The wastes and extra fluid become urine that is stored in your bladder until you urinate. When your kidneys fail, dialysis can take over a small part of the work your damaged kidneys can no longer do. You can make treatments work better by
                
- sticking to your treatment schedule  - taking all medicines your doctor prescribes  - following a special diet that keeps wastes from building up in your blood  - being active most days of the week
                
Hemodialysis
                
Hemodialysis is a treatment for kidney failure. Hemodialysis uses a machine to filter your blood outside your body. First, a dialysis nurse places two needles into your arm. A pump on the hemodialysis machine draws your blood through one of the needles into a tube. The tube takes the blood to a filter, called a dialyzer. Inside the dialyzer, your blood flows through thin fibers that are like straws. The wastes and extra fluid leave the blood through tiny holes in the fibers. Then, a different tube carries the filtered blood back to your body through the second needle.
                
More information is provided in the NIDDK health topics, Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Hemodialysis and Home Hemodialysis.
                
Peritoneal Dialysis
                
catheter
                
Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Peritoneal Dialysis
                
Kidney Transplant
                
A kidney transplant places a healthy kidney from another person into your body. The kidney may come from someone who has just died. Your doctor will place your name on a waiting list for a kidney. A family member or friend might be able to give you a kidney. Then you dont have to wait.
                
The new kidney takes over filtering your blood. The damaged kidneys usually stay where they are. The new kidney is placed in the front lower abdomen, on one side of the bladder. Your body normally attacks anything that shouldnt be there, such as bacteria. Your body will think the new kidney shouldnt be there. You will take medicines called immunosuppressants to keep your body from attacking the new kidney.
                
More information is provided in the NIDDK health topic, Treatment Methods for Kidney Failure: Transplantation.
                
*See the Pronunciation Guide for tips on how to say the the words in bold type.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000180-2" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for What I need to know about Living with Kidney Failure ?</Question>
			<Answer>Learning about different treatments for kidney failure will help you choose the one that best fits your lifestyle. Talk with your doctor and people on hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis to learn about the pros and cons of each treatment. Ask your doctor about the transplant waiting list and about medicines required after a transplant. Talk with people who have had kidney transplants and ask how it has changed their lives.
                
If you plan to keep working, think about which treatment can help make that easier. If spending time with family and friends means a lot to you, learn about which treatment may give you the most free time. Find out which treatment will give you the best chance to be healthy and live longer.
                
Talking with your doctor ahead of time about your options can help you take control of your care. Understanding the treatment you choose and getting used to the idea that you will be receiving this treatment takes time. If you choose one type of dialysis treatment and find it is not a good fit for your life, talk with your doctor about selecting another type of dialysis treatment that better meets your needs.
                
While kidney failure can make your life harder, treatments can help improve your life.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000180-8" qtype="considerations">What to do for What I need to know about Living with Kidney Failure ?</Question>
			<Answer>Eating the right foods can help you feel better when you are on dialysis or have a kidney transplant. Staying healthy with kidney failure requires watching how much of these elements are included in your diet:
                
- Protein is in many foods you eat. Protein is in foods from animals and plants. Most diets include both types of protein. Protein provides the building blocks that maintain and repair muscles, organs, and other parts of the body. Too much protein can cause waste to build up in your blood, making your kidneys work harder. However, if you are on hemodialysis or peritoneal dialysis, you need lots of protein to replace the protein that dialysis removes.  - Phosphorus is a mineral that keeps your bones healthy. Phosphorus also keeps blood vessels and muscles working. This mineral is found naturally in foods rich in protein, such as meat, poultry, fish, nuts, beans, and dairy products. Phosphorus is also added to many processed foods. You need phosphorus to turn food into energy; however, too much can cause your bones to weaken.  - Water is in drinks and in foods such as fruits, vegetables, ice cream, gelatin, soup, and popsicles. Your body needs water; however, too much can cause fluid to build up in your body and make your heart work harder.  - Sodium is a part of salt. You can find sodium in many canned, packaged, and fast foods and in seasonings and meats. You need sodium to help control the amount of fluid in your body; however, too much can cause high blood pressure.  - Potassium is a mineral that helps your nerves and muscles work the right way. Potassium is found in fruits and vegetables such as oranges, bananas, tomatoes, and potatoes. You need potassium for healthy nerves and brain cells; however, too much can make your heartbeat irregular.  - Calories are found in all foods and are especially high in oils and sugary foods. You need calories for energy; however, too many can cause weight gain and high blood sugar.
                
Talk with your clinics renal dietitian to find a meal plan that works for you. Each treatment requires a different diet. If you are on hemodialysis, you have to stay away from foods such as potatoes and oranges because they have lots of potassium. If you are on peritoneal dialysis, eating potassium is fine. Instead, you may need to watch your calories. Your food needs will also depend on your weight and activity level.
                
Changing your diet may be hard at first. Eating the right foods will help you feel better. You will have more strength and energy. Having more energy will help you live a fuller, healthier life. More information is provided in the NIDDK health topic, Eat Right to Feel Right on Hemodialysis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000180-9" qtype="considerations">What to do for What I need to know about Living with Kidney Failure ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Kidney failure means your kidneys no longer work well enough to do their job.  - Learning about treatments for kidney failure will help you choose the one that best fits your lifestyle.  - Many people with kidney failure continue to work.  - Physical activity is an important part of staying healthy when you have kidney failure.  - You can help prevent relatives from having kidney failure by talking with them about their risk.  - Eating the right foods can help you feel better when you are on dialysis or have a kidney transplant.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
