<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000036" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/Diabetes/financial-help-diabetes-care/Pages/index.aspx">
<Focus>Financial Help for Diabetes Care</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0580931</CUI>
			<CUI>C0011860</CUI>
			<CUI>C0011849</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000036-1" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Financial Help for Diabetes Care ?</Question>
			<Answer>Diabetes management and treatment is expensive. According to the American Diabetes Association (ADA), the average cost of health care for a person with diabetes is $13,741 a yearmore than twice the cost of health care for a person without diabetes.1
                
Many people who have diabetes need help paying for their care. For those who qualify, a variety of government and nongovernment programs can help cover health care expenses. This publication is meant to help people with diabetes and their family members find and access such resources.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000036-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Financial Help for Diabetes Care ?</Question>
			<Answer>Health insurance helps pay for medical care, including the cost of diabetes care. Health insurance options include the following:
                
- private health insurance, which includes group and individual health insurance  - government health insurance, such as Medicare, Medicaid, the Childrens Health Insurance Program (CHIP), TRICARE, and veterans health care programs
                
Starting in 2014, the Affordable Care Act (ACA) prevents insurers from denying coverage or charging higher premiums to people with preexisting conditions, such as diabetes. The ACA also requires most people to have health insurance or pay a fee. Some people may be exempt from this fee. Read more about the ACA at HealthCare.gov or call 18003182596, TTY 18558894325.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000036-4" qtype="information">What is (are) Financial Help for Diabetes Care ?</Question>
			<Answer>Insurance companies sell private health insurance plans. Two types of private health insurance are
                
- Group health insurance. People may be eligible to purchase group health insurance through their employer or union or through a family members employer or union. Other organizations, such as professional or alumni organizations, may also offer group health insurance.  - Individual health insurance. People may purchase individual health insurance for themselves and their families. The website HealthCare.gov provides information about individual insurance plans. The website also provides a search function, called the Health Insurance Marketplace, to find health insurance options by state. Depending on their income and family size, some people may qualify for lower-cost premiums through the Health Insurance Marketplace. People can select or change individual health insurance plans during the open enrollment period each year. HealthCare.gov lists open enrollment period dates. The website also provides information about life events that may allow people to enroll outside the open enrollment period.
                
Employers may have a waiting period before an employee and his or her family members can enroll in the company health plan. Under the ACA, the waiting period can be no longer than 90 days. Certain health plans called health maintenance organizations (HMOs) may have an affiliation perioda time that must pass before health insurance coverage becomes effective. An affiliation period can be no longer than 3 months.
                
The ACA expanded coverage of preventive services. For example, adults with sustained high blood pressure may have access to diabetes screening at no cost. Adults and children may have access to obesity screening and counseling at no cost.
                
Each states insurance regulatory office, sometimes called the state insurance department or commission, provides more information about health insurance laws. This office can also help identify an insurance company that offers individual coverage. The National Association of Insurance Commissioners website, www.naic.org/state_web_map.htm , provides a membership list with contact information and a link to the website for each states insurance regulatory office.
                
The ADA also provides information about health insurance options at www.diabetes.org/living-with-diabetes/health-insurance .
                
Keeping Group Health Insurance after Leaving a Job
                
When leaving a job, a person may be able to continue the group health insurance provided by his or her employer for up to 18 months under a federal law called the Consolidated Omnibus Budget Reconciliation Act, or COBRA. Although people pay more for group health insurance through COBRA than they did as employees, group coverage may be cheaper than individual coverage. People who have a disability before becoming eligible for COBRA or who are determined by the Social Security Administration to be disabled within the first 60 days of COBRA coverage may be able to extend COBRA coverage an additional 11 months, for up to 29 months of coverage. COBRA may also cover young adults who were insured under a parents policy after they have reached the age limit and are trying to obtain their own insurance.
                
Read more at www.dol.gov/dol/topic/health-plans/cobra.htm or call the U.S. Department of Labor at 18664USADOL (18664872365).
                
If a person doesnt qualify for coverage or if COBRA coverage has expired, other options may be available:
                
- Some states require employers to offer conversion policies, in which people stay with their insurance company and buy individual coverage.  - Some professional and alumni organizations offer group coverage for members.  - Some insurance companies offer short-term stopgap policies designed for people who are between jobs. However, these policies may not meet ACA requirements. For example, they may not cover preexisting conditions.  - People can purchase individual health insurance policies.
                
Each states insurance regulatory office can provide more information about these and other options. Information about consumer health plans is also available at the U.S. Department of Labors website at www.dol.gov/dol/topic/health-plans/consumerinfhealth.htm.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000036-5" qtype="information">What is (are) Financial Help for Diabetes Care ?</Question>
			<Answer>Medicare is a federal health insurance program that pays health care costs for eligible people who are
                
- age 65 or older  - under age 65 with certain disabilities  - of any age with end-stage renal diseasetotal and permanent kidney failure that requires a kidney transplant or blood-filtering treatments called dialysis
                
What health plans does Medicare offer?
                
Medicare has four parts:
                
- Part A (hospital insurance) covers inpatient care, skilled nursing home residence, hospice care, and home health care. Part A has no premium for those who have paid enough Medicare taxes. A premium is an amount a person must pay periodicallymonthly or quarterlyfor Medicare, other health plan, or drug plan coverage. Part A does have a deductible, an amount a person must pay for health care or prescriptions before the health plan will pay. A person must pay a daily amount for hospital stays that last longer than 60 days.  - Part B (medical insurance) covers services from health care providers, outpatient care, home health care, durable medical equipment, and some preventative services. Part B has a monthly premium based on a persons income. Rates change each year. After a person pays the deductible each year, Part B pays 80 percent for most covered services as a primary payer. The billing staff of the service providerhospital or cliniccan calculate how much a person will owe.  - Part C (Medicare Advantage Plans) are part of Medicare and are sometimes called MA Plans. Medicare must approve Medicare Advantage Plans. Each Medicare Advantage Plan must cover Part A and Part B services and may cover other services, too. Medicare Advantage Plans may have Part D prescription coverage. If not, a person can buy a Part D plan separately. Medicare Advantage Plans are not all the same. A person who is thinking of choosing a Medicare Advantage Plan should ask about the rules of the plan. The rules may specify which health care providers or hospitals a person may use. The plan may require a referral from a primary care provider to see a specialist. The plan may not cover medical expenses incurred during travel. How much a person has to pay out-of-pocket each year will vary by plan. People who have a Medicare Advantage Plan cannot have a Medigap plan to help pay out of-pocket costs. See the section on Medigap.  Four types of Medicare Advantage Plans are available:      - HMOs    - preferred provider organizations (PPOs)    - private fee for service plans    - special needs plans for certain groups    - Part D (prescription drug coverage) has a premium and covers some medications. Private insurance companies offer different Part D plans approved by Medicare. Costs and coverage vary by plan. A person who has few assets and earns less than 150 percent of the federal poverty level may qualify for extra help to pay Part D premiums and medication costs. People can apply for this help by calling the Social Security Administration, visiting www.socialsecurity.gov to apply online, visiting their local Social Security office, or contacting their state medical assistance (Medicaid) office. People can find the current-year guidelines at www.aspe.hhs.gov/poverty or by calling Social Security at 18007721213, TTY 18003250778. People can find information and applications for Part D plans at www.medicare.gov. A person can also apply for Part D with an insurance company that sells one of these plans.
                
Other Medicare health plans are for certain groups, such as frail people living in the community and people with multiple chronic illnesses, and include hospital and medical coverage. Some pay for prescribed medications, too. State health insurance programscalled Medicaidpartially finance and administer these services. The plans include the following:
                
- Medicare Cost Plans are HMOs, like the ones offered as Medicare Advantage plans, only out-of-network providers are paid as if the policyholder had Original Medicare. Original Medicare is Medicare Part A and Part B.  - Program of All-Inclusive Care for the Elderly (PACE) combines medical, social, and long-term care services for frail people who live and get health care in the community.  - Medicare Innovation Projects are special projects that test improvements in Medicare coverage, payment, and quality of care.
                
Read more about Medicare Cost Plans and Demonstration or Pilot Programs on the state Medicaid website at www.medicaid.gov or call 1800MEDICARE (18006334227). State Medicaid offices can provide more information about PACE. See the section on Medicaid.
                
Does Medicare cover diabetes services and supplies?
                
Medicare helps pay for the diabetes services, supplies, and equipment listed below and for some preventive services for people who are at risk for diabetes. However, coinsurance or deductibles may apply. A person must have Medicare Part B or Medicare Part D to receive these covered services and supplies.
                
Medicare Part B helps pay for
                
- diabetes screening tests for people at risk of developing diabetes  - diabetes self-management training  - diabetes supplies such as glucose monitors, test strips, and lancets  - insulin pumps and insulin if used with an insulin pump  - counseling to help people who are obese lose weight  - flu and pneumonia shots  - foot exams and treatment for people with diabetes  - eye exams to check for glaucoma and diabetic retinopathy  - medical nutrition therapy services for people with diabetes or kidney disease, when referred by a health care provider  - therapeutic shoes or inserts, in some cases
                
Medicare Part D helps pay for
                
- diabetes medications  - insulin, excluding insulin used with an insulin pump  - diabetes supplies such as needles and syringes for injecting insulin
                
People who are in a Medicare Advantage Plan or other Medicare health plan should check their plans membership materials and call for details about how the plan provides the diabetes services, supplies, and medications covered by Medicare.
                
Read more at www.medicare.gov/publications/pubs/pdf/11022.pdf (PDF, 1,023 KB) or call 1800MEDICARE (18006334227) to request the free booklet Medicares Coverage of Diabetes Supplies &amp; Services.
                
Where can a person find more information about Medicare?
                
A person can find more information about Medicare by
                
- visiting the Medicare website  - calling 1800MEDICARE
                
Medicare website. Read more about Medicare at www.medicare.gov, the official U.S. Government website for people with Medicare. The website has a full range of information about Medicare, including free publications such as Medicare &amp; You, which is the official Government handbook about Medicare, and Medicare BasicsA Guide for Families and Friends of People with Medicare.
                
Through the Medicare website, people can also
                
- find out if they are eligible for Medicare and when they can enroll  - learn about their Medicare health plan options  - find out what Medicare covers  - find a Medicare Prescription Drug Plan  - compare Medicare health plan options in their area  - find a health care provider who participates in Medicare  - get information about the quality of care provided by hospitals, home health agencies, and dialysis facilities
                
Calling Medicare. Calling 1800MEDICARE (18006334227) is another way to get help with Medicare questions, order free publications, and more. Help is available 24 hours a day, every day, and is available in English, Spanish, and other languages. TTY users should call 18774862048.
                
Access Personal Medicare Information   People who enroll in Medicare can register with www.MyMedicare.gov, a secure online service, and use the site to access their personal Medicare information at any time. People can view their claims and order history, and see a description of covered preventive services.
                

                
What is Medigap?
                
A Medigap plan, also known as a Medicare supplement plan, can help pay what Original Medicare does not pay for covered services. Insurance companies sell Medigap coverage. People who have a Medicare Advantage plan cannot also have a Medigap plan. A person can buy a Medigap policy from any insurance company licensed to sell the policy in the persons home state.
                
For people who are 65 and older, federal law says that in the first 6 months a person has Part B, companies cannot deny an application or limit payment for anything Original Medicare covers. Some states make insurance companies sell at least one Medigap coverage plan to those under 65 with Medicare. State insurance offices can explain the plans in their state. Find local offices on a map at www.naic.org/state_web_map.htm .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000036-6" qtype="information">What is (are) Financial Help for Diabetes Care ?</Question>
			<Answer>People who enroll in Medicare can register with www.MyMedicare.gov, a secure online service, and use the site to access their personal Medicare information at any time. People can view their claims and order history, and see a description of covered preventive services.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000036-8" qtype="information">What is (are) Financial Help for Diabetes Care ?</Question>
			<Answer>Medicaid is a state health insurance program for those with low incomes and few assets. Each state runs its own program. The Federal Government requires that Medicaid programs cover a specific set of services; however, states can choose to cover more services in addition to the ones required. A person may have Medicaid alone or Medicare and Medicaid. If a person has both types of coverage, Medicare pays first and Medicaid pays second. Medicaid may pay for things Medicare does not. A person can apply for Medicaid at a city or county department of social services office. The state medical assistance (Medicaid) office can help people find out whether they qualify for Medicaid and can provide more information about Medicaid programs. A social worker can also explain a states Medicaid program and help a person apply.
                
To contact a state Medicaid office, people can
                
- search for Medicaid information for a state at www.medicaid.gov or call 18772672323  - search online or check the government pages of the phone book for the local department of human services or department of social services
                
CHIP gives free or low-cost Medicaid to children whose parents earn too much for Medicaid, though not enough to pay for a health plan. CHIP may also provide assistance to parents. CHIP is a federal and state program. Read more at www.insurekidsnow.gov or call 18775437669.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="15">
			<Question qid="0000036-15" qtype="information">What is (are) Financial Help for Diabetes Care ?</Question>
			<Answer>Assistive technology is any device that assists, adapts, or helps to rehabilitate someone with a disability so he or she may function more safely, effectively, and independently at home, at work, and in the community. Assistive technology may include
                
- computers with features that make them accessible to people with disabilities  - adaptive equipment, such as wheelchairs  - bathroom modifications, such as grab bars or shower seats
                
The following organizations may be able to provide information, awareness, and training in the use of technology to assist people with disabilities:
                
Alliance for Technology Access 1119 Old Humboldt Road Jackson, TN 38305 Phone: 18009143017 or 7315545ATA (7315545282) TTY: 7315545284 Fax: 7315545283 Email: atainfo@ataccess.org Internet: www.ataccess.org
                
National Assistive Technology Technical Assistance Partnership 1700 North Moore Street, Suite 1540 Arlington, VA 222091903 Phone: 7035246686 Fax: 7035246630 TTY: 7035246639 Email: resnaTA@resna.org Internet: www.resnaprojects.org/nattap
                
United Cerebral Palsy 1825 K Street NW, Suite 600 Washington, D.C. 20006 Phone: 18008725827 or 2027760406 Internet: www.ucp.org/resources/assistive-technology</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="16">
			<Question qid="0000036-16" qtype="considerations">What to do for Financial Help for Diabetes Care ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Diabetes management and treatment is expensive. Many people who have diabetes need help paying for their care. For those who qualify, a variety of government and nongovernment programs can help cover health care expenses.  - Health insurance helps pay for medical care, including the cost of diabetes care. Health insurance options include private health insurance and government health insurance.  - Insurance companies sell private health insurance plans. Two types of private health insurance are group health insurance and individual health insurance.  - Medicare is a federal health insurance program that pays health care costs for eligible people who are age 65 or older, under age 65 with certain disabilities, or of any age with end-stage renal disease.  - Medicaid is a state health insurance program for those with low incomes and few assets. Each state runs its own program.  - The Childrens Health Insurance Program (CHIP) gives free or low-cost Medicaid to children whose parents earn too much for Medicaid, though not enough to pay for a health plan.  - Many local governments have public health departments that can help people who need medical care. Local resources such as charitable groups may offer financial help for some expenses related to diabetes.  - People should talk with their health care providers if they have problems paying for diabetes medications. Less expensive generic medications for diabetes, blood pressure, and cholesterol are available. If a health care provider prescribes medications that a person cannot afford, the person should ask the health care provider about cheaper alternatives.  - Health care providers may also be able to assist people who need help paying for their medications and diabetes testing supplies, such as glucose test strips, by providing free samples or referring them to local programs. Drug companies that sell insulin or diabetes medications often have patient assistance programs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
