<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Document id="0000158" source="NIDDK" url="http://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health-topics/kidney-disease/kidney-failure-what-to-expect/Pages/facts.aspx">
<Focus>Kidney Failure: What to Expect</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0035078</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="13">
			<Question qid="0000158-13" qtype="considerations">What to do for Kidney Failure: What to Expect ?</Question>
			<Answer>For people who are on dialysis or approaching total kidney failure, adequate nutrition is important for maintaining energy, strength, healthy sleep patterns, bone health, heart health, and good mental health. A persons treatment will dictate the type of diet that should be followed:
                
- People on hemodialysis must watch how much fluid they drink and avoid eating foods with too much sodium, potassium, and phosphorus.  - In contrast, people on peritoneal dialysisa type of dialysis that uses the lining of the abdomen, or belly, to filter the blood inside the bodymay be able to eat more potassium-rich foods because peritoneal dialysis removes potassium from the body more efficiently than hemodialysis.  - Both hemodialysis and peritoneal dialysis can remove proteins from the body, so anyone on either form of dialysis should eat protein-rich foods such as meat, fish, and eggs.
                
All dialysis centers and transplant clinics have a renal dietitian who specializes in helping people with kidney failure. People who are on dialysis or have a kidney transplant should talk with their clinics renal dietitian to develop a meal plan that will enhance the effectiveness of their treatment.
                
For more information about nutrition for people with advanced CKD or who are on dialysis, see NIDDK health topics, Nutrition for Advanced Chronic Kidney Disease in Adults or Kidney Failure: Eat Right to Feel Right on Hemodialysis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="14">
			<Question qid="0000158-14" qtype="considerations">What to do for Kidney Failure: What to Expect ?</Question>
			<Answer>- Kidney failure can affect a persons health in several ways.  - When the kidneys stop working, waste products build up in the blood, a condition known as uremia.  - People with kidney failure can avoid most of the problems of uremia by having regular dialysis treatments and limiting foods that contain sodium, potassium, and phosphorus.  - Anemia is common in people with chronic kidney disease (CKD), as well as those on dialysis, because the damaged kidneys slow the produc-tion of the hormone erythropoietin (EPO), which helps the bone marrow make red blood cells.  - People with kidney failure, particularly dialysis patients, have far higher rates of heart and blood vessel problems than people without kidney problems.  - People who have uremia often lose their appetite.  - Many people treated with hemodialysis complain of itchy skin.  - Kidney failure weakens the bones due to a condition called chronic kidney disease-mineral and bone disorder.  - Kidney failure can cause pain, stiffness, and fluid in the joints. These symptoms result from amyloidosis, a condition in which an abnormal protein in the blood called amyloid is deposited in tissues and organs, including the joints and tendons.  - People on dialysis often have insomnia, sleep apnea syndrome, and restless legs syndrome.  - People who have kidney failure and depression should tell their health care provider because depression can often be treated with adjustments to the diet and dialysis dose, medications, counseling, and cognitive behavioral therapy.  - For people who are on dialysis or approaching total kidney failure, adequate nutrition is important for maintaining energy, strength, healthy sleep patterns, bone health, heart health, and good mental health.  - All dialysis centers and transplant clinics have a renal dietitian who specializes in helping people with kidney failure. People who are on dialysis or have a kidney transplant should talk with their clinics renal dietitian to develop a meal plan that will enhance the effectiveness of their treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>
